CHAPTER 45

Decembris 1786

CAPÍTULO 45

CROWTHER WAS STILL ABSENT FROM HEADQUARTERS, SO Helena had no choice but to take her report to Ilva.

Diciembris 1786

As she ascended the floors to Ilva’s office in the main building, she kept thinking about all the things Ilva knew about her.

Crowther todavía no había regresado al Cuartel General, por lo que a Helena no le quedó más remedio que dar parte a Ilva.

She’d been on the board that had approved Helena’s scholarship each year, and likely the admissions board, too.

Mientras subía los pisos hacia su despacho, ubicado en el edificio principal, Helena no podía dejar de pensar en todo lo que Ilva sabía sobre ella.

The particular interest Ilva had personally taken in her since her father’s death felt much less warming now.

Durante años había formado parte de la junta que aprobaba la beca de Helena y lo más probable era que también estuviera en la de admisiones.

Ilva was staring down at a report, a pen dangling from one hand as she read, and didn’t look up when the guard let Helena in.

El interés particular que Ilva le había demostrado desde la muerte de su padre le parecía ahora menos generoso.

“Marino,” she said, her voice cool. “Sit.

Ilva estaba leyendo un informe, jugueteando distraídamente con un bolígrafo en la mano, y no levantó la vista cuando el guardia dejó pasar a Helena.

I’ll be with you in a moment.”

—Marino —pronunció con tono frío—.

Helena waited, fingers flexing.

Siéntate.

“How is your work on the nullium with Shiseo progressing?” Ilva asked, flipping the file closed and looking up.

Ahora mismo estoy contigo.

The Council had named the lumithium-mo’lian’shi alloy nullium for the sake of convenience.

Helena aguardó sin parar de abrir y cerrar las manos.

While the knowledge of the alloy was not widespread, several metallurgists and chymists were all experimenting with it.

—¿Cómo vais Shiseo y tú con el anulitio? —preguntó Ilva cuando cerró la carpeta y levantó la vista.

The question caught Helena off guard; she’d expected enquiries about Kaine.

Para una mayor comodidad, el Consejo había bautizado como «anulitio» a la aleación de lumitio con mo’lian’shi.

“Good.

Aunque no se había extendido la noticia de su existencia, ya había algunos metalúrgicos y quimiatras experimentando con el material.

We’ve finished synthesising the chelating agent using the samples I took from Ferron.

La pregunta la tomó por sorpresa; esperaba que le preguntara sobre Kaine.

If any of our combatants are injured by it, hopefully it will be able to capture and remove the traces of metal in the blood.”

—Bien.

The shrapnel samples Helena had retrieved could not make a sturdy weapon, but the alloy wasn’t supposed to.

Estamos terminando de sintetizar el agente quelante a partir de las muestras que recogí de Ferron.

The fusion was intentionally unstable; it shattered on impact and the shards tended to deteriorate quickly when exposed to blood, dissolving like a poison blade targeting resonance.

Si alguno de nuestros combatientes resulta herido con anulitio, podremos extraer todas las piezas metálicas de la sangre.

Helena and Shiseo had been instructed to pursue potential treatment methods.

La metralla que Helena había extraído no era suficiente para fabricar un arma robusta, pero la aleación no tenía por qué serlo.

Because metal toxicity could happen frequently in certain fields of alchemy, chelators were already commonplace.

La fusión estaba diseñada para ser inestable, para que se hiciera añicos en el impacto y las esquirlas se deterioraran rápidamente al entrar en contacto con el torrente sanguíneo.

Ilva nodded. “What does Shiseo think?”

Allí se disolvían como un veneno, atacando a la resonancia de la víctima.

“He doesn’t think that true alchemy suppression is possible with the method they’re using.

Helena y Shiseo tenían órdenes de investigar posibles tratamientos.

While it does prevent healing and alchemical surgery, it’s of limited use for combat, but that could change if they reconfigure the ratio and composition.”

Dado que la toxicidad en los metales era algo habitual en ciertos campos de la alquimia, lo más lógico sería empezar con los agentes quelantes.

Ilva’s eyes narrowed. “Is there an alternative method that you and Shiseo have in mind?”

Ilva asintió.

Helena swallowed, trying not to squirm. “We have an idea, but it’s purely theoretical.

—¿Qué piensa Shiseo?

We don’t have enough nullium to test it.”

—Cree que es imposible que el enemigo consiga suprimir la alquimia por completo mediante el método que están usando.

“And it is …”

Es cierto que impide la sanación y la cirugía alquímica, pero su uso en batalla suele ser limitado.

Helena’s stomach knotted.

Aunque eso podría cambiar si aciertan con la ratio y la composición.

She hated these kinds of conversations.

Ilva entrecerró los ojos.

“Given the alloy’s behaviour and how resonance is used, making it into a weapon or injecting nullium into the blood is less effective than simply targeting the limbs with it.

—¿Shiseo y tú tenéis algún método alternativo en mente?

If that kind of interference was focused near the hands, it would be almost impossible for an alchemist to accurately sense their resonance.

Helena tragó saliva e intentó no mostrar debilidad.

Shiseo thinks that if the alloy was paired with something that has a high, sharp resonance point—like copper processed with a high level of lumithium emanations—that could create a type of interference that would suppress most kinds of resonance regardless of the alchemist’s repertoire.”

—Tenemos una idea, pero por el momento es solo una teoría.

“How would we counter that?” Ilva leaned forward with interest.

No disponemos de anulitio para probarla.

“Well, any good metallurgist could, if they were comfortable working without resonance.

—Y esa teoría se basa en…

But that’s not something most Paladian metallurgists have ever had to worry about.”

A Helena se le formó un nudo en el estómago.

“Fortunate, then, that you fished those shards out of Ferron,” Ilva said, although the sentiment was hardly reflected by her tone.

Detestaba mantener este tipo de conversaciones.

Helena gave a tight nod. “Here’s his report,” she said, pushing the envelope across the table.

—Teniendo en cuenta cómo se comporta la aleación y cómo funciona la resonancia, hacer un arma de anulitio o inyectarlo en sangre es menos efectivo que dirigirlo hacia las extremidades.

Ilva plucked it up and dropped it into a drawer.

Si centráramos esa interferencia en las manos, los alquimistas perderían la capacidad de percibir su propia resonancia.

“And I—” Helena hesitated, heat rising to her hairline and the tips of her ears. “He gave me a set of daggers as a solstice gift, using the titanium-nickel alloy.”

Shiseo cree que, si combinamos la aleación con un material que tenga una gran sensibilidad a la resonancia, como, por ejemplo, el cobre procesado con una alta concentración de efluvios de lumitio, lograríamos una interferencia capaz de suprimir casi todas las resonancias, independientemente del repertorio del alquimista.

She pulled out the oilcloth and opened it on the desk for Ilva’s inspection.

—¿Y cómo contrarrestamos algo así? —preguntó Ilva con interés.

Ilva raised an eyebrow, glancing for a moment before flicking the cloth to cover them as if she found the mere sight distasteful.

—Bueno, podría hacerlo cualquier metalúrgico, siempre y cuando se sienta cómodo trabajando sin resonancia.

Helena’s stomach dropped and she wrapped them up quickly, wishing she hadn’t shown them without being asked. “It’s a good sign, isn’t it?”

Aunque la mayoría de los paladinos nunca han tenido que preocuparse por eso.

Ilva tilted her head, studying Helena for a moment. “Ferron’s climbing rank,” she said as she reached into a drawer and pulled out a file, dropping it onto the desk. “Did you know?”

—Qué suerte tuvimos de que le sacaras esa metralla a Ferron —dijo Ilva, a pesar de que el tono no reflejó el sentimiento.

Helena’s heart stalled.

Helena se limitó a asentir.

She had noticed his uniform was darker.

—Aquí tienes el informe —dijo dejando el sobre en la mesa.

“It seems he’s already surpassed everything he’d ever achieved prior to that injury of his.

Ilva lo cogió y lo metió en un cajón—.

He controls several extremely valuable districts.

Por cierto… —Helena dudó y sintió que se ruborizaba hasta el nacimiento del cabello y las puntas de las orejas—.

Recently he’s taken over the factory Outpost where you’ve been visiting him, consolidating power at a remarkable speed.

Me ha regalado un par de dagas por el solsticio de invierno.

It seems all our recent successes have benefitted him greatly.”

Están hechas de titanio y níquel.

Ilva tapped a fingernail on the desk, looking up at Helena with a cold smile.

Sacó el paño impermeable y lo abrió sobre el escritorio para que Ilva les echara un vistazo.

“I didn’t know,” Helena said.

La mujer arqueó una ceja y contempló las dagas un instante para, acto seguido, cubrirlas con la tela, como si mirarlas le pareciera de mal gusto.

Ilva shook her head. “No, I didn’t imagine so.

A Helena se le cayó el alma a los pies.

I’m beginning to worry whether you remember what he is.”

Envolvió las armas rápidamente, deseando no habérselas enseñado sin preguntar antes.

Helena’s breath caught, but Ilva continued, flipping through page after page in the file before her.

—Es una buena señal, ¿no?

“There have been rumours for months that Morrough has a new weapon.

Ilva la miró con la cabeza ladeada, como si la estuviera analizando.

We thought it was a chimaera, like the one that nearly killed Lila, or the nullium, but no.

—Ferron está subiendo de rango —comentó mientras abría un cajón y sacaba otra carpeta.

It’s neither of those things, is it?” Ilva folded her hands, looking squarely at Helena. “How is it that he’s still alive?”

La dejó sobre el escritorio—.

“Crowther told me to do what I could.”

¿Lo sabías?

Ilva’s eyes flicked down from Helena’s face to her neck, where the chain of her necklace was barely visible beneath her collar.

A ella se le detuvo el corazón.

Helena went very still.

Sí que se había percatado de que su uniforme cada vez era más oscuro.

“You know, Ferron’s not our only spy,” Ilva said. “We have a number of informants.

—Al parecer, ha superado todas las limitaciones que tenía antes de sufrir aquellas lesiones.

Based on their reports, following the recovery of the ports, he was punished.

Tiene controlados varios distritos de gran valor.

Extensively.

Hace poco tomó posesión de la fábrica del Reducto, justo donde tú vas a verlo, y está consolidando su poder a una velocidad alarmante.

He was dying.

Es evidente que está aprovechando al máximo nuestros últimos éxitos.

I was assured of that.”

Ilva tamborileó los dedos sobre el escritorio y, cuando levantó la vista, le dedicó a Helena una sonrisa gélida.

“You knew?” Helena asked, her voice shaking. “You knew what they did to him, and you—you didn’t tell me?”

—No lo sabía —admitió la chica.

Ilva stared piercingly at her. “Why would we have told you?”

Ilva negó con la cabeza lentamente.

Helena could hardly speak. “Is that why the attack was so elaborate and used so much of the intelligence?

—Ya, eso me lo imaginaba.

Because you expected he’d be killed for it.

Me preocupa que se te haya olvidado de quién estamos hablando. —Helena contuvo el aliento, pero Ilva continuó con calma, sin dejar de pasar páginas de la carpeta que tenía entre manos—: Hace meses que circulan rumores de que Morrough tiene un arma nueva.

Because you wanted him killed for it.”

Pensábamos que se trataba de las quimeras, como la que estuvo a punto de acabar con Lila, o del anulitio.

Ilva said nothing, but now Kaine’s resentment and disbelief when Helena kept coming back began to make sense.

Pero no es así.

“Why didn’t you tell me?” Helena’s voice trembled with rage.

No se trata de nada de eso, ¿verdad? —Ilva entrelazó las manos y miró a Helena fijamente—.

Ilva’s lips pursed, her eyes flicking across Helena’s face. “You’ve always been—remarkably forthright.” A smile stretched across her lips. “That’s why Luc trusts you so much.

¿Cómo es posible que siga vivo?

If we’d told you the plan, do you really think you could have gone, knowing, without giving any sign to Ferron?”

—Crowther me pidió que hiciera todo lo posible por salvarle la vida.

Helena began to tremble.

La mirada de Ilva pasó de la cara de Helena al cuello, donde asomaba la cadena de su collar.

She gripped the arms of her chair as the room blurred.

Helena se quedó muy quieta.

“We assumed you’d realise it,” Ilva added. “When it became clear that you hadn’t—that you felt some sort of obligation to him—we agreed to let you try to heal him in the hope that once you realised the futility of it, you’d be able to bring his talisman back.”

—Verás, Ferron no es el único espía que tenemos —continuó Ilva—.

Ilva cleared her throat. “So you can imagine our surprise that he has not only survived but become more dangerous than ever before, that treacherous spy of ours.

Disponemos de varios informantes.

How did you do it?”

Según sus informes, Ferron recibió un castigo cuando recuperamos los puertos.

Helena swallowed hard. “We were losing, and it was only because of him that we could retake the ports.

Un castigo brutal.

He did that for us.

Me aseguraron que estaba muriéndose.

You didn’t see him the day I went back.

—¿Tú lo sabías? —preguntó Helena con voz trémula—.

He knew he’d be punished; he expected to die.” She gave a panicked breath. “If you wanted him dead, you should have told me.

¿Sabías lo que le hicieron y no… no me lo dijiste?

Crowther said to do what I could.”

Ilva le dedicó una mirada penetrante.

“What did you do?” Ilva had become impossibly more tense. “Did you—” Her lips thinned, her eyes flickering to the chain around Helena’s neck once more. “Did you use something to manage it?”

—¿Y por qué habríamos de decírtelo?

Helena squeezed her hand into a fist. “I assumed that if you had to choose between the two of us, you’d want him.”

Helena no encontraba las palabras.

Ilva’s face went white.

—¿Por eso el ataque fue tan complejo y necesitó tanta información confidencial?

“So I used the amulet you gave me, I thought it—”

Estabais seguros de que lo matarían por cometer ese error.

“You gave the amulet to him?” The question was almost a shriek.

Porque queríais que lo mataran por ello.

Helena had never heard Ilva raise her voice. “No, I—”

Ilva no respondió, pero Helena empezó a entender por qué Kaine la había mirado con tanto resentimiento y desconfianza cada vez que acudía a las citas.

“Do you still have it or not?”

—¿Por qué no me lo contaste? —Le temblaba la voz de la rabia.

Helena’s stomach twisted into a tight knot as she reached up, pulling the chain over her head. “I have the amulet, but the sunstone is gone.”

Ilva frunció los labios y miró a Helena con atención.

Ilva snatched it from her so quickly, the chain ripped open Helena’s kidskin glove.

—Siempre has sido… especialmente sincera. —Esbozó una sonrisa—.

Ilva pressed her thumb against the centre where the stone was missing, staring in horror before looking at her. “What did you do?”

Por eso Luc confía tanto en ti.

Helena swallowed nervously. “It broke and this—substance came out.

Si te hubiéramos contado el plan, ¿crees que habrías sido capaz de ir allí sabiéndolo todo sin que Ferron se diera cuenta?

Like quicksilver, and—it—it fused with Ferron.”

Helena empezó a temblar y la visión se le volvió borrosa.

There was a ghastly silence.

Se aferró con fuerza a los reposabrazos de su asiento.

Ilva looked so stunned she said nothing, just looked at the amulet again, as if the stone could magically rematerialise.

—Dimos por sentado que acabarías dándote cuenta —continuó Ilva—.

Finally, Helena couldn’t bear it anymore.

Cuando se hizo evidente que no había sido así, y que sentías que le debías algo, decidimos que era mejor que intentaras curarlo.

“If you didn’t want him healed, you should have told me.”

Con suerte, comprenderías que no servía de nada y acabarías trayéndonos su talismán. —Ilva se aclaró la garganta—.

Ilva didn’t reply, just stared at the amulet in her hand. “Do you know the story of the Stone of the Heavens?” she finally said, still running her thumb over the empty setting.

Así que ya puedes imaginar nuestra sorpresa cuando descubrimos que nuestro espía traicionero no solo había sobrevivido, sino que se había vuelto más peligroso que antes.

Dread swept through Helena like a tidal wave.

¿Cómo lo hiciste?

“No,” she said, shaking her head. “It’s a myth.

Helena tragó saliva a duras penas.

Everyone knows that was a misinterpretation.

—Estábamos perdiendo la guerra, y solo remontamos porque él nos ayudó a retomar los puertos.

Luc said it wasn’t real.”

Lo hizo por nosotros.

“Every choice I have made was to protect Luc,” Ilva said.

Tú no lo viste el día que volví.

She wasn’t talking to Helena so much as speaking aloud or perhaps to the amulet in her hand. “I was never trained to be a steward, to bear the weight of this legacy.

Ferron era consciente de que lo castigarían; había asumido su muerte. —Estaba jadeando del pánico—.

I was happy with my role, but Luc was too young for all this.

Si queríais que muriera, deberíais habérmelo dicho.

I’ve tried to make the best choices I could.”

Crowther me pidió que hiciera todo lo posible.

Ilva looked up at Helena. “When your—vivimancy made its appearance, I thought I’d been given my way forward.

—¿Qué le hiciste? —El tono de Ilva se había vuelto mucho más tenso—.

That Sol had provided a fail-safe so that I could protect him.

¿Usaste…? —Frunció aún más los labios y, de nuevo, buscó con la mirada la cadena que rodeaba el cuello de Helena—.

Of course there was still the politics of it to contend with.

¿Usaste algo para curarlo?

Matias did not make it easy.

—Supuse que, si teníais que elegir entre uno u otro, preferiríais que sobreviviera él —respondió Helena apretando el puño.

With all the concessions he demanded, I was concerned about the Toll taking you too prematurely.

Ilva palideció—.

That amulet had been locked away for centuries, lying idle as generations of Holdfasts protected it.

Así que usé el amuleto que me regalaste.

I’d hoped this war might rouse it to do something.”

Pensé que…

“What was it?” Helena asked.

—¿Le diste el amuleto a Ferron? —su voz sonó casi histérica.

Ilva stood, seizing her cane so tightly that her swollen knuckles showed white as she walked past Helena to the window, looking out towards the Alchemy Tower.

Helena jamás la había escuchado alzarla.

“My family built this Institute and this city to ensure that necromancy would never come to power again.

—No, yo…

They gave their lives to that cause and kept countless secrets to that end.”

—¿Lo sigues teniendo o no?

Ilva fell silent for a long time.

La chica sintió que se le formaba un nudo en el estómago.

Helena didn’t dare speak.

Acto seguido, se sacó el amuleto por encima de la cabeza.

“Have you heard the stories of Rivertide?”

—Tengo el amuleto, pero la heliolita ha desaparecido.

Rivertide was the name of Paladia back before the first Necromancy War.

Ilva se lo arrebató con tanta ansia que la cadena se rompió contra el guante de cuero que llevaba.

It had been wiped out by a plague, and when the Necromancer found it, he’d used the corpses for his army.

Su mano derecha acarició el amuleto, ahí donde debía haber estado la piedra.

“There was no plague,” Ilva said, still not looking back. “Orion called it a plague because it was kinder than immortalising what truly happened to them all.” She pressed her hand, still clutching the amulet, against her chest. “The Necromancer realised the alchemical potential of the area and came to Rivertide specifically because of the people living here.”

Parecía completamente horrorizada.

“He killed them?” Helena couldn’t understand the purpose of that secret.

—¿Qué has hecho?

That the Necromancer massacred Rivertide was even more believable than a story of finding a convenient town of corpses.

Helena tragó saliva, nerviosa.

Ilva shook her head. “No, they’re still alive, to this day.”

—Se rompió y salió una especie de… sustancia.

Helena stared at her, not understanding.

Algo parecido al mercurio.

“The Necromancer was a vivimancer, just like you, but the ability was even more mythical back then.

Se… se fusionó con Ferron.

He came to Rivertide performing miracles.

El silencio que siguió fue casi insoportable.

They thought he was a god.

Ilva parecía tan perpleja que no dijo nada, solo se quedó mirando el amuleto, como si la piedra vacía fuese a materializarse por arte de magia.

They built him a temple on the plateau, gave him everything he asked for, and he promised them immortality if they only had the faith for it.

Helena esperó unos momentos, pero ya no podía soportarlo más.

Then one day, he brought them all together in a great assembly, in a secret place he’d carved underground, and declared that if they trusted him fully, utterly, he could make them live forever.

—Si no querías que lo sanara, deberías habérmelo dicho.

I’m not sure of the process, but afterwards, his temple was full of corpses, and their souls were bound together, synthesised into this—substance.

Ilva no respondió; era incapaz de apartar la mirada del amuleto.

He used it, the power, to reanimate them all.”

—¿Conoces la historia de la Gema de los Cielos? —dijo finalmente, acariciando el engarce vacío con el pulgar.

Ilva began to pace, her steps jerky, her cane trembling in her hand; she was too agitated to be still. “When Orion fought the Necromancer, the souls were still conscious, aware of the betrayal exacted upon them—that the gift of ‘immortality’ came at the price of eternal enslavement.

Helena sintió un miedo que le helaba los huesos.

During the battle, the Necromancer’s control slipped, and the Stone turned on him.

—No —admitió sacudiendo la cabeza—.

There was a light as bright as the sun.

Es un mito.

It filled the valley, destroying the Necromancer and all the necrothralls in a wave of fire.

Todo el mundo sabe que fue una malinterpretación.

When it was over, Orion and his followers were all that remained.” Ilva shook her head. “If the truth of the Stone’s nature were known, Orion feared that others might be inspired to rediscover the methods, and so, when those who’d witnessed the battle called the Stone a gift from Sol, Orion had no choice but to let them believe it.”

Luc me contó que no era verdad.

Ilva paused, her expression mournful.

—Todas las decisiones que he tomado han sido para proteger a Luc —afirmó Ilva.

“It’s all a lie?”

No parecía estar hablando con Helena, sino más bien consigo misma, o tal vez con el amuleto que tenía agarrado—.

Ilva whirled on her, looking furious. “What else could he do?”

No me educaron para ser su mano derecha ni para soportar la carga de este legado.

Helena stood up, ready to ignite. “Tell the truth!

Yo estaba satisfecha con mi papel, pero Luc era demasiado joven para asumir la responsabilidad del principado.

You don’t get to make up history to suit your preferences.

He intentado tomar buenas decisiones. —Ilva miró a Helena—.

Do you realise what you’ve done?

Cuando descubrimos que eras una… vivemante, pensé que serías mi salvación, que Sol me había concedido un medio infalible para protegerlo.

Luc thinks he’s supposed to be earning a miracle.

Por supuesto, tuve que lidiar con los prejuicios políticos, y Matias no me lo puso fácil.

That the reason he hasn’t already won this war is because he hasn’t suffered or been enough like Orion to earn it, and that’s his fault.

Después de todas las exigencias que te impuso, me preocupaba que el Estrago te matara antes de tiempo.

But there will never be a miracle that will save us.

Este amuleto llevaba siglos bajo llave, protegido por varias generaciones de Holdfast.

You’re torturing him to death on a lie.”

Confiaba en que esta guerra lo hiciera despertar de alguna forma.

“That’s why I am making him miracles,” Ilva snapped back.

—¿Qué era? —preguntó Helena.

She looked equally incensed, as if Helena were the traitor. “You think I want him to suffer?

Ilva se irguió, apoyándose con tanta fuerza en su bastón que los nudillos se le volvieron blancos.

I want to tell him, but when is there time for that?” She swept her arm out. “Apollo should have been the one to tell him—when he was old enough, and ready for it all.

Pasó junto a Helena y se asomó a la ventana, desde donde se veía la Torre de Alquimia.

There’s a process to it, but all that was destroyed when Ferron murdered Apollo and brought this war upon us.

—Mi familia construyó esta institución y esta ciudad para asegurarse de que la nigromancia no volvía a hacerse con el poder.

All I can do is try to make that faith real and keep him from losing hope.”

Entregaron sus vidas a esa causa y mantuvieron secretos con el mismo fin. —La mujer se sumió en un silencio profundo durante un buen rato.

The whole city, the Principate, the Faith, the history, every mural, every amulet.

Helena no se atrevió a interrumpirla—.

All lies.

¿Has escuchado hablar de Caudalón?

“You have to tell Luc the truth.

Caudalón era el nombre que tenía Paladia antes de que se produjera la Primera Guerra Nigromántica.

You can’t keep doing this to him.”

La ciudad fue arrasada por una plaga y, cuando el Nigromante se enteró, usó los cadáveres para crear un ejército.

“And what do you think would happen if he knows that no help is coming?

—No hubo ninguna plaga —confesó Ilva sin mirar atrás—.

What will he have then?” Ilva glared at her. “That is too great a risk, but now thanks to you, I am left with nothing but terrible choices.”

Orion contó que había sido una plaga porque esa era una explicación más amable que la verdad. —Cerró la mano y apretó el amuleto junto a su pecho—.

Helena set her jaw, too angry to accept the fault. “Why would you give me something like that without explaining what it was?”

El Nigromante se enteró del poder alquímico de esta zona y vino a Caudalón por la gente que vivía aquí.

Ilva’s eyes flashed. “Because I was trying to save you, spare you.

—¿Los mató a todos? —La chica no entendía el sentido del secreto.

I thought maybe the damned thing could manage that much, and it seemed that it did.

Si el Nigromante había masacrado Caudalón, la historia sería mucho más creíble que la de que había encontrado una ciudad llena de cadáveres cuando más la necesitaba.

But when Ferron made his offer, Crowther said it was the only chance we had left.

Ilva sacudió la cabeza.

I considered taking it back that night.

—No, siguen vivos.

I could have, after what you’d said before the Council, but I remembered your face when I first put it on you.

Todavía están vivos.

I thought you treasured it enough to have sense.

Helena la miró sin comprender.

You stupid, stupid girl.” All the strength seemed to suddenly leave Ilva, and she nearly collapsed into a seat.

—El Nigromante era un vivemante, igual que tú, aunque en aquella época esas habilidades parecían sacadas de un cuento mitológico.

“You don’t get to lie to me and then get angry when I make the mistake of believing you,” Helena said. “If the Stone’s that special, why not let Luc use it.”

Llegó a Caudalón haciendo milagros.

Ilva’s expression twisted bitterly. “It doesn’t serve the Holdfasts.” She looked away from Helena, jaw set. “Even in Orion’s own hands, it was hard and cold, never bestowing its power or favour upon anyone of the Holdfast line.

La gente pensaba que era un dios.

There have been a few whom it would warm to, but it always went cold eventually.

Le erigieron un templo en la meseta, le entregaron todo lo que pidió, y él les prometió la inmortalidad a quienes tuvieran fe.

And you of all people had it.

Sin embargo, un día los convocó a todos en una asamblea multitudinaria, en un sitio secreto que había excavado bajo tierra, y declaró que, si confiaban plenamente en él, les concedería la inmortalidad.

You could have done anything, and you healed Ferron with it.”

No sé exactamente qué hizo, pero, cuando terminó, el templo estaba lleno de cadáveres, y las almas de los presentes se habían fusionado.

“So sorry I wasn’t the puppet you wanted,” Helena said bitterly, standing.

Se habían combinado para formar esta… sustancia.

She felt as if the entire world had dropped out from beneath her feet; she had no idea how to navigate this newfound reality.

El Nigromante usó el poder que emanaba de esa gema para reanimarlos a todos.

After so much time being maligned for her lack of faith, it was all an invention.

Ilva empezó a caminar de un lado a otro, cojeando; el bastón temblaba constantemente en sus manos.

She wasn’t sure what was real.

Estaba demasiado nerviosa para quedarse quieta.

Even being given to Kaine had been an elaborate con.

—Cuando Orion se enfrentó al Nigromante, las almas todavía conservaban consciencia; sabían que los había traicionado, que el regalo de la «inmortalidad» los condenaba a ser esclavos toda la eternidad.

It had never been about securing Kaine’s loyalty, but simply about giving the earnest appearance that she was trying to.

Durante la batalla, el Nigromante perdió el control, y la gema se volvió en su contra.

And Luc.

Se produjo un fogonazo tan brillante como el sol, que iluminó todo el valle y aniquiló al Nigromante y a todos los necrómatas en un estallido de fuego.

Her heart ached.

Cuando todo terminó, solo quedaron Orion y sus seguidores. —Ilva negó con la cabeza—.

What would he do if he learned the truth?

Si alguien hubiera conocido el verdadero origen de la gema, Orion temía que otros intentaran usar el mismo método, así que, cuando los testigos de la batalla dijeron que la gema había sido un regalo de Sol, Orion no tuvo más remedio que permitir que lo creyeran.

Could she tell him this?

Ilva se quedó callada con tristeza.

After all she’d omitted over the years, was she going to come clean by destroying everything he believed in?

—¿Todo es una mentira?

She couldn’t.

La mujer se giró hacia ella y le lanzó una mirada furibunda.

There was too much at stake, and Ilva knew that.

—¿Qué otra cosa podía hacer?

Helena paused as she reached the door. “In the future, perhaps tell me what you want instead of expecting me to fail where it’s convenient to you.

Helena se levantó, exasperada.

Maybe then we’ll both end up less disappointed in each other.”

—¡Decir la verdad!

“You want honesty?” Ilva’s voice was viperous. “I want you to kill Kaine Ferron.”

No podemos inventarnos la historia para que encaje en lo que deseamos creer.

Helena froze, turning slowly back.

¿Es que no ves adónde nos ha llevado esto?

Ilva met her eyes.

Luc piensa que debe suceder un milagro, que aún no ha ganado la guerra porque no ha sufrido lo suficiente, porque no se parece a Orion, porque no se lo merece… Y que todo es culpa suya.

She was composed again, chilly as a lake. “He was always going to die, but I want you to do it.

Pero ese milagro nunca llegará.

You created this new threat to Luc, so you will put an end to it.”

Lo estás torturando con una mentira.

“He hasn’t done anything to betray us.”

—Por eso soy yo quien le concede milagros —espetó Ilva.

“He murdered my nephew.” Ilva’s voice cracked like a whip, and Helena saw the fury and hatred that the woman kept so carefully concealed.

También estaba enfurecida, como si Helena fuera una traidora—.

It rose like a beast from inside her. “You want to what?

¿Crees que quiero hacerle sufrir?

To wait and see who he’ll kill next?

Quisiera contárselo, pero ¿cuándo es el momento adecuado? —Estiró un brazo—.

Whose life are you prepared to gamble on that?”

Apollo debía haber sido quien se lo explicara, cuando tuviese edad suficiente y estuviera listo para comprenderlo.

Her chest clenched. “You can’t ask me to betray—”

Hay que respetar ciertas pautas, pero todo se vino abajo cuando Ferron asesinó a Apollo y desató la guerra.

“Why not?

Ahora, lo único que puedo hacer es mantener viva la fe para que Luc no pierda la esperanza.

What has he done for you, Marino, except play you like the fool you are?

La historia de la ciudad, del principado, de la Fe, todos los murales y amuletos… Todo era mentira.

Are a few trinkets all your loyalty costs?” Ilva’s eyes flicked derisively to the oilcloth still clutched in Helena’s hand. “If Ferron wanted you, he would have taken you by now.

—Tienes que contarle la verdad a Luc.

You’re just a toy; he winds you up and watches you spin.”

No puedes seguir haciéndole esto.

“No.

—¿Y qué crees que pasará cuando sepa que no recibirá ayuda de los dioses?

I’m making progress.

¿Qué le quedará entonces? —Ilva fulminó a Helena con la mirada—.

A little more time and I’ll have him just the way Crowther wants him.”

Es un riesgo que no podemos correr y ahora me has dejado sin más opción que tomar decisiones terribles.

Ilva gave a disbelieving laugh. “Crowther was delusional, thinking to use you to tame Ferron.

Helena apretó la mandíbula.

You cannot bring a mad dog to heel.” She shook her head. “But very well, you’re welcome to refuse; it doesn’t matter, we have more than enough evidence of his treachery.

Estaba demasiado enfadada para aceptar la culpa.

Jan has been assembling a comprehensive package.

—¿Por qué me diste algo así sin explicarme lo que era?

It would be a trivial matter to send along to the Undying.

Los ojos de Ilva brillaron con intensidad.

I suppose you could say the case is ironclad.

—Porque intentaba salvarte, evitarte sufrimiento.

Do you prefer that?

Pensé que este maldito amuleto sería capaz de contener el Estrago, y parece que así ha sido.

Do you think they’ll kill him this time?”

Pero, cuando Ferron puso sus condiciones, Crowther pensó que no nos quedaba más remedio que aceptarlas.

Helena’s chest felt as if it had been punched through. “You can’t do that to him.”

Aquella noche me planteé quitártelo, y lo habría hecho después de lo que le dijiste al Consejo, pero entonces recordé la cara que pusiste cuando te lo entregué.

Ilva was unmoved. “Why not?

Creí que lo considerarías un tesoro, que lo cuidarías… Pero has cometido la mayor de las estupideces. —Ilva pareció desfallecer y estuvo a punto de desplomarse en el asiento.

It would be fitting, no?

—No tienes derecho a mentirme para luego enfadarte porque he cometido el error de creer tus palabras —replicó Helena—.

After everything he’s done.

Si la gema es tan especial, ¿por qué no se la diste a Luc?

I’d say he more than deserves it.”

El semblante de Ilva se contrajo con amargura.

Helena realised then what she should have realised long before, that Ilva had always wanted revenge.

—No responde a los Holdfast. —Apartó la vista de Helena con los dientes apretados—.

Crowther looked at the civil war and saw all the political machinations of the surrounding countries; Ilva’s game of war was equally intricate, but hers was wholly personal.

Ni siquiera en manos de Orion fue más que una piedra dura y fría, jamás mostró su poder a ninguno de sus descendientes.

It was about Luc, it was about her family’s legacy, and it was about revenge.

Se volvió cálida para algunas personas, pero siempre se enfriaba con el tiempo.

Crowther had been the ambitious one who’d wanted Helena to make Kaine loyal, something utilised in the long term.

Pero contigo funcionó.

That had never been Ilva’s goal.

Podrías haber hecho lo que fuera con ella, pero decidiste gastarla para curar a Ferron.

“We need him, though.

—Siento mucho no ser la marioneta que tú querías que fuese —repuso Helena con amargura.

We’ve only come this far because of him.

Se incorporó con dificultad.

If we lose him, if things start falling apart again, people will blame Luc for that.”

Era como si el mundo entero hubiese desaparecido bajo sus pies; no sabía cómo asimilar lo que acababa de descubrir.

Ilva gave a thin smile. “Fortunately for us, Ferron has made himself quite the integral figure among the Undying in recent months.

Después de haber pasado tanto tiempo sintiéndose culpable por su falta de fe, resultaba que todo era un invento.

With him suddenly gone, the destabilisation will be widespread.”

Ya no sabía qué era real y qué no.

“You can’t do this,” Helena said.

Todo había sido un engaño enrevesado hasta que la vendieron a Kaine.

“I am trying to save everyone, Marino.” Her voice crackled with intensity. “That includes you.

Y Luc… Le dolió en el alma pensar en su amigo.

No matter how you’ve romanticised him, Kaine Ferron is not a person.

¿Qué haría si se enteraba de la verdad?

He is a monster.” Ilva pressed her hand over her heart, a gesture many people made when alluding to Apollo. “He and his family should have been dealt with long ago, but Pol worried about how the guilds might react.

¿Debía ser ella quien se lo contara?

He let that boy attend the Institute despite the suspicions surrounding his birth, and look how that kindness was repaid.

La religión era un tema del que siempre había evitado hablar, así que ¿por qué iba ahora a sincerarse y destruir todas sus creencias?

I will not make that mistake with Luc.”

No podía hacerlo.

“Please, Ilva, I can make him loyal.

Había demasiado en juego, e Ilva lo sabía.

I just need more time.”

Helena se detuvo bajo el marco de la puerta.

Ilva stared at her. “Are you choosing Ferron over Luc?

—La próxima vez será mejor que me digas qué quieres en vez de confiar en que fracase cuando tú lo consideres oportuno.

Over all the vows you made?”

Tal vez así evitemos decepcionarnos la una con la otra.

The question stopped her cold.

—¿Quieres que te sea sincera? —La voz de Ilva era viperina—.

“No,” Helena said quickly. “No,” she said again, her voice breaking. “I am loyal.

Quiero que mates a Kaine Ferron.

But”—her throat worked several times—“if I had proof that he was loyal, that he’d do whatever you wanted, would you let him live?

Helena se quedó paralizada y se giró lentamente.

I swear, if I can’t, I will—I will kill him.

Ilva la miró fijamente a los ojos.

But if he was loyal, he could be useful.

Había recuperado la compostura y volvía a mostrarse fría como un lago.

“Please, Ilva.” Her voice shook.

—Nuestra intención desde el principio fue que muriera, pero quiero que lo hagas tú.

Ilva gave a small sigh and looked tired. “If you can present Ferron on his knees, crawling, willing to do anything, within a month, I’ll let you keep him.” Then she shook her head. “But be honest with yourself.

Has creado una nueva amenaza para Luc, así que debes ser tú misma quien le ponga fin.

There’s no such thing as loyalty in his kind.

—Kaine no nos ha traicionado.

The Ferrons are as corruptible as their resonance.”

—Asesinó a mi sobrino. —La voz de Ilva resonó como un látigo.

There was pressure in her throat like a stone, but Helena forced herself to speak. “I’ll do it.

Helena se percató de la furia y el odio que mantenía ocultos bajo la superficie; ahora estaban emergiendo de lo más hondo como si fuera una bestia—.

One way or another.

¿Qué pretendes hacer?

I’ll finish it.

¿Esperar a que elija a su próxima víctima?

Don’t let Crowther send what he has.”

¿Cuántas vidas estás dispuesta a arriesgar?

Ilva had leaned forward on her desk, the chain from the empty amulet dangling between her fingers. “One month, Marino.”

A Helena se le formó un nudo en la garganta.

—No puedes pedirme que traicione…

—¿Por qué no?

¿Qué ha hecho por ti, Marino, salvo tratarte como la idiota que eres?

¿Te da unas cuantas baratijas y ya estás dispuesta a ofrecerle tu lealtad? —Los ojos de Ilva repararon en la tela impermeable que Helena seguía aferrando entre las manos—.

Si Ferron quisiera poseerte, ya lo habría hecho.

No eres más que un juguete para él; se dedica a darte cuerda y ver cómo das vueltas.

—No, estoy avanzando.

Si me dejas algo más de tiempo, conseguiré lo que Crowther me pidió.

A Ilva se le escapó una carcajada seca y llena de escepticismo.

—Crowther estaba muy equivocado si pensaba que serías capaz de domar a Ferron.

Ni siquiera un perro te haría caso. —Sacudió la cabeza con desdén—.

Pero adelante, eres libre de negarte a hacerlo.

Sinceramente, no importa; tenemos pruebas suficientes para demostrar su traición.

Jan ha reunido un buen montón de documentación.

No nos costará nada entregársela a los inmarcesibles.

Te aseguro que este asunto está más que blindado.

¿Prefieres que hagamos eso?

¿Crees que esta vez lo matarán de una vez por todas?

Helena sintió como si le hubiesen dado un puñetazo en el pecho.

—No podéis hacerle eso.

La mujer ni se inmutó.

—¿Por qué no?

A mí me parece lo más adecuado después de todo lo que ha hecho él.

De hecho, diría que hasta se lo merece.

Fue entonces cuando Helena cayó en la cuenta de algo de lo que debería haberse percatado desde el principio: Ilva solo buscaba venganza.

Mientras que Crowther pensaba en la guerra civil, analizaba los tejemanejes políticos de los países vecinos, la estrategia bélica de Ilva se reducía a un tema personal.

Todo giraba en torno a Luc, al legado de su familia y a una sed implacable de venganza.

Crowther era lo suficientemente ambicioso como para querer que Helena se ganara la lealtad de Kaine para usarlo a largo plazo.

Sin embargo, Ilva nunca había contemplado ese objetivo.

—Pero lo necesitamos.

Sin él no habríamos avanzado tanto.

Si lo perdemos, la guerra volverá a torcerse y la gente culpará a Luc.

Ilva sonrió, ladina.

—Afortunadamente, en los últimos meses Ferron se ha convertido en pieza clave entre los inmarcesibles.

Cuando desaparezca sin dejar rastro, se generará el caos en sus filas.

—No puedes hacer esto —repitió Helena.

—Estoy intentando salvar a todo el mundo, Marino. —La voz de Ilva se rompió de la emoción—.

Y eso te incluye a ti.

Por mucho que lo hayas idealizado, Kaine Ferron no es una persona, sino un monstruo. —Ilva se llevó la mano al corazón, un gesto que solía reservar para hablar de Apollo—.

Deberíamos haberlo eliminado a él y a su familia hace tiempo, pero a Pol le preocupaba la reacción de los gremios.

A pesar de las sospechas que rodearon su nacimiento, dejó que ese chico estudiara en la Academia, y mira cómo le pagó su generosidad.

No cometeré el mismo error con Luc.

—Ilva, por favor, puedo conseguir que me sea leal.

Solo necesito tiempo.

La mujer la miró fijamente.

—¿Estás eligiendo a Ferron antes que a Luc?

¿Vas a renunciar a los votos que hiciste?

La pregunta la dejó helada.

—No —repuso rápidamente—.

No —repitió con la voz quebrada—.

Soy leal a la causa, pero… —tragó saliva varias veces—, si tuviera alguna prueba de que me es leal, de que hará todo lo que le pidáis, ¿permitirías que siguiera con vida?

Si no lo consigo, te juro que lo… lo mataré yo misma.

Porque, si es leal, podría sernos de utilidad.

Por favor, Ilva.

La mano derecha de Luc dejó escapar un suspiro; parecía cansada.

—Si eres capaz de poner a Ferron de rodillas, si consigues que se arrastre y esté dispuesto a hacer cualquier cosa, te dejo quedártelo.

Te doy un mes. —Luego negó con la cabeza—.

Pero sé sincera contigo misma.

La gente como él no sabe lo que es la lealtad.

Los Ferron son tan corruptos como el hierro que tanto aprecian.

Helena sintió un nudo en la garganta que apenas le dejaba hablar.

—Lo conseguiré, sea como sea.

Terminaré el trabajo.

Dile a Crowther que no envíe esa documentación.

Ilva apoyó los codos en el escritorio y la cadena del amuleto vacío quedó colgando entre sus dedos.

—Tienes un mes, Marino.

CHAPTER 46

Decembris 1786

CAPÍTULO 46

A MONTH.

Diciembris 1786

THE DAYS FELT BRANDED INTO HER bones.

Un mes.

Helena couldn’t sleep that night.

Fue como si lo hubieran grabado a fuego en los huesos.

The future haunted her.

Aquella noche, Helena no pudo conciliar el sueño.

There was an Ember Service before first light as Falcon Matias consecrated the coming year to Sol’s guidance, and then Helena began her hospital shift.

La atormentaba el futuro.

She felt cornered, as if the world were closing in, and there was no escape.

Antes del amanecer, asistió a una misa de ascuas en la que el falcón Matias consagró el año nuevo a las manos de Sol y, cuando terminó, se fue a trabajar al hospital.

No one to turn to.

Se sentía acorralada, como si el mundo se cerrase a su alrededor y no tuviera escapatoria ni a nadie a quien recurrir.

She tried to push her dread down using animancy, but it consumed her utterly; every thought led to the same despair.

Trató de aplacar sus miedos mediante la animancia, pero aquella práctica le consumía demasiadas fuerzas y acabó sumida en la desesperación.

When her shift was over, she went to the desk to see if she could perhaps stay on for the next one.

Cuando terminó su turno, fue a la oficina para ver si podía quedarse durante el siguiente.

Surely someone would rather celebrate solstice, and Helena could keep busy.

Lo más probable era que todos prefirieran celebrar el solsticio, y a Helena le convenía mantenerse ocupada.

Purnell was on duty at the hospital desk, wearing a pin with SOFIA P etched into it.

En el escritorio de la oficina se encontraba Purnell, tras un letrero que rezaba Sofia P.

Helena tensed at the sight of her, and before she could speak, Purnell held out a slip of paper.

Helena se puso en tensión nada más verla, pero, antes de que pudiese decir algo, Purnell le entregó un folio.

“The steward said to give you this when your shift was over.”

—Ilva Holdfast me pidió que te diera esto al acabar el turno.

Helena hesitated a moment before reading it.

Helena dudó un instante antes de leerlo.

There were only a few words.

Solo había unas líneas.

As thanks for all her hard work, Ilva had ensured Helena could have a few hours off to attend the solstice celebrations at Solis Splendour.

Como agradecimiento por su esfuerzo, Ilva le concedía unas horas libres para que acudiera a la fiesta del solsticio de Solis Splendor.

Luc would be present and happy to see her.

Luc estaría allí y deseaba verla.

Rhea was expecting her.

Rhea también quería que asistiera.

Helena stared dully at the obvious manipulation.

Helena contempló el papel sin inmutarse.

Ilva was losing her touch.

Ahora veía claramente la manipulación.

Or perhaps Helena was finally getting wise to her.

Ilva estaba perdiendo facultades.

She put on the green wool pullover that Rhea had gifted her over her uniform and made her way to Solis Splendour.

O tal vez Helena empezaba a darse cuenta de cómo era en realidad.

It was already dark, the year and the sun both preparing for rebirth.

Se puso sobre el uniforme el jersey de lana verde que Rhea le había regalado y se encaminó hacia Solis Splendor.

In four weeks, Kaine would be dead.

Ya era de noche y tanto el año como el sol se estaban preparando para renacer.

She barely knocked on the door, but it swung immediately open, and warmth and light, music and laughter all spilled out.

En cuatro semanas, Kaine estaría muerto.

She squinted, dazed.

Cuando iba a llamar, la puerta se abrió de par en par, derramando calor y luz, música y carcajadas.

Had she knocked at the wrong house?

Helena tuvo que entrecerrar los ojos por la sorpresa.

“Marino?

¿Se había equivocado de casa?

I didn’t know you were coming.” It was Alister, one of the boys from Luc’s unit.

—¿Marino?

He held the door for her. “Come in.

No sabía que venías. —Se trataba de Alister, uno de los soldados del pelotón de Luc—.

We’ve got loads of food.”

Pasa, pasa.

Helena entered, feeling as if she’d somehow stepped out of reality into a dreamlike version of Solis Splendour.

Hay un montón de comida.

The house was lively, decorated with tinsel and streamers and bits of evergreen, and the children ran through like a pack of feral puppies.

Nada más entrar, sintió que había escapado de la realidad para adentrarse en una versión de ensueño de Solis Splendor.

She knew the faces, recognised people, but everything felt different.

La casa rebosaba vida, adornada con guirnaldas, serpentinas y ramas de hojas verdes; los niños correteaban por todas partes como una jauría de cachorros salvajes.

Wrong.

Helena sabía quiénes eran, reconocía a cada una de esas personas.

Why was everyone so happy?

Sin embargo, algo se le antojaba extraño, como si estuviera… mal.

There was music from a gramophone and drunken laughter filling the next room.

¿Por qué estaban todos tan contentos?

A mug of mulled wine was shoved into her hands before she’d gotten across the room, and she sipped it on instinct.

En la primera habitación, la música fluía desde un gramófono, acompañada de risas ebrias.

It was warm and sweet, instead of sour and watery from being stretched.

Apenas había atravesado la sala cuando alguien le puso una taza de vino especiado en las manos.

The signs of their access to the ports and river trade were everywhere, but all she could think was Kaine did this, remembering the wounds lacerating his back, the dead tissue rotting and poisoning him.

Le dio un sorbo; estaba caliente y dulce.

He’d been gaunt and grey, paper-thin, and he’d just wanted to know if it worked.

No se parecía en nada al vino agrio y aguado del racionamiento.

The room blurred.

Era evidente que habían recuperado los puertos y que el comercio volvía a surcar el río.

She wandered in a daze until she caught sight of Titus Bayard sitting cross-legged on the floor, peeling oranges.

Aun así, lo único en lo que Helena podía pensar era: «Kaine os ha conseguido todo esto», y, al mismo tiempo, recordaba las heridas lacerantes de su espalda, el tejido muerto que lo había envenenado.

They must have come all the way from the southern coast.

A pesar de estar demacrado, gris y a punto de desfallecer, lo primero que quiso saber era si había funcionado.

There was a small mountain of peeled fruit on the table beside him.

La vista se le nubló.

Helena searched for other familiar faces.

Caminó sin fijarse en nada hasta que reconoció a Titus Bayard sentado en el suelo con las piernas cruzadas.

Lila was sitting crammed in an armchair with Soren, who was wearing the expression of a beleaguered cat.

Estaba pelando naranjas; debían de haberlas traído de la costa sureña.

Ever since her injury, Soren let her get away with anything.

En la mesa que tenía al lado había toda una montaña de mondas de naranja.

Lila had made a complete, and stunningly rapid, recovery and acted as if the entire thing had been overblown.

Helena buscó otras caras que le resultaran familiares.

When she’d learned about Luc’s attempts to disregard orders, they’d had an explosive argument.

Lila y Soren estaban apretujados en un mismo sillón; este último tenía cara de pocos amigos.

Helena had only heard gossip, but it had been bad enough that the entire unit had been held on reserve for several weeks until things simmered down.

Desde que estuvo en el hospital, Soren dejaba que su hermana se saliera con la suya en todo momento.

Things seemed better now but Helena couldn’t help but feel that somehow Soren was the one most irrevocably damaged by the attack.

Lila se había recuperado por completo a gran velocidad y se comportaba como si todos hubieran exagerado lo ocurrido.

One of the unavoidable bits of Bayard lore that Helena had heard many times over the years was the fact that Soren was older than Lila.

Cuando se enteró de que Luc había intentado saltarse las órdenes, discutieron acaloradamente.

Twenty minutes the elder twin.

Helena solo lo sabía de oídas, pero el asunto debió de ser grave, porque el pelotón se mantuvo en la reserva durante semanas hasta que se calmaron los ánimos.

The disparity of age was treated as gravely significant in matters of hierarchy in times past.

Ahora parecía que todo iba mejor, aunque Helena no pudo evitar sentir que el ataque, de alguna forma, había perjudicado a Soren más que a los demás.

It was mostly a joke, but Helena suspected that Soren took it more seriously than he let on.

Uno de los detalles que se recalcaban siempre que se contaba la historia de los Bayard era que Soren era mayor que Lila.

Paladin primary or not, Lila wasn’t only his twin, she was his younger sister.

Había nacido veinte minutos antes que ella.

Luc was playing cards with a group of convalescent soldiers, and Lila and Soren both watched him, Lila’s leg swinging back and forth, the gears making a soft click, click, click.

En el pasado, esa diferencia de edad fue una cuestión de vital importancia para establecer una jerarquía.

Helena knelt down next to Titus, trying to complete her list of obligations quickly so she could leave.

Aunque se comentaba como una broma, Helena sospechaba que Soren se lo tomaba más en serio de lo que parecía.

The mood of the house was so dissonant it made her feel ill.

Independientemente de su puesto como paladina primera, Lila no solo era su gemela, sino también su hermana pequeña.

“Hello, Titus,” Helena said, following the script she always did. “Do you mind if I look inside your head a little bit?”

Luc estaba jugando a las cartas con un grupo de soldados convalecientes, mientras que Lila y Soren se limitaban a observar en silencio.

He didn’t react.

Lila no paraba de mover la pierna hacia delante y hacia atrás; los engranajes de la prótesis chasqueaban al mismo ritmo: clic, clic, clic.

She slipped a glove off, touching the scar along his temple.

Helena se arrodilló junto a Titus.

She closed her eyes as she reached with her resonance, and it was all the same except Helena was not the same.

Quería tachar de la lista todo lo que se sentía obligada a hacer antes de marcharse.

Her techniques and understanding of the mind had changed in a year.

El ambiente festivo de la casa encajaba tan poco con sus ánimos que le daba náuseas.

There were patterns of energy that she had not understood the intricacies of before.

—Hola, Titus —lo saludó.

Now she could sense where her errors lay.

Siempre seguía el mismo guion—.

She had transmuted tissue without knowing how to follow the currents of energy that carried the mind through the brain matter.

¿Te importa si miro un poco dentro de tu cabeza?

Of course, Titus was often unresponsive, his mind limited; she’d hemmed him inside his own consciousness.

Titus no respondió, pero Helena se quitó un guante y posó los dedos sobre la cicatriz que lucía en la sien.

The connection between them snapped as Titus suddenly shoved her hand away.

Cerró los ojos para concentrarse en la resonancia.

His face was contorted, the orange in his hand crushed into pulp.

Todo seguía igual, salvo ella misma.

He shook his head several times as if trying to clear it.

Durante el último año había mejorado su técnica y comprendía mejor cómo funcionaba la mente.

Helena stared at him, her eyes searching as he scooted away from her, his expression unsettled.

Había descubierto ciertos patrones de energía que antes desconocía.

She pulled her glove back on automatically.

Ahora veía en qué se había equivocado.

Was it possible that she could cure him?

Cuando transmutó el tejido no siguió esas corrientes de energía que impulsaban la consciencia a través del cerebro.

She was almost afraid to think it.

Por supuesto, Titus era incapaz de responder y tenía un cerebro limitado; Helena lo había dejado atrapado dentro de su propia consciencia.

She had to be certain before she brought the possibility to Rhea.

La conexión se rompió de repente cuando Titus le apartó la mano.

She couldn’t break her heart again.

Tenía el rostro compungido y la naranja que sostenía en la mano se había convertido en pulpa entre sus dedos.

She was startled from her thoughts at a burst of laughter.

Agitó la cabeza un par de veces como si quisiera aclarar sus pensamientos.

She slipped into another room that was quieter and less crowded, trying to collect herself in a window alcove that was cooler, the drapes creating a barrier from all the noise.

Helena lo observó, buscando algún indicio de la persona que fue, pero Titus se alejó de ella con expresión inquieta.

“Helena.”

Volvió a ponerse el guante.

She looked up to see Penny Fabien slipping into the alcove with her.

¿Sería capaz de curarlo?

“I thought it was you slipping in here,” Penny said. “Are you all right?

La idea le provocaba vértigo.

You looked upset.”

Tenía que estar segura.

Penny was a year older.

No podía darle esperanzas a Rhea para acabar rompiéndole el corazón de nuevo.

She’d been the dorm monitor for Helena’s room during their Institute days.

Un estallido de risas la sobresaltó y la hizo volver a la realidad.

“Just a bit close in there,” Helena said, looking away. “Did something happen?”

Se dirigió a una habitación en la que había menos ruido y también menos gente, y se apoyó en el alféizar de una ventana tratando de recobrar la compostura.

Penny looked at her. “What do you mean?”

Allí hacía más frío, y las cortinas amortiguaban un poco el ruido.

“Why is everyone so happy?”

—Helena.

Penny blinked with surprise. “We’re happy because the war’s almost over.”

Cuando alzó la vista, vio a Penny Fabien a su lado.

Helena stared at her in bewilderment.

—Sabía que eras tú —dijo—.

The war wasn’t almost over.

¿Te encuentras bien?

They didn’t even have a plan to win.

Tienes mala cara.

Six years of fighting for survival while waiting for a miracle that would never come.

Penny era un año mayor que ella.

“Weren’t you at the Ember Service?” Penny asked. “Falcon Matias was talking about the stages of transmutation, how each one correlates to a period in the war, and how we’re nearly at the final transformation where the soul becomes truly purified.

Había sido la responsable de la residencia de Helena cuando estaban en la Academia.

Think about it.

—Hay demasiada gente —respondió, y luego apartó la vista—.

A year ago, we were hemmed in around Headquarters, no supplies, barely enough rations to keep fighting, and now we’ve retaken the entire East Island.

¿Ha pasado algo?

The ports.

Penny la miró con curiosidad.

All because we had faith.”

—¿A qué te refieres?

Helena had not paid any attention to Matias during the service.

—¿Por qué está todo el mundo tan contento?

All she’d heard was Ilva’s voice in her ears, saying a month over and over.

Penny parpadeó, confundida.

“What?” Helena’s voice came out strangled.

—Estamos contentos porque la guerra está llegando a su fin.

A look of sympathy swept across Penny’s face. “I guess you’re not really out there at the front, are you?

Helena la miró desconcertada.

You must not have any idea.

La guerra no estaba llegando a su fin.

Things have been going so well this year.” Penny’s face was alight. “It’s because we passed the test.

Ni siquiera tenían una estrategia para ganar.

We held firm and didn’t let our fears corrupt us, and now Sol is bestowing his favour.

Llevaban seis años luchando por sobrevivir y esperando un milagro que nunca sucedería.

We can’t lose now.”

—¿No has ido a la misa de ascuas? —preguntó Penny—.

Helena flinched as if she’d been struck and stared at Penny in such abject shock that Penny’s smile faded, and a look of comprehension and discomfort suddenly swept across her face.

El falcón Matias nos ha hablado de las fases de la transmutación y cómo cada una se corresponde con un periodo de la guerra.

“Oh, right …” Penny said, wringing her hands. “I heard about what happened with you and the Council.

Estamos a punto de sufrir la última transformación, aquella en la que el alma se purifica por completo.

I’m sorry, I didn’t mean to imply anything about your soul—”

Piénsalo.

Helena’s jaw started trembling uncontrollably, and then it spread until her whole body was shaking.

Hace un año, estábamos arrinconados en el Cuartel General, no había suministros y apenas teníamos raciones para seguir luchando.

Penny stepped towards her, stroking her arm. “Don’t feel bad.

Pero ahora hemos recuperado toda la isla Este y los puertos.

I’m sure you—meant well.

Todo porque hemos mantenido la fe.

We’ve all hit points when we think anything would be worth it to make it all stop.

Helena no había escuchado ni una sola palabra de Matias durante la misa.

Just think of how much things turned around after that.

Lo único que oía era la voz de Ilva repitiendo «un mes» sin cesar.

Maybe you were—a final test for us.”

—¿Qué? —preguntó con un hilo de voz.

Helena was going insane.

Penny la miró con pena.

She was about to start screaming right there in the alcove.

—Supongo que, como no estás en el frente, no tienes ni idea de lo que está pasando, ¿no?

She had never imagined this possibility.

Este año nos ha ido de maravilla. —Penny estaba radiante—.

They thought the war was being won because her proposal of necromancy had been so sharply reprimanded that the Resistance passed some final spiritual test, and all the success of the last year was a reward for it?

Y eso es porque hemos superado la prueba.

Without even realising it, she’d proven their mythos.

Nos hemos mantenido firmes y no hemos permitido que el miedo nos corrompiera.

No matter what happened now, no one would ever listen to her.

Por eso, el dios Sol está remando a nuestro favor.

She was cast forever into the role of doubter, of tempter.

Ahora ya no podemos perder.

Standing there, she suddenly remembered the odd expression in Ilva’s and Crowther’s eyes as she was censured and dismissed.

Helena se encogió como si hubiera recibido un golpe y miró a Penny con tanto desprecio que la chica perdió la sonrisa y le devolvió la mirada con cierta incomodidad.

What a perfect opportunity she’d given them in that moment.

—Ah, es cierto… —dijo Penny retorciendo las manos—.

No wonder Ilva had told her the truth about Orion.

Me enteré de lo que pasó en el Consejo.

She knew that no one would ever believe Helena’s claims.

Perdona, no quería decir que tu alma estuviera…

Now Ilva wanted one last trick.

Helena estaba apretando la mandíbula tan fuerte que empezó a temblarle todo el cuerpo.

Kill Kaine.

Penny dio un paso hacia ella y le acarició suavemente el brazo.

Bury the evidence, the true means of their success.

—No te sientas mal.

Create one more miracle.

Estoy segura de que lo hiciste… con buena intención.

Helena forced herself to breathe.

Todos llegamos a un punto en el que pensamos que lo mejor es rendirse.

It came out as a choking gasp.

Pero piensa en lo mucho que todo ha mejorado desde entonces.

Penny pulled her suddenly into a tight hug.

Tal vez tú fueras… la última prueba que necesitábamos superar.

“It’s all right,” Penny was saying, as if Helena were a child who needed soothing. “We all make mistakes.

Helena sintió que perdía el control.

Don’t feel bad, it’s all right now.” Penny patted her back. “You know what, the real trouble is that you’re too isolated.

Estaba a punto de ponerse a gritar.

With everyone at the front and you always in the hospital, you never get to see how it really is.”

Jamás había imaginado algo así.

“I guess so,” Helena said dully. “That must be it.”

¿De verdad creían que habían tenido éxito el último año, y que estaban a punto de ganar la guerra porque la Resistencia se había negado a su propuesta de usar la nigromancia?

Penny was nodding as she stepped back. “It’s all right.

¿Pensaban que habían pasado una especie de prueba espiritual final?

You just stay with me.

Sin pretenderlo, Helena había alimentado sus fantasías.

I’ll make sure no one bothers you.”

Ahora ya daba igual lo que sucediera, nadie la escucharía.

Helena was too dazed to resist as Penny pulled her out of the alcove into another room, where Alister was currently playing the piano.

Siempre sería la que sembró la duda, la que los tentó.

Soren was now playing a card game in the corner, and Lila had disappeared.

De repente, recordó la extraña expresión que adoptaron Ilva y Crowther cuando rechazaron su idea y le pidieron que se marchara.

Several people, including Luc, were crowded around the piano singing.

Les había dado una oportunidad de oro.

Penny installed Helena on a sofa and then, after trying to coax her into joining, went over to the piano, too.

Por eso Ilva le había revelado la verdad sobre Orion.

Helena sat tense, waiting for Penny to grow distracted so she could slip away, but before she could, Luc caught sight of her and immediately left the group.

Porque sabía que nadie creería lo que Helena tuviera que decir.

He dropped onto the seat next to her. “I’m glad you’re still here.

Y, por si fuera poco, Ilva quería que hiciera algo más: matar a Kaine, enterrar las pruebas, el verdadero motivo por el que habían ganado.

I was afraid you’d snuck out already.”

Ese era su último milagro.

She gave a mute shake of her head.

Helena se obligó a respirar, pero apenas logró emitir un sollozo ahogado.

“You all right?” he asked.

Penny le dio un abrazo con todas sus fuerzas.

“Tired is all.”

—No pasa nada —le decía, como si Helena fuera una niña que necesitase calmarse—.

He leaned forward. “Your trainees not pulling their weight?”

Todos cometemos errores.

“No, they’re fine.

No tienes por qué sentirte mal.

Just—always seems to be something new to do.”

Ya ha pasado. —Penny le dio una palmadita en la espalda—.

“I don’t know, I think you like being busy.” There was a teasing note in his voice.

¿Sabes qué pasa?

Helena’s stomach clenched into a hard knot. “Maybe so,” she managed to say.

El problema es que estás muy aislada.

Soren slunk over and slid across the arm of the sofa into the space on the other side of Helena. “You two have to hide me.

Nosotros estamos en el frente, pero tú siempre estás en el hospital y no ves lo que está pasando en realidad.

Someone told Mum we were gambling.”

—Supongo que debe de ser eso —replicó Helena sin añadir nada más.

“You’re dead,” Luc said with a laugh. “Did you manage to win at least?”

Penny la soltó y asintió.

Soren shook his head mournfully. “Fuck me, why’s Lila coming over here?”

—No te preocupes.

“Language in your mother’s house,” Luc tsked, “and as your precious sister approaches.”

Quédate conmigo esta noche.

“Fuck off.”

Me aseguraré de que nadie te moleste.

Lila was headed in their direction with a large, intricate box hanging from her neck.

Helena se sentía tan aturdida que no pudo impedir que Penny la apartara de la ventana y la llevara a otra habitación donde Alister estaba tocando el piano.

She stopped in front of them. “Mum has me on photo duty.” She tapped the contraption.

Soren jugaba a las cartas en un rincón, y Lila había desaparecido.

Soren groaned.

Varios del grupo se habían reunido alrededor del piano, cantando, entre ellos Luc.

“Sit up and hold still.

Penny dejó a Helena en el sofá y, tras intentar convencerla de que la acompañara, también se colocó junto al piano.

This thing is finicky.” Lila was peering into the apparatus, adjusting lenses, shifting back and forth. “Soren, don’t you have a spine somewhere?

Helena permaneció en tensión y esperó a que Penny se distrajera lo suficiente para poder escabullirse de allí.

How do you manage to slouch in armour?

Sin embargo, no tuvo ocasión; en cuanto Luc la vio, se acercó y se sentó a su lado.

You’re folded up behind Helena like a wet noodle.

—Me alegro de que sigas aquí.

Luc, poke him, would you?”

Temía que ya te hubieras ido.

Luc reached behind Helena and obliged.

Ella no dijo nada y se limitó a negar con la cabeza.

“Much better.” Lila grinned, and Luc instantly did, too. “Right.

—¿Te encuentras bien? —preguntó su amigo.

No serious faces, it’s solstice.

—Solo estoy cansada.

Be cheery.”

Luc se acercó un poco más.

They stared at the contraption, and just before the click, Luc’s arm wrapped around Helena’s shoulders, squeezing tight.

—¿Tus aprendizas no son capaces de seguirte el ritmo?

Helena tried to force the corners of her mouth up as the camera flashed.

—No, lo hacen bien.

Luc moaned, shielding his eyes. “Sol’s light, I think I’m going blind.”

Pero… parece que siempre hay algo más que hacer.

“Soren, Mum wants a picture of you and Dad.” Lila peeled a reluctant Soren off the sofa and dragged him into the next room.

—No sé, yo creo que te gusta estar ocupada. —Había cierta ironía en su voz.

Helena watched them go and felt as though her chest were being crushed.

Helena sintió que se apretaba aún más el nudo que tenía en el estómago.

Her hands were clenched into fists so tight, the leather bit at her knuckles.

—Será eso —consiguió responder.

“Are you thinking about your father?” Luc asked quietly.

Soren se sentó en el brazo del sofá y luego se dejó caer junto a Helena.

She hadn’t been, but perhaps that was what was wrong with her.

—Tenéis que esconderme.

She should think more about all the people who were dead, whose common trait was the way their life had overlapped with hers.

Le han contado a mi madre que estaba apostando.

Whether or not vivimancy was a curse, she was becoming quite sure that she was one.

—Estás muerto —dijo Luc entre risas—.

“Hel, what’s wrong?” Luc touched her arm.

¿Has ganado al menos?

She looked at him and realised that she was being forced to choose.

Soren negó con la cabeza, apesadumbrado.

Luc or Kaine?

—Joder, ¿por qué viene Lila para acá?

She could only save one.

—Esa boca, por favor… Y encima en la casa de tu madre. —Luc chasqueó la lengua—.

She had to choose Luc, but it was going to kill her to do it.

Y con tu hermana tan cerca.

“I have to go.” She started to stand.

—Vete a la mierda.

“No, you don’t.” He wrapped his fingers around her hand. “You always say that, but I’m not letting up this time.

Lila se dirigía hacia ellos con un rectángulo enorme colgado del cuello.

Stay with us.”

Se paró delante de los tres.

He gave a teasing, pleading smile.

—Mamá me ha obligado a hacer fotos —dijo señalando el aparato.

He’d always had a terrible talent for persistence.

Soren emitió un gruñido—.

From the very start, when he’d found her crying after her first class because the lecturer’s Northern dialect was thick and spoken so quickly.

Poneos derechos y quedaos quietos.

He’d coaxed the whole thing out of her in a dusty corner of the library.

Este aparato es muy tiquismiquis —añadió Lila mientras ajustaba la lente, moviéndola hacia delante y hacia atrás—.

The next week, the lecturer had talked slower and wrote all the key terms on the board so Helena could copy them down and look them up.

Soren, ¿es que has perdido la columna vertebral?

Having Luc in her life had always felt like magic.

¿Cómo es posible que parezcas un saco de patatas con una armadura?

There’d been no reason for him to go out of his way for her, but he had, and then he kept doing it.

Estás arrugado como un fideo pasado.

He’d just picked her out on that first day and decided she was the friend he wanted.

Luc, dale un codazo, ¿quieres?

And if that required sitting for hours in the library while she did homework, even though he hated homework, that was what he’d do.

Luc metió la mano por detrás de la espalda de Helena para complacerla.

She couldn’t imagine her time at the Institute without him.

—Así está mucho mejor —dijo Lila con una sonrisa de oreja a oreja y, al instante, Luc también iluminó su rostro—.

It was like imagining the world without the sun in it.

Muy bien, no quiero ver caras largas.

“Come on now, what’s wrong?” he asked, leaning in so their heads were together.

Estamos celebrando el solsticio.

Everything.

Alegraos.

Everything was wrong and it was going to be wrong forever, and it wasn’t their fault but they were paying for it.

Miraron fijamente el aparato y, justo antes de que sonara el chasquido, Luc le pasó el brazo a Helena por encima del hombro y la acercó a él.

She couldn’t tell him that; it would be too cruel to rip everything away, to expose the lie that was his whole life when it was all he had.

Helena intentó mantener las comisuras de los labios hacia arriba hasta que el flash los deslumbró a todos.

“Everyone seems so happy,” she finally said. “It makes me afraid.”

Luc soltó un gemido y se protegió los ojos.

He nodded slowly, his worry clearing. “I know, it’s hard to believe it might be over soon.

—Por la luz de Sol, creo que me has dejado ciego.

Doesn’t feel real.” He nudged her with his shoulder. “That’s why it’s so important to have people that ground you.” He glanced towards the next room where Lila and Soren were kneeling beside their father as Rhea snapped a photo. “When it doesn’t seem possible, it helps to think about everything I’m waiting for.”

—Soren, mamá quiere que nos hagamos una foto con papá. —A regañadientes, Soren dejó que su hermana lo levantara del sofá y lo llevase a rastras a otra habitación.

Helena’s chest clenched, wondering what fantasy Luc had spun for himself to get up each day.

Helena los observó alejarse.

When she said nothing, he gave her a sidelong grin. “We’ll finally go on our trip.

Sentía como si le aplastaran el pecho.

Once everything’s over and settled, Ilva can manage a bit longer.

Tenía las manos tan apretadas que se le estaba clavando el cuero de los guantes en los nudillos.

It won’t be the big trip like we said, but if we wait for the Abeyance, we could take a fast ship to Etras and spend at least a week there before the tides come back.

—¿Estás pensando en tu padre? —preguntó Luc con delicadeza.

I’ve always wanted to see the lost cities.

Lo cierto era que no, pero tal vez ese era el problema.

I’ve still got your map on the wall.”

Debería pensar más en toda la gente que había muerto, en aquellos que lo único que tenían en común era haberse cruzado en su camino.

“That’s not going to happen, Luc,” she said, her voice low.

No sabía si la vivemancia se trataba de una maldición, pero cada vez estaba más convencida de que ella sí lo era.

Even if he had to believe in this lie, she couldn’t be a part of it.

—Hel, ¿qué te pasa? —insistió Luc rozándole el brazo.

She couldn’t live as a prop in this deceit.

Helena lo miró y supo que no tenía más remedio que elegir.

“What?”

¿Luc o Kaine?

She looked down at her gloved hands, as emptiness hollowed her lungs.

Solo podría salvar a uno.

She swallowed hard. “When this is all over, I don’t want you to think of us as friends anymore.

Tenía que elegir a Luc, pero eso haría que Kaine muriese.

I think it will be better that way for both of us.”

—Tengo que irme. —Hizo amago de levantarse.

“Why?” He looked horrified.

—No es verdad. —Luc la cogió de la mano—.

“Because I’m not your friend anymore.

Siempre dices lo mismo, pero esta vez no pienso permitirlo.

Your friend Helena Marino died in a field hospital six years ago.

Quédate con nosotros.

She doesn’t exist anymore.

Le dedicó una sonrisa arrebatadora y suplicante.

I need you to let her go.”

Luc nunca había sido demasiado perseverante.

He didn’t, though.

Desde siempre, desde que la encontró llorando al salir de su primera clase porque el profesor tenía un acento norteño muy marcado y hablaba demasiado deprisa para ella.

Luc caught her hand again.

Luc se armó de paciencia y la hizo entrar en razón en un rincón lleno de polvo de la biblioteca.

His face was stricken, and he was so beautiful.

A la semana siguiente, el profesor habló más despacio y dejó escritos en la pizarra todos los conceptos clave para que Helena pudiera anotarlos y estudiar con calma.

Even in the depth of winter, he looked limned in sunlight.

Tener a Luc en su vida siempre había sido algo mágico.

Divine or not, the Holdfasts had a look as if they were born to be immortalised in marble.

No tenía por qué molestarse en hacer todas esas cosas por ella, pero lo hacía, y las seguía haciendo.

Like the sun, born for eternity.

Desde el primer día que la conoció, decidió que quería que fuese su amiga.

Helena was not a planet or any celestial thing.

Y si eso implicaba estar sentado durante horas en la biblioteca esperando a que Helena terminara los deberes, eso hacía, a pesar de que odiaba los deberes.

She was just a human bound tight to the present, to the brevity of existence, and she could feel time running out.

Helena no era capaz de imaginar sus años en la Academia sin Luc.

“No.

Era como imaginar un mundo sin sol.

I won’t let you go,” he said. “I can’t.

—Venga, dime, ¿qué pasa? —preguntó, inclinándose hacia delante hasta que quedaron cabeza con cabeza.

Hel, just tell me what’s wrong, and I’ll fix it.

Todo iba mal.

You and me, we’re friends forever.”

Todo iba mal y seguiría así, y no era culpa suya, pero eran ellos quienes lo sufrían.

She pulled away from him, shaking her head.

No podía decirle eso, claro.

All Luc knew was Paladia, alchemy, and the Eternal Flame, with their ideals about the refinement of fire, of trials and sacrifice, the purity of suffering.

Sería demasiado cruel acabar con todo, confesar que toda su vida se había basado en una mentira.

That it would be worthwhile eventually, in the next life if not this one.

—Están tan contentos que casi me da miedo —respondió al final.

Maybe if Helena were at the front, she could believe in all that, too.

Luc asintió despacio, parecía menos preocupado.

But she’d spent every day of the last six years watching people die.

—Lo sé.

She lived in the aftermath of every battle, breathed in the devastation until she was drowning in it.

Cuesta creer que todo vaya a acabar.

Nothing and no one would ever convince her that anything noble or purifying could come from this scale of suffering.

No parece real. —Le dio un suave empujón con el hombro—.

That any rewards could ever be worth it.

Por eso es importante tener gente que te ponga los pies en la tierra. —Miró a la habitación de al lado, donde Lila y Soren estaban arrodillados junto a su padre.

To trick people into embracing it was cruelty.

Rhea les estaba haciendo una foto—.

But how could she tell Luc that?

Cuando me parece imposible, me ayuda pensar en todo lo que me espera en la vida.

That none of it had ever meant anything.

Helena sintió una presión en el pecho y se preguntó a qué fantasía se aferraría Luc para despertarse cada mañana.

That the miracles he believed in were mere sleights of hand, bought and paid for with betrayal.

Como no dijo nada, su amigo le dedicó una sonrisa traviesa.

She couldn’t.

—Nos iremos de viaje, como dijimos.

“If I was ever your friend, let me go now.” She jerked her hand free and fled the house.

Cuando la guerra acabe y todo vuelva a su cauce, a Ilva no le importará seguir gestionándolo todo un poco más.

Her heart was beating so hard, it hurt.

No podremos hacer el viaje largo que planeamos, pero, si esperamos a la época de sublimación, podemos visitar Etras y pasar allí una semana antes de que suba la marea.

The blood pounded in her ears until she could barely hear the wind, the cold slicing across her cheeks.

Siempre he querido ver las ciudades perdidas.

Snowflakes fell, spiralling onto the street.

Todavía tengo en la pared el mapa que me regalaste.

She paused and looked up at the sky.

—Eso no va a pasar, Luc —replicó Helena en un susurro.

It was supposed to be good luck, snow on the solstice.

Si él quería creerse esa mentira, estaba bien, pero ella no pensaba hacerlo.

A brightening of the longest night.

No podía participar en sus engaños.

She stood watching it fall until her hands and feet were numb with cold.

—¿Qué?

She wanted to stay there and freeze to death.

Helena miró los guantes que cubrían sus manos, sintiéndose hueca por dentro.

She’d read it was a gentle way to go, like falling asleep.

Tragó saliva.

The beacon of the Eternal Flame burned overhead.

—Cuando todo esto acabe, no quiero que pienses que seguiremos siendo amigos.

She turned, putting her back to it, wandering without destination.

Creo que será lo mejor para los dos.

There was nowhere to go.

—¿Por qué? —Parecía horrorizado.

Her life was so small.

—Porque ya no soy tu amiga.

Beyond the gates of the Institute, she was homeless.

La Helena Marino que conociste murió hace seis años en un hospital de campaña.

She followed the only route she knew by heart.

Ya no existe.

It was eerily still on the Outpost.

Tienes que dejarla marchar.

The snow-heavy clouds had a dim silver glow from the moons.

Pero no lo hizo.

She’d always found the Outpost so ugly next to the elegant, natural lines of the islands’ architecture, but now she found the brutality of the towering steel, concrete walls, and jutting smokestacks fitting.

De hecho, Luc volvió a tomarla de la mano.

She didn’t want to be somewhere beautiful.

Tenía la cara compungida, aunque seguía siendo tan bello como siempre.

There was no pretence on the Outpost, no ornamentation to distract the eye; it didn’t hide what it was.

Incluso en lo más crudo del invierno, parecía bañado por la luz del sol.

Which was more than she could say about the city or Institute.

Aunque no fueran una extensión de la divinidad, los Holdfast tenían un aspecto que merecía ser inmortalizado en mármol.

A lie.

Habían nacido para pasar a la eternidad, como el sol.

All of it a lie, the celestial emblems that decorated the island, all those murals and paintings of the Holdfasts, the sun always rising with them.

Helena no era un planeta ni un ser celestial.

All lies.

Solo era un ser humano atado al presente, a la brevedad de la existencia, y sentía cómo se le agotaba el tiempo.

Her face grew numb, but she couldn’t bring herself to turn back.

—No, no pienso dejarte marchar —dijo—.

She went towards the tenement.

No puedo.

The door unlocked easily even though her fingers were stiff.

Hel, dime qué te pasa.

The wind rattled the windows.

Lo arreglaré.

She sat at the table, resting her head on the edge, and closed her eyes.

Tú y yo siempre seremos amigos.

The door banged open.

Helena se apartó, sacudiendo la cabeza.

Her head shot up, and she stared in astonishment at the sight of Kaine in the doorway.

Lo único que conocía Luc era Paladia, la alquimia y la Llama Eterna, junto con sus ideales de purificación entre llamas, pruebas y sacrificios, la pureza a través del sufrimiento.

There was ice flecking his hair, lashes, and eyebrows, as if he’d come through a blizzard.

Creía que todo merecía la pena con el tiempo, en esta vida o en la otra.

His eyes found her instantly, scanning her from head to toe.

Si Helena hubiera estado en el frente, tal vez también lo habría creído.

She stared back at him, a feeling like hunger rising inside her.

Sin embargo, llevaba seis años viendo morir a gente cada día.

“What is it?” he asked as the door closed behind him. “Did something happen?”

Había presenciado las consecuencias de todas las batallas, había sufrido la devastación hasta sentir que se asfixiaba.

“How did you know I was here?”

Nada ni nadie la convencería nunca de que ese sufrimiento era algo noble o puro.

He levelled her with a hard stare. “I keep an eye on this place.”

Ninguna recompensa valía algo así.

Of course.

Engañar a las personas para que pensaran lo contrario era una crueldad.

Just because she hadn’t seen necrothralls didn’t mean they hadn’t seen her.

Pero ¿cómo iba a contárselo a Luc?

“Why are you here?” he asked again, scanning her from head to toe once more. “And unarmed, I might add.”

No podía decirle que nada había tenido sentido, que los milagros en los que creía no eran más que trucos de magia, comprados y pagados con traición.

She’d hidden the knives in the lab.

No podía hacerlo.

It would raise more questions than she could possibly answer if anyone saw them, and after Ilva’s reaction, they felt too personal to let anyone see them.

—Si alguna vez fui amiga tuya, déjame marchar. —Se zafó de su mano y salió corriendo de la casa.

“I—didn’t know I was coming here.

Le latía tan fuerte el corazón que le dolía.

I didn’t have anywhere else to go.”

La sangre le retumbaba en los oídos hasta el punto de que apenas sentía el viento ni el frío que le abofeteaba las mejillas.

“If it wasn’t on Resistance business, you shouldn’t have come.”

Estaba nevando; los copos caían en espiral a la calle.

She nodded jerkily.

Alzó la mirada al cielo.

Of course he was right.

Decían que daba buena suerte que nevara el día del solsticio.

She should have just gone to the bridge.

Algo resplandeciente en la noche más larga del año.

And jumped.

Se quedó mirando la nieve hasta que el frío le entumeció las manos y los pies.

No.

Quiso quedarse allí y morir congelada.

She blinked the thought away.

Una vez leyó que era la forma más apacible de morir, como quedarse dormido.

The whole reason Ilva and Crowther had lied to her for so long was because they knew Kaine would see straight through her.

El faro de la Llama Eterna ardía en lo más alto.

Her feelings were always stamped right on her face.

Helena le dio la espalda y deambuló sin rumbo.

“You’re right.

No tenía adónde ir.

Sorry,” she said, her voice so hoarse it was barely more than a whisper. “I’ll go.”

Su vida era muy limitada, no tenía hogar más allá de la Academia.

She moved slowly, careful not to look at him, but as she passed, his fingers hooked her arm, swinging her around.

Siguió el único camino que conocía de memoria.

Her back was against the wall as he stared her square in the face.

En el Reducto se respiraba una calma aterradora.

“What’s wrong?”

Las nubes cargadas de nieve reflejaban el brillo tenue y plateado de las lunas.

“Nothing.” She looked down quickly.

Helena siempre había creído que el Reducto era un edificio feo, sobre todo comparado con las líneas orgánicas y elegantes de la arquitectura de la isla.

His gaze was like a brand on the top of her head. “I just came because I was—worried about you.”

Sin embargo, la brutalidad del acero, los muros de hormigón y las altas chimeneas le parecían mucho más apropiados para las circunstancias actuales.

He scoffed. “Since when have you worried about me?”

No quería estar en un lugar bonito.

She looked up without thinking.

El Reducto carecía de pretensiones y decoraciones que distrajeran la vista; no ocultaba lo que era, y eso no podía decirse de la ciudad ni de la Academia.

His expression was hard.

Una mentira.

Defensive.

Todo había sido una mentira: los emblemas celestiales que engalanaban la ciudad, los murales, los retratos de los Holdfast donde siempre salía el sol… Todo mentira.

The ice in his hair had melted into tiny droplets of water that trembled, glittering like stars on his face.

Se le entumeció la cara, pero no logró convencerse de dar la vuelta.

“I don’t know,” she confessed.

Fue directa al módulo, donde la puerta se abrió con facilidad a pesar de tener los dedos rígidos.

The habit had crept up on her without her realising.

El viento hacía vibrar las ventanas.

He scoffed. “And now—what?

Se sentó a la mesa y apoyó la cabeza en el borde.

You suddenly can’t help yourself?”

Cerró los ojos.

“I came because I wanted to see you.” She realised only as she said it that it was the truth.

La puerta se abrió de golpe.

That was why she’d come.

Helena levantó la cabeza al instante y contempló con asombro que Kaine se encontraba bajo el marco de la puerta.

His throat dipped. “Why?”

Tenía nieve en el pelo, en las pestañas y en las cejas, como si hubiera atravesado una nevisca.

Her chest tightened. “I’m afraid that someday I’ll come, and you—you won’t be here.”

Sus ojos la encontraron de inmediato y la recorrieron de arriba abajo.

He went still, his eyes darting across her face.

Ella le devolvió la mirada y sintió que el deseo la consumía por dentro.

His expression wavered, something she couldn’t decipher flickering in his eyes.

—¿Qué sucede? —preguntó en cuanto cerró la puerta—.

He gave a low laugh. “Is this goodbye, then, Marino?”

¿Ha pasado algo?

The question jolted through her, and she reached out, grabbing hold of him. “No!

—¿Cómo has sabido que estaba aquí?

No.”

La miró con dureza.

A month.

—Tengo este sitio vigilado.

She swallowed hard. “I got worried, and I—didn’t have anywhere else to go.”

Cómo no.

She’d said that already.

Que no hubiera visto a los necrómatas no significaba que ellos no la hubiesen visto a ella.

She felt so stupid, so blindly trusting.

—¿Por qué estás aquí? —repitió mirándola de arriba abajo otra vez—.

And she was too late, too slow; there wasn’t enough time left.

Y desarmada, además.

His right hand rested on her shoulder, heat seeping through her.

Había escondido las dagas en el laboratorio.

She bit down on her lip, swallowing hard.

Si alguien veía que las llevaba encima, le harían preguntas que no sabría cómo responder y, después de la reacción de Ilva, las consideraba demasiado personales como para mostrarlas.

“You always have to come back,” she said. “All right?

—N-no sabía que iba a venir.

Don’t die.

No tenía adónde ir.

Promise—”

—Si no es por un asunto de la Resistencia, no deberías haber venido.

Her voice failed.

La chica se limitó a asentir.

“Marino, what’s wrong?” He tried to step back, but she wouldn’t let go.

Tenía razón, claro.

“Nothing!

Debería haber ido al puente.

I just spent a lot of time making that medical kit for you, and I did spend an hour teaching you how t-to use it, so—I think it would be really ungrateful if you—d-died.”

Y saltar desde allí.

He gave a hollow laugh and stepped closer so that his chin grazed the top of her head.

No.

His sigh was almost despairing.

Parpadeó para alejar ese pensamiento de su mente.

“All right …” he said, “but only because you asked.”

El único motivo por el que Ilva y Crowther le habían mentido todo este tiempo era porque sabían que Kaine captaba sus emociones al vuelo.

The words ran through her like a knife through the chest.

Como si tuviera sus sentimientos escritos en la cara.

She’d thought for so long that she could do anything.

—Tienes razón, lo siento —respondió con voz áspera, apenas un susurro—.

For the war.

Ya me voy.

For Luc.

Se movió con lentitud, intentando no mirarlo, pero, al pasar por su lado, Kaine la tomó del brazo y la giró.

That she had it within her to pay any price.

La dejó con la espalda contra la pared y la miró fijamente a los ojos.

Now she’d found her limit.

—¿Qué ha pasado?

Kaine wasn’t innocent, but he wouldn’t deserve what would happen to him if he was caught.

—Nada. —Se apresuró a bajar la vista.

Even if she could rip out his talisman and take it back with her, he wouldn’t be dead.

Sentía su mirada como un hierro candente sobre la cabeza—.

He’d just be in some cursed limbo inside Morrough.

Solo… solo he venido porque estaba… preocupada por ti.

His hand slipped away from her shoulder.

Kaine soltó un bufido.

He stepped back, and there was a strained look in his eyes.

—¿Desde cuándo te preocupas por mí?

“You shouldn’t have come here,” he said. “I thought there was an emergency.

Sin pensarlo, levantó la cabeza.

If you show up like this for no reason, you risk my cover.

Kaine la miraba con dureza, a la defensiva.

I have to guess whether or not I need to respond.”

El hielo se había derretido sobre su cabello en gotas que temblaban y brillaban como si tuviera estrellas en el rostro.

It wasn’t until he’d told her about Blackthorne that she’d even begun to consider the magnitude of the risk Kaine was taking.

—No lo sé —contestó con sinceridad; era algo a lo que se había acostumbrado casi sin darse cuenta.

Crowther and Ilva had kept her so focused on the danger that Kaine represented to them, she’d never considered the threat they were to him.

Kaine resopló de nuevo.

The blood drained from her head.

—¿Y ahora qué?

She’d always thought of him as so much safer than her, that she was the one taking all the risks, venturing out into enemy territory, mortal as could be.

¿No puedes evitarlo?

That wasn’t an accurate way to view it at all.

—He venido porque quería verte. —En cuanto lo dijo, se dio cuenta de que era verdad; había venido por eso.

The Resistance spies and scouts often carried cyanide pills to escape interrogation if their capture was inevitable.

El chico tragó saliva.

That wasn’t an option for him.

—¿Por qué?

Even if he ran, hid, it wouldn’t matter, because Morrough had the phylactery.

Sintió un nudo en la garganta.

He’d be far safer if he only ever sent the necrothralls, but he was here right now.

—Me da miedo venir un día y que ya… que ya no estés.

He’d come because she had.

Kaine se quedó muy quieto y la miró con detenimiento.

Why couldn’t Ilva see the significance of that?

Se le notaba indeciso, y había un brillo en sus ojos que Helena no logró descifrar.

“I’m sorry,” she said. “I won’t do it again.”

—¿Te estás despidiendo de mí, Marino? —preguntó con una sonrisa.

He looked doubtful.

La pregunta la hizo sobresaltarse.

“I swear,” she said. “If I ever come back, it’ll be legitimate.”

Lo cogió por la camisa.

He gave a sharp nod. “You’ve given your word.

—¡No! No.

I’ll trust you to keep it.”

Un mes.

Her stomach clenched.

Tragó saliva.

Don’t trust me.

—Estaba preocupada y no… no tenía adónde ir.

Don’t trust the Eternal Flame.

Ya lo había dicho.

We’re all liars.

Se sentía estúpida por haber confiado a ciegas en todo el mundo.

She gave a small nod.

Y ahora era demasiado tarde.

When he was gone, Helena stood alone.

Había tardado tanto en darse cuenta de que ya no le quedaba tiempo…

The windows were rattled by the wind, but she lingered, growing colder and colder, wondering what to do.

Kaine tenía la mano apoyada sobre su hombro, y ella notaba su calor.

Helena se mordió el labio y tragó saliva con dificultad.

—Siempre tienes que volver —afirmó—.

¿De acuerdo?

No mueras.

Prométeme… —le falló la voz.

—Marino, ¿qué ha pasado? —Intentó apartarse, pero Helena no lo permitió.

—¡Nada!

Solo es que pasé un montón de tiempo haciendo tu botiquín y estuve casi una hora enseñándote a-a usarlo, así que… creo que serías muy desconsiderado si… si te m-murieras.

A Kaine se le escapó una carcajada seca.

Acto seguido, se acercó tanto que le acarició la coronilla con la barbilla.

Soltó un suspiro que sonó algo exasperado.

—Está bien —accedió—, pero solo porque me lo pides tú.

Esas palabras la atravesaron como si le hubiera dado una puñalada en el pecho.

Durante mucho tiempo, había pensado que podría con todo.

Por la guerra.

Por Luc.

Que tenía el valor de pagar cualquier precio.

Pero ahora sabía cuál era su límite.

Kaine no era inocente, pero tampoco se merecía lo que le harían si lo pillaban.

No moriría ni aunque ella pudiera arrancarle el talismán para llevárselo.

Acabaría en una especie de limbo maldito dentro de Morrough.

Él apartó la mano de su hombro y dio un paso atrás.

Se le notaba cansado.

—No deberías haber venido aquí —repitió—.

Pensé que era una emergencia.

Si vienes sin motivo, pones en peligro mi tapadera.

Tendré que decidir si es necesario acudir o no.

Hasta que no mencionó a Blackthorne, Helena ni siquiera se había planteado lo mucho que se estaba arriesgando Kaine.

Crowther e Ilva habían insistido tanto en el peligro que él suponía que jamás había pensado en la amenaza que la Resistencia representaba para Kaine.

Sintió que se mareaba.

Siempre pensó que él estaba más a salvo que ella, que era ella la que se arriesgaba al adentrarse en territorio enemigo con un cuerpo mortal.

Sin embargo, la realidad no era así.

Los espías y exploradores que trabajaban para la Resistencia llevaban pastillas de cianuro para evitar ser interrogados si eran capturados.

Para Kaine, eso no era una opción.

Tampoco podía huir, porque Morrough tenía la filacteria.

Habría estado más seguro enviando a los necrómatas, pero había venido en persona.

Y había venido porque Helena estaba allí.

¿Cómo era posible que Ilva no entendiera lo que eso significaba?

—Lo siento —admitió Helena—.

No volveré a hacerlo.

Él no pareció creerla.

—Lo juro —insistió—.

No volveré a menos que tenga una razón de peso.

Kaine se limitó a asentir.

—Me has dado tu palabra.

Espero que la mantengas.

Sintió un nudo en el estómago. «No confíes en mí.

No confíes en la Llama Eterna.

Somos unos mentirosos».

Helena asintió.

Cuando Kaine se marchó, Helena se quedó sola en el módulo.

Las ventanas seguían vibrando por el viento, y cada vez hacía más frío, pero aun así permaneció allí, pensando qué debía hacer.

CHAPTER 47

Janua 1787

CAPÍTULO 47

WHEN HELENA RETURNED TO THE OUTPOST THE next week, the room was covered in some kind of thick drop cloth that padded the floor and bunched up around the door when she tried to push it open.

Ener 1787

Ferron was already there, his cloak and coat stripped off, dressed down, and his shirtsleeves were rolled past the elbows.

Una semana después, cuando Helena regresó al Reducto, descubrió una especie de tela gruesa que cubría todo el suelo del módulo, arrugándose a los pies de la puerta.

She froze.

Ferron ya estaba allí.

Northerners were all so pale that they nearly glowed in the wintertime, while Helena turned sallow and sickly looking without sunlight.

Se había quitado la capa y el abrigo, vestía con ropa informal y se había arremangado hasta los codos.

She missed the warm southern sun so much, sometimes her skin ached for it.

Helena se quedó inmóvil al verlo.

“I’m not training you for a battlefield,” Kaine said. “The point of all this is to ensure you have the skills to get away.

Los norteños eran tan pálidos que parecían resplandecer en invierno, mientras que la piel de Helena se tornaba macilenta y enfermiza en cuanto escaseaba el sol.

At this point, you should be fine around necrothralls as long as there aren’t too many, but if you run into one of the Undying, they will pursue, and you’ll be lucky if they only kill you.”

Echaba tanto de menos el sol del Sur que, en ocasiones, hasta su piel lo anhelaba.

She gave a stiff nod.

—No voy a entrenarte para el campo de batalla —afirmó Kaine—.

“Your reflexes are passable now, but an actual fight is different.

El objetivo de todo esto es asegurarme de que tienes las habilidades mínimas para sobrevivir.

There are no rules; it’s close and dirty.

A estas alturas, eres capaz de defenderte de los necrómatas, siempre que no sean demasiados, pero, si te encuentras con un inmarcesible, te perseguirá.

Every second it takes you to attack or to get into position is a point against you.

Y será una suerte si se limita a matarte.

Time will never be on your side.

La chica asintió.

Your sole advantage is that they’ll underestimate you, but you’ll only get that advantage once.”

—Tus reflejos han mejorado, pero una pelea de verdad es algo distinto.

Why was it that every time he uttered anything vaguely complimentary, he had to couch it with six criticisms?

No hay reglas; es contacto físico cercano y sucio.

“Right.”

Cada segundo que tardes en atacar o colocarte en posición juega en tu contra.

He looked at her sidelong. “You’re hardly built for combat or particularly strong, but you can use that to your advantage.

El tiempo nunca estará de tu lado.

Looking at you, no one will see you as a threat.

Tu única ventaja es que van a subestimarte, pero solo la tendrás una vez, en el primer golpe.

They’re likely to send thralls after you first, but if they see your abilities, you’ll be in real danger.” He gave her a once-over. “I don’t particularly fancy being extensively stabbed today, so we’ll be using practice daggers.”

¿Por qué siempre que mascullaba algo vagamente parecido a un cumplido venía acompañado de un puñado de críticas?

He picked up a set from the table, tossing them.

—De acuerdo.

Helena fumbled but caught them.

Kaine la miró de soslayo.

They were light, about the same size and weight as her set, but wooden.

—Careces de complexión de combate o de fuerza, pero puedes usar eso a tu favor.

She squeezed.

Nadie te considerará una amenaza.

It was strange, not having any resonance.

Lo más probable es que primero manden a los necrómatas, pero, en cuanto reconozcan tus habilidades, correrás un grave peligro. —La miró de arriba abajo—.

“Your goal is to either escape and knock on the wall three times—we’ll count that as getting away—or else contact enough to form a resonance channel.

Hoy no me apetece recibir una puñalada, así que usaremos dagas de práctica.

We’ll consider that a hit.

Cogió un par de la mesa y se las lanzó.

You know what to do after that.”

Helena las atrapó a duras penas.

It sounded overly simple, but it was the first time they were properly sparring.

Eran ligeras, prácticamente del mismo peso y tamaño que las suyas, pero estaban elaboradas de madera.

He probably wanted to start easy.

Apretó la empuñadura y le resultó extraño no poder usar la resonancia.

“Now, imagine you’re out in that bog you’re so partial to.

—Tu objetivo aquí es escapar y dar tres golpes en la pared; si lo logras, lo consideraremos como una huida.

The terrain is terrible, and while you were up to your knees in mud gathering frogs or something, a few necrothralls spotted you.

O también establecer un canal de resonancia mediante el contacto: eso contará como un golpe.

Since you don’t have a combat partner to cover you, while you were dealing with them, you didn’t notice the Undying approaching.

Ya sabes qué hacer si lo consigues.

He’s seen you’re a vivimancer, and his guard’s up, but he knows he’ll be rewarded for getting you alive.” He stepped towards her until their bodies were touching. “What would you do now?”

Parecía demasiado simple, aunque era la primera vez que luchaban en serio, así que quizá solo quería empezar por algo fácil.

Helena went for his chest, but rather than dodge or parry, the flat side of his hand struck her wrist.

—Bien, imagínate que te encuentras en ese lodazal que tanto te gusta.

The blow was so sudden that her grip failed, and the wooden knife plummeted towards the floor.

Es un terreno difícil y, cuando estás de rodillas en el barro cogiendo ranas o vete a saber qué, unos necrómatas te descubren.

He caught it in midair.

Como no tienes un compañero de combate que te cubra las espaldas, mientras estás luchando con ellos, no te das cuenta de que se acerca un inmarcesible. Él ya sabe que eres una vivemante y está en guardia.

Helena tried to jump back and regroup into a better defensive position, but the cloths on the floor slowed her.

Quiere entregarte con vida porque recibirá una recompensa. —Kaine se acercó hasta que sus cuerpos se rozaron—.

Bad terrain.

¿Qué harías?

Kaine’s empty hand closed around her wrist, jerking her back.

Helena apuntó al pecho, pero, en vez de esquivar el golpe o luchar, Kaine le dio en la muñeca con el canto de la mano.

The knife, now in his hand, sliced through the air towards her throat.

Fue un manotazo tan rápido que se le escapó la daga de madera. Él la atrapó antes de que cayera al suelo.

She managed to block it with her second knife, but he caught the tip of the handguard, ripping it from her fingers.

Helena retrocedió e intentó adoptar una mejor posición defensiva, pero la tela del suelo la entorpecía.

It thumped to the floor.

Un terreno difícil.

“Five seconds and you’ve already lost both knives.” He pulled her closer until she could feel his breath on her skin.

La mano de Kaine le sujetó la muñeca y la empujó hacia atrás.

She tried to shove at him.

Adelantó la mano que empuñaba la daga y puso el arma contra su garganta.

A resonance touch, that was all she needed.

Ella intentó bloquearlo con la otra mano, pero Kaine agarró la empuñadura por detrás y se la arrancó de los dedos.

Forget the knives.

La dejó caer al suelo.

His left hand, which she’d sworn had a knife in it a split second prior, was suddenly empty, and it closed around her wrist before she could lay a finger on him.

—No han pasado ni cinco segundos y ya has perdido las dos dagas —dijo, atrayéndola hacia sí de manera que su aliento le hizo cosquillas en la piel.

She tried to wrench herself free, but his grip was iron.

Helena intentó darle un empujón.

“Now I have both hands captured,” he narrated, as if she hadn’t noticed.

Solo necesitaba establecer un punto de contacto para emplear la resonancia.

She threw herself backwards, trying to wrench free.

Al infierno las dagas.

“A word of advice,” he said conversationally, not even swaying as she used all her strength and weight trying to break his grip. “Don’t leave your wrists open.

Sin embargo, la mano izquierda de Kaine, que hacía un instante Helena habría jurado que sostenía una daga, de repente estaba vacía y se cerró sobre su muñeca antes de que pudiera rozarlo siquiera.

Once I have you by the wrists, I can do practically anything to you.

Trató de zafarse, pero él la sujetaba de forma implacable.

This is much easier for me to maintain than for you to escape from.

—Ahora tienes las dos manos atadas —le explicó como si no se hubiera dado cuenta.

That rule also applies to feet.

Helena se echó hacia atrás para intentar huir.

Be careful kicking above the knee.

—Te voy a dar un consejo —comentó con voz tranquila.

If I get you by the ankle, you’ll be on the ground in seconds.

Ni siquiera parpadeó mientras ella empleaba toda su fuerza y peso para liberarse—.

Most of the Undying are guild; they weigh twice what you do.

Nunca dejes las muñecas al alcance de nadie.

Even if you manage to kill them, you’ll be trapped.

Si te cojo de las muñecas, te tengo totalmente controlada.

Stomping or kneeing is much better than kicking.

Me resulta mucho más fácil sujetarte que a ti escapar.

Stomping uses your weight, rather than relying on your momentum.

Lo mismo ocurre con los pies.

Stomp hard and go for the ankles or the sides of the knees.

No des patadas por encima de la rodilla.

Disabling is key; dislocating the knee will take longer for them to regenerate than a stab wound.

Si te atrapan por el tobillo, estarás en el suelo en un abrir y cerrar de ojos.

A knee to the groin works, too.” He grinned. “Even the liches hate that.”

La mayoría de los inmarcesibles pertenecen a los gremios, es decir, pesan el doble que tú.

Helena promptly tried to knee him, but he effortlessly sidestepped.

Incluso si consigues matarlos, podrías quedar atrapada.

“See?

Es mucho más eficaz dar pisotones o rodillazos, sobre todo pisotones, porque ahí empleas todo tu peso, no solo tu fuerza.

It’s dangerous to lose your arms.”

Da un buen pisotón y apunta con el pie a los tobillos o a las rodillas.

His lecture was getting annoying.

Lo importante es dejarlos inutilizados.

Helena stomped on his foot and kicked him in the shin.

Si les dislocas una rodilla, tardarán más en regenerarse que con una puñalada.

He grunted. “Better, but if I were trying to capture you, I would have already drowned you in the marsh until you passed out.

También puedes usar un rodillazo en la entrepierna. —Sonrió de lado—.

Or taken you by the neck and rammed your head into my knee.

Hasta los liches detestan eso.

You need to fight dirty.

Helena probó a darle un rodillazo, pero Kaine lo esquivó apartándose a un lado.

Forget every word you’ve ever heard about honour in combat.

—¿Ves?

The honour is surviving.”

Es peligroso perder los brazos.

He let go, and she stumbled back, winded already.

Helena ya estaba harta de tanto consejo y le dio un pisotón y le propinó una patada en la espinilla.

He watched her, his gaze as intent as a predator.

El chico emitió un gruñido.

A shiver ran down her spine.

—Vas mejorando.

“If you’re ever attacked, you will be outnumbered, and even if you aren’t outnumbered, you will never be as strong or resilient as the Undying.

Aunque, si quisiera capturarte, ya te habría ahogado en la ciénaga para que te desmayaras.

We don’t tire.

O te habría cogido del cuello y te habría metido un rodillazo en la cabeza.

We can keep fighting for hours, and any injury you inflict, we will recover from in minutes if not seconds.

Tienes que luchar sucio.

If they hurt you enough to slow you, you’re worse than dead.”

Olvídate de todo lo que te hayan contado sobre el honor en la batalla.

“I know,” she said, her voice hollow.

El honor es sobrevivir.

“Do whatever you have to to get away.”

Kaine la soltó de repente y ella trastabilló hacia atrás.

Helena nodded.

Estaba jadeando, y eso que apenas acababan de empezar. Él la observó con la misma intensidad que un depredador.

“Be devious.

Helena sintió un escalofrío por la espalda.

When your opponent is stronger than you, it’s crucial to use that against them.

—Si te atacan, serán más de uno, y, aunque no fuera así, tú jamás serás tan fuerte ni tan resistente como un inmarcesible.

They will underestimate you, and they’ll be angry if you manage to injure or evade them.

No nos cansamos.

There’s risk and advantage to that.

Podemos luchar durante horas y, si consigues hacernos daño, nos recuperaremos en minutos, a veces incluso segundos.

If they’re angry, they will try harder to hurt you, but they’ll also stop thinking clearly; that’ll make their attacks predictable.

Pero, si tú resultas herida, perderás velocidad, y entonces estarás peor que muerta.

In combat, there’s no difference between an angry person and a stupid one.”

—Ya lo sé —afirmó Helena con voz cansada.

He let her pick up her knife and pulled the other from his pocket, tossing it back to her.

—Haz lo que tengas que hacer para escapar.

He attacked her again.

Helena asintió.

And again.

—Sé lista.

And again.

Si tu oponente es más fuerte que tú, aprovecha esa fuerza en su contra.

Winning every time.

Van a subestimarte, así que se enfadarán si consigues hacerles daño o huir.

Despite that, he was in a bizarrely good mood.

Eso es un riesgo… y también es una ventaja.

She couldn’t for the life of her figure out why, because usually he treated her mistakes like they were personal insults.

Si se enfadan, intentarán ir a por ti, pero también dejarán de pensar con claridad y sus ataques serán más predecibles.

All she needed to do to “win” a round was to get stable contact once.

En un combate, alguien enfadado actúa como si fuera estúpido.

Anywhere.

Le permitió recuperar su daga y se sacó la otra del bolsillo para devolvérsela.

One touch.

Luego la volvió a atacar.

Or else reach a wall with a few seconds before he caught her.

Una y otra vez.

Both were impossible.

Siempre ganaba.

Kaine could disarm her without effort, ripping the knives out of her hands, tripping her, dodging her blows, and sidestepping.

Aun así, estaba de un humor excelente, algo poco habitual en él.

Then she’d make a mistake, leave herself open for an instant, and that was all he needed.

Helena no entendió a qué se debía; normalmente se tomaba sus errores como un insulto personal.

He wasn’t armed or using his resonance.

Lo único que ella tenía que hacer para «ganar» un asalto era establecer contacto.

He didn’t need to.

En cualquier parte, solo un toque.

He’d get her by one arm and twist it up behind her back or into some other helpless position, all while relentlessly criticising her, telling her all the ways she was doing things wrong, all the advantages her incompetence gave him.

O, si no, llegar a la pared unos segundos antes de que él la alcanzara.

Helena grew progressively more and more enraged, which he also noticed and seemed amused by.

Sin embargo, ambas cosas le resultaron imposibles.

“You should be using your resonance,” he said as he attacked her the twentieth time, knocking her off balance by dodging a blow.

Kaine la desarmaba sin esfuerzo, le arrebataba las dagas de las manos, la derribaba, esquivaba todos sus golpes y se echaba a un lado fácilmente cuando ella lo intentaba atacar.

With a quick sweep of his boot, he sent her to the floor.

Y, en cuanto ella cometía un error, como, por ejemplo, bajar la guardia, la atrapaba.

She tried to jump back to her feet, but he caught her by the ankle, dragging her along.

Kaine no iba armado ni estaba empleando la resonancia; no le hacía falta.

When she tried to stab him, he managed to catch both her wrists in one hand.

Le bastaba con sujetarle del brazo y retorcérselo detrás de la espalda o de cualquier otra forma que la dejara indefensa.

He pinned her wrists over her head, forcing her knives to fall from her fingers, and then he proceeded to sit on her hips.

Mientras tanto, no paraba de corregirla: le señalaba todo lo que hacía mal, todas las debilidades que podría aprovechar para vencerla.

“If I were Blackthorne, I’d slit you open and eat your organs while your heart was still beating,” he said, leaning over her.

Helena empezó a enfurecerse cada vez más, algo de lo que Kaine se percató y que pareció divertirle.

His weight had her wrists so firmly pinned down, she could feel the tiles beneath all the fabric on the floor.

—Deberías usar la resonancia —le dijo cuando la atacó por enésima vez y le hizo perder el equilibrio al esquivar un golpe.

His fingers ghosted across her stomach.

Kaine le hizo un barrido con el pie y la derribó.

A shiver ran through her gut, heat rolling through her like a wave.

Ella se incorporó con rapidez, pero él la sujetó del tobillo y la arrastró por el suelo.

“You’re terrible at hand-to-hand combat.

Cuando intentó apuñalarlo, Kaine atrapó ambas muñecas con una sola mano.

I thought your stance-work was awful, but you’re even worse at this,” he said, but his eyes were following his fingers.

La inmovilizó, llevando sus muñecas por encima de la cabeza y la obligó a soltar las dagas.

“Well, I’ve never done this before,” Helena said mutinously as she tried to wriggle free.

Acto seguido, se montó a horcajadas sobre ella.

Her heart was pounding. “I thought we’d both be fighting with weapons.”

—Si fuera Blackthorne, te abriría en canal y me comería tus órganos mientras tu corazón aún late —afirmó inclinándose sobre ella.

He laughed. “Why would I need a weapon?

El peso que ejercía sobre sus brazos la mantenía tan clavada en el suelo que podía notar las frías baldosas a través de la tela.

You can’t even beat me when I’m empty-handed.”

Entonces Kaine le rozó el vientre con los dedos.

She frowned at him. “Why are you in such a good mood?”

Helena sintió un escalofrío interno y un calor que le recorrió todo el cuerpo.

He quirked an eyebrow and stood, extending a hand to help her up. “Do you prefer me angry?”

—Se te da fatal el combate cuerpo a cuerpo.

She ignored the question but watched him warily.

Pensaba que las posiciones de combate no eran lo tuyo, pero esto se te da aún peor —dijo, sin apartar la mirada de sus propios dedos.

He still seemed bizarrely cheerful, despite the endless criticisms and warnings about all the ways she could be killed.

—Bueno, es algo que no he hecho nunca —repuso Helena sarcástica mientras trataba de liberarse—.

It should have come as a relief—she’d grown so used to his anger—but instead she felt on the verge of a breakdown just looking at him.

Creía que íbamos a luchar con armas.

She was running out of time.

Kaine soltó una carcajada.

Even if she could manipulate him to some degree, by taking advantage of how contrary he was, it wouldn’t be reliable.

—¿Para qué quiero armas?

That wouldn’t meet Ilva’s demands.

No puedes vencerme ni con las manos vacías.

She picked up the knives.

Helena lo miró con el ceño fruncido.

There was a throbbing pressure inside her skull.

—¿Por qué estás de tan buen humor?

She’d barely slept since the solstice.

El chico arqueó una ceja y se puso en pie.

She kept dreaming of him going mad, ripping himself apart like Basilius did but then consuming it all, eating himself endlessly like the dragon in the Ferron crest.

Le extendió una mano para ayudarla a levantarse.

His voice broke her from her thoughts. “Don’t be afraid to use your elbows.

—¿Me prefieres enfadado?

When you’re fending off a close-range attack, elbows work well.

Helena ignoró la pregunta, pero lo observó con atención.

You’re more likely to break something with your elbow than your fist.”

A pesar de todas las críticas y advertencias que le había hecho sin parar durante el combate, sobre las formas en que podría haberla matado, seguía extrañamente animado.

He lunged at her.

Debería haber sentido alivio, porque ya estaba acostumbrada a su rabia, pero en cambio sentía que estaba a punto de derrumbarse solo con mirarlo.

Rather than bolt, she moved towards him, sidestepping at the last minute.

Se estaba quedando sin tiempo.

He pivoted, but she’d already gotten him in the leg with one of her knives.

Incluso si lograba manipularlo hasta cierto punto o se aprovechaba de lo obstinado que era, Kaine no era de fiar.

With a real knife, she would have severed a tendon and artery, enough to hobble him for a minute.

Y eso no bastaría para cumplir las exigencias de Ilva.

She tried to leap back for the next attack, but he used his remaining leg as leverage to tackle her, dragging her to the ground.

Recogió las dagas.

She tried to roll but his weight trapped her.

Sentía una presión constante en el cráneo.

Helena kicked and snarled as she tried to fight free, but his grip was relentless, blocking her hand.

Llevaba casi toda la semana sin dormir.

“If this were a real fight, I’d be very angry by now,” he said, his voice low as he slithered up her body, pinning her wrists to the floor, his torso moulded against hers.

En sus sueños, se volvía loca, y se despellejaba viva, como había hecho Basilius, y luego se devoraba a sí misma hasta el infinito, como el dragón del emblema de los Ferron.

His mouth reached the base of her neck, breath running hot across her skin.

La voz de Kaine la sacó de sus pensamientos.

She kept twisting and bucking her hips to try to break free.

—No temas usar los codos.

Kaine abruptly let go of her, shoving himself off.

En un ataque cuerpo a cuerpo, un codazo funciona muy bien.

The muscle in his jaw rippled, and his eyes were dark as he stood up, breathing heavily, a low flush in his cheeks.

Es más probable que rompas algo con el codo que con el puño.

“If you’re ever pinned down like that, I would not recommend trying to escape that way,” he said in a tight voice, turning as if catching his breath.

Se abalanzó sobre ella.

Helena was so tired, she lay there on the floor a moment longer. “How should I do it?”

Esta vez, en vez de salir corriendo, Helena fue a su encuentro y, en el último momento, se apartó.

“Like I said,” he said without turning, “elbows.

Kaine giró, pero la chica había conseguido rozarle la pierna con una de las dagas.

Target the nose and eye sockets.

De haber sido un cuchillo de verdad, le habría seccionado el tendón y la arteria, lo cual lo habría dejado inutilizado durante unos minutos.

Or go limp long enough that they get careless and let go of your wrists.

Intentó erguirse para seguir atacando, pero Kaine se impulsó con la otra pierna y la empujó contra el suelo.

Once you have a hand free, do whatever you want, liquefy their brain.

Ella intentó rodar sobre sí misma, pero estaba atrapada bajo su cuerpo.

Just don’t—squirm.”

Pataleó y arañó para liberarse, pero la tenía sujeta por las manos de una forma implacable.

She was following now.

—Si estuviésemos peleando de verdad, ahora mismo estaría muy enfadado —dijo con voz grave mientras se le echaba encima y apretaba sus muñecas contra el suelo.

She immediately sat up. “Noted.”

Sus torsos encajaron a la perfección y la boca de Kaine descendió hasta el hueco del cuello de Helena, que notó su aliento cálido sobre la piel.

“Again.” He’d turned back and attacked her before she’d gotten her knives back.

Ella siguió resistiéndose, arqueando las caderas para liberarse de su agarre.

When she left the Outpost, her whole body was aching.

Kaine la soltó de inmediato y se puso en pie entre jadeos.

She paused on the bridge to heal the bruises so that she could walk normally before reaching a checkpoint.

Tenía la mandíbula apretada y los ojos oscurecidos, y estaba algo ruborizado.

She found a few books on hand-to-hand combat in the library and read them diligently.

—Si alguna vez te sujetan así, no intentes escapar de esa forma —se limitó a decir, y se dio la vuelta como si quisiera recuperar el aliento.

She reviewed all her notes about Kaine, their interactions, his words, his tells, the things he said and all the things he didn’t, trying to understand him.

Helena estaba tan cansada que permaneció en el suelo un rato más.

All the time she’d spent with Crowther, dissecting his behaviour, and yet she still had no idea what any of it meant.

—¿Y cómo lo hago?

What could Kaine possibly want that could ever be worth this much risk?

—Tal como te he dicho: usa los codos —replicó sin girarse—.

She didn’t see the ambition or hunger for power that Crowther and Ilva were so convinced he possessed, but she had no alternative explanation for his choices.

Apunta a la nariz o a los ojos.

Everyone who’d returned to Headquarters for solstice had gone again, the heroes off to reclaim more of their city.

O quédate quieta el tiempo suficiente para que se descuiden y te suelten las muñecas.

There was no one to notice the strange hours Helena spent flitting between the hospital and the lab like a ghost.

En cuanto tengas una mano libre, haz lo que quieras, fríeles el cerebro si hace falta.

Each time she went back to the Outpost, they continued with hand-to-hand combat, her armed and him empty-handed, as he demonstrated technique after technique for disabling and killing the Undying.

Pero no te… retuerzas.

She wished he’d stop.

Ya lo estaba entendiendo.

“Is there any point in training you if you aren’t even paying attention?” he said, irritated at last after he’d disarmed her for the tenth time without effort.

Se incorporó de inmediato.

Helena retrieved the wooden knife from the floor automatically. “I just don’t see the point, if I’m being honest.

—De acuerdo.

If I’m attacked by one of the Undying, I doubt I’ll survive it.

—Otra vez. —Se dio la vuelta para atacar antes de que le diera tiempo a recuperar las dagas.

If I do, I’ll probably be so badly injured there won’t be any point in it.”

Cuando por fin se marchó del Reducto, a Helena le dolía todo el cuerpo.

He shifted his stance, eyes narrowing. “What’s wrong?”

Se detuvo en el puente para curarse los moratones y así caminar con normalidad cuando llegara al puesto de control.

“I’m tired,” she said, staring at the floor. “I’m tired of this war.

En la biblioteca encontró algunos libros sobre el combate cuerpo a cuerpo y los leyó de principio a fin.

I’m tired of trying to save people and watching them die anyway, or saving them only to watch them die later—in a worse way.

Repasó mentalmente todo lo que sabía sobre Kaine, las interacciones que habían tenido, sus palabras, sus gestos, lo que había dicho y lo que no.

It’s the same cycle, over and over.

Quería entenderlo.

I don’t know how to get out, and I don’t know how to keep going, either.”

Después de todo el tiempo que había pasado con Crowther analizando su comportamiento, todavía no tenía ni idea de qué significaba lo que hacía.

“I thought you’d do anything for Holdfast.” He was pacing the room.

¿Qué podría querer Kaine que justificase tantos riesgos?

“The price keeps getting higher,” she said quietly. “I don’t know if I can keep paying it.”

Por mucho que Crowther e Ilva insistieran en que solo era una persona ambiciosa y hambrienta de poder, Helena no lo veía así.

He stilled. “I suppose even martyrs have limits.”

Aunque tampoco tenía otra explicación.

She glanced up, glimpsing for a moment the intent way that he watched her when she wasn’t looking.

En el Cuartel General, quienes habían regresado para el solsticio ya se habían marchado de nuevo.

She wasn’t imagining it.

Los héroes tenían que reconquistar más zonas de la ciudad.

It was there, just below the surface.

Nadie se dio cuenta de las horas intempestivas que pasaba Helena yendo del hospital al laboratorio como un fantasma.

There was a want in him that practically shone in his eyes.

Cada vez que volvía al Reducto, retomaban las clases de combate cuerpo a cuerpo.

But he refused to give in.

Ella iba armada y él con las manos vacías, como si quisiera enseñarle todas las técnicas para desarmar y matar a los inmarcesibles.

Whenever she tried to beckon, to tempt him across the line he’d drawn, his malice surfaced, vicious as a serrated blade.

Helena deseó que dejara de hacerlo.

He was always cruellest when he was vulnerable.

—¿Qué sentido tiene que te enseñe si no me estás prestando atención? —exclamó irritado cuando la desarmó sin esforzarse una vez más.

Lately he’d hardly been cruel at all, which told her everything about her chances now.

Helena recogió el cuchillo de madera del suelo.

Perhaps if she’d been more dogged, she would have found a way to push through the pain, but he always seemed to know how to hurt her most.

—Es que no le veo la utilidad, sinceramente.

She had to do this, though.

Si me ataca un inmarcesible, dudo que vaya a sobrevivir.

She drew a deep breath, shaking her head, trying to focus. “Just an off day,” she said. “I’m fine now.”

Y, si lo consigo, seguramente esté tan herida que todo esto carecerá de sentido.

She retrieved her knife, and he lunged without warning.

Kaine cambió de postura y la miró con los ojos entornados.

She sidestepped, using her free hand to try shoving him past her, but he easily evaded her.

—¿Qué sucede?

With lightning speed his hand caught her wrist.

—Estoy cansada —confesó Helena con la vista clavada en el suelo—.

Her first knife dropped.

Estoy cansada de la guerra.

She pulled out the second, managing to elbow him in the ribs, and wrench herself free.

Estoy cansada de intentar salvar vidas y no conseguirlo, o de salvarlos para verlos morir más tarde de una forma más sangrienta aún.

She snatched the larger knife up off the ground as she got back into a defensive position, ready as he closed in again.

Es un bucle infinito, lo mismo una y otra vez.

He grabbed her by the arm when she stabbed at him, ripping the larger knife out of her grip again.

No sé cómo salir de él, pero tampoco sé cómo seguir haciéndolo.

She attempted to hook her foot behind his ankle, but he swept back and dodged, getting her arm twisted behind her back.

—Creía que harías lo que fuera por Holdfast —dijo Kaine mientras caminaba de un lado a otro de la habitación.

He liked that trick, it was almost predictable, and his hold always just marginally loosened as his grip rotated.

—El precio es cada vez más alto —admitió ella en voz baja—.

She lunged, breaking free, experiencing a flash of triumph before realising he’d let her go.

No sé si puedo seguir pagándolo.

Using the momentum of her escape, he spun her, caught her ankle with his boot, and slammed her to the floor.

Kaine se detuvo en seco.

The wind was knocked from her lungs, and she lay gasping.

—Supongo que hasta los mártires tienen un límite.

He knelt over her. “You’re still trying to win by being quick rather than clever.

Helena levantó la cabeza.

Use that brain of yours.

Por un instante, lo sorprendió mirándola de la forma en que solo lo hacía cuando pensaba que ella no lo veía.

Again.”

No lo había imaginado: estaba ahí, justo bajo la superficie.

Helena was tiring, but she managed to last longer.

El deseo que sentía Kaine se le notaba en cómo brillaban sus ojos.

She could tell she was getting the hang of it; starting to see the patterns, the openings, to begin spotting weaknesses and opportunities.

Pero no lo dejaba salir.

She wasn’t fast enough to exploit them, but with time, she could get there.

Siempre que ella intentaba acercarse, tentarlo a cruzar esa línea que él mismo había trazado, él respondía con sarcasmo, afilado como una sierra.

She managed to knock him down twice, but he always evaded.

Siempre se mostraba más cruel cuando era vulnerable.

He tried to pin her down, and she spun to the side, using his momentum.

Últimamente apenas se había mostrado cruel con ella, lo que le dejaba claro las pocas posibilidades que tenía ahora.

They fell, tumbling across the floor until he hit the wall, and she pinned him there.

Tal vez, si Helena hubiera sido más tenaz, habría encontrado la forma de ignorar el dolor, pero Kaine siempre sabía cómo hacerle daño.

His left hand was wrapped around her throat, but she had a knife across his, and her other palm was pressed flat against his chest, her resonance humming through him.

Aun así, tenía que conseguirlo.

She could feel his heartbeat as though it were cradled in her palm.

Respiró hondo, sacudió la cabeza e intentó concentrarse.

She gave a startled laugh as they both went still.

—Solo tengo un mal día —insistió—.

Their faces were so close, they were almost touching.

Ya estoy bien.

“Just like that,” he said, panting. “Just push in.

Recuperó el cuchillo y, sin previo aviso, Kaine se abalanzó sobre ella.

It’s right there.”

La chica se hizo a un lado, aprovechando la mano que tenía libre para intentar apartarlo de un empujón, pero Kaine la esquivó con facilidad.

She looked up sharply.

En un movimiento rápido, le atrapó la muñeca y le hizo soltar la primera daga.

He was watching her, making no move to stop her.

Helena sacó la segunda, le dio un codazo en las costillas y consiguió liberarse.

Waiting.

Adoptó una postura defensiva, recogió la daga larga del suelo y se preparó para seguir luchando.

Her smile fell, and she stared at him in horror.

En cuanto se lanzó a apuñalarlo, Kaine la sujetó del brazo y volvió a desarmarla.

That bitterness in his eyes—she finally understood it.

Helena intentó hacerle una zancadilla, pero él se apartó y le retorció el brazo por detrás de la espalda.

He had been waiting for her betrayal.

Le encantaba hacer eso, se había vuelto casi predecible.

This was what held him back.

Además, siempre relajaba el agarre justo antes de hacer el giro.

He’d known from the beginning, before the possibility had ever occurred to her, and he’d trained her anyway.

Helena arremetió hacia delante y se zafó.

She didn’t need a book or Crowther to tell her what the expression on his face meant.

Por un momento, disfrutó de la sensación de triunfo, pero enseguida comprendió que él la había soltado.

She could feel it.

Aprovechándose del impulso de su arremetida, Kaine la hizo girar, la agarró por la bota y la lanzó contra el suelo.

His hand was warm against her throat, and his thumb ran slowly along the scar below her jaw.

Helena notó que se le escapaba el aire de los pulmones y se quedó jadeando.

She leaned closer, her hand sliding up from his chest to his shoulder to pull him forward and kiss him.

Kaine se arrodilló a su lado.

It was not a slow, sweet kiss.

—Sigues intentando ganarme en rapidez en vez de con inteligencia.

It was not a kiss caused by alcohol or insecurity.

Usa ese cerebro que tienes.

It was born of rage, despair, and desire so hot, it threatened to burn her into oblivion.

Otra vez.

It was possibly a kiss goodbye.

Helena estaba exhausta, pero continuó luchando.

She wanted him to know.

Sabía que estaba empezando a entenderlo: veía patrones, oportunidades, se fijaba en las debilidades.

It was real.

Aún no era lo bastante rápida para aprovecharlo, pero lo haría con el tiempo.

For her, it had always been real.

Consiguió desestabilizarlo en dos ocasiones, aunque Kaine siempre se recomponía.

He froze when their lips met.

Cuando trató de sujetarla de nuevo, Helena giró a un lado aprovechando la fuerza residual del movimiento.

She felt his hand on her shoulder and braced herself to be pushed away even as she deepened the kiss, gripping the fabric of his shirt tighter, her lips frantic.

Al final, cayeron al suelo y Kaine se golpeó contra la pared.

He wavered a moment and then something broke inside him, like a dam bursting, and Helena was drowning in him.

Ella aprovechó entonces para arrinconarlo.

He wrapped his arms around her and kissed her savagely.

Aunque su contrincante tenía la mano alrededor de su garganta, Helena sostenía la daga contra la suya y la palma de su mano le sujetaba el pecho: lo estaba atravesando con su resonancia.

The heat was like wildfire.

Helena sentía el latido de su corazón como si lo tuviera en la mano.

The tension, the waiting.

Se le escapó una risa por la sorpresa y los dos se quedaron muy quietos.

Months of expectations.

Estaban tan cerca que casi rozaban sus rostros.

After being told this was what she was sent for, why she was wanted.

—Y ya está —concluyó Kaine respirando con dificultad—.

All a ruse.

Atraviésame, ahí mismo.

A feint to conceal his true motive.

Ella levantó la cabeza y lo miró intensamente.

Demanding her had been the same trick of misdirection he taught her to use to protect her memories.

Kaine la observaba en silencio, no iba a hacer nada por detenerla.

A lie, until it wasn’t.

Estaba a la espera.

Somehow she’d shifted in his estimation, manipulated her way into becoming the very obsession he’d pretended she was.

La sonrisa de Helena se desvaneció y lo contempló con horror.

His palm pressed against the side of her neck before he slid his fingers up under the braids and anchored her in place as he kissed her, twisting so that she was under him on the floor.

Esa amargura en sus ojos… Por fin lo entendía todo.

Her fingers slipped beneath the collar of his shirt, following the dip of his collarbones, the curve of his neck.

Había estado esperando a que lo traicionara.

She ran her fingers through his hair, wanting to lose herself completely in the nearness.

Por eso se había contenido.

Her fingernails bit into his shoulders.

Siempre lo había sabido, incluso antes de que Helena lo supiera, y aun así la había enseñado a luchar.

She could feel the scars on his back, the thrum of energy inside them.

No necesitaba a Crowther ni ningún libro para interpretar lo que veía en su rostro.

Despite how cold he often was, a dragon was an apt sigil for the Ferrons.

Lo notaba: era calor en el vientre, una presión en el pecho, una palpitación en las venas.

He kept walls of ice around himself, but there was fire in his heart.

Sentía la calidez de su mano en la garganta y cómo recorría con su pulgar la cicatriz que tenía bajo la mandíbula.

Her shirt ripped as he tore it out of the way.

Helena se inclinó y movió la mano del pecho al hombro.

She pulled him close, tight against her body until she could feel his skin on hers.

Lo atrajo hacia sí y lo besó.

She bit him without thinking.

No fue un beso lento ni tierno.

There was a hunger inside her that she couldn’t explain, a pit of want to taste and feel and hold and not be always, always empty.

No fue un beso impulsado por el alcohol o la inseguridad.

She wanted to curl up so tight alongside him that she vanished.

Fue un beso nacido de la rabia, la desesperación y un deseo tan ardiente que amenazaba con convertirlos en cenizas.

Her clothes were slipping out of the way as he ran his hands along her ribs and waist, kissing across her breasts, body pressed between her legs.

Seguramente fuera un beso de despedida.

Her skirts sliding up as his hand trailed along her thigh.

Quería que Kaine lo supiera, que entendiese que era real.

It happened so fast.

Para ella siempre había sido real.

She’d never thought it would be something soft or slow, but it was more like a collision, like breaking across each other.

Kaine se quedó paralizado en cuanto sus labios se encontraron.

The rush of skin and teeth as she let herself be consumed.

Helena notó cómo le ponía la mano en el hombro y pensó que la apartaría de un empujón.

He sank into her, and her heart stopped, eyes going wide.

Aun así, lo besó con más intensidad, aferrándose a su camisa, moviendo los labios con desesperación.

She bit down on her tongue so hard she tasted blood, her eyes squeezed shut.

Aunque él vaciló un instante, de repente algo en su interior cedió, como una presa que se rompe, y Helena se ahogó en él.

He paused and kissed her, his lips so searing she felt it in her bones, and she nuzzled her face against his, but it hurt.

La abrazó y le devolvió el beso con intensidad.

She’d known it might hurt if not done slowly, but she was glad it did.

Compartían una pasión desbordante.

Certain things were meant to hurt.

La tensión, la espera.

She’d seduced Kaine when it was abundantly clear that this was a line he had no desire to cross.

Los meses de anticipación.

She had pushed and persisted and done it anyway, because she was desperate.

Después de que le dijeran que había venido para esto, que solo la quería por esto.

That should hurt.

Era un truco que escondía sus verdaderos motivos.

His frame practically enveloped her, his lips nipping at her hairline.

Cuando Kaine exigió que fuera ella quien acudiese, había utilizado el mismo juego de distracción que le había enseñado a ella para proteger sus recuerdos.

His arms wrapped around her shoulders, holding her tight against himself.

Una mentira…, hasta que dejó de serlo.

She forced her eyes open, wanting a glimpse of what he felt in that moment.

De algún modo, Helena no había respondido a sus expectativas, y aun así lo había manipulado hasta convertirse en la obsesión que él solo había fingido tener.

Even now, his jaw was tense.

Kaine le rodeó el cuello con su manos y luego deslizó los dedos entre sus trenzas sin parar de besarla.

His expression guarded.

Al final, terminó colocado encima de ella, sobre el suelo.

His mouth held in that hard, flat line.

Helena introdujo sus dedos por debajo de su camisa, recorriendo el hueco de sus clavículas y la curva de su cuello.

But his eyes …

Le pasó la mano por el cabello y quiso perderse por completo en esta intimidad.

She could tell—

Después, le clavó las uñas en sus hombros mientras sentía las cicatrices de su espalda, percibiendo cómo vibraba la energía en su interior.

He was hers.

Aunque en ocasiones se mostrara frío, un dragón era un símbolo perfecto para los Ferron: levantaba muros de hielo a su alrededor, pero había fuego en su corazón.

The realisation broke her heart.

Kaine le arrancó la camisa de un tirón.

Kaine dropped his head against her shoulder, moaning into her skin, pulling her closer, and then suddenly, it wasn’t merely a pleasure he was taking in her.

Helena lo atrajo hasta que sus cuerpos se encontraron piel con piel.

Heat came to life inside her, her sense of control untethering as it threatened to engulf her.

Lo mordió sin pensar, impulsada por una voracidad insaciable que no conseguía entender, un hambre de sentimiento, de cercanía, de dejar de sentirse vacía.

But shame and guilt rose equally quick, cold and bitter as seawater, until she was on the verge of sundering.

Quería acurrucarse en su cuerpo hasta fundirse con él.

His body shook.

La ropa de Helena fue desapareciendo a medida que las manos de Kaine recorrían sus costillas, su cintura.

He gave a low groan, slumping, arms still around her.

La besó en los pechos, presionando el cuerpo contra sus piernas, acariciándole el muslo mientras le subía la falda.

His breath dragged across her skin as he panted, pressing a kiss on her bare shoulder.

Todo ocurrió muy deprisa.

Helena lay still, the weight of his body against her, suddenly aware of the cold radiating from the floor.

Helena nunca había creído que sería tierno o pausado, pero fue como una colisión, como si ambos se estrellaran.

The dirt and gravel and rough cloths that bit against her skin, rubbing it raw.

Un alud de piel y dientes que la arrasó.

The only thing she could think of was how relieved she was that it was over before anything else had happened.

Cuando Kaine se introdujo en su cuerpo, el corazón de Helena se detuvo por un instante.

Even whores were not so low as to find pleasure in their work the way she nearly had.

Abrió los ojos de par en par.

She tried to lie still and not tremble.

Se mordió la lengua con tanta fuerza que saboreó la sangre.

Kaine’s body and breath were the only warmth in that cold place.

Los cerró de nuevo, apretándolos. Él se detuvo y la besó con una pasión tan honda que la atravesó hasta los huesos.

Then he went rigid and shoved himself away.

Helena apoyó el rostro contra el suyo, pero el dolor seguía ahí.

His expression was drawn, and he didn’t even look at her as he scrambled off, pulling his clothes back on.

Sabía que, si no se hacía poco a poco, le dolería.

Helena slowly sat up, watching him because she didn’t know what else she was supposed to do.

Y aun así lo prefirió de esa manera.

He was growing paler and paler as he re-dressed.

Había cosas que, sencillamente, tenían que doler.

His expression disbelieving.

Había seducido a Kaine sabiendo perfectamente que era una línea que él no quería cruzar.

“Fuck—” he muttered, dragging a hand through his hair before he pulled his shirt back on.

Había insistido una y otra vez hasta lograrlo, porque estaba desesperada.

His breathing was growing unsteady.

Se merecía ese dolor.

When his shirt was on, he fumbled for the buttons, and when he found some missing, he seemed blindsided.

El cuerpo de Kaine la cubría por completo; sus labios le rozaban el nacimiento de su cabello.

He clamped a hand over his mouth as if he were about to be sick.

Le rodeó los hombros con sus brazos y la sostuvo contra su pecho.

His throat dipped, and he closed his eyes.

Helena abrió los ojos.

He drew a deep breath before he turned to face her, his expression cold.

Quería saber cómo se sentía.

He only looked at her face for an instant before his eyes dropped down, and the little colour remaining in his face vanished.

Incluso en ese momento tenía la mandíbula tensa y estaba en guardia.

“You—were you a virgin?”

Su boca estaba fruncida en una fina línea.

Helena looked down.

Pero sus ojos…

There was blood smeared at the top of her inner thigh.

En ese momento, Helena lo comprendió.

No wonder it had hurt.

Era suyo.

She pressed her knees together instantly and shoved her skirts farther. “It was assumed that was how you’d want me,” she said, trying not to think about everything the question insinuated.

Y darse cuenta de ello le rompió el corazón.

For a respectable girl to lose her virginity was to give up everything, a career, education, alchemy.

Kaine dejó caer la cabeza contra su hombro y gimió sobre su piel, acercándola más, y, de repente, el acto dejó de ser placentero solo para él.

Only virgins were given Lumithia’s grace.

Helena sintió el calor extendiéndose en su interior, mientras su autocontrol desaparecía completamente.

If Helena were somebody of note, Kaine would be expected to marry her now.

Pero al mismo tiempo surgieron la vergüenza y la culpa, frías y amargas como el agua del mar, hasta que llegó al borde del desgarro.

An indiscretion like this was the reason for his parents’ marriage after all.

Kaine se estremeció.

Clearly he’d never considered her as belonging in that category.

Emitió un gemido grave y se relajó, sin dejar de abrazarla.

Her lungs shrivelled inside her chest.

Su respiración le rozó la piel mientras le dejaba un beso en el hombro desnudo.

“I—” His voice failed him. “I—I would have been gentler—if I’d known.”

Ella permaneció quieta, sintiendo el peso de Kaine encima.

She drew her legs closer, as if being smaller would shield her from being so seen.

De repente era consciente de lo frío que estaba el suelo.

“I didn’t really want you to be,” she said quietly.

La tierra, la gravilla y la tela áspera le arañaban la piel hasta dejársela en carne viva.

Her hands shook as she tried to get her clothes back on.

Lo único en lo que pensaba era el alivio que sentía de que todo hubiese terminado antes de que pasara algo más.

His mouth closed then, and the room went still.

Ni siquiera las prostitutas caían tan bajo como para deleitarse de su trabajo como ella había estado a punto de hacer.

She could feel the change in the air between them.

Intentó mantenerse quieta, sin temblar.

But she didn’t understand why it mattered, why this was the line he’d drawn.

El cuerpo de Kaine y sus jadeos eran lo único que le proporcionaba calor en ese lugar tan frío.

The array must be part of it.

Pero entonces él se apartó con rigidez.

Just after he was healed and fully internalising its effects, he’d kissed her.

Tenía el rostro desencajado y, sin mirarla siquiera, se puso en pie y comenzó a vestirse.

Wanted her.

Helena se incorporó poco a poco, observándolo, sin saber qué tenía que hacer.

It had created a crossroads for him; that was why he’d stayed away for so long after that.

Kaine cada vez estaba más pálido, su semblante era de incredulidad.

Perhaps giving in, even once, was enough to tip the scales.

—Joder… —murmulló pasándose la mano por el pelo.

Perhaps he couldn’t change course now; he’d made his choice.

Después se puso la camisa.

Obsessive and possessive.

Empezaba a respirar con dificultad.

She had him.

En cuando tuvo la camisa puesta, intentó abrocharse los botones con torpeza y, cuando descubrió que le faltaba uno, se quedó paralizado.

If she was smart enough to leverage it.

Se llevó una mano a la boca como si estuviera a punto de vomitar.

On his knees, ready to do anything, Ilva had said.

Tragó saliva y cerró los ojos.

She still didn’t know how to do that, though.

Respiró hondo antes de volverse hacia Helena con un gesto de frialdad.

It wasn’t as if Ilva or Crowther would see any significance in the fact Kaine had finally slept with her; that was what they’d expected him to do from the start.

Le dedicó una mirada fugaz, pero no tardó en apartar la mirada.

She was torn between the desire to laugh and cry, her mouth twisting in a grimacing smile.

Perdía color a cada segundo.

“Well, you seem pleased,” he said in a bitter voice, his lip curling, “to have finally whored yourself.”

—¿Eras… eras virgen?

Her fingers froze, and the room went out of focus.

Helena bajó la vista.

“That was my job,” she said. “You had to have known it was my mission.”

Tenía una mancha de sangre en la parte superior del muslo.

“Of course,” he said tonelessly, looking around the room as if he couldn’t quite believe he was there.

No le extrañaba que le hubiera dolido.

His arms were hanging limp at his sides. “I just—I never thought you’d actually succeed.”

Juntó las rodillas de golpe y se bajó la falda.

There was a pause while Helena finished dressing.

—Supuse que lo preferirías así —replicó sin querer pensar en todo lo que esa frase implicaba realmente.

“I wasn’t going to betray the Resistance,” he finally said. “I was never going to.

Cuando una chica respetable perdía la virginidad, lo perdía todo: su carrera, su educación, la alquimia.

You were already losing when I made the offer, and you’re probably still going to lose now, but I never cared.

Solo las vírgenes recibían la gracia de Lumitia.

I just wanted to avenge my mother.”

Si Helena fuese alguien importante, Kaine se vería obligado a casarse con ella.

He pressed his lips into a tight line and looked down at the floor. “Unfortunately, by the time I had an opportunity to offer my services, she’d been dead too long and there was the coroner’s report saying she’d died of natural causes.

Una indiscreción así fue lo que motivó el matrimonio de sus padres.

What could I possibly have to avenge?” The bitterness in his voice and on his face was unadulterated. “I knew Crowther well enough to know he’d only consider me as valuable as the strings he could pull, so I thought I’d give him a dead end to dig himself into.”

Evidentemente, él jamás la consideraría alguien importante.

Then his expression turned vicious and disdainful. “I tried to think what could I possibly want from the Eternal Flame.

Sintió una presión en el pecho.

A pardon, because it was as ridiculous as it was obvious.

—Yo no… —le falló la voz—.

But the Resistance was losing, everyone knew you were losing.

Habría… habría sido más amable… si lo hubiera sabido.

I knew I’d need a contact, someone who could retrieve messages for me and come when called.

Helena encogió las piernas, como si hacerse más pequeña pudiera protegerla de la vulnerabilidad que sentía.

I didn’t want Crowther choosing one of his rats, and I thought demanding someone specific would play into—what they expected of me.”

—No quería que lo fueras —dijo en voz baja.

He swallowed. “But the Eternal Flame’s noble families are too precious, I had to want someone they’d consider disposable, and Crowther was standing there, waiting for an answer.

Le temblaron las manos cuando se dispuso a vestirse.

I had to come up with something.

Kaine se quedó en silencio.

I remembered your name, on the exam lists.

Helena supo que había cambiado algo entre ellos, pero no entendía por qué había trazado esa línea, por qué justo ahora.

When I said Helena Marino, Crowther got this look in his eyes, and I knew he’d taken the bait.”

Debía de ser por el sello de la espalda.

He sneered. “As if I would betray the High Necromancer for you.

La había besado justo después de curarse, después de haber interiorizado todos sus efectos.

I knew they’d send you with instructions to try to play up the obsession I was supposed to have—to ensure I wouldn’t get bored or change my mind—but I wasn’t worried.

La quería para él.

You were no one, just an awkward shadow behind Holdfast, following him like a dog.

El sello lo había puesto en una encrucijada, por eso se había mostrado tan distante después de aquello.

I thought it would be funny, watching you try.”

Porque tal vez, si cedía aunque fuera una sola vez, eso bastaría para desequilibrar la balanza.

He looked away from her then, his face twisting. “But you—you—” He shook his head. “It doesn’t really matter.

Quizá ya no había vuelta atrás, había tomado su decisión.

You outmanoeuvred me.

Obsesivo y posesivo.

Or maybe I’m just too tired and grieving to keep pushing you away.

Lo tenía en sus manos, si era lo bastante lista para aprovecharlo.

You won.” He met her eyes for a moment, his expression bitter and derisive. “Well done.”

Lo tenía de rodillas, dispuesto a cualquier cosa, tal como Ilva le había pedido.

Then he went and leaned against the wall, shutting his eyes.

Aunque todavía no sabía cómo hacerlo.

Helena watched him sceptically.

Era como si Ilva y Crowther consideraran importante que Kaine se hubiese acostado con ella, y por eso esperaban que lo hiciera el primer día.

She wasn’t sure what angle he was trying to play with this confession.

Helena no sabía si reír o llorar, así que su expresión solo logró quedarse entre el dolor y la sonrisa.

What he said about her was believable enough.

—Vaya, pareces satisfecha de haberte vendido como una puta barata —comentó Kaine con una expresión amarga y despectiva.

It aligned with their inconsistent interactions, but to claim that avenging his mother was his true impetus?

Ella se quedó inmóvil y notó que se le nublaba la vista.

Avenging her for what?

—Ese era mi trabajo —repuso en voz baja—.

“You switched sides because your mother died of a heart attack?” She gave a loud scoff, standing up, hiding a wince. “Her death wasn’t anyone’s fault, and even if it was, did you murder Principate Apollo by ripping out his heart by accident?

Siempre supiste que esa era mi misión.

Ran off with it and joined the Undying for three years, saw her die, kept going, and then what?

—Por supuesto —dijo sin más, mirando a su alrededor como si no pudiera creer que estuviera allí.

You got so melancholy because you can’t get drunk that you decided to turn spy?”

Los brazos le colgaban inertes a los lados—.

She was baiting him.

Pero… nunca pensé que lo conseguirías. —Se produjo una pausa mientras Helena terminaba de vestirse—.

She knew it would enrage him.

No tenía pensado traicionar a la Resistencia —admitió entonces—.

She hoped that if she goaded him enough, he’d finally tell the truth.

No era mi plan.

His eyes snapped open.

Ya estabais perdiendo cuando os hice la oferta y, aun así, es probable que acabéis perdiendo igualmente, pero a mí siempre me dio igual.

They’d turned silver, and two splotches of colour flushed in the hollows of his cheeks. “Fuck you.”

Yo solo quería vengar a mi madre.

She flinched but spat back, “You already did.”

Frunció los labios y bajó la mirada al suelo.

Her back felt bruised, the skin rubbed raw from the floor, and her lower abdomen ached as if she’d been punched low in the pelvis.

—Por desgracia, cuando tuve la oportunidad de ofrecer mis servicios, ya llevaba demasiado tiempo muerta y el informe de un coronel aseguraba que había fallecido por causas naturales.

She’d never felt so cold as she did then, standing there, but she was so angry, and finally it was all out in the open.

Así que ¿qué había que vengar? —Había amargura en su voz, aunque se mostraba impasible—.

No more of this game.

Sabía que Crowther solo consideraría mi propuesta si pensaba que era tan valioso como las cuerdas que pudiera mover, por eso le di un cabo suelto al que aferrarse. —Su voz se volvió más seca, más mordaz—.

“You are a monster,” she said, crossing her arms. “Do you expect me to forget what you’ve done?

Estuve dándole vueltas a qué podía ofrecerme la Llama Eterna.

To think you became so high-ranking because of that delightful personality of yours?

El perdón, por supuesto, eso era evidente.

You think invoking your mother’s death can erase all that?

Pero estabais perdiendo, y todo el mundo lo sabía.

Everyone has lost someone, and most of them, more than you ever could.

Así que entendí que necesitaba un contacto, alguien que se encargara de llevar mensajes y acudir cuando yo lo pidiera.

If you want to blame her death on Morrough, then maybe you shouldn’t have spent all that extra time supporting him after she was gone.

No quería que Crowther eligiera a uno de sus esbirros, así que se me ocurrió que si exigía a alguien concreto me verían como lo que ellos creían que era.

After you started this war.

Tragó saliva.

And chose to become Undying.”

—Pero la Llama Eterna valora demasiado a sus familias de la nobleza.

He was so angry that she could feel his resonance humming in the air, pushing at her skin.

Tenía que encontrar a alguien que consideraran prescindible, y Crowther me observaba, esperando una respuesta.

He would probably flay her if she didn’t use her own resonance to push back.

Tenía que improvisar.

“Do you want to know why I’m like this?” he asked slowly, his teeth flashing like fangs. “You asked once if it was a punishment, and I was honest when I said it wasn’t.

Y entonces recordé tu nombre de las listas de exámenes.

It was the bargain I made.”

Cuando dije «Helena Marino», a Crowther le brillaron los ojos de tal forma que supe que había mordido el anzuelo. —Puso una mueca de desprecio—.

He walked towards her, rage radiating off him until she could feel the room warp.

Como si fuera a traicionar al Sumo Nigromante por ti.

“After my father’s failure, after he revealed Morrough’s plans, do you think the High Necromancer was understanding?”

Sabía que te darían órdenes de someterte a esta supuesta obsesión mía, para asegurarse de que no me aburriera ni cambiase de opinión.

Helena stared at him, frozen in place.

Pero a mí eso me daba igual.

“I was still at the Institute, finishing up the year.

No eras nadie, solo el perrito faldero de Holdfast.

Who do you imagine was alone with him when word came that my father had been caught and confessed to treason?” Kaine’s expression contorted with grief. “He had my mother in a cage when I got home.

Pensé que sería divertido ver cómo lo intentabas.

He’d been torturing her for weeks.”

Kaine apartó la vista con el rostro sombrío.

His breathing grew ragged and uneven. “You sold yourself to save the person you care about.

—Pero entonces… tú… —Negó con la cabeza—.

Well, so did I.

En realidad, da igual, has superado mis expectativas.

What was I supposed to do, fail to kill Principate Apollo knowing I wouldn’t be the one who’d suffer for it?

O tal vez esté demasiado cansado y triste para alejarte de mí.

This”—he gestured towards himself—“this was how I proved I’d be loyal, how I got him t—” His breath caught. “—to stop hurting her.”

Tú ganas. —La miró, apenas unos segundos, con gesto amargo y burlón—.

Helena’s head had grown light. “We—I didn’t know.”

Buen trabajo.

His lip curled up in a snarl, but then he turned away and his voice grew thick. “She never recovered.

Después se apoyó en la pared y cerró los ojos.

Morrough and Bennet were short on subjects at the time.

Helena lo observó en silencio, escéptica.

They liked to experiment together.

No estaba segura de qué pretendía con esta confesión.

I’d hear her screaming for hours sometimes.

Parecía que estaba siendo sincero, y todo encajaba con la forma errática, contradictoria, con la que siempre se había relacionado con ella.

They’d do things to her and then reverse them, so there were no traces after.”

Pero no entendía a qué se refería cuando hablaba de vengar a su madre.

He shoved his hair away from his face, his throat working. “The whole summer.

¿Vengarla de qué?

I couldn’t—do anything but tell her I was sorry.

—¿Cambiaste de bando solo porque tu madre murió de un infarto? —Se le escapó un bufido.

That I’d do it and come back for her.

Se puso en pie, ignorando el dolor que sentía—.

That I wouldn’t fail.”

Su muerte no fue culpa de nadie.

He braced against the wall as if he were about to fall.

Y, aunque lo hubiera sido, ¿asesinaste al principado Apollo arrancándole el corazón sin querer?

The words, so furious at first, were turning into a tidal wave of grief that seemed to pour from him.

Saliste corriendo con su corazón en la mano, te uniste a los inmarcesibles, la viste morir, seguiste siendo leal… ¿Y entonces qué?

“When the Principate was dead and I brought the heart back, the High Necromancer let her out and made us leave with him before the Eternal Flame came for me.

¿Te deprimiste porque no puedes emborracharte y decidiste jugar a los espías?

Even before that, my mother—she was never very strong.

Lo estaba provocando.

When she was pregnant, she wouldn’t listen when the doctors warned her what I’d cost her.

Sabía que así lo enfurecería.

She was always fragile after that.

Confiaba en que, si lo provocaba lo suficiente, por fin le contaría la verdad.

My father always said I had to take care of her.

Kaine abrió los ojos, sorprendido; se habían vuelto plateados.

That I was—responsible.

El rubor coloreó sus mejillas hundidas.

He used to make me swear again and again, growing up, that I’d always take care of her.

—Que te follen.

I tried to make her flee.

—Ya lo has hecho tú —replicó con una mueca.

I got it all arranged but—she wouldn’t go.

Notaba la espalda llena de moratones, la piel en carne viva por haberse arañado contra el suelo, y le dolía el bajo vientre como si le hubieran dado un puñetazo.

Not without me.

Jamás había tenido tanto frío como en ese momento, ahí de pie, pero estaba tan enfadada que lo único que quería era sacarlo todo.

Said she couldn’t leave me here.”

Se habían acabado los jueguecitos.

He pressed the heels of his hands against his eyes. “I was trying to figure out if there was a way, and there were these parties they’d hold, the Undying.

—Eres un monstruo —lo insultó cruzándose de brazos—.

She said I should go, thought if I had friends, I’d be—protected.

¿De verdad esperas que me olvide de lo que has hecho?

But that wasn’t why I’d been invited.

¿Que crea que has subido de rango por la maravillosa persona que eres?

They thought it would be interesting to find ways to make an injury that would last on one of us, and I was the youngest.

¿Que mencionar la muerte de tu madre borre todo lo demás?

Automatic short straw …” He blinked as if he wasn’t seeing the room anymore. “I thought she’d be in bed when I got back, but she’d waited up for me.

Todos hemos perdido a alguien, y muchos han perdido más de lo que tú perderás jamás.

She was by the door, and when she saw me, she started screaming.

Si quieres culpar a Morrough de su muerte, no deberías haber pasado tanto tiempo apoyándolo después de que muriera.

I kept trying to tell her that it would heal, but she kept saying it was all her fault, and her heart stopped, and I—couldn’t—”

Fuiste tú quien dio comienzo a esta guerra.

His voice broke and he slid down the wall, shuddering as if he were about to split open.

Tú elegiste convertirte en uno de los inmarcesibles.

When he spoke again, his voice had deadened.

Kaine estaba tan cabreado que incluso Helena podía sentir la vibración de su resonancia a su alrededor.

“After she died, I was being watched.

Le hacía cosquillas en la piel y, si no la hubiera contrarrestado con su propia resonancia, le habría hecho daño.

Morrough knew I’d joined for her.

—¿Quieres saber por qué soy así? —preguntó con lentitud, mostrando los dientes como si fueran colmillos—.

I had to earn back trust before I could risk doing anything.

Una vez me preguntaste si esto era un castigo y te dije que no.

I’m not one of your fucking idiots who thinks one moment of self-sacrifice can change everything.

Y no te mentí.

If I wanted my betrayal to matter, he couldn’t see it coming.”

Fue el trato que hice.

Helena stood frozen in horror.

Se acercó a ella, y la maldad que irradiaba era tan intensa que Helena sintió que la habitación se encogía.

How had no one known this?

—Después del fracaso de mi padre, después de que revelara los planes de Morrough, ¿crees que el Sumo Nigromante se mostró comprensivo?

“I am so sorry.” She felt faint with shock.

La chica lo miró, incapaz de moverse.

“I don’t need your false sympathy, Marino,” he snarled, but his voice was shaking.

—Yo aún estaba en la Academia, acabando el curso.

He’d probably never told anyone what happened.

¿Sabes quién estaba con Morrough cuando llegó la noticia de que habían capturado a mi padre y había confesado su traición? —En el rostro de Kaine se mostraba una expresión de dolor—.

His mother’s death had been dismissed by everyone.

Cuando volví a casa, mi madre ya llevaba semanas encerrada en una jaula.

Why would a heart attack matter, when people were dying in battle.

Morrough la estaba torturando. —Empezó a respirar de forma entrecortada—.

But Helena knew the kind of torture a vivimancer could perform and fix without leaving a trace.

Tú te vendiste para salvar a una persona que te importa.

She could imagine what that would do to a heart over time.

Pues yo hice lo mismo.

Kaine had been carrying that guilt for years, trying to make amends as best he could, trying to exact some form of revenge for her, knowing the indescribable punishment that awaited him.

¿Qué pretendías que hiciera?

“I’m not lying,” she said. “I’m sorry.

¿Que me negara a matar al principado Apollo sabiendo que entonces me harían sufrir a mí en su lugar?

I am truly sorry for what happened to her.”

Así —se señaló a sí mismo—, así fue como demostré mi lealtad.

She drew closer to him.

Así conseguí que… que dejara de hacerle daño —terminó con el pecho encogido.

He looked so utterly broken, as if he were about to collapse into himself.

Helena estaba empezando a marearse.

She placed a tentative hand on his arm, half expecting him to fling her across the room, but his shoulders trembled and he dropped his head onto her shoulder.

—La Resistencia… Yo no lo sabía.

She pulled him into her arms; he gripped her close and sobbed.

Kaine le dedicó un gesto de desprecio y se dio la vuelta.

“I can’t—I can’t—” he kept saying over and over.

—Nunca se recuperó —continuó en voz grave—.

Helena didn’t know what to do.

Morrough y Bennet andaban escasos de sujetos para experimentar en aquella época.

She ran her fingers through his hair and just held him.

Les gustaba hacerlo juntos.

“I can’t—I can’t do this again—” he finally gasped out. “I can’t care for someone again.

En ocasiones mi madre se pasaba horas gritando.

I can’t take it.”

Hacían con ella experimentos que luego revertían para que no le quedaran secuelas. —Se apartó el pelo de la cara y tragó saliva varias veces—.

She blindly found his face, pressing her hand against his cheek, felt tears slide along her palm and down her wrist.

Estuvieron así todo el verano.

“I’m sorry.

No pude… hacer nada, salvo decirle que lo sentía.

I’m so sorry, Kaine.” She said it again and again.

Que asesinaría a Apollo y la rescataría, que no fallaría.

She was apologising for everything.

Se apoyó contra la pared como si fuera a caerse.

For the first time, Kaine Ferron was fully human to her.

Las palabras, al principio llenas de rabia, se fueron impregnando de la pena que parecía abrirse paso desde su interior.

She’d slipped through his walls and peeled away the defensive layers of malice and cruelty, and found that there he carried a broken heart.

—Cuando el principado murió y entregué su corazón, el Sumo Nigromante la dejó salir y nos obligó a marcharnos antes de que la Llama Eterna viniera a buscarme.

She could use that.

Pero para entonces mi madre… Nunca fue una mujer especialmente fuerte.

Cuando estaba embarazada, no hizo caso a los médicos, que le advirtieron de lo mucho que le costaría tenerme.

Una vez que dio a luz, se volvió una persona frágil.

Mi padre siempre me decía que tenía que cuidar de ella, que yo era el… el responsable.

De niño me obligaba a jurarlo una y otra vez, debía prometer que siempre cuidaría de ella.

Quise sacarla del país.

Lo había preparado todo, pero… ella no quiso hacerlo.

No quería irse sin mí.

Me dijo que no podía dejarme atrás.

Se llevó el borde de las manos a los ojos.

—Intenté buscar una salida.

Los inmarcesibles organizaban fiestas y mi madre me dijo que debía ir yo también, porque pensaba que, si tenía amigos, tal vez me… me protegerían.

Aunque no me invitaron por eso.

Querían probar hasta dónde se podían provocar lesiones duraderas en alguno de nosotros, y yo era el más joven.

Fue la elección más fácil. —Parpadeó como si hubiera dejado de ver lo que lo rodeaba—.

Pensé que mi madre estaría dormida cuando regresé, pero me había esperado despierta.

Estaba en la puerta y, en cuanto me vio, empezó a gritar.

Yo no paraba de decirle que me iba a curar, pero ella insistía en que era culpa suya.

Se le paró el corazón y yo… yo no pude…

Entonces, la voz se le rompió y Kaine se dejó caer hasta el suelo, estremeciéndose como si estuviera a punto de partirse en dos.

Después volvió a hablar, pero lo hizo con un tono apagado, desprovisto de emociones.

—Cuando murió, empezaron a vigilarme.

Morrough sabía que me había unido a la causa por ella.

Tuve que ganarme su confianza antes de arriesgarme a hacer nada más.

Yo no soy uno de tus amigos idiotas que creen que un solo acto de sacrificio puede cambiarlo todo.

Si quería vengarme de verdad, Morrough no podía verlo venir.

Helena permaneció quieta, horrorizada.

¿Por qué nadie sabía todo esto?

—Lo siento mucho —dijo, algo mareada de la impresión.

—No necesito tu compasión fingida, Marino —le escupió Kaine, aunque le temblaba la voz.

Seguramente nunca se lo había contado a nadie.

La muerte de su madre había pasado desapercibida.

En mitad de una guerra, ¿por qué le iba a importar a alguien un infarto cuando había gente muriendo en el campo de batalla?

Sin embargo, Helena sabía que un vivemante podía llevar a cabo torturas espantosas y arreglarlo después para no dejar rastro.

Ya imaginaba el desgaste que eso podía pasarle a un corazón con el paso del tiempo.

Kaine había cargado con la culpa durante años y había intentado enmendar sus errores de la mejor manera para vengarla, a pesar de conocer el terrible castigo que le aguardaba.

—No estoy fingiendo —replicó—.

Lo siento.

Siento mucho lo que le pasó.

Se acercó a Kaine, que parecía absolutamente destrozado, como si estuviera a punto de desmoronarse.

Helena posó una mano en su brazo, con cuidado, como si esperara que fuera a darle un empujón.

Pero a él solo le temblaban los hombros y dejó caer la cabeza.

Ella lo envolvió entre sus brazos, y él la abrazó con fuerza mientras lloraba.

—No puedo… no puedo… —decía una y otra vez.

Helena no sabía qué hacer.

Le pasó los dedos por el cabello y siguió abrazándolo.

—No puedo… no puedo volver a hacerlo —consiguió decir entre sollozos—.

No puedo volver a preocuparme por nadie.

No lo soportaría.

A ciegas, buscó su rostro.

Colocó la mano en su mejilla y sintió que las lágrimas recorrían la palma de su mano hasta su muñeca.

—Lo siento.

Lo siento mucho, Kaine —repitió una y otra vez.

Se estaba disculpando por todo.

Por primera vez, Kaine Ferron se estaba mostrando como un ser humano.

Helena había derribado sus muros, había desmontado todas sus capas defensivas de maldad y crueldad, y había descubierto que tenía el corazón roto.

Podía aprovecharse de eso.

CHAPTER 48

Janua 1787

CAPÍTULO 48

WHEN KAINE STOPPED CRYING, HELENA SAT BACK, studying him soberly.

Ener 1787

His expression turned guarded and embittered, as if he’d wept out all his softness and once again only his venom remained.

Cuando Kaine dejó de llorar, Helena se apartó para observarlo con detenimiento.

She had him, she could feel it.

Su expresión se había vuelto cauta y agriada, como si el llanto hubiera borrado toda su ternura y, en su lugar, solo quedara el veneno.

She’d followed orders, done what she’d been instructed to do, but she still didn’t know how to prove that.

Helena sabía que lo tenía bajo control.

The right way to leverage it into demonstrable loyalty.

Había cumplido con las órdenes que le dieron y, aun así, no estaba segura de cómo demostrarlo, de cómo poner a prueba su lealtad de una forma tangible.

Ilva would not lend any credence to a feeling Helena had.

Ilva no le daría crédito a lo que Helena sentía.

Caring about Helena didn’t make Kaine a dog she could command.

Que Kaine se preocupara por ella no era lo mismo que tenerlo atado como un perro, y eso era justo lo que Ilva había pedido.

“If you really want the Eternal Flame to win, why keep climbing rank?

—Si de verdad quieres que gane la Llama Eterna, ¿por qué continúas ascendiendo de rango?

What are you doing?” she asked.

¿Qué pretendes hacer? —preguntó.

His eyes shone like mirrors.

Los ojos de Kaine eran como un espejo, en ellos podía verse reflejada hasta la más mínima expresión. Él hizo un gesto burlón.

She could almost see herself in their reflection.

De no ser porque su rostro aún estaba humedecido, jamás habría dicho que había estado llorando.

His mouth twisted into a mocking smile.

—Siempre supe que el único motivo por el que aceptasteis mi oferta era porque estabais desesperados.

If his face weren’t still wet, she’d never have known he’d been crying.

La Llama Eterna afirma ser una organización respetable, pero Crowther es una serpiente.

“It was obvious that my offer was only accepted out of desperation.

Y da igual lo que prometa Ilva Holdfast, al final no es más que la mano derecha del principado, y encima un lapsus.

The Eternal Flame may claim to be honourable, but Crowther is a snake.

Sabe perfectamente que, si ganan, la Llama Eterna decidirá cuáles de sus acciones son legítimas y cuáles no, y las que no gusten a los Holdfast desaparecerán en el viento.

Ilva Holdfast can promise whatever she wants; she’s only a steward, and a Lapse at that.

Di por hecho que, una vez que dejase de ser útil, pondríais en riesgo mi tapadera para aprovecharos de la inestabilidad que causaría la traición. —Enseñó los dientes—.

She knows full well that if they win, the Eternal Flame will pick and choose which of her actions were legitimate.

Así que he intentado llegar lo más alto posible, para que las consecuencias sean mucho más devastadoras.

Anything Holdfast doesn’t like will vanish like smoke.

Helena frunció el ceño sin apartar la mirada.

I assumed that once I’d outlived my usefulness, you’d blow my cover to take advantage of the instability it would cause.

Aquello le resultaba demasiado generoso por su parte.

So.” His teeth flashed. “I tried to position myself to maximise that fallout.”

Aunque quisiera vengar a su madre, Kaine no sentía ningún aprecio por la Llama Eterna.

Helena furrowed her eyebrows, studying him.

Para él, no eran más que un medio para conseguir un fin.

That seemed a bit too selfless for him.

—¿Por qué me has besado? —preguntó de repente—.

He might want to avenge his mother, but he had no fondness for the Eternal Flame.

¿De qué ha servido… todo esto?

They were merely a means to an end.

Helena bajó la vista, sin estar segura de qué responder.

“Why kiss me?” he abruptly asked. “What was the point—in all this?”

—Yo no sabía que debías morir una vez que retomaron los puertos.

She looked down, not sure she had an answer. “I didn’t know you were supposed to die after we retook the ports.

Por lo visto, era algo evidente, pero no caí en la cuenta.

Apparently it was obvious, but I didn’t realise.”

Kaine soltó una carcajada amarga, pero ella no fue capaz de mirarlo a los ojos cuando volvió a hablar.

Kaine gave a deadened laugh.

—Creían que morirías por el sello de la espalda.

She couldn’t meet his eyes as she spoke. “They expected you to die from the array, and they were—waiting for that.

De hecho, lo estaban… esperando.

When they realised you’ve been climbing rank, they assumed you’ve been playing the two sides against each other, so you’ll be the one who comes out on top in the end.”

Cuando supieron que habías subido de rango, dieron por sentado que habías estado enfrentando a un bando contra otro para ser el único que resultara victorioso cuando todo terminara.

“Did you think that?” he asked softly.

—¿Y tú también lo crees? —le preguntó en voz baja.

She swallowed hard, still not meeting his eyes. “No, but it doesn’t really matter what I think.

Helena tragó saliva, todavía incapaz de mirarlo a los ojos.

They said just before solstice that I had a month to”—her voice dropped, lower than a whisper—“make you crawl or kill you, or they’d let Morrough do it instead.”

—No, pero da igual lo que yo piense.

He laughed again. “One more meeting to go, then.

Justo antes del solsticio, me dijeron que tenía un mes para conseguir que te arrastraras o matarte.

So this was a goodbye fuck?

Si no, Morrough se encargaría de ello.

Final payment for services rendered?”

Kaine volvió a reírse.

A tremor ran through Helena. “No.

—Me queda una semana, por lo que veo.

I—I just—”

Entonces ¿esto era un polvo de despedida?

Her throat closed.

¿El último pago por los servicios prestados?

She leaned forward, gripping his shirt, wanting to shake him.

Helena sintió un escalofrío por todo el cuerpo.

She hated the way he’d switch, one moment vulnerable and the next so bitterly cruel.

—No.

“I just have to prove that you’ll do what I ask.

Yo… solo quería… —Sintió que se le formaba un nudo en la garganta.

If I can—they won’t kill you.” She studied his face desperately.

Lo agarró por la camisa, con ganas de sacudirlo.

His eyebrows rose mockingly. “Really?

Odiaba la forma en que cambiaba de personalidad.

Is that all?

Pasaba de mostrarse vulnerable a tener una actitud cruel en cuestión de segundos—.

Just servitude and I’ll get to continue this delightful existence of mine so long as I’m more useful alive than dead?

Solo tengo que demostrar que harás lo que yo te pida.

That’s so generous.

Si lo consigo…, no te matarán.

How could I possibly refuse?”

Lo miró desesperada. Él arqueó las cejas con sorna.

Her grip loosened, and she gave a disbelieving laugh.

—¿En serio?

He didn’t want to be saved.

¿Eso es todo?

Her efforts had only made things worse.

Si les sirvo, podré seguir existiendo tan tranquilamente como hasta ahora, siempre que les sea más útil vivo que muerto, ¿no?

All because Ilva and Crowther hadn’t told her, they’d made her believe it was all real, but it didn’t matter—it had never mattered whether she believed it—because Kaine had always known.

Qué oferta más generosa.

She drew a slow breath trying to reorient herself, but her mind wouldn’t comprehend it.

¿Cómo podría rechazarla?

It couldn’t end like this.

Helena lo soltó y se rio con algo de amargura.

She’d done what she’d been told to do.

Kaine no quería que lo salvaran.

She’d followed orders.

Ella solo había empeorado las cosas, y solo porque Ilva y Crowther no le habían contado la verdad.

She wasn’t supposed to have to make this choice.

Le habían hecho creer que todo era real, pero en el fondo no importaba; nunca importó lo que ella creyera o dejara de creer… porque Kaine siempre lo había sabido.

“I—I have to follow orders.

Respiró hondo para aclarar sus pensamientos, pero su mente se resistía a asimilar la realidad.

I can’t choose you.

No podía acabar así.

There’s too many people at stake,” she said, her voice shaking.

Había hecho lo que le habían pedido.

“I know.”

Había cumplido con las órdenes.

Her mouth opened and closed, but there was nothing else to say.

No debería tener que tomar esta decisión.

“All right,” she finally managed, her voice far away.

—He… he seguido las órdenes.

She felt as though she’d been knifed, reality cold as tempered steel driven into her heart.

No puedo elegirte a ti.

“Do you—” Her voice broke. “Do you want it to be me?

Está en juego la vida de mucha gente —confesó con la voz temblorosa.

Or does it—not matter?”

—Lo sé.

She knew Ilva probably wanted the Stone back if it could be recovered, but she couldn’t bring herself to care.

Helena abrió y cerró la boca, pero no podía añadir nada más.

He scoffed. “You lost your chance.”

—De acuerdo —aceptó al cabo de un rato con tono distante.

Her throat worked several times before she could speak. “I’m sorry.”

Sentía como si la hubiesen apuñalado; la cruda realidad era como una daga de acero clavada en el corazón—.

He didn’t reply.

¿Quieres…? —Le falló la voz—.

There was not even a flicker of remorse in his eyes.

¿Quieres que lo haga yo?

He looked cruelly satisfied.

¿O… te da igual?

There was no air in the room.

Sabía que Ilva querría recuperar la gema, si es que eso aún era posible, pero a Helena ya le daba absolutamente igual.

She kept trying to breathe, but there wasn’t any oxygen.

Kaine soltó un bufido.

A dull ringing filled her ears.

—Has perdido la oportunidad.

She looked blindly for her satchel, trying to remember where she’d left it.

Helena tragó saliva varias veces hasta reunir el valor necesario para hablar.

She knelt, wavering, willing her mind to function.

—Lo siento.

“So, what happens to you now?”

Él no respondió.

Helena blinked. “Me?”

Sus ojos no mostraban ni una pizca de arrepentimiento, solo una cruel satisfacción.

“Yes.” He leaned forward and caught her chin, tilting her face so that the light from the windows fell across it, a pale slice of winter. “What happens to you?”

Helena sentía que el aire desaparecía de la habitación.

“When you’re—gone?”

Por más que tratara de respirar, ya no quedaba oxígeno.

He gave a short nod.

Oía un pitido resonando en sus oídos.

“I don’t know,” she said with a short hysterical laugh.

Buscó a ciegas su bolsa e intentó recordar dónde la había dejado.

She pulled away. “Like you said, I’ve always been expendable, so maybe they’ll offer me to the next spy.”

Con un movimiento titubeante, se puso de rodillas, pero su mente se negaba a funcionar.

“Don’t joke.

—¿Y qué pasará contigo?

I want a real answer.” There was a sharp undercurrent to his voice.

La chica parpadeó.

She met his eyes then. “I promised I was yours.

—¿Conmigo?

You made me swear it.

—Sí. —Kaine se inclinó hacia delante y le sostuvo la barbilla de manera que la luz de la ventana iluminó su rostro con un pálido rayo del sol de invierno—.

I didn’t make plans.”

¿Qué pasará contigo?

Anger darkened his face. “Surely there’s something you’re looking forward to now.”

—¿Cuando… tú ya no estés?

She reached out, her fingers brushing over his heart. “No.

Kaine asintió.

I’m—spent.”

—No lo sé —respondió con una carcajada nerviosa, y se apartó—.

As she stood, she thought of Luc standing on the top of the Alchemy Tower, so close to the edge.

Como bien dijiste, siempre he sido prescindible, así que tal vez me ofrezcan al siguiente espía.

She hadn’t understood why he’d gone there.

—No bromees con eso.

How she and everyone else who needed him weren’t enough to hold him back, but now that edge called her, the abyss that would open once she’d split across the marble.

Quiero una respuesta sincera —expresó con un deje mordaz en la voz.

The air swam, her eyes struggling to focus because all she could hear was the drumbeat of her heart inside her skull.

Helena lo miró a los ojos.

Everyone who touches you dies.

—Te prometí que sería tuya.

“What do they want?” His voice was almost a whisper.

Me obligaste a prometerlo.

She looked back. “What?”

No he hecho más planes.

“Is it—actual crawling?

La rabia se dibujó en su rostro.

Or was there something more constructive Ilva had in mind?”

—Ahora que voy a morir, seguro que tienes ganas de hacer otras cosas.

Her throat closed. “I—I’d have to ask.”

Helena le acarició con los dedos ahí donde estaba el corazón.

“Find out.

—No, estoy… agotada.

I’ll do it.” He looked exhausted, but now there was an edge of something seething in him.

Al ponerse en pie, recordó a Luc en lo alto de la Torre de Alquimia, demasiado cerca del borde.

“Are you really offering?” she asked, certain it was a trick.

En aquel momento, no entendió por qué estaba allí, cómo era posible que ni ella ni las demás personas que lo necesitaban fueran suficientes para darle ganas de vivir.

He gave no response.

Ahora, ese mismo abismo parecía llamarla, un abismo que se abriría tan pronto como tomara esta decisión.

“Why are you offering?” Her voice rose, a note of hysteria in it.

Todo le daba vueltas.

He looked up at her a moment. “I realised just now that I’d miscalculated something.

No podía concentrarse, porque lo único que escuchaba era el latido de su propio corazón.

It hadn’t occurred to me that I’d made you marketable.”

«Todo el que te toca muere».

The words thudded against her chest. “Oh.”

—¿Qué es lo que quieren? —preguntó Kaine en un susurro.

Apparently, Crowther was right after all.

Helena lo miró.

The Ferrons were possessive enough to eat themselves alive before they’d let go of anything they considered theirs.

—¿Cómo?

“I’ll bring an answer back,” she said.

—¿Lo de… arrastrarse es algo literal o Ilva tiene algo más constructivo en mente?

He gave a short nod and looked away from her, saying nothing else as she went and pulled on her cloak, using it to hide her ripped clothes.

Helena notó un nudo en la garganta.

She slung her satchel over her shoulder.

—T-tendría que preguntar.

His hand twitched as she reached the door, but when she glanced back one last time, he’d looked away, still leaning against the wall, staring across the room, so pale he could have been a ghost.

—Descúbrelo.

She walked out of the tenement into a downpour of rain.

Lo haré. —Parecía exhausto, pero algo ardía en su interior.

She stood beneath it, trying to gain her bearings, drawing rapid breaths.

—¿Lo dices en serio? —preguntó Helena, aunque estaba segura de que había gato encerrado.

She was on a precipice; she could still feel that edge, the plunge if she misstepped.

Kaine no respondió—.

She kept her hood pulled up at the checkpoint, but she was familiar enough that they waved her through without being thorough.

¿Por qué te estás ofreciendo? —insistió alzando la voz con un matiz de histeria.

A security failure, but she was grateful for it.

Él la miró durante unos instantes.

She split from her usual route, heading to the drop point.

—Acabo de caer en la cuenta de algo que he pasado por alto.

She couldn’t show up at Headquarters like this.

Hasta ahora no había caído en que te he convertido en una baza a mi favor.

As she neared it, signs of the war began to appear, as they did in every part of the city below Headquarters.

Las palabras le golpearon como una patada en el pecho.

The walls were scorched and distorted from combat.

—Ah.

The drop-point safe house was little more than a sub-basement storage room.

Crowther tenía razón desde el principio: los Ferron eran tan posesivos que preferían devorarse a sí mismos antes que renunciar a algo que consideraban suyo.

Her hands were stiff and trembling as she shoved the door closed.

—Te traeré la respuesta —respondió Helena.

She focused first on lighting a fire in the portable stove using the discarded pile of kindling and old newspapers.

Kaine se limitó a asentir y apartó la mirada.

She was struggling to coax the fire to life, wishing her knowledge of pyromancy extended beyond the theoretical, when the door opened.

No dijo nada mientras Helena se ponía la capa, cubriendo la ropa hecha jirones, y cogía su bolsa para marcharse.

She turned quickly, hoping it wasn’t Ivy, although a stranger might be worse.

Cuando llegó a la puerta, se percató de que hacía un movimiento con la mano, pero, al girarse por última vez, Kaine apartó la vista y apoyó su espalda contra la pared.

It was Crowther who entered.

Se quedó con la mirada perdida, tan pálido que podría haber sido un fantasma.

He stopped short, irritation pinching his face.

Al salir del módulo, la recibió un chaparrón.

Helena looked back to the fire.

Helena se quedó bajo el agua y trató de recobrar la compostura, aunque no respiraba con dificultad.

“Are you injured?”

Estaba al borde del abismo; aún sentía la caída que le esperaba si daba un mal paso.

She shook her head.

A pesar de tener la capucha puesta cuando pasó por el puesto de control, los guardias la reconocieron rápidamente y no le hicieron el chequeo.

He nudged her out of the way.

Era un fallo de seguridad, pero lo agradeció.

With the snap of his fingers, there was fire, the wood igniting with a crackling roar.

Se desvió de su ruta habitual y se dirigió al punto de encuentro.

Helena held her hands out towards the flames, saying nothing.

No podía aparecer por el Cuartel General con esas pintas.

He went into the next room and returned with a towel.

Conforme se acercaba, la devastación de la guerra se hacía patente, igual que ocurría en todos los rincones de la ciudad.

She took it wordlessly, scrubbing until water stopped trickling from her hair.

Los muros estaban calcinados, deformados por el combate.

She could feel him scrutinising her.

El piso franco no era más que un almacén en un sótano.

“Is it done, then?” he asked when she lowered it to her lap and reached towards the fire again.

Al cerrar la puerta tras de sí, notó que sus manos estaban rígidas.

Her throat caught.

No podía dejar de temblar, así que, nada más entrar, encendió un fuego en el hornillo portátil empleando un montón de pedazos de leña y periódicos viejos que había por allí.

After a moment’s hesitation, she nodded. “Yes, I did it.”

Se esforzaba por avivar las llamas, deseando que sus conocimientos de piromancia fueran algo más que teoría, cuando se abrió la puerta.

He released a soft breath of relief, and his right hand briefly patted her shoulder. “You can give the talisman to Ilva.”

Se giró rápidamente con la esperanza de que no fuera Ivy, aunque si se tratase de un desconocido, sería peor.

She kept staring at the fire. “He was being honest when he said he wanted to avenge his mother.”

Era Crowther.

Crowther sighed, but Helena kept speaking.

Se detuvo con gesto contrariado.

“Back when Atreus was arrested, Kaine was safe at the Institute, but his mother wasn’t.

Helena volvió a mirar el fuego.

You know vivimancy for torture doesn’t always leave evidence behind.

—¿Estás herida?

Kaine killed Principate Apollo because it was the only way to save her.

La chica negó con la cabeza, y Crowther la apartó de un leve codazo.

But she never recovered from it.

Con solo chasquear los dedos, las llamas se avivaron y la madera crujió y prendió con fuerza.

Certain kinds of stress for too long can damage the heart.”

Helena extendió las manos sobre las llamas sin decir nada.

There was a tense pause, and she could feel Crowther’s doubt permeating the air.

Crowther se dirigió a la habitación contigua y volvió con una toalla.

Helena didn’t look away from the fire.

Helena la aceptó en silencio y se frotó el rostro hasta que dejó de gotearle el pelo.

The heat singed her hands, but she didn’t draw them away.

Sentía sus ojos clavados en ella.

If her hands were scorched, maybe she wouldn’t feel the rest of her body.

—¿Está hecho? —le preguntó en cuanto Helena dejó la toalla sobre su regazo y volvió a extender las manos sobre el fuego.

“Atreus used to make Kaine swear he’d take care of his mother, because he blamed him for Enid being sickly afterwards.

Notó que se le formaba un nudo en la garganta, pero, tras un instante de duda, asintió.

She wouldn’t leave Paladia, though, and eventually the torture caught up with her.

—Sí, lo he hecho.

She died at home, but there was nothing natural about it.”

Crowther exhaló un suspiro de alivio y le dio una suave palmada en el hombro.

There was no sound but the crackle of fire.

—Dale el talismán a Ilva.

Perhaps Crowther already knew all that.

Helena siguió contemplando el fuego.

She had no idea how much he and Ilva had lied to her, choosing to present Kaine’s motive as power because that was how they’d wanted Helena to perceive him.

—Decía la verdad cuando dijo que quería vengar a su madre.

She closed her eyes, wanting to sink into the floor. “He wants to know what you want.

Crowther suspiró, pero Helena continuó hablando:

You and Ilva.

—Cuando arrestaron a Atreus, Kaine estaba a salvo en la Academia, pero su madre no.

What proof of loyalty you expect from him.”

Ya sabes que la vivemancia no siempre deja marcas visibles.

The air shifted and then Crowther’s fingers grasped hold of Helena’s shoulder, pulling her to her feet and turning her to face him.

Kaine mató al principado Apollo porque era la única forma de salvarla, pero ella nunca se recuperó.

His eyes swept from the top of her head and slowly down, catching on various points along the way.

Cuando se sufre un estrés prolongado, este puede ocasionar daños en el corazón.

“What did you do?” he finally said.

Se produjo un silencio tenso, cargado por el escepticismo de Crowther.

She met his eyes, lifting her chin. “I completed my mission.

Helena no apartó la vista del fuego.

I made him loyal.”

Sentía un calor abrasador, pero no retiró las manos.

She was used to Crowther being unfazed by nearly everything, but he looked as if he’d been struck by lightning.

Si se quemaba, tal vez dejase de sentir también el resto del cuerpo.

Then he pulled her over to the window where the light was strongest, pushing her cloak off with his right hand, so he could get a good look at her.

—De niño, Atreus le hizo prometer a Kaine que cuidaría de su madre, ya que lo culpaba por lo enfermiza que se volvió Enid después del parto.

Her braids had been pulled loose, the sections hanging haphazardly.

Sin embargo, ella se negó a abandonar Paladia y, al final, la tortura acabó con ella.

His fingers dropped down to her neck, brushing against a spot that made her flinch.

Murió en casa, pero su muerte no tuvo nada de natural.

Before she could stop him, he flipped the clasp on her cloak; heavy with rain, it slid off her shoulders and to the floor with a wet thud, revealing her torn clothes, and all the bruises from the training that she usually healed before she got back.

No se oía más que el crepitar del fuego.

She recoiled, shrinking back towards the shadows.

Era posible que Crowther ya supiera todo eso.

She wanted to say it wasn’t what it looked like, but she didn’t think he’d believe her.

Helena no era consciente aún de cuánto le habían mentido él e Ilva; habían decidido contarle que la motivación de Kaine se basaba en el poder porque querían que Helena lo percibiera de esa forma.

“I’m fine,” she said, but her voice shook. “I only came here to clean up.

Cerró los ojos y deseó desplomarse en el suelo.

You said not to go back to Headquarters if I wasn’t put together.”

—Quiere saber qué queréis.

Crowther’s mouth was pressed into a hard line, and he started to speak—but then his eyes swept over her again and he slowly let go.

Ilva y tú.

Helena twisted free, shoulders hunching inward.

Qué prueba de lealtad estáis exigiendo.

There was a small bathroom through the next room.

Hubo un cambio en el ambiente.

She locked the door and stared at the reflection in the mirror; she was so pale that she was nearly grey, but her lips were red and bruised.

Crowther apretó el hombro de Helena y la obligó a levantarse y a mirarlo.

Her hair looked like a bird’s nest, only made worse by the rain.

Sus ojos la recorrieron de arriba abajo y se detuvieron en algunos detalles al hacerlo.

She turned away, rummaging for a cloth, anything to clean herself up with.

—¿Qué has hecho? —preguntó al fin.

Stripping off her underclothes and trying to scrub them clean.

Helena lo miró a los ojos con la barbilla levantada.

The cold, stinging wet between her legs had her feeling almost hysterical.

—He cumplido mi misión.

Her hands were shaking as she threw the rag into a bin under the sink, barely steady enough to remove the hairpins tangled in her hair.

Ahora me es leal.

Her lips were trembling, eyes burning as she braided her hair.

Estaba acostumbrada a que Crowther se mostrara siempre impasible, pero ahora parecía que lo había alcanzado un rayo.

She bit down on her lip as she coiled the long braids carefully at the base of her neck.

Sin mediar palabra, la empujó hacia la ventana, donde había más luz, y le retiró la capa para verla mejor.

Her fingers were trembling too hard to make her resonance stable, so she left the bruises.

Sus trenzas estaban deshechas, con mechones sueltos en todas direcciones.

Calm down.

Crowther deslizó los dedos por su cuello y acarició un punto que hizo que ella torciera el gesto de dolor.

You only have one chance to convince Crowther.

Antes de que pudiera reaccionar, desanudó el cierre de su capa; empapada por la lluvia, esta resbaló de sus hombros y cayó al suelo con un sonido húmedo y denso.

But the more she thought it, the more unsteady her breathing became.

Quedaron al descubierto sus ropas hechas jirones y los moratones que le salían en los entrenamientos, que normalmente se curaba antes de volver.

She crouched on the floor, pressing her hands over her face until she was quiet.

Helena dio un paso hacia atrás y se encogió entre las sombras.

She looked at her reflection again.

Quiso decir que no era lo que parecía, pero dudaba que la fuera a creer.

She was thinner now than she’d been when she first saw Kaine last spring.

—Estoy bien —afirmó, aunque le temblaba la voz—.

Her cheeks had hollowed, there were craters of exhaustion under her eyes, and her collarbones jutted out.

Tan solo he venido a asearme.

Stress had carved her away like water cutting through sand.

Me dijiste que no volviera al Cuartel General con este aspecto.

She rummaged through her satchel and found a salve for bruises, spreading it across her lips.

Crowther frunció los labios hasta convertirlos en una línea tensa y, aunque parecía a punto de replicar, volvió a observarla de arriba abajo y decidió soltarla.

Eventually her hands were steady enough that she could conceal the bruises with a tingle of resonance, watching the only colour in her skin slowly fade.

Helena se apartó de un tirón y hundió los hombros.

She pulled on a fresh shirt and walked out.

La habitación contigua era un baño, y ella se encerró dentro y contempló su reflejo en el espejo: tenía la piel de un gris macilento, pero sus labios estaban rojos e hinchados.

The rooms were silent.

El pelo parecía el nido de un pájaro, y la lluvia solo lo había empeorado.

“Crowther,” she called, her voice hollow.

Apartó la vista y buscó un paño, cualquier cosa con la que asearse.

There was no answer.

Se quitó la ropa interior y la frotó con fuerza, para intentar que quedara limpia.

She went to the front room; the fire had dimmed to embers, and he was gone.

La humedad fría y punzante que sentía entre las piernas estaba empezando a ponerla histérica.

She swallowed hard, trying not to cry.

Las manos le temblaban cuando tiró el paño en una papelera que había debajo del lavabo, y así siguieron mientras se deshacía de las horquillas que tenía enredadas en el cabello.

Of course he’d gone.

Empezó a trenzarse el pelo, aunque le ardían los ojos y le temblaba el labio.

He wasn’t going to listen.

Se le estremecían tanto las manos que no consiguió estabilizar su resonancia, así que dejó los moratones tal como estaban.

No one would.

«Cálmate.

He’d picked up whatever he’d come for and left again.

Solo tienes una oportunidad para convencer a Crowther».

A pit of despair opened in her stomach.

Sin embargo, cuanto más lo pensaba, más se alteraba su respiración.

Your failure was always the plan.

Se acuclilló, cubriéndose el rostro con las manos hasta que recuperó el control.

The room seemed to stretch as she reached the door.

Al alzar la vista, volvió a mirar su reflejo.

Her hands were shaking too much to manage the knob.

Estaba más delgada que la primavera pasada, cuando vio a Kaine por primera vez.

It swung open, Crowther reentering.

Las mejillas se le habían hundido, dos surcos de agotamiento le marcaban la mirada, y se le notaban demasiado las clavículas.

He was dripping wet, his thin hair plastered against his scalp.

El estrés le había dejado rastro, como una corriente de agua atravesando la arena.

He looked like a wet cat.

Rebuscó en su bolsa y encontró un bálsamo para los moratones que se aplicó en los labios.

“What are you doing?” he said as he came back in. “Sit down.”

Para entonces ya había recuperado el pulso suficiente como para eliminar las marcas con una pizca de resonancia, aunque aquello le borró también el leve rubor de su piel.

He had a paper packet in his hand, already tearing from the rain.

Se puso una falda limpia y salió del baño.

He ripped it open, and several bottles tumbled out.

Todo estaba en silencio.

“I wasn’t sure what was needed,” he said.

—Crowther —lo llamó con voz hueca.

She looked at the vials.

No obtuvo respuesta.

He must have gone back to Headquarters and taken them from the hospital.

Fue a la habitación principal; el fuego se había reducido a unas ascuas, y Crowther había desaparecido.

The drop point kept basic medical supplies but nothing too valuable or prone to supply shortages.

Tragó saliva e intentó no romperse.

She recognised her own handwriting on the labels.

Por supuesto que se había marchado.

She stared at them, and considered taking the laudanum, something to smooth down the razor-sharp edges of her emotions, but she needed to stay clearheaded.

No pensaba escucharla.

She inspected the next option.

Nadie lo haría.

A contraceptive.

Habría cogido aquello que había venido a buscar y se había ido.

Her throat worked as she set it down. “You know I don’t need that.”

Sintió cómo un pozo de desesperación se le abría en el estómago.

The only useful thing he’d brought was a valerian tincture, which the hospital used to calm patients who were in shock.

«El plan siempre fue que fracasaras».

“What happened?” Crowther asked as she unscrewed the lid and swallowed it.

La habitación pareció estirarse cuando quiso dirigirse hacia la puerta.

“You know what happened,” she said. “Exactly what you expected when you sent me there.

Le temblaban demasiado las manos para girar el pomo.

I’m just a bit slow.”

Entonces se abrió, y Crowther volvió a entrar.

“Marino.” His voice was sharp but then he seemed to catch himself and softened it. “What happened?”

Estaba chorreando, con el pelo fino pegado al cuero cabelludo.

She’d planned to go to Headquarters and make her report without any explanations about exactly why or how, to be calm and assured, but Crowther had caught her before she was ready.

Parecía un gato mojado.

Her jaw began trembling uncontrollably.

—¿Qué estás haciendo? —le espetó cuando cruzó el umbral—.

She felt so used.

Siéntate.

She understood rationally that it had to be like that.

Llevaba un paquete de papel en las manos, aunque ya se estaba deshaciendo por culpa de la lluvia.

The war was larger than any one person.

Lo abrió y sacó varios frascos.

Even Luc, whether his family legacy was real or not, was a figurehead, an idea greater than himself.

—No sabía qué necesitarías —explicó.

She knew that and she was willing to follow orders, knowing the consequences, understanding the sacrifice.

Helena contempló los frascos.

She didn’t need any promises of reward or acknowledgement or eternity; she would do what was necessary because it was necessary.

Debía de haber regresado al Cuartel General y pasado por el hospital.

They knew that, and they had still lied to her.

En el punto de encuentro solo había suministros médicos básicos, pero nada de valor o que pudiera escasear.

“I told Ilva that all I needed was more time,” she said simply. “It was just—abrupt.

Reconoció su propia letra en las etiquetas.

We’d been training.

Al leerlas, se planteó tomar láudano, algo que calmara la nitidez de sus emociones, pero tenía que mantener la cabeza fría.

The bruises were from that.”

Evaluó la siguiente opción: un anticonceptivo.

Crowther said nothing, but she could feel him watching her like a hawk.

—Sabes que no lo necesito —afirmó, y lo dejó en su sitio al tiempo que tragaba saliva.

She could only wonder what he was noticing, dissecting her behaviour, organising all the details of his observations into a mental file.

Lo único útil que había traído era una tintura de valeriana, de las que el hospital empleaba para calmar a los pacientes en estado de shock.

Helena pressed her hand against her sternum, trying to make the warmth from her palm seep into her, to speak calmly so that Crowther would believe her, not write her off as hysterical.

—¿Qué ha pasado? —preguntó Crowther mientras Helena abría el frasco y lo bebía de un trago.

“He was so upset afterwards that he told me everything.

—Ya sabes lo que ha pasado —repuso—.

He started crying after he told me about his mother.

Lo que querías que sucediera cuando me mandaste allí.

He always knew you were going to betray him.

Simplemente voy un poco lenta.

It was part of his plan.

—Marino. —Había empleado un tono cortante, pero pareció arrepentirse, porque enseguida su voz se suavizó—: ¿Qué ha pasado?

That’s why he’s kept climbing rank; he figured the more important he was, the greater the blow—when it happened.”

Helena tenía pensado presentarse en el Cuartel General y dar parte sin explicaciones sobre por qué o cómo, mostrarse tranquila y decidida, pero Crowther la había pillado antes de tiempo.

There was a long silence after that.

Empezó a temblarle la mandíbula.

Crowther gave a low sigh that sent Helena’s heart skyrocketing.

Se sentía usada.

“If he’s such a suicidal martyr, why would he cooperate now?”

Y, en el fondo, entendía que así era como debía ser.

Her throat closed.

La guerra estaba por encima de las personas.

Her fingers twisted at the loose fabric of her shirt. “Well, now that he can’t deny the obsession to himself, I don’t think he knows how to let go.

Incluso Luc era solo una figura simbólica, una idea más grande que sí mismo, con independencia de la veracidad de su linaje.

Like you said, the Ferrons are self-destructively possessive.

Ella lo sabía y estaba dispuesta a cumplir órdenes.

The array made it worse.

Era consciente de las consecuencias y entendía el sacrificio.

He regards me as—” She swallowed. “—as his.

No necesitaba que le prometieran nada a cambio; ni recompensas, ni reconocimiento, ni la vida eterna.

I think that’s what changed things.

Hacía lo que había que hacer porque era necesario.

He still doesn’t care about survival, but he also doesn’t know how to let go.”

Sus superiores lo sabían y, aun así, le habían mentido.

Crowther’s lips pursed.

—Le dije a Ilva que únicamente necesitaba más tiempo —se limitó a decir—.

He ran his thumb slowly against them, considering.

Solo ha sido algo… abrupto.

Helena watched him, twisting her fingers, squeezing until her knuckles ground together. “Will you—will you tell Ilva?

Estábamos entrenando.

I know you both think I’m compromised, but I did what I was told to.

De ahí los moratones.

He said he’ll do whatever you want.

Crowther no dijo nada, pero Helena notaba su mirada fija, como la de un halcón.

I did it—I did—”

Le hubiera gustado saber de qué se estaba dando cuenta, qué estaba analizando de su comportamiento mientras la observaba con tanta atención.

Her voice failed, and she started shaking uncontrollably.

Helena se llevó la mano al esternón y extendió el calor desde la palma de la mano por todo el cuerpo, para así poder dirigirse a Crowther con calma.

She gripped her arm, using her resonance to force the valerian to take effect.

Era la única forma de que la creyese sin considerarla una histérica.

Calm down.

—Cuando me lo confesó todo, estaba muy alterado.

“Yes,” Crowther said, “I’ll speak with Ilva.

Empezó a llorar después de contarme lo de su madre.

You—did do as instructed.” He cleared his throat. “If he’s prepared to prove himself, that changes things.”

Siempre supo que lo ibais a traicionar.

Helena nodded, glancing blindly around the room, unable to feel relief. “Thank you.”

Era parte de su plan.

She started towards the door, although she wasn’t sure where she was going to go.

Por eso ha subido de rango; imaginó que, cuanto más importante fuera, mayor sería el golpe… cuando muriera.

She didn’t think she was calm enough to return to Headquarters, but she couldn’t stay here.

Le siguió un largo silencio, interrumpido por un suspiro grave de Crowther que hizo que a Helena le latiera fuerte el corazón.

“Marino.”

—Si es un mártir tan suicida, ¿por qué quiere cooperar ahora?

She winced.

Notó que se le cerraba la garganta.

Crowther was still watching her.

Retorció la tela suelta de su falda entre los dedos.

There was an odd look in his eyes, like he was seeing more than she wanted him to.

—Bueno, ya no puede negar la obsesión que siente.

He swallowed several times and pressed his fingertips together. “I was about the same age you were when the Holdfasts brought me to Paladia.”

Creo que no sabe cómo dejarme ir.

Helena drew back.

Tenías razón: los Ferron son posesivos de una forma autodestructiva.

She knew that Crowther had been one of the Holdfasts’ sponsored students, but he’d been brought in as an orphan after the Holdfasts had saved him.

Y el sello de la espalda ha agravado esa característica.

Helena had never considered their experiences as similar.

Me considera una… —tragó saliva— posesión.

“My family and village were murdered at the hands of a necromancer.

Creo que eso es lo que ha cambiado.

They crawled up from the ground and left me in the snow to die.

No le importa sobrevivir o no, simplemente no sabe cómo dejarme marchar.

When the Eternal Flame came, there was no saving them, only lighting the fires to erase the atrocities they’d become.

Crowther frunció los labios y se los acarició con el pulgar mientras reflexionaba.

I chose to distinguish myself with my willingness to do what is necessary.

Helena lo observó mientras sus propios dedos se retorcían y apretaban hasta que los nudillos quedaron alineados.

Not for glory or for the Faith, but because someone must do whatever it takes to stop the rot.

—¿Puedes… puedes decírselo a Ilva?

I’ve never regretted my choice.”

Sé que los dos pensáis que me he involucrado demasiado, pero he hecho lo que me pedisteis.

He looked down at his right hand, slowly opening and closing it.

Kaine dice que hará lo que queráis.

It was thinner than his other hand—the muscles had wasted over the years.

Lo he hecho… He logrado que…

He was silent for so long that Helena finally realised the speech was meant as a sort of apology.

La voz se le quebró y empezó a temblar sin control.

That in some way he regarded them as alike, and she had done something for him and now he regretted treating her so poorly.

Se sujetó el brazo y empleó la resonancia para forzar el efecto de la valeriana.

She didn’t want an apology, though.

Necesitaba calmarse.

“Are you—” He blinked and started again. “Is there—healing you require?”

—Sí —accedió Crowther—.

Her spine went rigid.

Hablaré con Ilva.

The last thing she wanted was Elain or Ivy anywhere near her.

Has… has hecho lo que te pedimos —carraspeó—.

“He wasn’t violent,” she said sharply.

Si Ferron está dispuesto a demostrarlo, eso cambia las cosas.

She folded her arms tightly around herself.

Helena asintió y miró a su alrededor sin ver nada.

Her voice was very tense, her throat refusing to relax. “It was just—abrupt.

No sentía alivio.

Besides”—she let her voice grow venomous—“wasn’t healing myself part of your instructions from the very beginning?”

—Gracias.

Crowther looked away. “If you need clearance for anything, I’ll see that it’s signed off.”

Se dirigió hacia la puerta, aunque no sabía adónde ir.

“I just came here to fix my hair and get a new shirt.

Estaba demasiado alterada para regresar al Cuartel General, pero tampoco podía permanecer ahí.

I wasn’t injured,” she said, growing angry at this sudden and belated attempt at concern.

—Marino.

They’d been so clear that she was alone in this, and now that the ruse was finally up, now that it had come out that they hadn’t really sold her off, forever, without a second thought, they thought she’d want them to care?

Helena se encogió.

A sick heat burned in the pit of her stomach.

Crowther seguía observándola.

“You should allow people to look out for you.”

La miraba de una forma extraña, como si estuviera viendo más de lo que ella habría querido revelar.

A harsh, sobbing laugh split her chest at the absurdity of his words.

El hombre tragó saliva un par de veces y juntó las yemas de los dedos.

His expression grew pinched. “There was no time to train you for the assignment.

—Yo tenía la misma edad que tú cuando los Holdfast me trajeron a Paladia.

We thought it best to let the deal run its course and—collect the pieces afterwards.

Ella dio un paso hacia atrás.

It made you more convincing.”

Sabía que Crowther había sido uno de los alumnos becados por los Holdfast.

A lump rose in her throat. “Well, he saw through you both.

Había llegado a Paladia siendo huérfano, rescatado por ellos.

I was the only fool in the end.

Helena nunca se había planteado que sus historias pudieran parecerse.

But you got what you wanted.

—Mi familia y todo mi pueblo fueron masacrados por un nigromante.

Lucky you, I guess.”

Se alzaron del suelo y me dejaron atrás, en la nieve, para que muriera.

“You—” He said it heavily and then paused.

Cuando llegó la Llama Eterna, ya no había salvación posible, salvo prender fuego a la aberración en la que se habían convertido.

“What?” she asked sharply, anger evaporating as panic closed around her again.

Yo me aseguré de distinguirme mostrando que estaba dispuesto a hacer lo que fuera necesario.

Was it not enough?

Nunca quise la gloria ni me interesaba la Fe, simplemente sabía que alguien tenía que detener la putrefacción.

Was he trying to break it to her gently that Ilva would still choose to kill Kaine?

Jamás me he arrepentido de mi decisión.

That the month had been a lie, too.

Se miró la mano derecha, la abrió y cerró con lentitud.

That there was nothing Kaine could do that was as valuable as betraying him?

Era más pequeña que la otra; los músculos se habían atrofiado con el paso de los años.

Crowther’s eyebrows furrowed as he studied her. “I’ve spent a year working on the logistics of replacing you … I must admit, you are the most exceptional asset the Eternal Flame possesses.

Guardó silencio durante tanto tiempo que Helena acabó por comprender que aquel relato era como una disculpa velada y que, de algún modo, Crowther la veía ahora como una igual.

And I am sorry for that.”

Helena había hecho algo por él y ahora se arrepentía de haberla tratado con tanta condescendencia.

Knowing now the Holdfasts’ method of selecting their “prodigies,” she did see the parallels between them: both brought to Paladia as talented children with nowhere else to go, their lives spent being lonely and useful because it was all they knew.

Pero Helena no quería una disculpa.

Perhaps, looking at her as his successor, he did find her tragic.

—¿Estás…? —Parpadeó y volvió a empezar—: ¿Necesitas… que alguien te cure?

CROWTHER WENT WITH HELENA TO the Outpost the next week.

Ella se puso en tensión.

After his brief interlude of humanity, Crowther had retreated back into his shadows, and when he reemerged, he’d reverted to his normal self.

Lo último que quería era tener a Elain o a Ivy cerca.

Still, Helena could feel how her place in his strategy had shifted with the new developments.

—No ha sido violento —puntualizó.

She said nothing to him on the way there.

Se cruzó de brazos con fuerza.

They took a lorry as far as the gate and then walked to the Outpost.

Su voz sonaba tan contenida que se obligó a calmarse—.

It was startling how quick the journey was when not taken on foot.

Solo fue algo… abrupto.

There was a light, misting rain draped like a shroud over the city, frothing into a thick mist near the dam.

Además —permitió que el veneno impregnara su voz—, sanarme sola formaba parte de las instrucciones que me diste desde el principio, ¿no?

The necrothralls on the Outpost faded into the rain when they passed.

Crowther apartó al vista.

Kaine was waiting inside the tenement as though he’d never left.

—Si necesitas permiso para algo, te lo firmaré.

He looked gaunt.

—Solo he venido a peinarme y a cambiarme de camisa.

Tired.

No estaba herida —replicó Helena, cada vez más enfadada por esa muestra de preocupación repentina tan tardía.

He didn’t meet her eyes.

Le habían dejado claro que estaba sola en esto, pero ahora que había descubierto la trampa, ahora que sabía que la habían vendido sin pensárselo dos veces y para toda la vida, ¿creían que necesitaba su preocupación?

He barely even looked at her.

Un calor nauseabundo bullía en el fondo de su estómago.

The cloths that had covered the floor had all been folded and lay in a pile against one wall.

Solo de pensar en lo absurdas que sonaban sus palabras, se le escapó un sollozo a medio camino entre la pena y la risa.

If Crowther had any reaction to the tenement, he didn’t show it, but Helena felt a visceral sense of discomfort as his eyes swept over the room.

Crowther pareció enfadarse.

She was used to it, but now she saw all the dirt, chipped paint, and cracked tiles again.

—No tuvimos tiempo de prepararte para la misión.

Remembered how degrading it had felt the first time she’d arrived.

Creímos que lo mejor era dejar que el trato siguiera su curso y… arreglar las consecuencias después.

As he stood surveying the space, the air in the room grew tense.

Así resultarías más convincente.

Like a forest going abruptly silent.

Se le hizo un nudo en la garganta.

Crowther had not seen combat in years, but Helena had healed enough of his interrogation victims to know he had a talent for precision pyromancy, and now he had two hands to wield it with.

—Bueno, Kaine os caló desde el principio.

She wasn’t sure about the extent of Kaine’s abilities, but even the Undying struggled against flame alchemists.

Al final, la única idiota he sido yo.

The feeling of hatred between Crowther and Kaine was so tangible, the air sang with it.

Pero ya tenéis lo que queríais.

Crowther was the one who spoke first, eyes glittering. “I understand you wish to make a new deal with the Eternal Flame, Ferron.”

Supongo que ha sido una suerte.

There was mocking insinuation in his tone.

—Tienes que… —empezó con pesar, pero se calló.

Kaine had gone startlingly pale. “So it would seem.”

—¿Qué? —insistió Helena.

Helena had thought she was supposed to act as an intermediary between them, but Kaine glanced towards her.

La furia que sentía estaba dando paso al pánico.

“You can go now, Marino.

¿Acaso no era suficiente?

I’m sure Crowther can find his way back on his own.”

¿Estaba intentando decirle con delicadeza que Ilva pensaba matar a Kaine igualmente?

Helena hesitated, looking between the two men.

¿Que ese último mes también había sido una mentira?

Amusement lit Crowther’s face as he glanced at Helena, too. “No need to walk back alone.

¿Que, por mucho que hiciese, Kaine no podía evitar que lo traicionaran?

Wait outside, Marino.

Crowther la observó con el entrecejo fruncido.

I’m sure Ferron won’t let anything happen to you on the landing.”

—He pasado un año intentando encontrar la forma de reemplazarte… Tengo que admitir que eres la integrante más excepcional de la Llama Eterna.

The muscle in Kaine’s jaw ticked, but he didn’t speak.

Y, por ello, te pido disculpas.

Helena looked between them and then turned reluctantly and went out to the landing.

Ahora que conocía el método que usaban los Holdfast a la hora de elegir a sus «prodigios», sí que veía el paralelismo entre ambos: los dos habían venido a Paladia por su talento, sin tener ningún otro sitio al que ir, y habían dedicado su vida a estar solos y ser útiles, porque eso era lo único que conocían.

She only heard Crowther utter one word before the door sealed shut:

Tal vez, si ahora la consideraba su sucesora, sí que le parecía una tragedia.

“Beg.”

Una semana después, Crowther acompañó a Helena al Reducto.

She wandered the hallway, peeking through the tenements missing doors at the identical units.

Tras aquel breve interludio de humanidad, el hombre volvió a retirarse a la sombra y, cuando emergió de nuevo, era el mismo de siempre.

She followed the stairs to the top floor and wandered back down.

Aun así, Helena se percató de que después de los últimos acontecimientos su estatus dentro la estrategia había cambiado.

The rain was falling through the broken skylight, creating a constant drip and patter.

Durante el trayecto, no le dirigió la palabra.

As she reached the second floor, a glimpse of something hidden in the shadows caught her attention.

Tomaron un camión hasta la barricada y luego caminaron hasta el Reducto.

She went closer, rising on her toes and squinting, trying to see clearly what it was.

Era desconcertante lo rápido que se hacía el viaje cuando no iba a pie.

It had been strategically concealed to make it almost invisible in the shadows.

Había luz, y caía una llovizna que cubría la ciudad como un sudario.

A human eye encased in glass stared down at her.

Una neblina espesa lo envolvía todo alrededor de la presa.

When Helena moved to the side, it rotated, following her.

Los necrómatas del Reducto se esfumaron entre la lluvia al verlos pasar.

A shiver ran down her spine.

Kaine los esperaba en el módulo, como si no se hubiera marchado nunca.

She hadn’t even known that it was possible to animate only a part of a body, but it was undeniably animated.

Estaba demacrado, cansado.

Perfectly preserved.

No la miró a los ojos.

Angled to see the entire landing from the shadows.

De hecho, apenas le dedicó un vistazo.

That was how Kaine always knew when she was there.

La tela que antes cubría el suelo estaba doblada en un rincón.

She sat on the steps for half an hour before Crowther emerged from the room.

Si Crowther tuvo alguna impresión del lugar, no la dejó entrever, aunque Helena advirtió cierta incomodidad cuando sus ojos recorrieron la estancia.

She knew he probably wouldn’t tell her the terms, but she hoped that after having her wait, he’d tell her something.

Ella ya se habría acostumbrado, pero en ese momento solo vio la suciedad, la pintura descascarillada y los azulejos resquebrajados.

He merely paused, studying her. “Good work, Marino.”

Se acordó de lo denigrante que le había parecido aquel lugar la primera vez que entró en él.

Crowther observó todo sin decir nada, y el aire se volvió cada vez más tenso, como un bosque que se sume en el silencio de repente.

Aunque hacía años que no participaba en ninguna batalla, Helena había sanado a suficientes víctimas de sus interrogatorios para saber que Crowther tenía la capacidad de usar la piromancia de forma precisa, y ahora tenía dos manos con las que emplearla.

No sabía con certeza hasta dónde llegaban las habilidades de Kaine, pero incluso los inmarcesibles temían enfrentarse con los alquimistas de fuego.

El odio entre Crowther y Kaine era tan denso que hasta el aire parecía vibrar en su presencia.

Fue Crowther quien habló primero, y cuando lo hizo le brillaban los ojos.

—Tengo entendido que quieres renegociar tu trato con la Llama Eterna, Ferron. —Había cierta burla en su voz.

Kaine se había quedado sorprendentemente pálido.

—Eso parece.

Helena había supuesto que tendría que mediar entre ellos, pero Kaine la fulminó con la mirada.

—Puedes marcharte, Marino.

Estoy seguro de que Crowther sabrá volver solo.

Ella vaciló y miró a ambos hombres alternativamente.

A Crowther se le iluminó el rostro con diversión cuando posó la vista en Helena.

—No me apetece volver caminando solo.

Espérame fuera, Marino.

Estoy convencido de que Ferron no permitirá que te suceda nada en el descansillo.

Kaine apretó los dientes, pero no replicó.

Helena les dedicó una última mirada a los dos y se dio la vuelta a regañadientes.

Al salir al rellano, antes de cerrar la puerta, oyó una sola palabra de los labios de Crowther:

—Suplícamelo.

Se paseó por el pasillo, inquieta, y se asomó a los módulos que carecían de puerta.

Eran todos iguales.

Subió a la planta de arriba y volvió a bajar.

La lluvia caía por el tragaluz desprovisto de cristal como una cascada infinita.

En la segunda planta, algo escondido entre las sombras le llamó la atención.

Se acercó, se puso de puntillas y entrecerró los ojos para ver mejor lo que era.

Lo habían colocado de tal forma que apenas se distinguía en la oscuridad.

Era un ojo humano metido en una caja de cristal.

La estaba mirando.

Cuando ella se movía, giraba y la seguía.

Helena se estremeció.

No sabía que se podía reanimar solo una parte del cuerpo, pero era evidente que ese ojo había cobrado vida.

Estaba perfectamente conservado y había sido colocado en ángulo para que vigilase todo el rellano desde el rincón.

Así era como Kaine siempre se enteraba de que había llegado.

Estuvo media hora más sentada en los escalones hasta que Crowther salió del módulo.

Sabía que probablemente no le contaría los detalles del trato, pero confiaba en que, después de hacerla esperar, al menos le diría algo.

Sin embargo, el hombre se detuvo y la miró de arriba abajo.

—Buen trabajo, Marino.

CHAPTER 49

Februa 1787

CAPÍTULO 49

THE MOOD IN HEADQUARTERS GREW SOMBRE AS the winter crawled on.

Febre 1787

The days felt endlessly dark, the air so cold and damp that even quick walks across the commons were bone-chilling.

El ambiente del Cuartel General se tornó sombrío conforme avanzaba el invierno.

After months of largely successful defence and fortification, the Resistance was hit hard and sudden.

Los días eran largos y oscuros, y hacía tanto frío y humedad que hasta dar un breve paseo por los jardines dejaba el cuerpo helado.

One of the walls along the East Island was blown up by a bomb blast so large, it took down several buildings.

Después de meses de avance en la defensa del territorio y la fortificación de las zonas recuperadas, la Resistencia recibió un duro golpe.

Then more blasts, and before they’d even begun to evacuate the survivors, the necrothralls and chimaeras poured in.

Una bomba de enorme potencia derrumbó una de las murallas y varios edificios de la isla Este.

The Resistance lost a battalion and an entire swath of the East Island.

A continuación, se produjeron más explosiones y, sin disponer de tiempo para evacuar a los supervivientes, aparecieron los necrómatas y las quimeras.

Luc’s battalion was trapped inside a building, pursued down to the river level where they ended up cornered for more than a day until the Resistance assembled a large enough force to get them out.

La Resistencia perdió un batallón entero y toda una franja de territorio de la isla Este.

The casualties were terrible.

El escuadrón de Luc se quedó atrapado en un edificio y fue perseguido hasta el río, donde acabó acorralado durante más de un día, hasta que la Resistencia reunió una compañía lo bastante numerosa como para rescatarlos.

Half of them were badly injured.

Sufrieron numerosas bajas, la mitad de los integrantes resultaron heridos de gravedad, uno de los médicos fue asesinado en la retirada y otra falleció por las heridas sufridas durante el asalto.

One medic was killed in the retreat, and another died from injuries during the siege.

Luc logró contener a las quimeras y a los necrómatas levantando un muro de llamas durante horas.

Luc had held back the chimaeras and necrothralls by maintaining a wall of flame for hours on end.

A Soren y a varios soldados se les había derrumbado encima un edificio, y él tenía el brazo derecho destrozado.

He and Lila had been coated in smoke and grime, too exhausted to even speak when they were brought back.

Cuando se produjo el asalto, solo pudo cuidar a los heridos y ver cómo morían uno tras otro.

Soren sustained a shattered right arm when the floor collapsed under him and several others.

Se negó a hablar del tema.

He’d been held back from defence during the siege, caring for the injured and watching them die one by one.

Antes de que Helena regresara al Reducto, Crowther le informó de que, a partir de entonces, solo vería a Kaine una vez por semana.

He refused to talk about it.

No le dio explicaciones.

BEFORE HELENA COULD RETURN TO the Outpost, Crowther informed her that she would see Kaine only once a week now.

Eran los nuevos términos del trato.

No explanation about why; those were simply the new terms of the deal.

Cuando llegó el martis, Helena no sabía qué esperar, si todo sería diferente entre ellos, pero, cuando Kaine llegó, desplegó la tela acolchada sobre el suelo sin mediar palabra y se dispuso a entrenar con ella como si nada hubiera sucedido.

When Martiday came, she didn’t know what to expect, how different things might be, but when Kaine arrived, he wordlessly kicked the padding cloths across the floor and began training her as if nothing had changed, except he didn’t look at her anymore.

Aunque ya no parecía el mismo, ya no era capaz de mirarla a los ojos.

His eyes seemed to go through her.

—¿Cómo sabes todo esto? —le preguntó ella cuando dejó de atacarla para enseñarle varias formas de romper un brazo de manera que el hueso quedara destrozado o atravesara la piel, porque así se ralentizaba la regeneración.

“How do you know all this?” she asked when he paused in attacking her to show her several techniques for breaking arms in ways that would shatter the bone or pierce the skin, slowing regeneration.

—Igual que sé todo lo demás —contestó con la mirada perdida—.

“The same way I know any of it,” he said, staring across the room. “When you can’t die, people keep hurting you until you can hurt them more.”

Cuando uno no puede morir, la gente te hace daño hasta que consigues devolvérselo.

“I’m sorry.”

—Lo siento.

He looked at her sharply, fury in his eyes. “I’m sure you are.”

La miró con un brillo furioso en los ojos.

There was no more conversation.

—Seguro que sí.

He attacked and she had to fend him off.

No hubo más conversación.

She managed to get a jab in under his arm but experienced only a moment of triumph before his fingers were wrapped around her throat, dragging her close.

La atacó y Helena no tuvo más remedio que defenderse.

They both froze, eyes meeting, and it was as if time stopped.

En un momento de descuido, consiguió darle un puñetazo, pero apenas tuvo tiempo de celebrarlo porque Kaine le rodeó la garganta con una mano y la atrajo hacia sí.

He snatched his hand back with a scathing glare. “Unless you start thinking faster than you move, you’re going to be killed.”

Los dos se quedaron quietos, mirándose a los ojos, como si el tiempo se hubiera detenido.

She failed twice more.

Kaine apartó la mano y le dedicó una mirada desdeñosa.

“That’s enough for today.” He finally turned away from her, reaching into his cloak, and pulled out an envelope, setting it on the table.

—Como no aprendas a pensar más rápido de lo que te mueves, acabarás muerta.

Helena’s chest clenched in dread as she went over to her satchel and pulled out an envelope of her own, fidgeting with it as she turned to face him.

Falló otras dos veces más.

“Crowther said to give you this.”

—Ya basta por hoy.

A sort of deadness filled his eyes as he looked over. “Right … My orders for the week.”

Kaine le dio la espalda, metió la mano en el bolsillo de su capa y sacó un sobre que dejó sobre la mesa.

He pulled it from her fingers with a listless jerk.

Helena sintió una presión en el pecho cuando se agachó a coger su bolsa y sacó otro sobre.

“Kaine—”

Lo sostuvo, inquieta, antes de darse la vuelta.

“Run along, Marino.

—Crowther me pidió que te diera esto.

I have work to do.”

Cuando la miró, sus ojos carecían de vida.

IT WAS HELENA’S JOB TO examine Luc to ensure he was healthy before he was allowed to leave Headquarters.

—Cierto… Mis órdenes de esta semana.

He was still so shattered he scarcely seemed to notice her, which was for the best, as they hadn’t spoken since the solstice.

Se lo arrancó de los dedos sin miramientos.

He and Lila watched each other with a fervent intensity, as though the other person were their only touchstone.

—Kaine…

If it were possible, Helena would have recommended a break—a few weeks to recuperate at least.

—Lárgate, Marino.

Luc was dangerously haggard, and his lungs worried her, but they could not afford the luxury.

Tengo cosas que hacer.

Both were dispatched back to the front in their newly polished armour to reassure the now nervous battalions.

Helena fue la encargada de asegurarse de que Luc se encontraba en condiciones de salir del Cuartel General.

Soren was only a few days behind them.

El principado seguía tan conmocionado que apenas pareció reparar en que se trataba de ella, lo cual, en realidad, era lo mejor, ya que no habían hablado desde el solsticio.

Each week Kaine would train her, hand over intelligence reports, take his orders, and leave without even a backwards glance.

Luc y Lila se miraban con intensidad y fervor, como si fueran la piedra angular el uno del otro.

They didn’t talk anymore.

De haber podido, Helena habría recomendado que descansaran, que al menos se tomaran unas semanas para recuperarse.

If she asked questions and it wasn’t about combat, he ignored them.

Luc estaba tan demacrado que daba miedo verlo, y le preocupaban sus pulmones, pero en ese momento no podían permitirse el lujo de descansar.

It felt as if there were a canyon between them now.

Ambos regresaron al frente con su armadura recién pulida para insuflar ánimos a los batallones, que cada vez se mostraban más inquietos.

It was fine, though.

Soren los acompañó unos días después.

He was alive.

Una vez a la semana, Kaine entrenaba con ella durante media hora, le entregaba informes de inteligencia, aceptaba sus órdenes y se marchaba sin mirar atrás.

Every week she got to see him and know he was alive.

Ya no hablaban.

However, that was not something he seemed to care about.

Si Helena preguntaba algo que no tuviera que ver con el combate, él la ignoraba.

There was a raw despair visible in his eyes.

Era como si se hubiera abierto un desfiladero imposible de salvar entre ellos.

Even his rage was smothered, as though he were existing out of sheer obligation.

Pero no importaba.

After three weeks, she caught him by the wrist as he was taking Crowther’s envelope from her. “Please—look at me.”

Estaba vivo.

He snatched his hand back but then stared squarely at her, that cold rage briefly reappearing. “Is this not enough for you?

Cada semana lo veía y sabía que estaba vivo.

Is there something else you want, too?”

Sin embargo, a él ya no parecía importarle lo más mínimo.

“No—” She looked at him helplessly. “I’m sorry.

En sus ojos no había más que una desesperación descarnada.

I thought—”

Hasta su rabia se había extinguido, como si continuara existiendo por pura inercia.

He gave a dry laugh. “Perhaps someday, if I have time again, I can make you a list of all the things that apologies don’t fix.”

Al cabo de tres semanas, lo sujetó por la muñeca cuando iba a coger el sobre de Crowther.

Her hands dropped. “Kaine, I—”

—Por favor…, mírame.

“Don’t—use my name.

Kaine retiró la mano, pero la miró de frente.

I hate the way it sounds on your tongue.” He ripped the envelope from her fingers and left.

De nuevo, asomó en sus ojos esa rabia helada.

There was another deluge of injuries.

—¿Es que esto no es suficiente?

Helena could barely keep track of all the battles and skirmishes, the victories and losses.

¿Quieres más?

In the hospital it all blurred together into endless screaming.

—No… —Lo miró sintiéndose impotente—.

Time seemed to morph into a horrific monotony, punctuated only with Kaine’s cold resentment.

Lo siento, pensé…

She tried to stay busy.

Él soltó una carcajada seca.

With Rhea’s permission, she attempted a tentative treatment of Titus, but he reacted poorly, becoming severely sick with a fever, putting an immediate end to the attempt.

—Algún día, cuando vuelva a tener tiempo, te haré una lista de todas las cosas que no se arreglan con una disculpa.

She was cut loose.

Helena dejó caer las manos.

Left to her own devices.

—Kaine, no…

Everyone else seemed to come and go—even the other healers got dispatched down-island to the new hospital every few weeks—but Helena was always at Headquarters.

—No… No me llames por mi nombre.

Ilva and Crowther no longer made any demands of her except to pass on their orders.

Odio cómo lo pronuncias. —Le arrancó el sobre de los dedos y se marchó.

She was a collar around Kaine’s neck, and her job now was to bear it.

Poco después, hubo otra avalancha de heridos.

SHE WAS RETURNING FROM THE Outpost when her hospital charm grew hot.

Helena apenas conseguía mantenerse al tanto de las batallas y escaramuzas, de las victorias y derrotas.

She sprinted the rest of the way back.

En el hospital, todo se entremezclaba en un grito infinito.

There was blood smeared across the ground of the gatehouse.

El tiempo se convirtió en una monotonía insoportable, interrumpida únicamente por el frío resentimiento de Kaine.

The guards were waiting for her. “Where were you?”

Helena intentó mantenerse ocupada.

“Who?

Con permiso de Rhea, quiso tratar a Titus, pero este no reaccionó como esperaba.

What—” she gasped out as they cleared her.

Después de sufrir unas fiebres gravísimas, no le quedó más remedio que renunciar a ello.

“Lila,” said one of the young guards. “And Soren.”

Se sentía libre, a su aire.

Dread flooded through her like poison. “Where’s Luc—”

Todos los demás iban y venían; muchas sanadoras eran destinadas al sur de la isla para trabajar en el hospital nuevo, pero Helena siempre permanecía en el Cuartel General.

There was a pause and she knew before the older guard spoke.

Ilva y Crowther solo le exigían llevar sus órdenes a Kaine.

“Missing.”

Helena se había convertido en el collar que Kaine llevaba al cuello, y su trabajo era soportarlo.

Helena’s body moved but her mind had stalled as she raced to the hospital.

Estaba volviendo del Reducto cuando notó que el brazalete del hospital se calentaba.

No.

Recorrió el camino que quedaba a la carrera.

This couldn’t be happening.

El suelo de la garita de la entrada estaba lleno de sangre.

The casualty ward was in a frenzy as Helena entered.

Los guardias la estaban esperando.

Elain immediately turned to Helena, hands covered in blood, her face white with panic.

—¿Dónde te habías metido?

“My resonance doesn’t work!” she said, her voice rising with panic. “I can’t stop the bleeding.”

—¿Quién está herido?

Lila was laid out on a bed, covered in dust and dirt and blood.

¿Qué ha…? —dijo entre jadeos cuando la dejaron pasar.

The remains of her armour were smashed and split, her clothes shredded, as if she’d been caught in an explosion.

—Lila —respondió uno de los guardias más jóvenes—.

Nurses were cutting off the straps and transmuting her armour to get it off her.

Y Soren.

A wide gouge ran down her face, from temple to cheek, and below that, at the base of her neck, a large puncture was pouring blood.

Sintió que la embargaba el terror.

“I don’t know what’s wrong!” Elain was saying as Helena washed her hands under scalding water and doused them in carbolic dilution. “I think there’s something inside her, but my resonance doesn’t work!

—¿Dónde está Luc?

When I try to feel her, it’s like—my hands—”

Se hizo un silencio que le dejó claro a Helena lo que había pasado.

“Soren too?

—Ha desaparecido.

Or just Lila?”

Ella echó a correr, pero su mente se quedó paralizada mientras se dirigía al hospital.

“I don’t know, I haven’t tried him.

No.

We just got them in.

Eso no podía estar pasando.

She’s bleeding out, and I can’t feel anything!”

El pabellón de heridos estaba desbordado.

“Check Soren,” Helena said. “I need medics for Lila, and Pace.

Nada más entrar, Elain interceptó a Helena.

Tell her I need her now.”

Tenía las manos empapadas de sangre y la cara lívida de pánico.

She moved next to Lila.

—¡No me funciona la resonancia! —exclamó, histérica—.

The neck was one of the few openings in her armour if her helmet had been off.

No puedo detener la hemorragia.

Her blood was soaking the bed.

Lila yacía sobre una camilla, cubierta de polvo, tierra y sangre.

She’d been hooked up to an intravenous drip with plasma expanders, but it wouldn’t do any good if they couldn’t get her to stop bleeding.

Las partes de la armadura que habían sobrevivido estaban destrozadas y rajadas, y su ropa hecha trizas, como si una explosión la hubiese alcanzado de lleno.

Lila’s head was lolled back.

Las enfermeras se afanaban por cortar la tela y transmutar la armadura para quitársela.

She was still conscious, muttering under her breath, over and over. “… told him—to run.

Un tajo profundo le cruzaba la cara, de la sien a la mejilla, y más abajo, justo en la base del cuello, un agujero del que no dejaba de brotar sangre.

I—told him—t-to run—”

—¡No sé qué está pasando! —decía Elain mientras Helena se lavaba las manos con agua hirviendo y las sumergía en una solución carbólica—.

Helena reached out with her resonance and felt the horribly familiar disruption of nullium.

Creo que tiene algo dentro, pero la resonancia no me responde.

She’d hoped to be wrong.

Cuando he intentado sanarla, ha sido como si… como si mis manos no…

That Elain was just hysterical.

—¿A Soren le sucede lo mismo?

Or even burned out.

¿O solo a Lila?

Anything but this.

—No lo sé, no he probado con él.

The nullium was much stronger than the shrapnel Helena had retrieved from Kaine.

Acaban de llegar.

Altered in some way to intensify the effect.

Se está desangrando, ¡y no noto nada!

She tried to at least get a vague sense of the size of what had been driven into Lila’s chest cavity.

—Ve a examinar a Soren —le ordenó Helena—.

Trying to determine if there was a risk of puncturing her heart if they put pressure on the wound.

Necesito médicos para Lila.

It was like peering through fog.

Y avisa a Pace, dile que quiero que venga ahora mismo.

Her hands felt as though they were asleep, needlepoints pricking across her nerves as she tried to search for the most intense sense of dissonance.

Se acercó a Lila.

It was long and slender.

El cuello era una de las pocas zonas desprotegidas de su armadura.

It had likely pierced her lung, possibly grazed her heart, but it was hard to tell.

Estaba empapando la cama de sangre.

This was so much worse than she and Shiseo had been prepared for.

Le habían colocado una sonda intravenosa con expansores de plasma, pero no le serviría para nada si no conseguían cortar la hemorragia.

“What is it?” Pace appeared at her side.

Lila tenía la cabeza torcida, como si se le hubiese dislocado el cuello.

Helena was pressing gauze over the wound, trying to keep it from bleeding more.

Todavía estaba consciente y no dejaba de mascullar entre dientes:

Lila had gone silent.

—… le dije que… corriera.

“It’s nullium.

Le… dije que… que corriera.

She’s going to need manual surgery to get it out.

Helena extendió su resonancia y sintió la perturbación inconfundible del anulitio.

Maier isn’t trained, but you were in the hospitals, back when they still used it, right?”

Había rezado para estar equivocada, para que Elain se hubiera confundido al estar histérica o, simplemente, exhausta.

Pace went very white. “It’s been a long time.

Cualquier cosa menos eso.

I only assisted.”

Este anulitio era mucho más potente que la metralla que le había extraído a Kaine.

Helena drew a harsh breath.

Lo habían alterado de alguna forma para intensificar su efecto.

She couldn’t disclose her own surgical experience with nullium. “I—used to help my father, sometimes.

Intentó hacerse una idea, aunque vaga, de lo que había en la cavidad torácica de Lila.

If you’ll lead, and I keep her stable, then maybe.

Si iban a aplicar presión en la herida, necesitaba saber si corrían el riesgo de perforar el corazón.

Is Soren—?”

Fue como querer ver a través de una niebla espesa.

She was afraid to know if Soren had nullium injuries.

Sentía las manos dormidas, con pinchazos como agujas en los nervios, pero buscó el origen de la disonancia.

If she and Pace had to choose which twin to save, protocol dictated that the person with better odds of survival should receive priority, but as paladin primary, Lila had priority.

Era un objeto largo y fino.

“The others can heal him,” Pace said. “He took a bad blow to the head, but it’s nothing Elain can’t manage.”

Probablemente, le había atravesado un pulmón y estaba cerca del corazón, aunque no podía saberlo con certeza.

Helena closed her eyes as she fought to stay calm, trying to will Lila to survive, because this time she could not make her do it.

—¿Qué tiene? —Pace estaba a su lado.

“Move her into the operating theatre,” Pace said. “I’m sure Maier will help as much as he can.

Helena presionaba una gasa contra la herida para evitar la hemorragia.

We’ll need medics and nurses for support.

Lila había perdido el conocimiento.

I’ll brief them.

—Es anulitio.

You keep her stable.”

Vamos a tener que operarla manualmente para extraerlo.

It had been only a handful of times that Helena had assisted her father with surgery.

Maier no sabe hacerlo, pero tú trabajabas en los hospitales cuando todavía se hacía así, ¿verdad?

Before the massacre.

Pace palideció de pronto.

Observant with a good head in a crisis, he’d said.

—De eso hace mucho tiempo, y yo solo era auxiliar.

But that was a long time ago.

Helena respiró hondo.

Handing over surgical instruments was very different from performing surgery without resonance.

No podía explicar la experiencia quirúrgica que tenía con el anulitio.

No one was prepared.

—Yo solía… ayudar a mi padre.

The nullium they’d been familiar with only interfered when they worked with it directly.

Si tú guías y yo la mantengo estable, podemos conseguirlo.

This was much more diffuse.

¿Soren tiene…?

When Lila was sedated, Matron Pace used a long pair of clamps to reach into the puncture just above Lila’s collarbone and pull out a long, rusting spike.

Le daba miedo saber si Soren tenía lesiones provocadas por el anulitio.

It was fragile, degrading already due to the unstable fusion.

Si había que elegir a qué gemelo salvar, el protocolo dictaba que debía recibir tratamiento la persona con más probabilidades de sobrevivir, pero al ser Lila paladina primera tenía prioridad.

Shards kept breaking off, forcing Pace to reach in over and over, removing them piece by piece.

—Las otras se encargarán —respondió Pace—.

Helena could feel through her resonance that even with the bulk of the spike removed, there were shards dissolving into Lila’s blood.

Ha recibido un fuerte golpe en la cabeza, pero nada que Elain no pueda arreglar.

The nullium was spreading through her body like a fog, thicker and more impenetrable with every passing moment.

Helena cerró los ojos como queriendo obligarse a recuperar la calma y suplicar que Lila sobreviviera, porque esta vez no podría hacerlo todo ella sola.

The fragility of the nullium was both a gift and a curse.

—Llévala al quirófano —le ordenó a Pace—.

It had taken the path of least resistance.

Estoy segura de que Maier hará todo lo posible por ayudarnos.

There was a small puncture in Lila’s lung, but her heart was not damaged, nor her oesophagus.

Necesitaremos personal de medicina y enfermería.

It had stayed within the cavity.

Yo me encargo de ponerlos al día.

But the pieces were everywhere, and the alloy was so unstable that it was rapidly dissolving.

Tú mantenla estable.

Pace wiped her forehead with a cloth. “We’re going to need to do a thoracotomy to get the pieces out.

Helena solo había asistido a su padre en algunas operaciones antes de la masacre.

Is she stable enough?”

Él siempre le decía que había que ser observadora y mantener la calma en los momentos de crisis, aunque de eso hacía ya mucho tiempo.

An alchemical surgeon like Maier could normally perform a thoracotomy without needing to open a patient.

Manejar instrumental quirúrgico era muy distinto a operar sin resonancia.

It only needed incisions large enough to get slender tools inside; with training and resonance, their instruments were an extension of their fingers and senses.

Nadie sabía cómo hacerlo.

Helena held back her resonance, using ordinary touch to check Lila’s vital signs, because it was easier than trying to parse all the interference. “She’s holding on.”

El anulitio que conocían solo interfería si se tocaba directamente, pero este era mucho más difuso.

They made an incision between Lila’s ribs, using makeshift retractors to pry the bones apart so they could reach all the remaining shards.

Una vez que Lila estuvo sedada, la enfermera Pace introdujo un par de pinzas largas en la perforación que tenía en la clavícula y extrajo una especie de lanza alargada y oxidada.

The pieces varied in size and crumbled if they weren’t picked out carefully enough.

Era frágil y, debido a la fusión inestable, estaba empezando a degradarse.

There were little cuts and grooves in Lila’s lungs and heart where shards had nicked her—wounds that could be easily repaired if Helena could use her resonance but were laborious and dangerous now, each requiring manual sutures.

Cada vez que se partía, Pace tenía que meter la pinza de nuevo para sacar uno a uno todos los fragmentos.

The procedure was all unfamiliar, and they were racing against time.

Usando su resonancia, Helena comprobó que, a pesar de que habían sacado la mayor parte de la lanza, aún quedaban esquirlas disolviéndose en la sangre de Lila.

The longer the nullium had to break down and distribute into Lila’s blood, the greater the likelihood that she might die from the metal toxicity.

El anulitio se extendía por su cuerpo como una neblina y, a cada segundo que pasaba, se volvía más espesa e impenetrable.

The surgery was pushing her body to its utmost limits, and Lila had to survive on her own.

La fragilidad del anulitio era a la vez una bendición y una maldición.

Helena manually siphoned the blood, keeping Lila’s heart beating as Pace worked.

Se había abierto paso por donde encontraba menos resistencia.

A nurse had taken the larger shards to Shiseo to analyse and synthesise the sequestering agent, but that treatment was hours away.

Lila tenía un pulmón levemente perforado, pero el corazón estaba intacto, al igual que el esófago.

It was possible that until they managed to purge the metal from Lila’s bloodstream, they would be unable to use any kind of resonance on her.

La lanza solo había afectado a la cavidad torácica, aunque los fragmentos estaban por todas partes, y la aleación era tan inestable que se disolvía rápidamente.

“A thoracic lavage next,” Pace said at last, setting down her tools.

Pace se secó la frente con un paño.

Her eyes were bloodshot from strain by the time they finished.

—Vamos a tener que hacerle una toracotomía para sacar todos los fragmentos.

Maier took over the sutures.

¿Está estable para soportar una operación así?

His stitches were beautifully neat, but he looked shaken as he worked.

En circunstancias normales, un cirujano alquímico como Maier habría realizado una toracotomía sin necesidad de abrir al paciente.

Helena looked up and found it was growing dark outside. “I should check on Soren.”

Las incisiones solo eran necesarias cuando había que introducir instrumental fino, pero, con resonancia y la formación adecuada, el trabajo se limitaba a los dedos y los sentidos.

She felt so strange as she washed her hands.

Helena retiró la resonancia y tocó a Lila para comprobar sus signos vitales; así era más sencillo que tratar de abrirse paso entre toda aquella interferencia.

She’d barely used her resonance, but the pressure of the last several hours had her head throbbing.

—Está aguantando.

Stepping out of the operating theatre, she found most of the hospital crowded around one bed.

Le hicieron una incisión entre las costillas y emplearon unos retractores improvisados para apartar los huesos y sacar todas las esquirlas que quedaban.

Soren was awake and propped up.

Los fragmentos variaban en tamaño y se deshacían si no se sujetaban con sumo cuidado.

All the privacy curtains had been pushed aside, and at the forefront of the people surrounding him was Ilva.

Lila tenía pequeños cortes y fisuras en los pulmones y en el corazón, justo donde la habían alcanzado los fragmentos.

Soren’s arm was in splints, and bandages covered half his face.

Eran heridas que Helena podría reparar fácilmente si pudiera usar su resonancia, pero, dadas las circunstancias, tendrían que coserla a mano, un trabajo laborioso y que implicaba mucho riesgo.

He kept shaking his head. “I don’t—remember.

La operación superaba todo lo que conocían, y además trabajaban contra reloj.

It happened so fast.”

Si el anulitio seguía partiéndose y mezclándose con la sangre de Lila, moriría por la contaminación que provocaba el metal.

“Did you recognise anyone?

El cuerpo de Lila estaba llegando al límite y debía resistir sin ayuda de la resonancia.

Even imagine that you saw a face?” Ilva said, grasping Soren’s wrist.

Helena continuó bombeando sangre de forma manual para que el corazón de Lila no dejara de latir mientras Pace la operaba.

“I don’t know,” Soren said again, his voice straining. “There was—an explosion.

Una enfermera llevó los fragmentos más grandes a Shiseo para que los analizara y sintetizara un agente quelante, pero tardaría horas en desarrollar un tratamiento eficaz.

Something hit me.

Si no conseguían purgar el metal del torrente sanguíneo de Lila, no podrían sanarla mediante la resonancia.

Might have been out seconds or minutes.

—Ahora le haremos un lavado torácico —informó Pace, que dejó finalmente el instrumental a un lado.

When I got up, I couldn’t see.

Cuando terminaron, tenía los ojos inyectados en sangre del esfuerzo.

Luc was gone, and Lila was on the ground, bleeding out.

Maier se encargó de la sutura.

She kept saying, Told him to run.

Los puntos quedaron limpios y perfectos, aunque parecía conmocionado por todo el asunto.

I didn’t know where to look—so I came back.”

Cuando Helena levantó la cabeza, se dio cuenta de que empezaba a hacerse de noche.

“There was no warning?” The questions seemed to be exploding from Ilva.

—Voy a ver cómo está Soren.

She was visibly agitated. “No signs at all?

Se sintió extraña al lavarse las manos.

Who was leading the unit?”

No había usado demasiado la resonancia, pero la tensión de las últimas horas le provocó dolor de cabeza.

“I—” Soren’s expression twisted, and he seemed to struggle to remember.

Salió del quirófano y se encontró a todo el hospital congregado alrededor de una cama.

“I always said it was a mistake, allowing a female paladin,” Matias said. “If I had been Falcon at the time, I would never have allowed such a violation of tradition to be entertained.

Soren estaba despierto y sentado.

I warned you, Ilva, Luc was partial to her, but no: Lila Bayard was too exceptional to separate from him.

Habían apartado las cortinas que le daban algo de privacidad y, a la cabeza de todos los que lo rodeaban, se encontraba Ilva.

Now look what’s happened.”

Soren tenía un brazo escayolado y medio rostro cubierto de vendas.

“Shut your mouth!” Ilva snarled over her shoulder at Matias, her fingers still digging into Soren’s wrist.

No paraba de negar con la cabeza.

Then she turned back and shook him. “Did she say Luc surrendered himself?

—No… no lo recuerdo.

Did he hand himself over because of Lila?”

Todo sucedió muy rápido.

“I don’t know,” Soren half whispered.

—¿Reconociste a alguien?

Elain was standing near Soren’s bed, too awed by the number of Eternal Flame members currently flanking the bed to interfere.

¿Alguna cara, por casualidad? —insistió Ilva, sujetando a Soren de la muñeca.

“Pardon,” Helena said in a curt voice, and she pushed herself through the crowd. “Soren Bayard has a head injury.

—No lo sé —repitió Soren con voz cansada—.

It’s inadvisable to stress him.”

Hubo… hubo una explosión.

Everyone turned to look at her.

Recibí un golpe.

“Is Lila awake?

No sé si pasaron segundos o minutos.

Can she answer questions?” Ilva said, instantly rising to her feet.

Cuando me levanté, no veía nada.

Helena shook her head sharply. “She is not available for anything.

Luc había desaparecido y Lila estaba en el suelo, desangrándose.

We performed an extensive manual surgery to remove a spike of nullium that she’d been stabbed with, but the alloy deteriorated and distributed through her bloodstream, which will interfere with anything involving resonance until it’s removed.”

No paraba de decir: «Le dije que corriera».

“How long will that take?” The panic on Ilva’s face was clear.

No sabía dónde buscar, así que regresé aquí.

Helena shook her head. “We have her under anaesthesia right now, but we’re working blind.

—¿Nadie os advirtió? —Ilva parecía desbordada de preguntas por hacer, visiblemente afectada—.

She may wake in the next few hours, or it could take days.

¿No visteis ninguna señal?

Lila is very strong, but this will still be harder on her than past injuries.

¿Quién lideraba la unidad?

Nothing’s certain yet.”

—No… —Soren frunció el ceño, como si tratara de recordar.

Soren had slumped back and looked as if he was on the verge of a panic attack, but Ilva drew herself up like a viper.

—Siempre mantuve que era un error permitir que una mujer fuese paladina —intervino Matias—.

“I thought you had prepared for this eventuality,” Ilva said. “What have you all been doing?”

Si hubiese sido falcón en aquella época, jamás habría consentido semejante violación de las tradiciones.

Helena’s jaw tensed.

Te lo advertí, Ilva.

Why was it always the hospital’s fault when things went wrong?

Luc no era imparcial con ella, pero nada.

If Helena had come out and said that surgery was a success and Lila was already getting out of bed, they’d all be off to the perihelion to offer Sol flames of thanksgiving.

Lila Bayard era demasiado excepcional para separarlos.

But bad news was always the hospital’s fault.

Y ahora mira lo que ha pasado.

How nice it must be, to be a god.

—¡Cállate! —le espetó Ilva por encima del hombro.

“The alloy has been altered, and the interference is much more intense.

Todavía tenía los dedos clavados en la muñeca de Soren.

Manual procedures are not simple, especially in a hospital where only two people have any experience performing them.

Luego se giró y lo zarandeó—.

If you want the hospital prepared to perform manual surgery, the Falcon will need to approve the cadavers for practice, as we requested several months ago.”

¿Lila dijo algo sobre que Luc se entregara?

Matias coughed as if he’d swallowed something the wrong way and suddenly stopped looking like he wanted to be present.

¿Se entregó por culpa de ella?

Ilva was gripping her cane but looked ready to topple.

—No lo sé —respondió Soren en un susurro.

It was as if Luc’s loss had ripped the ground out from beneath her.

Elain estaba de pie junto a la cama de Soren, demasiado impactada por la presencia de tantos miembros de la Llama Eterna como para atreverse a intervenir.

“Examine him, then,” Ilva said, moving unsteadily away from Soren’s bed. “There will be a Council meeting in an hour.

—Perdonad —dijo Helena en tono cortante, y se abrió paso entre la multitud—.

I want full reports on both the Bayards.”

Soren Bayard ha sufrido una contusión cerebral.

Everyone filed out.

En estos casos es mejor evitar cualquier tipo de estrés.

Helena glared and jerked her head, indicating that Elain put the privacy curtains back as she sat down next to Soren.

Todo el mundo se giró hacia ella.

He was leaning back amid the pillows which had propped him up, covered in newly healed cuts.

—¿Lila ha recobrado el conocimiento?

She could tell, as soon as her resonance touched him, that he’d lost his right eye.

¿Puede responder a mis preguntas? —soltó Ilva poniéndose en pie al instante.

Whatever had hit him had fractured the socket and crushed it.

Helena negó con la cabeza, con un gesto algo distante.

Her fingers trembled.

—No está en condiciones.

“She’s never going to forgive me,” he said, his voice a near whisper.

Le hemos hecho una operación complicada de forma manual para extraer la lanza de anulitio con la que fue apuñalada.

Helena didn’t know if he was referring to Ilva or Lila.

Sin embargo, la aleación se ha deteriorado y distribuido por su torrente sanguíneo, así que no podemos sanarla con resonancia hasta que expulse todo el anulitio.

She squeezed his hand. “If you’d gone after Luc in this state, all three of you might be dead.

—¿Cuánto tardará en recuperarse? —preguntó Ilva, con el pánico dibujado en el rostro, pero Helena volvió a negar con la cabeza.

That wouldn’t have been any help.

—Ahora mismo está anestesiada, pero estamos trabajando a ciegas.

I’m sure there’s more people looking for him because you came back.”

Puede que se levante en unas horas, o tal vez tarde algunos días.

Elain had done well with her healing.

Lila es muy fuerte, pero esta lesión es más grave que cualquiera de las anteriores.

He’d had several broken bones, including the same arm he’d shattered just a few weeks ago.

No podemos dar nada por sentado.

It hadn’t fully healed, and it was likely to have lingering issues now.

Soren se encogió sobre sí mismo; parecía que estaba a punto de sufrir un ataque de pánico.

“Do you think he’s still alive?” Soren asked.

En cambio, Ilva se envaró como una serpiente.

Helena’s heart caught.

—Creía que estabais preparados para esto —declaró Ilva—.

She couldn’t think of any reason the Undying wouldn’t immediately kill Luc.

¿Qué habéis estado haciendo todo este tiempo?

“Until we know he’s dead, he’s still alive.

Helena apretó los dientes.

And we’re going to get him back,” she said, forcing her voice to sound hopeful. “Stop worrying now.

¿Por qué cuando las cosas se torcían era siempre culpa del hospital?

I need to check your head.”

Si Helena hubiera salido diciendo que la operación había sido un éxito y que Lila estaba levantándose de la cama, todos habrían ido corriendo a encender velas en honor a Sol.

He had a concussion, but his eye and brow bone had absorbed most of the blow.

Sin embargo, las malas noticias eran siempre responsabilidad del hospital.

All her visits to Titus had made her more familiar with brains; she felt as if she understood them better and could at least diagnose accurately, rather than shying away.

Qué tranquilos debían de estar los dioses.

Elain hadn’t known what to do with the destroyed eye and had left it, just wrapping gauze over it and repairing only the bone.

—Han hecho cambios en la aleación y la interferencia es mucho más potente.

“Soren, your right eye’s—”

Las operaciones manuales no son simples, sobre todo en un hospital donde solo hay dos personas con algo de experiencia para llevarlas a cabo.

“I know,” he said brusquely, as if it didn’t matter. “I can still fight, though, right?”

Si queréis que el hospital esté preparado para la cirugía manual, el falcón deberá aprobar el uso de cadáveres para practicar, tal como solicitamos hace meses.

Her hands stilled. “You’ve broken your arm and lost half your range of vision.

Matias tosió con violencia, como si se hubiera atragantado y, de repente, ya no parecía querer estar allí.

That’s going to require adapting.

Ilva estaba apoyada en su bastón, como si estuviese a punto de desplomarse.

You’re going to be vulnerable.

Era como si la pérdida de Luc la hubiera dejado totalmente descolocada.

You won’t see things from the right.”

—Adelante, examínalo —cedió Ilva, que se apartó de la cama de Soren con un paso algo inestable—.

“I’ll just turn my head,” he said in a flat voice. “Handy thing, necks.”

Nos reuniremos dentro de una hora.

She sighed. “You’re not going back out.

Quiero informes completos de los dos Bayard.

Not for weeks at least.”

Se fueron todos.

He shook his head. “Lila’s out.

Cuando la sala quedó despejada, Helena le lanzó una mirada fulminante a Elain para indicarle que volviera a cerrar las cortinas y se sentó junto a Soren.

I have to bring Luc back before she wakes.

El gemelo estaba apoyado en las almohadas que lo mantenían erguido, cubierto de cortes que ya habían sido tratados.

She can’t wake up and find out I didn’t go after him.” His chin trembled.

En cuanto lo rozó con su resonancia, supo que había perdido la visión del ojo derecho.

In twelve years of knowing him, Helena had never seen Soren cry.

El golpe que recibió le había fracturado el hueso del cráneo y aplastado el nervio óptico.

He looked down. “I didn’t tell them, but she told me to leave her.

Helena notó que le temblaban las manos.

To go find him.

—No me lo perdonará jamás —masculló Soren en apenas un susurro.

But I didn’t.

La chica no supo si se refería a Ilva o a Lila.

I told her I’d go, as soon as I got her safe—”

Le apretó la mano.

He started trying to climb out of the bed.

—Si hubieras ido a por Luc en este estado, ahora los tres estaríais muertos.

It only took one hand to push him back.

Eso no le habría servido a nadie de nada.

He was barely strong enough to sit up.

Estoy segura de que hay más gente buscándolo porque has vuelto para contarlo.

“Soren, I need to deal with the ruptured tissue in your eye,” she said, trying to sound firm.

Elain lo había sanado bien.

He ignored her, trying to shove her off, but she was adept enough at combat now.

Cuando llegó, tenía varios huesos rotos, incluido el mismo brazo que se había fracturado unas semanas antes.

She deflected his hand and slipped her fingers behind his head.

Como no había terminado de curarse, probablemente le quedarían secuelas.

It took only a frisson of resonance and his remaining eye rolled back as he collapsed, unconscious.

—¿Crees que sigue vivo? —preguntó Soren.

She closed his eye gently so it wouldn’t dry out. “I’m so sorry,” she whispered as she set to work.

A Helena se le paró el corazón.

If there was anything intact inside the socket, there would have been a small chance of saving some of his sight, but Soren’s eye was wrecked.

No se imaginaba un motivo por el que los inmarcesibles hubieran querido mantenerlo con vida.

She removed all the tissue that couldn’t be repaired so that it wouldn’t rot or cause infection, then carefully rebandaged him.

—Hasta que no sepamos que está muerto, sigue vivo.

In a few weeks, someone would make a beautiful glass eye for him, or perhaps shape a gem.

Y vamos a traerlo de vuelta —se obligó a decir Helena con esperanza—.

Assuming there still was a Resistance in a few weeks.

Deja de preocuparte.

Rhea arrived just as Helena finished.

Tengo que examinarte la cabeza.

It had been a long time since both twins had been in the hospital.

Tenía una contusión, pero el ojo y el hueso frontal del cráneo eran lo más preocupante.

Rhea’s expression was stoic, but her eyes were searching as she moved towards Soren.

Después de visitar a Titus en tantas ocasiones, se había familiarizado con la forma del cerebro y creía entenderlo mejor.

Helena stood up. “I just finished.

Al menos, ahora podía diagnosticar con más precisión en lugar de salir corriendo sin saber qué hacer.

I can wake him,” she said, quickly covering all the eye tissue with a cloth.

Elain no se había atrevido a arreglar el ojo destrozado.

“No, let him rest.” Rhea sat down slowly on the edge of the bed, studying the parts of Soren’s face that weren’t obscured. “My little boy,” she said softly, her voice a murmur, as if she feared Soren might wake.

Se había limitado a vendarlo y reparar el hueso.

Helena stepped back, not sure if Rhea would want privacy or answers.

—Soren, el ojo derecho…

“You know, he was such a little thing when he was born,” Rhea said, one of her hands reaching and covering Soren’s. “Titus could fit him into one hand.

—Lo sé —repuso con brusquedad, como si no importara—.

The doctors didn’t think he’d make it.

Pero puedo seguir luchando, ¿no?

Lila came out bright red and screaming, but my little Soren was just a wisp of a baby.

Helena dejó de mover las manos.

Quiet and pale.

—Tienes un brazo roto y has perdido la mitad de tu visión.

Even when he needed to nurse, he’d barely make a sound.

Necesitas adaptarte a esto.

He always followed Lila around, never caused trouble himself, but was always right there, getting into hers.”

Serás más vulnerable.

Rhea gave a sobbing laugh. “I thought I was doing such a great thing when they were born.

No verás nada que se acerque por tu lado derecho.

Twins.

—Pues giraré la cabeza —replicó, seco—.

Two babies for the Bayard family.

Para eso tengo cuello.

Our little paladins.” Rhea’s body trembled as she held Soren’s hand. “And now Titus doesn’t even know what’s been done to our beautiful children—all my family, I only have pieces of them left.”

Helena suspiró.

She folded over Soren.

—No vas a volver al frente, al menos hasta dentro de unas semanas.

Her body was shuddering, but she cried silently.

Soren sacudió la cabeza.

There was a trick to sobbing like that; it was something a person had to learn to do.

—Lila está inconsciente.

Helena slipped away, to give her space to grieve.

Tengo que encontrar a Luc antes de que despierte.

THE MEETING WAS SOMBRE.

No puede abrir los ojos y enterarse de que no lo he traído de vuelta. —Le tembló la barbilla.

ILVA sat at the Council table, looking almost drugged while the reports were being given.

En los doce años que lo conocía, Helena nunca había visto llorar a Soren.

The attack had occurred on the lower part of the East Island.

El chico bajó la mirada—.

Luc and Lila had been leading the battalion towards Headquarters; they’d passed a condemned building, and just as Luc and Lila stepped beyond it, there had been an explosion.

No lo he contado, pero Lila me pidió que la abandonara allí y que fuera a buscar a Luc.

The building had collapsed.

No lo hice.

Soren had been on the edge of the blast and thrown by it.

Le respondí que iría en cuanto la pusiera a salvo…

Only two others had survived, because they’d fallen behind.

Intentó levantarse de la cama, pero no necesitó más que una mano para volverlo a empujar contra el colchón.

They’d been caught in the rubble with only minor injuries.

Apenas tenía fuerzas para sostenerse.

There’d been signs of a fight, char marks and a pool of blood, presumed to be Lila’s.

—Soren, tengo que arreglar el tejido desgarrado del ojo —dijo Helena con firmeza.

Burned human remains, presumed to be necrothralls, a lich with his talisman ripped out.

El chico la ignoró y quiso apartarla de un manotazo, pero Helena ya tenía cierta soltura en combate.

Luc’s sword, rings, and other weapons were found discarded, as if he’d left first and then been stripped.

Esquivó el gesto con facilidad y deslizó los dedos por detrás de su cabeza.

There’d been no word from the Undying.

Solo necesitó un cosquilleo de resonancia para dejarlo inconsciente.

No proclamation that Luc was dead or even captured.

Soren se desplomó.

The guards had all been told to prepare for the possibility that he might return reanimated or with his body possessed by a lich.

Helena le cerró el ojo con cuidado para que no se secara.

If Luc reappeared, all due diligence must be performed.

—Lo siento —murmuró, y se puso manos a la obra.

No one was to believe in any miraculous escapes.

Si quedaba algo intacto en la cuenca del ojo, tal vez existía una posibilidad mínima de que recuperara parte de la visión, pero Soren tenía el ojo destrozado.

As time passed, the questions grew.

Helena retiró todo el tejido irreparable para evitar que se pudriera y provocara infecciones, y volvió a vendar la zona con cuidado.

Why would the Undying keep him alive?

En unas semanas, podrían conseguirle un buen ojo de cristal o tal vez una gema.

Wouldn’t they announce if he was dead, or were they keeping him hostage to negotiate a surrender?

Eso si la Resistencia seguía existiendo dentro de unas semanas.

If he was a hostage, why hadn’t they reached out?

Rhea llegó justo cuando Helena estaba terminando.

“Until we know that Lucien is dead, we will assume that he is alive,” Ilva said in an icy voice, rousing herself when one of the lead metallurgists referred to planning for contingencies. “The Undying have no reason to conceal his capture.

Hacía mucho que ninguno de los gemelos acababa en el hospital.

It’s been twelve hours, and we haven’t received word.

Su rostro se mantenía sereno, pero sus ojos revelaban un pánico contenido mientras se dirigía hacia Soren.

It may be a sign that not everything is as it seems.”

Helena se incorporó.

As the meeting closed, Matias stood, announcing his intention to entreat the heavens to return Luc to them safely.

—Ya he terminado.

Many people followed him.

Puedo despertarlo —afirmó, cubriendo la cuenca del ojo con un paño.

Ilva remained at the table, speaking to Crowther.

—No, déjalo descansar. —Rhea se sentó lentamente en el borde de la cama y observó el resto de la cara de Soren—.

“Marino, a word before you go,” Ilva said when Helena rose to return to the hospital.

Mi niño… —susurró, como si temiera que Soren pudiese despertarse.

Helena waited until the room was empty.

Helena retrocedió un poco; no estaba segura de si necesitaba privacidad o quería respuestas.

Ilva flicked a hand, and the guards closed the doors.

—¿Sabes?

“You’ll head to the Outpost.

Cuando nació, era un bebé muy pequeño —contó Rhea, que cogió la mano de Soren en la suya—.

We’re going to use Ferron,” Ilva said in a brusque voice. “Every piece of information he has or can obtain about the circumstances of Luc’s capture—I want it all.

Le cabía a Titus en la palma de la mano.

As well as an explanation as to why we received no warning about this.”

Los médicos no creían que sobreviviera.

“Of course.” She’d expected as much.

Lila nació gritando, con la cara roja, pero mi pequeño Soren no era más que un suspiro, callado y pálido.

“Tell him this is a critical mission,” Ilva added as Helena turned to go. “Those precise words, Marino.

No hacía ni un ruido, ni siquiera cuando mamaba.

A top priority.

Siempre iba detrás de Lila, jamás causó un problema, pero acababa metido en todos los líos por acompañarla a ella. —A Rhea se le escapó un gemido a medio camino entre el sollozo y la risa—.

If he has an opportunity to get Luc back for us, that would be preferable to the losses we’ll suffer with a rescue.”

Cuando nacieron, pensé que había logrado una hazaña.

They meant to sacrifice Kaine to recover Luc.

Gemelos, dos bebés para la familia Bayard.

It was the obvious choice.

Nuestros pequeños paladines. —Rhea temblaba mientras sostenía la mano de Soren—.

An easy trade-off.

Y ahora Titus ni siquiera es consciente de lo que están sufriendo nuestros maravillosos hijos… Toda la familia.

The kind that any strategist would make.

Solo me quedan los restos.

But—

Se inclinó sobre Soren.

“All right.” Her voice was lifeless.

Aunque lloraba en silencio, Helena vio cómo su cuerpo se estremecía.

LUMITHIA HUNG LIKE A GIANT silver disc in the sky, so near full Ascendance that she blotted out the planets, leaving the night sky as an endless black abyss overhead.

Desahogarse así era una rareza: había que aprender a hacerlo.

The bright silver light cast glaring shadows across the city.

Ella se retiró con discreción, para que tuviera espacio para llorar.

When Helena reached the landing in the tenement, she paused and stepped intentionally into the silver shaft of light cascading from the broken skylight, looking up at the eye hidden in the corner.

La reunión del Consejo fue lúgubre.

Then she waited.

Ilva se sentó a la mesa, aunque parecía que estaba sedada mientras escuchaba todos los informes.

It was a long wait.

El ataque se había producido en los barrios bajos de la isla Este.

The windows rattled in the wind, but she didn’t hear anything until the door clicked and Kaine strode in.

Luc y Lila encabezaban un batallón hacia el Cuartel General cuando pasaron junto a un edificio en ruinas y, en cuanto lo dejaron atrás, hubo una explosión.

Everything about him seemed sharper. “What happened?”

El edificio se desplomó.

The instant he asked the question, she realised he didn’t know.

Soren era el que se encontraba más cerca en el momento del estallido, fue alcanzado de lleno por la onda expansiva y salió despedido por los aires.

Ilva had been right: If the Undying had Luc, it was being kept secret.

Solo sobrevivieron dos soldados más, los únicos que se habían quedado atrás.

“There was an attack today.

Los encontraron entre los escombros con heridas leves.

A bombing,” she said, and her voice trembled. “Killed most of a battalion, the Bayard twins barely survived, and Luc—is missing.”

En el lugar de los hechos había indicios claros de combate: restos calcinados y un charco de sangre que creían que pertenecía a Lila.

“Are you sure?”

También encontraron cadáveres humanos, probablemente de necrómatas, y un liche con el talismán arrancado.

She gave a stiff nod. “They used a weapon made from that resonance-interference alloy.

Más lejos, como si alguien los hubiera arrojado a propósito, estaban la espada y los anillos de Luc.

We call it nullium.

Los inmarcesibles no se habían pronunciado aún.

Lila was stabbed and nearly killed with it.

No anunciaron la muerte ni la captura de Luc.

You didn’t know this was in the works?”

Se ordenó a los guardias que se prepararan por si Luc aparecía reanimado o por si un liche hubiera poseído su cuerpo.

He shook his head slowly. “I didn’t.

Si Luc reaparecía, había que tomar todas las medidas necesarias.

There’s suspicion of a spy due to—recent sabotage.

Nadie creería que había escapado de milagro.

And I haven’t had the leisure to be as present as I used to be.”

El tiempo solo agravó la incertidumbre.

She looked down, drawing a deep breath before she spoke. “We have to get Luc back.

¿Por qué los inmarcesibles lo habían dejado con vida?

I was told to tell you it’s critical.

¿Por qué no habían anunciado que estaba muerto?

Your top priority.”

¿O quizá lo tenían encarcelado para negociar una rendición?

“Right …”

Y, si estaba preso, ¿por qué no se habían puesto en contacto con ellos?

“Any information you can get on his capture, who did it, where he is, if he’s alive … The Council wants you—” Her words caught. “—to do anything you can.”

—Hasta que sepamos con certeza que Lucien está muerto, daremos por sentado que sigue con vida —declaró Ilva con tono gélido.

“Of course,” was all he said, and he turned to go.

Se había sentido ofendida cuando uno de los metalúrgicos jefe preguntó cuál era el plan en caso de que sucediera lo peor—.

She watched his back, the shift of his shoulders, one dipping as he reached for the knob.

Los inmarcesibles no tienen motivos para ocultar un triunfo como este.

She didn’t know if she was ever going to see him again.

Han pasado doce horas y no se han puesto en contacto con nosotros.

“Wait,” she said.

Puede que esto signifique que no todo es lo que parece.

He paused but didn’t look back. “I’ll call you when I have something.”

Cuando la reunión terminó, Matias se levantó y anunció que iba a suplicar a los cielos que Luc regresara sano y salvo.

“Kaine … when I kissed you, I—”

Hubo muchos que lo siguieron.

He turned suddenly.

Ilva permaneció en la mesa conversando con Crowther.

In one moment he was across the room and in the next, he was in front of her, his expression venomous, his teeth bared. “Really, you want to discuss this now?”

—Marino, no te vayas, tenemos que hablar contigo —dijo Ilva cuando Helena se disponía a volver al hospital.

Her throat was so thick with guilt, she could barely speak.

Ella esperó a que la sala de reuniones estuviera vacía.

But she was desperate. “Will you look at me, at least?”

Con un gesto de Ilva, los guardias cerraron las puertas.

A cruel glint entered his eyes as they locked squarely on her face.

—Tienes que ir al Reducto.

It was like being punched to have his full attention again.

Vamos a usar a Ferron —dispuso Ilva con brusquedad—.

“You want me to look at you?” His voice was light, almost cajoling, but there was fury beneath the surface.

Quiero saber cualquier información que tenga o que pueda conseguir sobre la posible captura de Luc, y también una explicación de por qué no hemos recibido ninguna advertencia al respecto.

He leaned towards her. “Fine.

—Por supuesto. —Era lo que esperaba.

I’m looking.

—Dile que se trata de una misión de vital importancia —añadió Ilva cuando Helena se giró para marcharse—.

I must say, it’s delightful, seeing all the guilt in your eyes.”

Usa esas palabras, Marino.

He sneered, drawing back. “You know, I used to think the circumstances of my servitude to the High Necromancer as cruel an enslavement as anyone could conceive, but I must admit, it pales beside you.”

Es una prioridad absoluta.

He tilted his head. “At least before, I could console myself that it wasn’t my fault; acceptance was the best I could do to keep my mother safe.

Si él puede traer a Luc de vuelta, nos ahorraríamos las pérdidas que implicaría organizar un rescate.

It’s different when I have no one to blame but myself.”

Querían sacrificar a Kaine para recuperar a Luc.

His hand came up, his gloved fingers wrapping around her throat, pulling her forward. “After all, I did choose you.”

Era la opción más lógica.

She met his eyes, that deadened despair so visible when he looked at her.

Un intercambio fácil que cualquier estratega consideraría.

“I envied your naïveté, how you credited me with goodness and failed to realise that it was a setup from the very beginning.

No obstante…

When you begged for a chance to heal me, I gave in.

—De acuerdo —asintió Helena sin emoción.

When you touched me, I didn’t push you away.

Lumitia pendía del cielo como un enorme disco de plata.

I thought, Where’s the harm?

Estaba tan cerca de la sublimación absoluta que deslumbraba los planetas y convertía el firmamento nocturno en un abismo negro e infinito.

It all ends soon enough, and life has been cold for such a long time.”

La luz plateada brillante proyectaba sombras por toda la ciudad.

She didn’t realise she’d started crying until his thumb brushed across her cheek.

Cuando Helena llegó al rellano del módulo, se detuvo a propósito bajo un rayo de sol que entraba por el tragaluz roto y miró el ojo oculto en el rincón.

“By the time I realised I’d miscalculated, you’d already forced your way in.

A continuación, esperó.

You were so obvious, but that only made it worse; knowing you’d let me do anything to you in the hope it would save everyone else, even the people who’d sold you in the first place.

Tuvo que aguardar un buen rato.

At least when I sold my soul, my mother prostrated herself, begging to take my place.

El viento hacía vibrar los cristales, pero no oyó nada hasta que la puerta se abrió con un chasquido y apareció Kaine.

I suppose, in some regards, I am luckier than you.”

Todo él parecía más… nítido.

She gave a low sob.

—¿Qué ha pasado?

“After you nearly bled to death here, I thought, at least I can keep her alive.

En cuanto formuló la pregunta, Helena supo que no sabía nada.

She deserves to have someone who cares enough to try to keep her alive.

Ilva tenía razón: si los inmarcesibles habían capturado a Luc, lo mantenían en secreto.

I thought eventually you’d give up.

—Hoy hubo un ataque, una bomba —explicó con voz temblorosa—.

But you will do anything to save the people you feel responsible for.

Ha masacrado a casi todo un batallón.

Of course you’d weaponise your guilt in order to use mine.” He gave a low bitter laugh. “I’m sure there’s something poetic in it all, but right now all I feel is a new set of manacles.”

Los hermanos Bayard han sobrevivido de milagro, pero Luc… ha desaparecido.

He let go and stepped away from her, heading for the door. “So forgive me if I dislike looking at you.

—¿Estás segura?

I’m still adjusting to the ways these new ones chafe.”

Helena asintió con rigidez.

SOREN WAS SITTING NEXT TO Lila when Helena returned to the hospital, heart dead in her chest.

—Emplearon un arma fabricada con esa aleación que interfiere con la resonancia.

In her absence, nothing had happened except meetings and arguments in which no one agreed about what to do.

La llamamos anulitio.

Helena had known it was Luc who held everything together, but it was startling to see how fast it all crumbled.

Apuñalaron a Lila y ha estado a punto de morir.

Lila’s hair was cropped short like a boy’s, the area near the wound was shaven.

¿No sabías que estaban desarrollando algo así?

Her face was so swollen and bruised, she was almost unrecognisable.

Kaine negó con la cabeza.

Maier’s careful sutures had tried to rejoin the torn skin, but that scar would stay with her for the rest of her life.

—No.

“She’s younger than me, you know,” Soren said.

Sospechan que hay un espía por culpa de un… sabotaje que se produjo hace poco.

Helena nodded. “No one ever guesses that.”

Y yo ya no estoy tan presente como antes.

He leaned forward and whispered something in Lila’s ear, his voice so low Helena couldn’t make out the words.

La chica bajó la mirada y respiró hondo antes de hablar:

Then he straightened, walking out.

—Tenemos que recuperar a Luc.

Helena followed him.

Me han pedido que te diga que es de vital importancia, una prioridad absoluta.

The hollow under his remaining eye looked like a crater.

—Claro…

His face was drawn, pain lines visible around his mouth and the corner of his eye.

—Cualquier información que tengas sobre la captura: quién lo hizo, dónde está, si sigue vivo… El Consejo quiere que… —se le trabó la lengua— que hagas todo lo posible.

Someone had removed his cast already.

—Por supuesto —se limitó a contestar antes de darse la vuelta.

Elain.

Helena lo observó cuando se alejaba, el movimiento de sus hombros, cómo hundió uno de ellos para alcanzar el pomo de la puerta.

“Come on,” she said, taking him into a curtained-off area and making him sit down.

No sabía si volvería a verlo.

She worked on his arm and hand first.

—Espera —le instó.

The bone had been mended well, but it was a new injury, which made it more at risk of being broken again.

Kaine se detuvo, pero no se giró.

She knew he wasn’t going to be careful.

—Te llamaré cuando sepa algo —dijo sin más.

He’d be out in the field as soon as there was word.

—Kaine… Cuando te besé, yo…

The best she could do was heal as far as she could, imitating the way Kaine’s body regenerated, not merely to “fixed” but all the way back to its prior state.

El chico se volvió de pronto.

“I need your help,” he said as she placed new gauze over his eye.

En un momento estaba al otro lado de la habitación y, al siguiente, justo delante de ella.

Her hands stilled. “For what?”

Su expresión estaba tan cargada de veneno que le dejaba los dientes a la vista.

“I need a healer, and you’re the best.”

—¿De verdad quieres hablar de esto ahora?

She drew back, tilting his head to study his face even though his expressions were always evasive. “Soren, what have you done?”

Helena sintió un nudo en la garganta.

He raised his eyebrow. “Nothing … yet.” A helpless smile just barely touched the edge of his lips. “You have to promise to help first before I can tell.”

Se sentía culpable y no podía casi ni articular palabra.

Helena hesitated.

Pero estaba desesperada por hacerlo.

With Luc or Lila around, Soren had never needed to create his own trouble.

—¿Puedes mirarme al menos?

He was, Lila once joked, like a cat, feigning indifference but somehow always in the same room with you.

Un brillo cruel asomó a sus ojos cuando se miraron cara a cara.

Soren alone was a mystery.

Recibir toda su atención fue como si le diese un puñetazo en el estómago.

She didn’t know what he might do when all the choices were his to make.

—¿Quieres que te mire? —Kaine empleó un tono casual, como si pretendiera seducirla, pero por debajo solo había rabia.

“All right.

Se acercó más—.

I promise.

Bien.

Tell me.”

Te estoy mirando.

“Not here,” he said, standing up.

Y debo decir que es un auténtico placer ver toda esa culpa en tu cara. —Hizo un gesto de desdén y retrocedió un paso—.

They left Headquarters, wound through several alleys, and entered an abandoned shop.

¿Sabes?

“I got a healer,” he said as they entered the back room, his hand on Helena’s shoulder to push her through the door as if she might bolt otherwise.

Antes pensaba que estar al servicio del Sumo Nigromante era la peor esclavitud posible, pero, sinceramente, palidece en comparación con la tuya.

Which she might have, given how clearly planned her presence was.

Ladeó la cabeza.

Waiting there, fully armed, stood the two remaining members of Luc’s unit, Alister and Penny, as well as Sebastian and Crowther’s informant from the hospital, Purnell, who carefully avoided Helena’s eyes.

—Al menos, antes me consolaba pensando que no era culpa mía.

“Marino?” said Alister. “I thought you were getting a medic.”

Hacía lo que fuera para mantener a mi madre a salvo.

“A medic’s not good enough,” Soren said as he walked up to the table in the centre of the room.

Pero todo cambió cuando ya no quedó nadie a quien culpar salvo a mí mismo.

Helena hung back. “We need a healer.

Levantó la mano y envolvió los dedos alrededor de la garganta de Helena para acercarla hacia él.

Helena’s the best.”

Ella sintió el roce del cuero de sus guantes.

“Maybe …” Alister said, dubiously, “but she’s never been in combat.

—Después de todo, fui yo quien te eligió.

She’ll be deadweight in a fight.

Helena lo miró a los ojos y contempló la absoluta desesperanza de su mirada.

Same as this one.” He pointed at Purnell. “You’re going to get us all killed if we don’t get this perfect.”

—Envidiaba lo ingenua que eras, que quisieras ver mi lado bueno y no te dieras cuenta de que todo fue una argucia desde el principio.

“We don’t need her to fight.

Cuando me suplicaste que te dejara curarme, accedí.

We can fight.

Y, cuando me tocaste, no me aparté.

The thing none of us can do is make sure we can get Luc out alive.

Pensé: «¿Qué daño puede hacerme?

Hel’s the best bet for that.

Todo acabará dentro de poco y la vida ya ha sido bastante cruel conmigo».

We don’t know what kind of condition he’s going to be in when we find him.

Helena no se dio cuenta de que estaba llorando hasta que Kaine le acarició la mejilla con el pulgar.

She can fix anything.”

—Cuando comprendí que te había subestimado, ya te habías abierto paso hasta mi corazón.

Helena wasn’t sure she appreciated the degree of confidence Soren was placing in her.

Eres un persona muy predecible, pero eso solo empeoró todo: sabía que me dejarías hacerte cualquier cosa con tal de salvar a los demás, incluso a quienes te vendieron sin pensárselo dos veces.

“Have you ever been to the front?” Alister was staring at her.

Al menos, cuando yo vendí mi alma, mi madre se puso de rodillas y suplicó ocupar mi lugar.

“No.”

Supongo que, en cierto modo, tengo más suerte que tú.

“This is insane,” Alister said. “I’d follow you anywhere, Soren, but this is not a good plan.

A Helena se le escapó un sollozo.

What if Luc’s in a bad way, and all we have is her; is she going to carry him out?”

—Y, cuando estuviste a punto de morir desangrada aquí, pensé que al menos podía mantenerte con vida. «Se merece tener a alguien que se preocupe lo suficiente como para intentarlo».

“I’ll help!” Purnell spoke up abruptly. “After I show you the way, I can help with Luc.

Creí que, con el tiempo, te rendirías.

I’m good in the hospital.”

Pero harás lo que sea por salvar a aquellos de los que te consideras responsable.

“Soren.” Helena’s voice was tight. “Can I talk to you?” She dragged him back outside. “What are you doing?”

Por supuesto, después usarás tu culpa para aprovecharte de la mía. —Soltó una carcajada amarga—.

“We’re getting Luc back,” he said.

Estoy seguro de que todo esto encierra algo poético, pero ahora mismo lo único que veo es un nuevo par de grilletes. —La soltó y se alejó de ella para ir hacia la puerta—.

“Yes, I’ve gathered that,” she said, shaking him, not caring that he was injured, because he was about to go commit suicide. “You’re barely recovered.

Así que perdóname si no me apetece mirarte.

Why is Purnell here?”

Todavía me estoy acostumbrando a cómo se me clavan.

“Sofia?”

Soren estaba sentado junto a Lila cuando Helena regresó al hospital con el corazón muerto en el pecho.

Since when was Soren on a first-name basis with a hospital orderly?

No había sucedido nada en su ausencia, salvo reuniones y discusiones en las que nadie se había puesto de acuerdo.

“Yes, the orderly.

Helena siempre había sabido que era Luc quien los mantenía unidos, pero resultaba descorazonador ver lo rápido que todo se estaba viniendo abajo.

Do you know who she is?”

A Lila le habían cortado el pelo como a un chico, y se lo habían rasurado en la zona donde tenía la herida.

“She’s the one who knows where Luc might be.”

Su cara estaba tan hinchada y amoratada que apenas se la reconocía.

Helena stared stunned as it dawned on her why Purnell was there.

Maier había intentado cerrar la piel con unos puntos de sutura muy delicados, pero, aun así, la cicatriz la acompañaría el resto de su vida.

This had Crowther’s fingerprints all over it.

—Es más joven que yo —comentó Soren.

This wasn’t Soren’s rescue, this was Crowther, pulling the strings once again.

Helena asintió—.

But then, what was he planning to do with Kaine?

Nadie lo diría.

Was Kaine a distraction?

Se inclinó hacia delante para susurrarle algo a Lila al oído, pero lo hizo tan bajo que Helena no alcanzó a oírlo.

Or was this because Crowther hoped to avoid losing Kaine prematurely?

Después, se levantó y se fue.

Helena’s molars ground together.

La sanadora lo siguió.

“And how would she know that?” she asked, trying to get Soren to see how insane this all was.

Bajo el ojo que le quedaba, se le marcaba un surco que parecía un cráter, y estaba demacrado, se le notaban arrugas de dolor alrededor de la boca y en las comisuras de los ojos.

Soren gave a tight smile. “Crowther uses her to keep an eye on us, but she doesn’t like it.

Alguien le había quitado ya la escayola: seguramente, Elain.

She came clean with Luc a while back.

—Ven aquí —le dijo, llevándolo a una zona protegida por cortinas donde lo obligó a sentarse.

She’s seen maps for a secret prison that can be accessed from the West Island’s waterways.”

Primero le atendió el brazo y la mano.

“Soren.” Helena exhaled, closing her eyes. “Why would she have seen maps like that?”

El hueso se había soldado sin problema, pero la fractura era tan reciente que corría el riesgo de partírselo de nuevo.

Soren shrugged, not seeming concerned about it. “Crowther uses her for carrying messages.

Sabía que Soren no tendría cuidado, que volvería al campo de batalla en cuanto le dieran permiso.

I guess she peeked.”

Lo mejor que podía hacer por él era sanarlo por completo, del mismo modo que lo hacía con Kaine: no se limitaba a «arreglarlo», sino que lo revertía a su estado anterior.

If Crowther was the mastermind behind this, Helena wanted him directly involved, giving clear instructions about how he thought it was going to work, not some shadowy an orderly saw a map sleight of hand.

—Necesito tu ayuda —le comentó cuando le estaba poniendo una gasa limpia sobre el ojo.

She was sick of how Ilva and Crowther both defaulted to manipulation to get their “miracles” to show up.

Helena se quedó quieta.

As if people couldn’t be counted on unless they were tricked.

—¿Para qué?

“If that’s the case, then that means Crowther knows about this prison, and he might have a lot more information than just a map.

—Necesito una sanadora, y tú eres la mejor.

We should talk to him.”

La chica se apartó y ladeó la cabeza para observar su gesto, aunque siempre se mostraba esquivo.

Soren immediately shook his head. “No.

—Soren, ¿qué has hecho?

The Council is adamant that no one can take any action until they ‘know’ who has Luc.

Este arqueó una ceja.

Ilva somehow thinks she’s going to negotiate a trade to get Luc back.

—Nada… todavía. —Se le escapó una sonrisa sin remedio, tan leve que apenas le curvó los labios—.

No mention, though, of what she possibly thinks we could offer.”

Tienes que prometer que me ayudarás antes de que te lo cuente.

Helena knew exactly what it was that Ilva probably had in mind.

Helena se lo pensó.

“My duty is to Luc,” Soren was saying, “not the Eternal Flame.

Soren jamás se había metido en problemas, salvo cuando iba acompañado de Luc y Lila.

As long as Lila’s out, I’m primary.

De hecho, Lila una vez bromeó con que Soren era como los gatos que fingían indiferencia, pero al final siempre acababan contigo en la misma habitación.

The Council doesn’t command me, my duty is to my vows and my vows are to Luc.”

Soren era un enigma.

She’d thought they wanted Kaine to rescue Luc—to risk his cover to spare their own troops.

Helena no tenía ni idea de qué camino elegiría ahora que actuaba por su cuenta.

But if that failed, Ilva would sell him out without a second thought.

—De acuerdo, te lo prometo.

Which meant Crowther was being forced to go behind Ilva’s back.

Cuéntamelo.

That was why he was using Sofia Purnell to pass the relevant information to Soren, the one person with the ability to act on his own.

—Aquí no —repuso él, poniéndose de pie.

“All right,” Helena said, nodding. “I’ll come.”

Abandonaron el Cuartel General, recorrieron varios callejones y entraron en una tienda abandonada.

Soren looked startled, then sagged with relief. “Good.

—Traigo una sanadora —dijo en cuanto entró en el almacén.

I don’t think I can do this without you.”

No apartaba la mano de la espalda de Helena, como si temiera que fuese a salir corriendo.

Helena scrutinised him. “What do you mean?”

Y no era tan descabellado, teniendo en cuenta lo planificada que parecía estar su presencia allí.

His eyes were heavy-lidded.

Armados hasta los dientes, los esperaban los dos soldados de la unidad de Luc que habían sobrevivido: Alister y Penny, junto a ellos estaban Sebastian y la informante de Crowther del hospital, Purnell, que evitó cruzar la mirada con Helena.

When he was pensive, they got soulful.

—¿Marino? —preguntó Alister—.

Now there was just one, but she still recognised the expression.

Creía que traerías a un médico.

“I need you to do anything, Hel, whatever it takes, to save him.

—Un médico no nos sirve —replicó Soren, que se dirigió a la mesa que había en mitad de la habitación.

No matter the price.

Helena se quedó atrás—.

Anyone in the Resistance would die for him; I need you there because it might take more than that.”

Necesitamos una sanadora.

Her eyes went wide. “Do you realise what you’re asking?”

Helena es la mejor que tenemos.

He held his head high. “My vow is to protect my Principate with my life and my death.

—Es posible… —masculló Alister—, pero nunca ha entrado en combate.

You’re the one who said that if someone’s willing to die, why not give them a chance to keep fighting.”

Será un peso muerto en una pelea.

Her hands had gone numb. “You can’t volunteer the others for a mission like that.

Igual que esta. —Señaló con desdén a Purnell—.

Are you planning to tell them that’s why I’m here?

Acabaremos muertos si no hacemos las cosas bien.

That you chose me because you want necromancy as your backup plan?” Her voice dropped to a furious whisper as she retreated, but he caught her by the arm.

—No tiene que luchar, para eso estamos nosotros.

“That’s not the only reason,” he said. “You are the best.

Pero, si queremos sacar a Luc de allí con vida, necesitamos a alguien que pueda lograrlo.

I’m not volunteering them, just me.

Hel es la mejor baza que tenemos.

If something goes wrong, you do anything you have to to get them out.

No sabemos en qué condiciones lo vamos a encontrar.

This is me giving you permission.”

Ella podrá arreglarlo todo.

She shook her head. “I don’t even know if I can.

Helena no estaba segura de si debía sentirse halagada o presionada por la confianza ciega que Soren estaba depositando en ella.

I’ve never—”

—¿Has estado en el frente alguna vez? —Alister la miró fijamente.

“We both know that if someone can do vivimancy, they can do necromancy.

—No.

And if there’s anyone who can figure it out on the fly, it’s you.

—Esto es una locura —insistió Alister—.

I’m not going to do anything stupid.

Te seguiré adonde sea, Soren, pero no es un buen plan.

I just—” He swallowed. “I need to know this is going to work.

¿Qué pasa si Luc está herido y solo contamos con ella?

Hel, this has to work.”

¿Podrá cargar con él?

She wavered a moment longer, but what were the alternatives?

—¡Yo puedo colaborar! —intervino Purnell de repente—.

Every choice had become unbearable.

Después de enseñaros el camino, os ayudaré con Luc.

And this was the price she’d already offered to pay.

En el hospital soy eficiente.

“Fine.” She swallowed. “For Luc.”

—Soren —dijo Helena con la voz tensa—, ¿podemos hablar? —Salió con él al exterior—.

“For Luc. Come on.”

¿Qué estás haciendo?

Helena wanted very much to corner Purnell and interrogate her about exactly what Crowther knew, and how he expected the mission to unfold, but Purnell was constantly in motion, moving around the room, staying out of reach.

—Vamos a rescatar a Luc —respondió.

“How do you know all this?” Helena asked pointedly, after she was told about the location of the prison and how there was a floodwater cathedral that they would use to reach it.

—Sí, de eso ya me he dado cuenta —replicó ella zarandeándolo.

“I know people who use them.

Le daba igual que estuviera herido, porque estaba a punto de embarcarse en una misión suicida—.

The scouts—and others, when they need escape routes and safe places to go,” Purnell said.

Aún no te has recuperado.

“Why aren’t they more patrolled?”

¿Qué hace aquí Purnell?

Purnell shrugged. “It’s a maze.

—¿Sofia?

The greys can’t see in the dark, or they get lost, and the Undying don’t like crawling in sewer water.”

¿Desde cuando trataba Soren con tanta familiaridad a una camillera del hospital?

Helena’s own throat convulsed at the thought. “I see.”

—Sí, la camillera.

“It won’t be bad, though.

¿Sabes quién es?

It’s flood season now,” Purnell said. “The water will mostly be mountain water.

—Es quien podría saber dónde esta Luc.

It’ll be cold, but nothing like it is in the summer.”

Helena se quedó paralizada cuando comprendió qué hacía allí en realidad Purnell.

Small mercies.

Se trataba de uno de los tejemanejes de Crowther.

Helena was well acquainted with how cold the river snowmelt was; the mere thought of crawling through it was enough to make her bones ache. “And these tunnels are connected to where Luc is?”

No era Soren quien estaba planificando el rescate, sino Crowther, tirando otra vez de los hilos.

Purnell was avoiding Helena’s eyes again. “A lot of old access points to the sewers were built over, but they’re easy to reopen if you have the building schematics.

Entonces ¿qué pretendía hacer con Kaine?

Someone investigated it a few months ago.

¿Era solo una distracción?

It’s very high-level compared with the other prisons, but almost completely empty.

¿O pretendía asegurarse de que no lo perdía antes de tiempo?

Like it’s being reserved for something.”

Helena apretó la mandíbula con fuerza.

“If Luc’s there, then this means his capture is something they’ve been working towards for a long time,” Sebastian said in a tight voice.

—¿Y cómo es posible que ella lo sepa? —preguntó Helena para ver si así Soren entendía la locura que estaba cometiendo.

Fear sliced down Helena’s spine. “Why are you so sure Luc’s there?”

Soren sonrió un poco.

“If it’s a secret they have him, they’d have to put him in a secret place,” was all Purnell said.

—Crowther la contrató para vigilarnos, pero a ella no le gusta hacerlo.

Helena couldn’t help but feel that the girl’s involvement had already destroyed Crowther’s chance at plausible deniability.

Hace tiempo que se lo confesó todo a Luc.

Surely he could afford to be less opaque.

Ha tenido acceso a mapas de una cárcel secreta a la que podemos acceder por el alcantarillado de la isla Oeste.

“If he’s not there, no one will even know we went in,” Soren said. “We have to go tonight.

—Soren… —Helena suspiró y cerró los ojos—.

Ascendance is tomorrow; the floodwaters are already high, and none of us will be clearheaded enough to go.

¿Cómo ha visto esos mapas?

We’d have to wait two more days, and Luc can’t afford that.”

Soren se encogió de hombros.

Helena hadn’t considered that aspect.

No parecía importarle.

They captured Luc just before Ascendance.

—Crowther la usa como mensajera.

Why?

Supongo que lo vio por ahí.

Just to increase the complexity of the rescue efforts?

Si Crowther era el cerebro detrás de todo eso, lo mínimo que podía hacer era dar la cara y ofrecer instrucciones claras, en vez de basarse en que una camillera había visto un mapa por accidente.

Or was it a coincidence?

Estaba harta de que Ilva y Crowther manipularan a las personas para conseguir sus «milagros».

The plan was only the vaguest shape of a plan.

Como si nadie fuera a prestar sus servicios a menos que los engañaran para hacerlo.

Get in, find Luc, get out.

—Si es así, supongo que Crowther conoce esa prisión y tiene mucha más información que un simple mapa.

Helena’s job was to keep Purnell close and out of the way.

Deberíamos hablar con él.

The others would deal with any fighting.

Soren se negó en el acto.

When they found Luc, she’d examine him, make sure he was still alive, and, if necessary, heal him as rapidly as possible.

—No.

Then she would get him out.

El Consejo ha dejado claro que nadie moverá un dedo hasta que «sepan» quién tiene a Luc.

Purnell would help her carry him if he couldn’t walk on his own.

Ilva cree que puede negociar con los inmarcesibles para que nos lo devuelvan, pero no ha dicho qué está dispuesta a ofrecer a cambio.

Helena’s job was getting him back to the East Island by any means possible.

Helena sabía perfectamente qué tenía Ilva en mente.

If she had to leave everyone else behind, she was to do that.

—Yo le debo lealtad a Luc —siguió Soren—, no a la Llama Eterna.

Once Luc was safe, the others would scatter and regroup.

Mientras Lila esté de baja, soy el paladín primero.

“Let’s go,” Soren said, pulling on his armour as Alister and Penny snapped to attention.

El Consejo no tiene poder sobre mí, mi deber es para con mis votos y esos votos se los hice a Luc.

“Wait!” Helena said, fighting to keep her voice steady, overwhelmed with the feeling that the plan was wrong. “I need to get my medical kit.”

Ella había creído que querían que Kaine rescatara a Luc, que arriesgara su tapadera para evitar el envío de tropas.

Soren’s eye narrowed with suspicion. “Don’t you just use your hands?”

Y, si fracasaba, Ilva lo delataría sin pensárselo dos veces.

She shook her head. “No.

Por eso Crowther se había visto obligado a actuar a espaldas de Ilva.

If Luc’s really hurt, there’s elixirs and salves, restoratives that will make him recover faster.

Y por eso había usado a Sofia Purnell para filtrar la información a Soren, la única persona que podía actuar por su cuenta.

Relying on vivimancy would—drain him or me.

—De acuerdo —asintió Helena—.

If I have my medicines, we’ll have a better chance of him making it out if he’s badly hurt.”

Os acompañaré.

Soren relaxed marginally. “All right.

Al principio, Soren la miró sorprendido, como si no se esperase que aceptara tan rápido, pero al instante se le escapó el aire en un suspiro de alivio.

Go fast.

—Bien, creo que no podremos hacerlo sin ti.

If you don’t come back in fifteen minutes, we’ll leave without you.”

Helena lo observó con atención.

She ran out the door, straight to Headquarters and the Alchemy Tower.

—¿A qué te refieres?

The lift had never felt so slow as it cranked upwards.

Soren tenía una expresión conmovedora cuando se ponía pensativo con sus párpados caídos.

“Please be there, Shiseo,” she prayed as the doors opened and she hurried to her lab, beginning to doubt whether she was making the right decision.

Aunque ahora solo le quedaba uno, Helena seguía reconociendo el gesto.

Shiseo was there, synthesising chelators when she burst in.

—Hel, necesito que hagas lo que consideres oportuno para salvarlo.

“I need your help,” she said as she rushed to her satchel.

Cueste lo que cueste.

She went to the cabinet filled with all her medicine and snatched up vial after vial, enough doses for everyone twice.

Sé que los miembros de la Resistencia morirían por él, pero yo quiero que tú vayas más allá.

She found needles, bandages, manual medical tools, then packed everything she could into waxed, water-sealed bags and put all of it into her satchel until it was full to bursting.

La chica abrió los ojos, incrédula.

Then she opened a small drawer that held her knives and started strapping them on.

—¿Te das cuenta de lo que me estás pidiendo?

“You got the titanium-nickel,” Shiseo said, watching the knives mould against her skin. “May I see them?”

Soren mantuvo la cabeza alta.

“Not now,” she said, pulling the satchel over her head and buckling the extra strap to her waist so she could run with it. “I need you to do something for me.

—Juré proteger al principado con mi vida y mi muerte.

I can’t tell you all the details, but I don’t have anyone else to turn to.”

Tú eres la única que ha dicho que, si alguien está dispuesto a morir, deberíamos darle la oportunidad de seguir luchando.

She snatched up a piece of paper and started scribbling notes.

Helena notó que dejaba de sentir las manos.

Everything she knew, all the relevant details.

—No puedes obligar a los demás a ofrecerse voluntarios en una misión como esta.

Location.

¿Vas a decirles por qué estoy aquí?

Strategy.

¿Que me has elegido porque piensas usar la nigromancia como último recurso? —Había bajado tanto la voz que se había convertido en un susurro lleno de rabia.

Exit.

Dio un paso hacia atrás, pero Soren la agarró del brazo.

Written out plainly, it was obvious there was no way it would work, but she didn’t know what else she could do but go along with it.

—Ese no es el único motivo —insistió—.

She looked up. “Do you know the way to the old factory Outpost?”

No mentía cuando dije que eres la mejor.

Shiseo nodded. “Yes.

Y no obligaré a nadie, solo me estoy ofreciendo yo.

I visited when it was operational.”

Si todo se tuerce, haz lo que tengas que hacer para sacarlos de allí.

She nodded shakily. “I need you to go there, as quickly as you can.

Te doy mi permiso.

It’s—enemy territory, but if you see a necrothrall, say ‘Helena sent me’ and they should leave you alone.

La chica negó con la cabeza.

Take this route.” She sketched it roughly on a slip of paper. “You’ll find a tenement building with the iron symbol on it.

—Ni siquiera sé si puedo hacerlo.

On the second floor there’s a door.

Nunca…

Shove this under the door and then come back.

—Los dos sabemos que quien practica la vivemancia puede practicar la nigromancia.

Or—if you don’t want to do any of that, give this to Ilva.

Y, si existe alguien capaz de aprenderla sobre la marcha, esa eres tú.

I can’t—I don’t know how to make this choice.”

No voy a hacer ninguna estupidez, simplemente… —Tragó saliva—.

She held the paper out.

Esto tiene que salir bien, Hel, no queda otra.

Shiseo looked from her to the paper, an odd gleam of interest in his dark eyes. “I always knew you were very interesting.”

Helena se lo pensó un momento, pero ¿qué alternativa tenía?

“I have to go,” she said.

Todas las decisiones le resultaban insoportables.

He took the paper, and she turned and ran, not waiting to see which choice he made.

Y este era el precio que ya había aceptado pagar.

She kept running.

—Está bien —dijo Helena—.

Soren and the others were emerging from the shop as she careened down the alley.

Por Luc.

“Thought you’d split,” Alister said, giving her a sideways grin.

—Por Luc. Vamos.

He seemed to have accepted her presence now.

Tenía pensado hablar con Purnell para que le dijera todo lo que sabía Crowther y averiguar cómo esperaba que se desarrollase la misión, pero la chica no paraba de moverse por la habitación, siempre fuera de su alcance.

“No,” Helena said, breathing raggedly. “I’m all in.”

—¿Cómo sabes todo esto? —preguntó Helena con un tono mordaz cuando les contó dónde estaba la prisión y que podían acceder a ella a través de unos tanques de inundación.

—Conozco a gente que los usa, exploradores sobre todo.

Les sirven para escapar y ponerse a salvo —explicó Purnell.

—¿Por qué no hay patrullas vigilando?

Purnell se encogió de hombros.

—Es un laberinto.

Los necrómatas no ven en la oscuridad, o se pierden, y a los inmarcesibles no les gusta reptar por las aguas residuales.

Helena sintió que le daban arcadas solo de pensarlo.

—Entiendo.

—Pero no estará tan mal.

Estamos en época de inundaciones —dijo Purnell—.

Casi toda el agua proviene de las montañas.

Estará fría, pero no será tan asqueroso como en verano.

Menudo consuelo.

Helena conocía demasiado bien lo fría que estaba el agua cuando se derretía la nieve e imaginarse que iba a tener que arrastrarse por ahí hizo que le empezaran a doler los huesos.

—¿Y esos túneles están conectados con la prisión donde está Luc?

Purnell esquivó de nuevo la mirada de Helena.

—Se han bloqueado muchos de los puntos de acceso de las alcantarillas, pero se pueden reabrir si tienes los planos originales de construcción.

Hace unos meses se hizo una investigación.

Es una prisión de máxima seguridad, pero casi siempre está vacía, como si la estuvieran reservando para algo en concreto.

—Si Luc está ahí, eso significa que llevan mucho tiempo planeando todo esto —intervino Sebastian con la voz tomada.

Helena se estremeció de miedo.

—¿Cómo estás tan segura de que Luc se encuentra allí?

—Si lo están ocultando, lo habrán metido en un sitio secreto —se limitó a contestar Purnell.

Helena no pudo evitar pensar que la participación de Purnell echaba por tierra cualquier intento de Crowther por negar su responsabilidad en todo aquello, aunque podría haberlo hecho mucho mejor.

—Si Luc no está allí, nadie sabrá que hemos ido —dijo Soren—.

Tenemos que hacerlo esta noche.

Mañana habrá sublimación.

La marea subirá y no tendremos la cabeza despejada entonces.

Tendríamos que esperar dos días más, y Luc no puede permitírselo.

Helena no lo había considerado.

Habían capturado a Luc poco antes de la sublimación.

¿Por qué?

¿Para hacer más complicado su rescate?

¿O era una coincidencia?

Tenían un plan que apenas era un esbozo: entrar, encontrar a Luc y salir.

El trabajo de Helena consistía en mantener a Purnell cerca y a la vez lejos de todo peligro.

El resto se encargaría de pelear.

Cuando encontraran a Luc, lo examinaría para asegurarse de que seguía con vida y, si era necesario, lo sanaría lo más rápido posible.

Después lo sacaría de allí.

Purnell la ayudaría a cargarlo si no podía salir por su propio pie.

Lo importante era traerlo de vuelta a la isla Este, costara lo que costase.

Si tenía que dejar a todos atrás, lo haría.

Cuando Luc estuviera a salvo, los demás se dispersarían y se reagruparían más adelante.

—En marcha —concluyó Soren mientras agarraba su armadura.

Alister y Penny se cuadraron de hombros.

—¡Esperad! —exclamó Helena, esforzándose por mantener la voz firme, aunque el plan no terminaba de convencerla—.

Tengo que ir a por mi botiquín.

Soren le dedicó una mirada cargada de sospecha.

—¿No puedes usar las manos?

Ella negó con la cabeza.

—No.

Si Luc está herido de gravedad, hay elixires y bálsamos que le ayudarán a recuperarse más rápido.

Si dependemos únicamente de la vivemancia, podría agotarse, pero, si disponemos de medicinas, tendremos más opciones de sacarlo con vida, incluso aunque esté grave.

El paladín se relajó un poco.

—De acuerdo, pero date prisa.

Si no has vuelto en quince minutos, nos iremos sin ti.

Salió corriendo por la puerta y se dirigió al Cuartel General, en concreto a la Torre de Alquimia.

El ascensor le pareció más lento que nunca mientras ascendía.

—Por favor, Shiseo, espero que estés ahí —rezó mientras se abrían las puertas.

Avanzó a paso ligero hasta el laboratorio, dudando de si había tomado la decisión correcta.

Shiseo estaba allí, concentrado en la síntesis de quelantes.

—Necesito tu ayuda —soltó Helena nada más entrar.

Cogió su bolsa, abrió el armario de las medicinas y metió en ella todos los frasquitos que encontró.

Quería que hubiera dosis doble para todos.

Añadió agujas, vendas y kits de sutura manual, y lo introdujo todo en unas fundas enceradas e impermeables para protegerlo de la humedad.

La bolsa parecía a punto de estallar.

Acto seguido, abrió el cajón en el que guardaba las dagas y empezó a anudárselas al cuerpo.

—Conseguiste las de titanio y níquel —comentó Shiseo, observando cómo se amoldaban a su piel—.

¿Puedo verlas?

—Ahora mismo no —respondió Helena, que se pasó la bolsa por encima de la cabeza y se la anudó a la cintura para poder correr con ella—.

Necesito que hagas algo por mí.

No puedo contarte todos los detalles, pero no tengo a nadie más en quien confiar.

Cogió un trozo de papel y escribió con rapidez todo lo que sabía, así como cualquier detalle que le pareciera relevante: ubicación, estrategia, escapatoria…

Cuanto más lo escribía, más evidente le resultaba que el plan era endeble, pero no había otra opción: solo seguir adelante.

Alzó la vista.

—¿Sabes llegar a la vieja fábrica del Reducto?

Shiseo asintió.

—Sí.

La visité cuando aún estaba operativa.

Helena asintió, temblando.

—Tienes que ir allí lo más rápido que puedas.

Es… territorio enemigo, pero, si te cruzas con un necrómata, dile: «Me envía Helena», y te dejará en paz.

Sigue este camino. —Trazó a toda prisa un boceto en un papel—.

Allí encontrarás unos apartamentos con el símbolo del hierro en la puerta.

En el segundo piso verás una entrada.

Desliza esto por debajo de la puerta y vuelve.

Y, si no quieres hacer nada de lo que te pido, entonces dáselo a Ilva.

No puedo… Yo no sé cómo tomar esta decisión.

Le tendió el papel.

Shiseo lo miró un momento y luego la observó a ella con un brillo en sus ojos oscuros que Helena no supo interpretar.

—Siempre supe que eras una persona muy interesante.

—Tengo que irme —afirmó Helena.

Shiseo cogió el papel, y ella salió corriendo, sin esperar a ver qué decisión tomaba.

Siguió corriendo.

Soren y los demás estaban saliendo de la tienda cuando enfiló el callejón.

—Creía que te habías rajado —comentó Alister lanzándole una sonrisa ladeada.

Al parecer, ya había aceptado su presencia.

—No —respondió Helena entre jadeos—.

Contad conmigo.

CHAPTER 50

Aprilis 1787

CAPÍTULO 50

ACCESSING THE WEST ISLAND’S FLOOD CATHEDRAL WAS a mission of its own.

Abrilis 1787

There were Resistance patrols they had to hide from until they finally found a weak point in the wall that Alister could open.

Llegar a los tanques de inundación de la isla Oeste fue casi una misión en sí misma.

They crawled through, straight into ice-cold floodwater.

Tuvieron que esquivar varias patrullas de la Resistencia hasta que, al fin, encontraron un punto débil en el muro, donde Alister se encargó de abrir un boquete.

The spring floods had started early, and with Lumithia at near Ascendance, the tributaries had climbed out of their banks and threatened to drag them all downriver.

Se adentraron por el hueco y se arrastraron por el agua gélida.

They had to cling to the wall as they made their way to a crossing point, one of the old pre-war bridges which was nearly destroyed.

Las crecidas de la primavera se habían adelantado y, con Lumitia a punto de alcanzar la sublimación, los afluyentes desbordados amenazaban con arrastrarlos a todos río abajo.

It swayed dangerously, threatening to collapse as Helena crawled across it, not daring to look down at the swirling, freezing death below.

Tuvieron que agarrarse a la pared de camino a uno de los antiguos puentes anteriores a la guerra.

Things only got worse once they were across.

Había sufrido muchos estragos y se mecía peligrosamente.

The flood cathedrals were immense towering underground rooms, designed to fill with several storeys of water and redirect it downriver, and they were filling.

Cuando Helena lo cruzó a cuatro patas, sin atreverse a mirar el abismo de aguas frías y arremolinadas que rugía debajo, el puente parecía a punto de venirse abajo.

The grate to access one was half covered in floodwater and made of inert iron, which required time to break through to reveal a terrifyingly deep drop.

Y todo empeoró cuando estuvieron al otro lado.

Even with electric torches, they couldn’t see the bottom.

Los tanques de inundación eran huecos de gran envergadura diseñados para contener millones de litros de agua y redirigirla hacia el río, y estaban empezando a llenarse.

The roar of water rose from the dark.

El agua alcanzaba ya la mitad de la altura de la reja que daba paso a uno de ellos, y estaba fabricada en hierro, por lo que tardaron un buen rato en abrirla.

The others were unfazed.

Cuando lo lograron, descubrieron que se asomaba a una caída aterradora: ni siquiera con las antorchas eléctricas veían el fondo.

They were used to traversing the city levels, rappelling up and down dozens of storeys during combat.

De la oscuridad solo emergía el rugido del agua.

Their armour had harnesses built in, with spools of wires and hooks to anchor themselves.

Los demás no se inmutaron.

Penny, a reconnaissance scout, went first.

Tenían experiencia en combate y estaban acostumbrados a atravesar el subsuelo de la ciudad, así como a subir y descender varios pisos en rapel.

She was terrifyingly quick.

Las armaduras contaban con arneses incorporados y, además, disponían de carretes de cable y ganchos para sujetarse.

In seconds, she was anchored and dove headfirst into the dark without a backwards glance.

Penny, exploradora de reconocimiento, fue la primera en bajar.

For a minute, there was nothing but the taut wires; then they slackened and drew tight again, and began to vibrate at intervals.

Se movió con una rapidez asombrosa.

Alister touched them with his fingers. “All clear,” he said, flicking the wires so they’d vibrate back down.

Unos segundos después, cuando estuvo anclada a la pared, se zambulló de cabeza en la oscuridad sin volver la vista atrás.

The anchors came loose, slithering into the darkness after Penny like a pair of serpents.

No sucedió nada en el primer minuto, pero después los cables se tensaron y se relajaron de nuevo.

The rest of them followed.

Era como si vibraran a intervalos.

Helena and Purnell, without their own armour and harnesses, were deadweight in the literal sense.

Alister los tocó con los dedos.

Alister took Helena with him, and Sebastian carried Purnell, and the water poured down on them like a waterfall.

—Despejado —anunció, y tensó los cables para enviar la señal a Penny, que esperaba abajo.

They were soaked to the bone, nearly numb by the time they reached the bottom.

Liberaron los anclajes, que se deslizaron en la oscuridad como serpientes metálicas, y los demás comenzaron a descender.

It was too loud to hear anything but water crashing down, echoing off the walls with a cacophonous roar.

Helena y Purnell, sin armadura ni arnés, se convirtieron en un peso muerto en el sentido más literal.

Alister was shaking with cold, but he knelt down, putting his hands underwater for several minutes.

Alister descendió con Helena enganchada a él, y Sebastian hizo lo mismo con Purnell.

“It’s shallow along the edges but about ten feet left, there’s a drop, and the water’s fast.

El agua les golpeaba como si estuvieran bajo una catarata, por lo que cuando llegaron al fondo estaban empapados hasta los huesos y totalmente entumecidos.

I can’t feel the bottom.” He had to shout to be heard. “If we go straight, it should be fine, but let’s anchor a line before we cross.

No se oía más que el estruendo del agua al caer, resonando en los muros con una violencia ensordecedora.

I’ll go first, I know the safest route.”

Alister estaba temblando de frío, aunque se arrodilló y sumergió las manos en el agua durante unos minutos.

Once they reached the far wall, there was a ladder leading to an upper walkway that ran above the dozens of huge tunnels feeding into the cathedral.

—Hay poca profundidad en los bordes, pero a unos tres metros a la izquierda hay un socavón por donde el agua va mucho más rápido.

Helena used her vivimancy to warm everyone, but there was nothing to be done about their soaking clothes except to keep moving.

No toco fondo. —Tenía que gritar para hacerse oír—.

Penny took the lead again.

Si seguimos recto, no habrá problema, pero será mejor que anclemos un cable antes de cruzar.

She’d memorised the route through all the tunnels that wound bewilderingly.

Yo iré primero; sé por dónde es más seguro.

She had a slight limp from an old injury, but she was still quick and light-footed.

Cuando llegaron a la pared opuesta, subieron por una escalera que los llevó a una galería superior que discurría por encima de los enormes tanques de inundación.

She moved forward, checking the route, making sure things were clear before using her torch to signal the rest of them forward.

Helena empleó la vivemancia para calentar a todo el equipo, pero no pudo hacer nada con la ropa empapada.

They did not encounter a single necrothrall.

Debían seguir moviéndose.

Helena’s dread grew.

Penny tomó la delantera.

They climbed an endless ladder that connected to a tunnel, and after crawling so long that Helena began to wonder if she’d ever see light again, they emerged into a basement.

Se había aprendido de memoria todos los túneles, cada recodo.

“Wait here,” Soren said.

Cojeaba levemente a causa de una lesión anterior, y aun así se movía con rapidez y ligereza.

Penny leaned against a wall.

Avanzó siguiendo la ruta establecida, asegurándose de que estaba despejada.

She was breathing hard, stooped over, her hand pressing against her knee.

Después les indicó a los demás que la siguieran con un movimiento de la antorcha.

“Let me see,” Helena said.

No se toparon con un solo necrómata.

There’d been a torn ligament—it had been healed, but she should have been on bedrest for a few days and then worked slowly back into active duty.

El miedo de Helena fue en aumento.

“I’m fine, I’ll get fixed up again once we get back,” Penny said, but Helena could tell she wouldn’t.

Subieron una escalera interminable que conectaba con otro túnel y, después de arrastrarse durante un buen rato, empezó a preguntarse si volvería a ver la luz del día.

There was a muffled shout, the quick snick of steel, and a thud.

Pero finalmente desembocaron en un sótano.

Soren’s head popped back through the doorway to those waiting in the basement. “Clear,” he said softly.

—Esperad aquí —ordenó Soren.

They ascended three floors.

Penny se apoyó contra la pared.

Helena had never seen Luc’s unit in actual combat, only their practices.

Respiraba con dificultad, encorvada, con una mano sobre la rodilla.

They were deadly.

—Déjame ver —dijo Helena.

Dark blurs of steel and spilled blood.

La chica había sufrido un desgarro en el ligamento y lo habían tratado, pero debería haber reposado en cama unos cuantos días antes de incorporarse paulatinamente al servicio activo.

Their weapons morphed like water in their hands, the blades twisting and altering, reaching out and slaughtering anything that crossed their paths, using their harnesses to make gravity-defying attacks.

—Estoy bien.

The prison was unquestionably occupied.

Me lo arreglarán cuando volvamos —replicó Penny, aunque Helena sabía que no era verdad.

There were too many guards and necrothralls for it to be abandoned, but not as many as would be expected for keeping Luc prisoner.

Oyeron un grito amortiguado, seguido de un chasquido metálico y un golpe sordo.

Helena kept telling herself it wasn’t a trap, but it felt like one.

Un instante después, la cabeza de Soren se asomó a la puerta del sótano donde aguardaban.

They moved fast, trying to search every room before their victims were discovered and the alarms went off.

—Despejado —anunció en voz baja.

There was no point in hiding the bodies; Soren left a trail of blood in his wake.

Ascendieron tres plantas.

Alister was defence.

Helena nunca había visto en acción al batallón de Luc, solo durante las prácticas.

He had spectacular resonance reach.

Eran letales.

He could throw up a wall, or shove back attackers by moving the ground under them.

Apenas distinguía destellos de acero y sangre derramada.

He’d hang back and queue them so that Sebastian and Soren could kill methodically without getting crowded or overrun in the narrow hallways.

Las armas se transformaban en sus manos como si fueran líquidas; retorcían y alteraban las hojas de metal para acabar con todo lo que se les pusiera por delante.

Penny, no longer scouting, acted as Alister’s cover, protecting him from any attacks.

Además, usaban los arneses para atacar de maneras que desafiaban a la gravedad.

They checked every room.

No cabía duda de que la prisión estaba en funcionamiento.

Cell after cell.

Había demasiados guardias y necrómatas como para considerarla abandonada, pero no tantos como cabría esperar si tenían a Luc prisionero.

No Luc.

Helena no dejaba de repetirse que aquello no era una trampa, pero en realidad así lo creía.

No prisoners at all.

Registraron todas las habitaciones; se movían rápido para evitar que alguien descubriera a las víctimas y diera la alarma.

The place seemed empty.

No tenía sentido esconder los cadáveres, por lo que Soren iba dejando un reguero de sangre a su paso.

Except there were guards.

Alister se encargaba de la defensa.

They finally found a prisoner in the last cell in the block.

Tenía un alcance de resonancia espectacular.

A huddled figure under a blanket.

Podía hacer volar una pared o derribar a los enemigos con una simple vibración del suelo.

“Luc?” Soren’s voice was ragged with desperation.

Solía quedarse atrás, cubriendo a Sebastian y Soren, mientras estos eliminaban de forma sistemática a sus objetivos en los estrechos túneles.

The figure lying on the cot stirred, and a grey-haired man lifted his head.

Cuando Penny terminó su tarea de explorar, se dedicó a cubrirle las espaldas a Alister y a protegerlo de los posibles ataques.

When he saw them, his eyes went wide and he lunged towards the bar, jabbering in broken Northern dialect.

Revisaron todas las habitaciones, todas las celdas.

“Resistance?”

No había ni rastro de Luc ni de otros prisioneros.

That was all Helena managed to make out among the many words she didn’t know.

Parecía que aquel sitio estaba vacío, y sin embargo había guardias.

He sounded western.

Al final, encontraron a un prisionero en la última celda del módulo: una persona encogida bajo una manta.

“Save?” The man pointed at himself.

—¿Luc? —La voz de Soren sonaba rota por la desesperación.

“No,” Soren said, shaking his head. “We’re looking for someone else.”

La persona que estaba tumbada en el catre se removió.

“Save.” He pointed at himself again.

Asomó la cabeza un hombre de cabello canoso.

“We’re only here for one person,” Soren said, already turning.

En cuanto los vio, abrió los ojos de par en par y se abalanzó contra los barrotes, farfullando en un dialecto norteño apenas inteligible.

The man’s eyes narrowed. “Boy?” He touched his own hair. “Gold?”

—¿Resistencia?

They all turned back.

Eso fue lo único que Helena entendió de todas las palabras que dijo.

“Is he here?” Helena asked.

Parecía del Oeste.

The man set his jaw. “Save.” He pointed at himself again.

—¿Salvar? —El hombre se señaló a sí mismo.

“We don’t have time to drag around a prisoner,” Soren said. “We’ll find him ourselves.”

—No —respondió Soren sacudiendo la cabeza—.

“No!” The man sounded terrified now.

Estamos buscando a otra persona.

Helena studied him. “What’s your name?”

—Salvar. —Volvió a señalarse a sí mismo.

“Vagner,” he said slowly.

—Hemos venido a por otra persona —insistió Soren, y se giró para marcharse.

The name was familiar.

El hombre entornó los ojos.

Vagner.

—¿El chico? —Se tocó el pelo—.

Wagner?

¿Dorado?

That was the name Crowther and Ivy had tortured out of Lancaster.

Todos se volvieron hacia él.

She turned to Soren. “We’ve been looking for him.”

—¿Está aquí? —preguntó Helena.

“Helena.” Soren looked at her with exasperation. “We can’t deal with a prisoner.”

El hombre tensó la mandíbula.

“This one is important.

—Salvar. —Volvió a señalarse.

Crowther’s had people trying to find him.

—No tenemos tiempo de llevarnos a un prisionero —repuso Soren—.

If this is where they’re hiding the prisoners they don’t want anyone knowing about, that’s all the more evidence this is a prisoner we need.”

Ya lo encontraremos nosotros.

Soren hesitated. “If he slows us down or does anything that puts the mission at risk, I will kill him, and you won’t stop me.

—¡No! —El hombre parecía aterrorizado.

Agreed?”

Helena lo miró atentamente.

Helena nodded.

—¿Cómo te llamas?

Luc wasn’t anywhere on that floor.

—Vagner —respondió el hombre.

They ascended again.

Le sonaba de algo… Vagner.

Hope dwindling.

¿Wagner?

Maybe all these guards were just for Wagner, who followed them, cowering behind her and Purnell as though they were human shields.

Ese era el nombre que le habían sonsacado Crowther e Ivy a Lancaster cuando lo torturaron.

They turned a corner and found an immense grey-skinned necrothrall standing in front of the door.

Se giró hacia Soren.

He smiled.

—Hemos estado buscando a este hombre.

Not a necrothrall, then, a lich.

—Helena. —Soren la miró exasperado—.

“There you are,” he said in a rasping voice, raising a huge spiked club, as his other hand rapped a warning on the door behind him. “I wondered if the remaining Bayards might show up.

No podemos cargar con un prisionero.

Two down and two to go.” He paid no attention to Soren, his focus on Sebastian. “That pretty niece of yours made a sound like a rotten gourd when I ran her through.

—Este es importante.

You should have seen how fast your Principate dropped his sword when she fell.”

Crowther ha contratado a gente para encontrarlo.

Sebastian stilled Soren. “Who are you?”

Si aquí es donde encarcelan a quienes no quieren que nadie encuentre, es porque el prisionero sabe algo.

The lich smiled again, the corpse’s bloated lips splitting into a rotten grin. “Don’t you recognise me, Sebastian?

Soren vaciló.

I’d think you would, after all the effort you and Apollo put into executing me.

—Si nos retrasa o pone en riesgo la misión, lo mataré y no me lo impedirás.

Afraid it didn’t stick.

¿Está claro?

Not like the axe did when I split your brother’s skull.”

Helena asintió.

“Atreus,” Sebastian said, his voice soft, but his grip on his weapon tightening.

Luc no estaba en esa planta.

Helena stared in horror.

Subieron un piso más.

Kaine’s father was still alive?

Cada vez albergaban menos esperanza.

Before she could process the revelation, both paladins attacked, and Atreus swung at them.

Tal vez todos esos guardias estuvieran allí por Wagner, que los seguía acobardado detrás de Helena y de Purnell, como si las estuviera usando de escudo humano.

The wall exploded, tile and stone flying, dust filling the air.

Al doblar una esquina, se toparon con un necrómata alto y macilento que estaba plantado delante de una puerta.

The hallway was narrow, a tiny combat space in which speed was a far greater advantage than size and muscle.

Sonrió.

If Atreus landed a blow, he would have killed Sebastian and Soren, but he had to hit them.

Aquello les indicó que no se trataba de un necrómata, sino de un liche.

They were faster, slicing at him a dozen times before he could raise the club and give it momentum.

—Aquí estáis —ronroneó con voz áspera.

The other wall cracked open as Atreus swung again.

Levantó una lanza enorme con una mano y con la otra tamborileó una advertencia sobre la puerta—.

The air was so thick with dust, it was almost impossible to see anything but the gleam of metal.

Me preguntaba si aparecerían los Bayard que aún quedáis.

There was a horrifying crunch and squelch and something came flying through the debris and hit the ground.

Nos hemos cargado a dos, así que solo nos quedan otros dos. —No le prestaba atención a Soren mientras hablaba, solamente miraba a Sebastian—.

The lich’s head.

Tu sobrina sonó como una calabaza podrida cuando la apuñalé.

“Come on,” Soren’s voice barked from amid the choking dust.

Deberías haber visto lo rápido que vuestro principado soltó la espada cuando me la cargué.

The rest of them moved forward.

Sebastian sujetó a Soren.

Soren was favouring his right arm and Sebastian was bleeding at the temple, but they were mostly unscathed.

—¿Quién eres?

The huge corpse that had been Atreus Ferron lay at their feet, gouged all over with deep wounds that would have killed anyone who wasn’t already dead.

El liche volvió a sonreír; los labios hinchados del cadáver se estiraron en una sonrisa putrefacta.

“Shouldn’t we get the talisman?” Helena asked as they all stepped around it.

—¿No me reconoces, Sebastian?

“There’s no time to search a corpse that big,” Soren said as he stumbled forward and shoved the door open.

Pensé que lo harías después de todo el empeño que os pusisteis Apollo y tú en ejecutarme.

There was Luc.

Me temo que no funcionó.

They all froze.

Al contrario que el hacha que le clavé a tu hermano en el cráneo.

He was strapped down on a medical table, a mask fitted over his nose and mouth attached to several tubes.

—Atreus —sentenció Sebastian en voz baja, pero agarró el arma con más fuerza.

There was a cluster of people around him, swathed in surgical gowns.

Helena lo observó horrorizada.

His torso had been sliced open, peeled back to expose all the organs, but they were blackened, almost necrotic.

¿El padre de Kaine seguía vivo?

“Fuck!” said a woman’s voice, and she glanced over towards them.

Antes de que pudiera procesar la información, los dos paladines se lanzaron al ataque y Atreus se abalanzó sobre ellos.

They were clearly trying to finish what they’d been doing when Atreus knocked to warn them.

La pared estalló; baldosas y piedras volaron por el aire, levantando una nube de polvo que lo cubrió todo.

Two people lunged across the floor and through a door on the far side without a backwards glance, leaving the rest.

La galería era estrecha, un espacio de combate reducido donde la velocidad era más valiosa que el tamaño y la fuerza.

The room exploded into violence.

Si Atreus conseguía acertar un golpe, mataría a Sebastian y a Soren, pero primero debía tenerlos al alcance.

Soren had been waiting for this moment.

Los Bayard eran más rápidos y lo acribillaron a cortes antes de que Atreus pudiera levantar la lanza y coger impulso.

He shot across the room, his weapon sweeping into a long curving blade.

Otra pared estalló cuando Atreus blandió su arma de nuevo.

He killed everyone violently.

El aire estaba tan cargado de polvo que apenas se distinguía nada salvo el fulgor del metal.

There was nothing quick or clean about it.

Se oyó un crujido espantoso y algo surcó los escombros y cayó al suelo: era la cabeza del liche.

Warm blood spattered across her face as Helena went for Luc.

—Vamos —bramó Soren entre el polvo sofocante.

Despite being strapped down, his hands had been pierced through with spikes of nullium that Helena instantly recognised by the telltale way they were dissolving into his blood.

Los demás se pusieron en marcha.

Her fingers trembled as she reached out, looking for a pulse, not sure if her resonance would work.

Soren empleaba más el brazo derecho y Sebastian estaba sangrando por una herida en la sien, pero ambos estaban ilesos.

She pressed her fingers below his jaw and gave a small sob of relief.

El enorme cadáver que había albergado el alma de Atreus Ferron yacía a sus pies, cubierto de tajos profundos que habrían matado a cualquiera que no estuviera ya muerto.

He was alive.

—¿No deberíamos sacarle el talismán? —preguntó Helena cuando todos pasaron por encima del cuerpo.

Drugged and cut open, but alive.

—No tenemos tiempo de hurgar en un cadáver tan grande —respondió Soren, que caminó a trompicones y abrió la puerta de un empujón.

She ripped the mask off his face as Purnell twisted a nozzle on the tank, cutting off whatever they’d been using on him.

Allí estaba Luc.

What had they done?

Todos se quedaron paralizados.

Her hands shook as she searched for a talisman inside him, but she felt no signs of lumithium or any other metal.

Estaba atado a una camilla y tenía una mascarilla sobre la nariz y la boca conectada con varios tubos.

His organs were darkened, as if he’d been poisoned with something, but there was no time to try to heal it all.

A su alrededor había un grupo de personas con batas médicas.

She closed the incisions, working carefully, aligning everything.

Luc estaba abierto en canal, y su torso había sido plegado hacia atrás para dejar a la vista todos los órganos, negros y gangrenosos.

Purnell was prying the spikes from his hands, her breath coming out in rapid pants as she struggled to get them loose.

—¡Mierda! —exclamó una mujer en cuanto vio al batallón.

There was a stark look of terror starting to creep across the girl’s face.

Era evidente que todavía no habían terminado lo que estuvieran haciendo cuando Atreus los alertó.

The veins and arteries in Luc’s arms had been constricted, the gas administered keeping his heartbeat impossibly sluggish.

Dos personas salieron corriendo por una puerta que había al fondo.

The combination had kept his resonance inactive while allowing the now dead scientists to use their own on him.

Dejaron allí a los demás a su suerte, sin tan siquiera mirar atrás.

He was also conscious, but just barely.

El quirófano se sumió en la violencia.

Soren and Alister were trying to force open the door that two attackers had attempted to escape through, without success.

Soren se había preparado para este momento.

Helena worked as fast as she could, speeding up Luc’s metabolism and forcing his damaged kidneys back into action, making his heart beat more rapidly once Purnell had the spikes out.

Recorrió la sala y transformó su arma en una hoja larga y curvada.

Helena shoved a decoction into her hands, ordering her to wash the wounds and get them wrapped in gauze.

Asesinó a todos los presentes con agresividad.

Then her ring burned.

No fueron muertes rápidas ni limpias.

Pain like fire ran up her left hand.

Helena notó que le caían chorros de sangre cuando se acercó a Luc.

She gave a choked gasp as she kept working.

Además de estar atado, le habían perforado las manos con unas púas de anulitio que Helena reconoció de inmediato por cómo el material se disolvía lentamente en su sangre.

The sensation barely faded before it burned again.

Le buscó el pulso con manos temblorosas, aunque no estaba segura de que fuera a funcionarle la resonancia.

“Is he alive?” she dimly heard Soren asking, his voice shaking.

Colocó dos dedos por debajo de la mandíbula de Luc y se le escapó un sollozo de alivio.

“Yes.

Estaba vivo.

Just give me a minute,” she said, touching Luc’s face desperately. “Come on, Luc.

Anestesiado y abierto en canal, pero vivo.

Do you hear me?”

Le arrancó la mascarilla de la cara y Purnell giró un botón de la bombona para cortar lo que le estuvieran suministrando.

Her ring burned again.

¿Qué le habían hecho?

Alarms started.

Helena palpó con las manos, por si le habían metido un talismán, si bien no encontró restos de lumitio ni de ningún otro metal.

A deafening ringing that filled the air.

Tenía los órganos negros, como si lo hubieran envenenado, pero no había tiempo de curarlo de verdad.

“We’ve got to go!” Soren yelled over the din. “Fuck.

Helena cerró las incisiones con todo el cuidado del que fue capaz, dejándolo todo en su sitio.

We’ll just carry him.”

Purnell estaba examinando las púas que tenía clavadas en las manos y no dejaba de jadear entrecortadamente mientras trataba de quitárselas.

“Luc, wake up.” Helena shook him.

Su expresión era de un terror absoluto.

They didn’t have the manpower for Luc to be deadweight.

Helena se percató de que las venas y las arterias de los brazos de Luc estaban obstruidas y que el corazón le latía demasiado lento por culpa del gas que le habían administrado.

There was no way that Helena and Purnell could carry him all the way out if there was fighting.

Aquello había silenciado su resonancia para que los científicos que acababan de morir pudieran emplear la suya propia.

She had a vial and a needle.

El principado no estaba del todo inconsciente, pero tampoco despierto.

Her hands were shaking as she filled a syringe.

Soren y Alister estaban intentando abrir la puerta por la que habían escapado los dos científicos, pero no lo conseguían.

She’d never used this—epinephrine combined with painkillers and a few other things to jump-start his body into action.

Helena trabajó lo más rápido que pudo y, cuando Purnell por fin le sacó las púas, aceleró el metabolismo de Luc para obligar a los riñones a ponerse en marcha y al corazón a latir con más fuerza.

If it was too strong, it would kill him.

También le dio un frasco a la chica para que le lavara las heridas y así poder vendarlas luego.

It would all be for nothing.

Entonces sintió que su anillo ardía.

“Come on,” she muttered, and jabbed it through his chest into his heart.

Empezó a dolerle la mano izquierda.

Luc lurched, giving a sudden gasp as his body jolted into violent consciousness.

Se le escapó un grito ahogado, pero siguió trabajando.

Helena saw a flash of sky blue as his eyes cracked open.

Apenas había desaparecido el calor cuando volvió a encenderse.

“Hel?” he croaked, his voice dry.

—¿Está vivo? —escuchó que decía Soren con voz trémula.

He reached out, touching her face with his bandaged hand as if he couldn’t believe she was real.

—Sí, dame un minuto —respondió, tocándole la cara con desesperación—.

“Yes,” she said, trying not to cry. “We’ve come to take you home.”

Vamos, Luc.

His eyes rolled around, searching, skimming past everyone clustered around him. “Where’s—where’s Lila?”

¿Me oyes?

“Headquarters,” Soren said, his voice gruff, “waiting for you.”

El anillo volvió a calentarse.

Luc stiffened. “Is she really—?”

Entonces sonaron las alarmas, un pitido ensordecedor que lo inundó todo.

“She’s alive,” Helena said quickly. “We took care of her.

—¡Tenemos que irnos! —gritó Soren por encima del escándalo—.

It’s your turn now.

Joder, lo llevaremos en brazos.

Come on.”

—Luc, despierta. —La chica lo zarandeó.

Luc gave a shuddering gasp of relief. “They said if I went—they wouldn’t kill her.

Pero Luc pesaba demasiado.

She was—bleeding—so much.

No podrían moverlo así.

Wouldn’t even let me burn it closed.

Helena y Purnell no conseguirían sacarlo de allí a rastras si había alguna pelea.

She’s—she’s all right?”

Helena sacó un frasco y una jeringuilla, y la rellenó con manos temblorosas.

“She’s alive, getting better,” Helena said. “Come on.

Nunca había usado esa combinación: epinefrina, calmantes y otras sustancias que activarían su cuerpo.

Take this.

Si era demasiado potente, lo mataría.

We’ve got to go.”

Y todo habría sido en vano.

She pulled him upright and he groaned, clutching at his chest.

—Vamos… —masculló clavándosela en el pecho, junto al corazón.

“What did they do to me?”

Al instante, Luc se incorporó y aspiró una bocanada de aire.

“I don’t know.

Su cuerpo recobró la movilidad con una sacudida violenta.

I’ll fix you better once we’re safe,” she said, breaking a tablet in half and pushing it past his lips.

Helena vislumbró el azul cielo de sus ojos.

She just had to hope he was still strong enough that everything she was doing wouldn’t kill him. “Hold still.”

—¿Hel? —gimió con voz áspera.

She pressed her hands on each side of his neck, and used the dissolving tablets to manipulate his physiology, getting his internal systems working the way they needed to.

Estiró la mano vendada para tocarle la cara, como si no creyese que fuera real.

He’d crash terribly once it all wore off, but she’d be there.

—Sí —confirmó ella, conteniendo las lágrimas—.

She could make up all the difference once they were safe.

Hemos venido para llevarte a casa.

“Up now,” she said.

El principado miró a su alrededor, intentando reconocer a quienes estaban en el quirófano.

He was breathing too fast; she could feel his heart racing dangerously.

—¿Dónde… dónde está Lila?

She tried to slow it a little, but the more conscious he became, the more he comprehended their danger.

—En el Cuartel General —respondió Soren con cierta brusquedad—, esperándote.

She pulled one of his arms over her shoulder and Purnell took the other, and they dragged him to his feet.

Luc se puso en tensión.

“You came …” Luc said, slumping heavily on her.

—¿Pero está…?

“You’re my best friend,” Helena said, staring ahead. “Of course I did.

—Está viva —se apresuró a decir Helena—.

Come on.

La hemos sanado.

We need to get you out.”

Ahora te toca a ti.

He kept tripping over his feet, his body bearing down so hard that her knees nearly buckled.

Tenemos que irnos.

She was grateful he was not in armour, or she didn’t know how they’d manage.

A Luc se le escapó un suspiro de alivio.

The floor was slick with blood and gore.

—Me dijeron que si los acompañaba… no la matarían.

“You shouldn’t be here.

Estaba… sangrando… tanto.

You’re not—trained,” he said when they were halfway down a flight of stairs.

No pude detener la hemorragia ni con fuego.

“Helping you is exactly what I’m trained for,” she said.

¿Está… está bien?

Her ring kept burning, again and again.

—Está viva, y recuperándose —respondió Helena—.

She ignored it.

Venga, coge esto.

She had been afraid that after all the fighting to get there, Soren and the others would be too exhausted to keep going, but recovering Luc had reinvigorated them.

Tenemos que irnos.

However secret the prison had been, it was not so secret that there weren’t plenty of necrothralls now that the alarms had gone off.

Lo ayudó a incorporarse, pero Luc gimió y se llevó una mano al pecho.

Not shoddy, damaged necrothralls that shambled and ravaged carelessly; these greys were expertly reanimated, so capable it was hard to believe they were dead except they kept coming no matter how Soren and Sebastian sliced them apart.

—¿Qué me han hecho?

The narrowness of the hallways and tight corners was both gift and curse.

—No lo sé.

“I need a weapon,” Luc said, trying to pull away from Helena as Soren was slammed against the wall and crumpled.

Lo arreglaré cuando estemos a salvo —contestó la chica.

A necrothrall nearly took his head off, but Sebastian rammed into it, buying Soren enough time to scramble to his feet and decapitate it.

Partió una pastilla por la mitad y se la introdujo en la boca.

He was fighting left-handed, his right arm cradled against his body.

Solo podía rezar para que su cuerpo aguantara todo lo que le estaba suministrando—.

The drugs were taking effect.

Estate quieto.

Luc was strong enough to resist Helena’s attempts to hold him back and alert enough to realise how outnumbered they were.

Colocó ambas manos a los lados de su cuello y usó la pastilla para reajustar su fisiología y para asegurarse de que sus órganos funcionaran tal como debían.

Still she tried to stop him.

Cuando se le pasara el efecto, se derrumbaría por completo, pero Helena estaría con él.

“Luc, you’re injured.

Lo solucionaría todo en cuanto estuvieran a salvo.

I’m not even sure how much.

—Levanta —le ordenó.

You’re just not feeling it.”

Luc estaba respirando demasiado rápido, y ella se percató de que el corazón le latía a una velocidad peligrosa.

“I’m not watching them die.” He tried again to shove her and Purnell off.

Trató de ralentizarlo, pero conforme recobraba el conocimiento era más consciente del peligro.

She dug her fingers into his arms. “Luc, you don’t have resonance.”

Helena se pasó uno de sus brazos por encima del hombro y Purnell hizo lo mismo por el otro lado.

“Then heal me again later,” he said, finally ripping himself free and throwing himself into the fight.

Tendrían que sacarlo a rastras.

He kicked a necrothrall so hard his foot went through its chest.

—Has venido… —dijo Luc dejándose caer con pesadez.

He snatched up its sword.

—Eres mi mejor amigo —replicó Helena con la vista al frente—.

Soren called him several names, but there was no time to do more than curse as they kept fighting their way down.

Claro que he venido.

Helena pulled out a knife when they reached the basement.

Venga, tenemos que salir de aquí.

Wagner was huddling behind Purnell as if he expected her to protect him.

Luc no paraba de tropezarse con sus propios pies y su cuerpo presionaba con tanta fuerza que sus rodillas casi se doblaron.

Purnell’s eyes were wide, the whites glaring with visible panic as she clutched back.

Agradeció que no llevase armadura, porque de haber sido así no lo habrían conseguido.

They shouldn’t have brought her.

El suelo resbalaba por la sangre y las vísceras.

The girl was beginning to fall apart.

—No deberías estar aquí.

She didn’t have the nerve for combat.

No tienes… formación —dijo cuando estaban a la mitad de las escaleras.

They got into the room and blocked the door, but it was barely secured before the whole wall shook.

—Me formaron para ayudarte —repuso Helena.

They fled into the tunnels, scrambling after one another into the sewers, trying to reach the flood cathedral.

El anillo no dejaba de arder.

Alister brought up the rear, crushing and sealing the tunnel behind them, step after step, so that pursuit would be slow.

Una y otra vez.

They reached one of the larger tunnels and paused, gasping for breath.

Lo ignoró.

“You’re not supposed to be fighting, you moron,” Soren said, slumping against the wall.

Temía que, después de todo lo que habían combatido para llegar hasta allí, Soren y los demás estuvieran demasiado agotados para seguir peleando, pero ver a Luc les había dado fuerzas.

In torchlight, he’d turned very grey and his nose was broken, blood streaming down his mouth and chin.

Por muy secreta que hubiera sido la prisión, una vez que se activó la alarma empezaron a salir numerosos necrómatas.

Purnell was crouched on the ground, rocking and muttering, Mummy?

No se trataba de los necrómatas lamentables y putrefactos que arrastraban los pies y se deterioraban rápidamente; a estos necrómatas los había reanimado una persona experta, y apenas se notaba que estaban muertos, salvo por el hecho de que seguían luchando a pesar de los golpes que recibían de Soren y Sebastian.

Mummy, please don’t, over and over.

La estrechez de los pasillos y lo anguloso de su recorrido eran a la vez una ventaja y una trampa.

“Don’t tell me what to do,” Luc said, breathing hard, shifting his grip on the sword. “This sword is shit.

—Necesito un arma —dijo Luc, e intentó apartar a Helena cuando Soren acabó estampado contra la pared y se derrumbó en el suelo.

You could have brought a weapon for me.

Un necrómata quiso arrancarle la cabeza, pero Sebastian lo apuñaló.

Do you have my rings at least?”

Así ganó algo de tiempo para que Soren se incorporara y lo decapitara.

“You don’t have resonance,” Helena snapped.

Estaba luchando con la mano izquierda; el brazo derecho lo mantenía pegado al cuerpo.

Luc grimaced but gripped the sword harder.

La medicación estaba surtiendo efecto.

“I don’t know how Lila’s never killed you,” Soren said, pushing himself up but looking ready to topple over.

Luc había recuperado la fuerza suficiente como para resistirse a Helena, que pretendía sujetarlo, y también era consciente de que los enemigos los superaban en número.

“Hold on.” Helena went over and checked him.

Aun así, Helena trató de detenerlo.

His arm was broken again.

—Luc, estás herido.

Three times in a year.

Ni siquiera estoy segura de cuánto.

It was unlikely to ever heal properly after this.

Simplemente no sientes el dolor.

She aligned the bones again and fused them.

—No voy a quedarme de brazos cruzados viendo cómo los matan. —Intentó zafarse de ella y de Purnell, pero Helena le clavó los dedos en los brazos.

“Do you have something for pain?” Penny asked in a small voice. “Or maybe you could block off some nerves.”

—Luc, no tienes resonancia.

When she was done with Penny, she made them all take her blood tonics, so that if they required healing, what she’d need would already be there.

—Pues ya me curarás luego —replicó y, al final, se libró de ambas y se lanzó a la batalla.

She’d brought two for everyone but hadn’t expected an extra prisoner.

Le propinó una patada a un necrómata con tanta fuerza que le atravesó el pecho.

Wagner drank hers while she was passing out the others.

Después, le arrebató la espada.

“We need to keep moving,” Soren said.

Soren lo llamó varias veces, pero no pudo más que maldecir, ya que no dejaban de abalanzarse sobre él.

They had to drag Purnell with them; she was completely gone, staring blankly as if she didn’t know where she was anymore, still saying Mummy, her voice chillingly childlike.

Helena desenvainó una de sus dagas cuando llegaron al sótano.

They retraced their steps, following the maze of tunnels back to their entry point.

Wagner seguía encogido detrás de Purnell, como si creyera que la chica podría protegerlo.

At first it was a relief that they weren’t being pursued, but the closer they got, the eerier it was.

Purnell tenía los ojos desencajados y la mirada perdida por el pánico.

Helena’s ring burned again.

No deberían haberla traído.

“Sol save us.

Estaba desmoronándose, no era capaz de resistir la guerra.

It’s Blackthorne!” Penny said, her voice strangled with terror as they rounded the corner.

Se metieron en el sótano y cerraron la puerta, pero apenas habían girado la llave cuando la pared se hizo trizas.

The shallow sections of the flood cathedral were filled not only with a horde of necrothralls but also a number of what looked to be the mortal Aspirants, lined up and blocking their path.

Huyeron por los túneles, arrastrándose uno tras otro por el alcantarillado en dirección a los tanques de inundación.

“Go back!” Soren immediately said, but he’d barely spoken the words before there came a scream of metal behind them, followed by a savage roar.

Alister se colocó en la retaguardia y echó abajo los túneles conforme pasaban, paso a paso, para dificultar la persecución.

Chimaeras.

Cuando llegaron a uno de los túneles principales, se detuvieron a tomar aliento.

They were penned in.

—No deberías estar luchando, idiota —le espetó Soren, desplomado contra una pared.

Blackthorne stood at the front, barely armoured. “Capture Holdfast, kill the rest, and you will receive the immortal reward!”

A la luz de las antorchas, se le veía muy gris.

There was an eager roar among the Aspirants, while the necrothralls just stood still, waiting.

Tenía la nariz partida y la sangre le corría por la boca y la barbilla.

“Stay close,” Luc ordered as he fell in, shoulder-to-shoulder, with Soren and Sebastian.

Purnell estaba encogida en el suelo, meciéndose.

“Get across,” Soren said.

—¿Mami?

The plan, as much as there had been a plan, fell apart.

Mamá, por favor, no lo hagas —musitaba una y otra vez.

There was no escaping with Luc when he was in the thick of the fighting.

—No me digas lo que tengo que hacer —replicó Luc, que respiraba entrecortadamente.

Helena’s fingers went for her daggers.

Agarró la espada con la otra mano—.

The first wave of necrothralls hit, and the group splintered like a wrecked ship.

Esta espada es una mierda.

Several necrothralls rushed towards Helena.

Podrías haberme traído algún arma.

There was no time to think.

¿Tenéis mis anillos al menos?

She moved on instinct, blocking, slicing, her dagger morphing to chase after crucial joints, while her other palm pressed flat and she jerked back, ripping their reanimation free.

—No tienes resonancia —le espetó Helena.

The energy struck her, a blistering flare of power, and she sent it outwards, pulverising the necrothralls closing in.

Luc torció el gesto, pero aferró la espada con más fuerza.

There was light somewhere, fire, torches, reflecting across the frigid water that was already up to their knees.

—Me parece increíble que Lila no te haya matado todavía —comentó Soren mientras lograba incorporarse.

The noise was deafening.

Se sostenía a duras penas, tambaleante.

The roar and chaos shattered the senses.

—Espera. —Helena se acercó y lo revisó.

She looked for the others, but it was impossible to see them in the throng.

Tenía el brazo roto otra vez, eran ya tres veces en el mismo año.

So many bodies, living and dead, moving through the dark.

Lo más probable era que esta vez no se le curara del todo.

Kaine had trained her to defend herself and flee, not fight in a melee.

Le colocó los huesos en su sitio y los soldó.

She tried to key up her resonance, but there were so many bodies and movements and weapons swinging, it was dizzying.

—¿Tienes algo para el dolor? —preguntó Penny en voz baja—.

She ducked a swinging club and lashed out with her knife, the blade singing with resonance as it tore through the waxy decaying skin, up the torso and throat, slicing through bones like butter, into the brain.

También me sirve si puedes seccionar algún nervio.

She twisted her resonance and the blade curved, severing the head completely.

Cuando hubo terminado con Penny, obligó a todo el equipo a tomarse sus tónicos regenerativos.

Something collided with her, bowling her over.

Quería asegurarse de que todos estaban en condiciones de asimilar la sanación si la necesitaban.

A warm hand, wrenching her up.

Había traído dos para cada uno, pero no había contado con un prisionero extra.

Ally, she thought, until she saw the steel-gauntleted fist, gripping a sword and swinging it towards her head.

Wagner se bebió el suyo mientras repartía el resto.

She drove her knife up, the handguard just barely large enough to deflect, and then she stabbed towards the weak point near the shoulder, narrowing the blade as thin as she could until her resonance with the metal told her she’d pierced flesh.

—Tenemos que ponernos en marcha —afirmó Soren.

She flared out the knife blade as it sank into the hilt.

Tuvieron que arrastrar a Purnell con ellos, porque seguía en estado catatónico y tenía la mirada perdida, como si no supiera quién era, y no dejaba de llamar a su madre con una voz infantil y escalofriante.

She jerked it back and felt the warm, heavy spurt of hot blood across her hand as the grip on her loosened.

Regresaron mientras desandaban sus pasos por la maraña de túneles hasta que llegaron al punto por donde habían entrado.

The sword fell, barely missing her head, and the Aspirant crashed into the water on top of her.

Al principio, sintieron alivio al comprobar que nadie los seguía, pero conforme se acercaban les parecía muy extraño.

Cold water hit her head-on, painful as a kick to the ribs.

El anillo de Helena volvió a arder.

She scrambled to her feet, fighting to get free of the body nearly drowning her.

—Que Sol nos ampare.

She stabbed blindly, the water and noise and disorientation making it impossible to sense anything clearly.

¡Es Blackthorne! —exclamó Penny con la voz estrangulada por el miedo en cuanto doblaron una esquina.

She crawled out of the throng, found a wall, and got up, trying to catch her breath, trying to find the others in the flickering dark.

En las partes bajas de los tanques de inundación se extendía una horda de necrómatas, acompañados por un buen número de aspirantes mortales.

There was screaming.

Permanecían en formación y les bloqueaban el paso por completo.

It kept going on and on.

—¡Atrás! —ordenó Soren al instante, pero nada más pronunciar la palabra se oyó un chirrido de metal a sus espaldas, seguido de un rugido monstruoso.

It was Purnell.

Quimeras.

She’d snapped out of her daze and was now screaming at the top of her lungs, the sound bouncing off the walls, drawing attention.

Estaban atrapados.

A group of necrothralls was closing in.

Blackthorne estaba al frente y no llevaba armadura.

Wagner, who was nearest to Purnell, shoved her straight at them as he tried to escape.

—Capturad a Holdfast y matad al resto.

As she fell, Purnell seemed to become lucid again, comprehending terror sweeping across her face.

¡Así conseguiréis la inmortalidad!

She was weaponless but quick.

Los aspirantes rugieron desesperados, mientras que los necrómatas permanecieron inmóviles, a la espera.

She leapt, somehow evading the clawing hands, and fled into the centre of the flood-filled room.

—Manteneos cerca —dijo Luc, que se colocó hombro con hombro entre Soren y Sebastian.

Half a dozen steps and then Purnell stepped too far, vanishing underwater.

—Tenemos que llegar al otro lado —indicó Soren.

Helena watched, praying that she’d resurface, that somehow she’d escaped the current.

El plan, si es que se podía llamar así, había fracasado.

Something rammed into Helena, knocking her sideways.

No podrían escapar con Luc si el principado se empeñaba en luchar.

A boot came down on her wrist, and she inhaled water when she gasped with pain.

Los dedos de Helena buscaron las dagas.

Fire tore along her ribs.

Cuando la primera oleada de necrómatas cayó sobre ellos, el grupo se dividió como un barco a la deriva.

She crawled back towards the wall.

Varios necrómatas se lanzaron contra Helena.

Her clothes freezing on her skin.

No tuvo tiempo de pensar.

She turned, looking desperately for the others, coughing up water.

Se movió por puro instinto: esquivó, bloqueó, apuñaló y transformó la daga para que dañara las articulaciones esenciales.

Wagner had somehow managed to reach the far wall and had a spear he was beating off necrothralls with.

Con la mano que le quedaba libre, cercenó la reanimación de los cadáveres.

Luc and Sebastian were fighting together in the centre of a horde, while Soren had broken away and was trying to reach Alister and Penny, who’d been backed into a corner far from everyone else.

La energía la golpeó con violencia, fue como una detonación.

The light flickered madly off the water, only giving glimpses.

Perdió el equilibrio, pero los necrómatas que había cerca acabaron pulverizados.

The chimaeras had caught up.

En alguna parte había luz, fuego, antorchas que se reflejaban en el agua pútrida que ya les llegaba hasta las rodillas.

Fangs and claws were flashing as Alister tried to raise a barrier.

El sonido era ensordecedor: el rugido y el caos impedían los sentidos.

Penny gave a cry as her weapon caught in the shoulder of a chimaera and was ripped from her hands.

Helena buscó a los demás, pero le resultó imposible distinguirlos en medio de la multitud.

Soren raced through the water, his weapon morphing as he ran, trying to reach them before the chimaeras closed in.

Había demasiados cuerpos, vivos y muertos, que se movían en la oscuridad.

An axe came swinging through the air, barely missing Soren’s leg.

Kaine la había enseñado a defenderse para escapar, no a luchar en una refriega como esa.

Soren caught himself, stumbling in the water, and turned hard, looking around wildly to find his attacker.

Intentó concentrarse en su resonancia, pero había tantos cadáveres, tantos movimientos y tantas armas que empezaba a marearse.

His weapon flashed, barely blocking a blow that nearly threw him off his feet.

Esquivó una porra que venía directa a por ella y respondió con un tajo de su cuchillo.

Now he was facing his opponent.

La hoja vibró con resonancia cuando atravesó la piel cerosa y putrefacta, del torso a la garganta hasta hundirse en el cerebro, rajando huesos como si fueran mantequilla.

Blackthorne barred the way.

Con un movimiento de resonancia, la hoja se curvó y cercenó la cabeza del necrómata de forma limpia.

Blackthorne, realising the disadvantage of his opponent, kept moving to the right.

Algo chocó con ella y la hizo tropezar.

Making all his attacks from Soren’s blind spot.

Una mano caliente impidió que cayera al suelo. «Será un aliado», pensó.

Tiring him.

Pero entonces vio un guantelete de acero que empuñaba una espada y la dirigía hacia su cabeza.

“Soren!” Luc suddenly shouted.

Helena levantó la daga, justo a tiempo para esquivar el golpe con la empuñadura y, acto seguido, la hundió en la clavícula del adversario.

Soren pivoted sharply as a chimaera leapt at him.

Haciendo uso de la resonancia, estrechó la hoja todo lo que pudo hasta que el metal la avisó de que había atravesado la carne.

He beheaded it in one clean sweep of his blade.

Cuando la tuvo metida hasta la empuñadura, hizo que la hoja se extendiera y la sacó de un tirón.

There was a horrible, wet cracking sound.

Helena sintió que la sangre cálida y espesa le manchaba la mano y, un segundo después, el guantelete le soltó el hombro.

When Soren turned, Blackthorne had swung from the right.

La espada cayó a varios centímetros de su cabeza, y el aspirante se desplomó encima de ella.

The axe head was buried all the way through his ribs to his spine.

Los dos cayeron al agua.

Blackthorne jerked the axe free and licked it as Soren dropped, vanishing into the water.

Helena sintió el frío como si fuera una patada en las costillas.

Everything went out of focus.

Intentó incorporarse para librarse del cadáver que estaba a punto de asfixiarla.

Luc was screaming, but Helena’s body seemed to abruptly come alive.

Blandió el arma a ciegas: el agua, el ruido y la desorientación le hacían imposible percibir nada más.

She stumbled forward, slashing at anything in her path, trying to reach Soren before the river took him.

Gateó para alejarse del tumulto hasta que encontró una pared y logró ponerse en pie.

Luc was faster.

Trató de recobrar el aliento mientras buscaba a los demás en los intervalos de luz que despejaban las sombras.

By the time Helena reached him, Luc was already on his knees, pulling Soren up into his arms, stained with the rush of blood that poured out of him.

Se oían unos gritos que no cesaban.

Sebastian was a moment behind him, immediately throwing himself into Blackthorne’s path and holding him off as Luc knelt in the water, Soren clutched against his chest.

Era Purnell, que había superado la congoja y ahora chillaba a pleno pulmón.

Luc looked up when Helena reached him.

Los gritos rebotaban en los muros y llamaban la atención.

“Y-You can heal him, right?”

Un grupo de necrómatas avanzaba hacia ella.

“Luc—”

Wagner, que estaba al lado de Purnell, la empujó hacia ellos y trató de escapar.

But he was already pushing Soren into her arms, the weight dropping her to her knees in the water.

Al caer al suelo, la chica pareció recobrar la lucidez, pero entonces comprobó con horror lo que estaba pasando.

She held on to Soren with trembling hands, ignoring the throb of her wrist.

No tenía armas, pero reaccionó rápido.

“I’ll cover you,” Luc said, picking up his sword.

Saltó y, de alguna forma, esquivó las manos que se le echaban encima.

And then he was gone.

Corrió hacia el centro del túnel, que estaba inundado de sangre.

The battle did not stop for Soren.

Apenas había dado unos pasos cuando desapareció bajo el agua.

Helena tried to ignore the fighting that raged around her, trying to focus.

Helena lo vio todo y rezó para que volviera a salir a la superficie, para que escapase de la corriente.

A thread was all she needed.

Sin embargo, justo entonces, algo golpeó a Helena y la hizo caer de costado.

She could keep him alive.

Sintió una bota aplastándole su muñeca y se atragantó con el agua al proferir un grito ahogado.

Just like she’d kept Lila alive.

Un dolor abrasador le atravesó las costillas.

But the wound was so big.

Retrocedió a gatas hasta la pared.

Wounds like this didn’t survive a journey to the hospital.

Tenía la ropa congelada y pegada a la piel.

This blow had been lethal.

Se giró buscando a sus compañeros, aunque no dejaba de toser agua.

Soren’s remaining life was feeble, slipping away as her resonance tried to grasp it.

No sabía cómo, pero Wagner había logrado llegar a la pared contraria y ahora blandía una lanza con la que combatía a los necrómatas.

Fingers brushed against her hand.

Luc y Sebastian luchaban juntos en el centro de la horda, mientras que Soren se había separado y estaba intentando alcanzar a Alister y Penny, que estaban acorralados, lejos de todo el mundo.

Soren was staring at her. “Two souls is still a bargain.”

Las luces parpadeaban sin parar sobre el agua, por lo que solo se veían destellos fragmentados de la acción.

The words had barely passed from his lips when a surge of cold deathly energy hit, slamming through Helena’s resonance.

Las quimeras habían llegado.

She was so raw with exhaustion, so focused on trying to keep him alive, her vision blotted out as a jolt of death ran through her.

Helena vio de reojo unos colmillos afilados y unas garras mientras Alister intentaba levantar un muro improvisado.

She doubled over, for a moment too dazed to comprehend what had happened.

Penny soltó un grito desesperado cuando clavó su arma en el hombro de una quimera y el monstruo la arrastró consigo.

Her vision cleared and Soren’s blank, sightless gaze met hers.

Soren atravesó el agua con gran rapidez, transformando su arma sobre la marcha, tratando de llegar antes de que las quimeras se les echaran encima.

He was gone.

Un hacha surcó el aire y estuvo a punto de clavarse en su pierna.

“No. No. No. Soren!”

El joven se detuvo, dando un traspié en el agua, y se giró bruscamente para buscar a su atacante.

He hung in her arms, his blood still flooding against her skin, the only warmth.

La guadaña que tenía en la mano esquivó un golpe de milagro, aunque estuvo a punto de perder el equilibrio.

Helena looked around.

Ahora ya sabía a quién se enfrentaba: Blackthorne le impedía el paso.

Alister was calling to Penny to fall back as she fought the chimaeras using a knife, letting them get dangerously close before she could hit them.

El inmarcesible, consciente de la desventaja de su contrincante, atacaba siempre a su derecha y dirigía todos los golpes al punto ciego de Soren.

One mistake was all it would take.

Lo estaba agotando.

Soren was dead.

—¡Soren! —gritó Luc de repente.

Purnell was dead.

Soren se giró en el mismo momento en el que una quimera se lanzaba a por él.

Sebastian was doing everything he could to keep Luc protected, holding off Blackthorne.

La decapitó de un movimiento certero.

Luc was fighting, but his focus was split.

Se oyó un sonido terrible, parecido a un crujido húmedo.

He kept checking on Helena where she knelt with Soren clutched in her arms.

Aprovechando que Soren se había vuelto, Blackthorne le había atacado por la derecha.

She could see the desperation in his eyes.

Tenía la cabeza del hacha enterrada entre las costillas y le sobresalía por la espalda.

The certainty that she was going to save Soren.

Blackthorne retiró el hacha y le dio un lametazo a la hoja mientras observaba a Soren caer y desaparecer bajo el agua.

That she could.

Todo ocurrió muy deprisa.

She met his eyes for one guilt-stricken moment and turned back, pulling Soren’s body against her.

Luc empezó a chillar, pero el cuerpo de Helena pareció cobrar vida de repente.

“Anything,” she said, pressing a hand against his neck. “Whatever the price.”

Se lanzó hacia delante apuñalando todo lo que encontró a su paso, desesperada por llegar hasta donde estaba Soren antes de que la corriente se lo llevara.

She pushed the energy out of her body and brought him back.

Pero Luc fue más rápido.

It was more than just easy.

Cuando Helena llegó, él ya estaba de rodillas, sujetando a Soren en sus brazos, bañado en la sangre que escapaba del cuerpo de su amigo.

It was instinctive.

Un instante después, apareció Sebastian, interponiéndose entre ellos y Blackthorne para impedirle el paso, mientras Luc permanecía arrodillado en el agua abrazando a Soren.

She knew Soren, knew exactly what it felt like when he was alive.

Cuando Helena se agachó a su lado, Luc alzó la vista.

Her resonance wound through him like a current, knitting the wound closed with absolute efficiency, stitching the severed sections of his organs back together, rejoining the bones, but she didn’t stop there.

—P-puedes curarlo, ¿verdad?

She felt his mind return, a shadow, the barest glimmer of him, and she poured her energy into that.

—Luc…

Come back.

Pero el principado ya estaba entregándole el cuerpo de Soren.

Come back.

El peso hizo que Helena cayera de rodillas en el agua.

You can’t go yet.

Agarró al paladín con manos temblorosas, ignorando el dolor punzante que sentía en la muñeca.

Soren blinked up at her, and she felt a connection materialise between them, a wisp.

—Yo te cubro —aseguró Luc cogiendo la espada.

She strengthened it, because she couldn’t let him go.

Y, sin más, se marchó.

“You can’t rest yet, you have to protect Luc,” she said, and heard the words echo through him.

La batalla no se había detenido por Soren.

Soren knew her.

Helena trató de aislarse de lo que sucedía a su alrededor y se concentró.

She could feel it.

Solo necesitaba encontrar un hilo de vida, así lo mantendría a salvo.

The familiarity she represented.

Así había mantenido a Lila con vida.

It was horrible, feeling this abomination of life in her arms.

Pero la herida era demasiado profunda.

For all her efforts, this was a shadow.

Los soldados con este tipo de heridas no sobrevivían el traslado al hospital.

Soren was a puppet she’d slipped her hand inside.

Había recibido un golpe letal.

After so many years of healing, necromancy was effortless.

La vida que le quedaba era frágil y se le escapaba de los dedos cada vez que intentaba usar su resonancia.

There was nothing to hurt.

Unos dedos le acariciaron la mano.

She simply told Soren’s body that it could not die.

Soren la estaba mirando fijamente.

He would fight as he’d always fought.

—Recuerda nuestro trato.

He would protect them, because he knew how to do that.

Apenas escaparon esas palabras de sus labios cuando Helena sintió un estallido de energía fría y letal que atravesó su resonancia.

He stood and helped her up, weapon already in hand.

Tenía la mente tan sensible del cansancio y estaba tan concentrada en mantenerlo con vida que se le nubló la vista cuando notó que la recorría la descarga de la muerte.

Muscle memory lingered, like a sleepwalker’s habits, even when the person was gone.

Se dobló sobre sí misma y, por un instante, no fue capaz de comprender lo que había pasado.

She could see herself through him.

Cuando se le aclaró la vista, se encontró con la mirada vacía e inexpresiva de Soren.

Her consciousness kept flickering back and forth along the connection forged between them.

Había muerto.

He turned then and saw Luc, and she felt the pull towards him.

—No. No. No. ¡Soren!

He looked for Lila next.

Lo tenía en brazos; su sangre seguía manchándole la piel.

Luc saw Soren standing, and for an instant, relief flooded across his face.

Era el único calor que sentía.

Then vanished.

Helena miró a su alrededor.

Luc knew.

Alister estaba pidiéndole a Penny que emprendiera la retirada.

In an instant, he somehow knew.

La chica estaba enfrentándose a las quimeras con un simple cuchillo, por lo que debía acercarse peligrosamente a ellas para darles un tajo.

Still Soren started towards him.

Un error y lo perdería todo.

Helena stopped him.

Soren estaba muerto.

“You need to protect Penny and Alister,” she said, both in her mind and aloud, pointing, turning his focus away from Luc. “Get us out.”

Purnell estaba muerta.

Soren turned and obeyed.

Sebastian estaba haciendo todo lo posible para contener a Blackthorne y proteger a Luc.

Helena watched, her mind swimming from the disorienting secondary awareness in her mind.

Luc seguía luchando, aunque distraído, con la mirada fija en Helena, que seguía arrodillada con Soren en sus brazos.

Her consciousness didn’t know where to go.

Percibió la desesperación en sus ojos.

A chimaera leapt towards her face.

La certeza de que iba a salvar a Soren porque podía hacerlo.

She dodged.

Pero era demasiado tarde.

A scythe flashed before her eyes.

Ella lo miró a los ojos un instante y, después, consumida por la culpa, le dio la espalda y acercó su cuerpo al de Soren.

Soren.

—Haré cualquier cosa —dijo posando una mano en su cuello—.

She blinked, trying to make out her own surroundings.

Cueste lo que cueste.

Soren killed the chimaera without breaking his stride as he reached Penny and Alister, shoving Penny to safety before turning back.

Vertió la energía de su cuerpo para devolvérsela a Soren.

A blur from the left.

Fue demasiado fácil, casi instintivo.

Helena lurched sideways, trying to dodge, not sure if she was seeing her assailants or Soren’s.

Conocía a Soren, sabía lo que había sentido cuando estaba vivo.

Her focus narrowed for an instant, bringing her surroundings back into the forefront of her own mind.

Su resonancia recorrió el cuerpo del paladín como un torrente de agua, cerró la herida de forma limpia, cosió los tajos de los órganos seccionados y recolocó los huesos en su sitio.

If she died, Soren would be gone, too.

Sin embargo, no se detuvo ahí.

She had to stay alive until they got Luc out.

Helena sintió que la mente de Soren regresaba: una sombra, un leve atisbo de su consciencia, así que centró en eso toda su energía.

She tried to block out Soren, but he was rooted in her mind.

«Vuelve.

She sensed something and turned an instant before it slammed into her.

Vuelve.

The air was knocked out of her lungs.

No puedes irte todavía».

She looked down, blinking through her fragmenting consciousness.

Soren parpadeó.

Soren.

Ella notó que había una conexión entre ambos, apenas un hilo.

Helena.

Lo sostuvo, incapaz de dejarlo marchar.

Soren.

—Todavía no puedes descansar, tienes que proteger a Luc —afirmó, y las palabras resonaron en el interior de Soren.

There was a knife driven to the hilt into the right side of her chest.

Soren la reconocía, de eso estaba segura.

Helena.

Sabía que era una amiga.

If she’d turned a split second later, it would have gone through her heart, but—as she squinted, struggling to focus—she didn’t think it had hit anything immediately vital.

Le resultó horrible sentir aquella vida abominable entre sus brazos.

Pain was what it took to drag Helena’s consciousness securely back into her own body.

A pesar de lo mucho que se había esforzado, no era más que una sombra.

She managed to slice off the hand of the necrothrall that had stabbed her before it could pull the knife out.

Soren era una marioneta y ella quien tiraba de los hilos.

Using her throbbing right hand, she held the knife in place, trying to keep it from being jostled as she stomped down on the inside of the necrothrall’s knee.

Después de pasar tantos años sanando, la nigromancia le pareció fácil.

She stumbled away, gasping, the edge of the blade slicing the wound wider as she moved.

No sintió dolor.

A chimaera’s fangs closed around Soren’s leg, tearing it open.

Se limitó a pedirle al cuerpo de Soren que no muriera, que luchara como siempre lo había hecho.

He cut off its head, unmindful of the injury.

Y Soren los protegería, porque sabía cómo hacerlo.

He was being torn apart.

El paladín se puso en pie y la ayudó a levantarse; ya tenía el arma en la mano.

She could feel the injuries, even though pain didn’t register.

La memoria muscular no se perdía.

She hadn’t brought that part of his brain back.

Era como si estuviera sonámbulo, a pesar de estar muerto.

He didn’t stop fighting.

Helena podía ver a través de sus ojos.

Get the knife out, close the wound.

Su consciencia iba y venía mediante la conexión que habían forjado entre ellos.

She went towards the far wall.

Soren se giró y, al ver a Luc, la chica sintió que deseaba acercarse.

She huddled in the freezing water.

Después buscó a Lila.

Another chimaera had attacked Sebastian and Luc.

El principado vio que Soren se ponía en pie y, por un instante, el alivio se hizo patente en su rostro.

The size of it, it had to be part bear.

Sin embargo, no duró mucho.

Luc’s strength was flagging.

Luc lo supo.

The chimaera was huge, mostly mammal but with longer, reptilian jaws and skin so thick, their weapons glanced off.

De alguna forma, lo supo nada más mirarlo.

It screamed like a human.

Aun así, Soren se dirigió hacia él.

She tried to focus, biting down on her lip, bracing herself to pull out the knife.

Helena lo detuvo.

Fingers dug into her braided hair, and Helena was abruptly dragged up until her toes barely touched the ground.

—Tienes que proteger a Penny y a Alister —le ordenó, en voz alta y mentalmente.

Basilius Blackthorne peered at her, teeth bared in a grin, bloodstains from mouth to chin.

Señaló hacia ellos para que dejara de prestarle atención a Luc—.

He ate his wife and children with those teeth …

Sácanos de aquí.

“The Eternal Flame has a necromancer, I see.” His voice was raw and rasping.

Soren se giró y obedeció.

She tried to stab the arm gripping her, but he batted her hand away with a blow so hard, her left hand nearly went numb.

Helena lo observó con la mente confusa; la desorientaba esa segunda consciencia que tenía ahora en su cerebro.

Her knife hit the water with a splash.

La suya propia no sabía adónde ir.

She grabbed for his wrist.

Una quimera se abalanzó sobre ella.

Her fingers grazed his skin, her resonance lashing out.

La esquivó, aunque por el rabillo del ojo vio una guadaña.

But Kaine had always warned her: Once the Undying knew what she was, they’d be wary.

Soren.

Before her resonance could connect, he wrenched her hand off, fingers closing around the knuckles of her left hand, squeezing and twisting.

Helena parpadeó intentando hacerse una idea de cómo estaban.

His grip was like iron, and her bones broke like twigs.

Soren mató a la quimera sin detenerse siquiera en su avance hacia Penny y Alister.

Helena screamed.

Antes de volver, puso a Penny a salvo.

The knife in her chest shifted, painful pressure growing inside her lungs.

Percibió un movimiento a la izquierda.

Blackthorne looked at her shattered hand expectantly and then laughed. “Forgot, you won’t regenerate.”

Helena se encogió para esquivar lo que fuera que se le acercaba, aunque no estaba segura de si estaba viendo a sus atacantes o a los de Soren.

His gaze turned to her right hand, eyeing the awkward way she had the knife braced. “I think this one is already broken, but let’s make sure.”

Trató de concentrarse un poco en su propia mente y se enfocó en lo que la rodeaba.

With unexpected gentleness, he pulled it away from the knife hilt and snapped her wrist.

Si moría, Soren también lo haría.

Black spots of pain danced in her eyes as another strangled scream burst out of her.

Tenía que permanecer con vida hasta que Luc estuviera a salvo.

“I should keep you alive,” he said as he pulled the knife from her chest very slowly, savouring the glide of the blade.

Intentó bloquear los movimientos de Soren, pero estaba demasiado enraizado en su mente.

Helena was in so much pain that her mind kept flickering over into Soren’s, seeking an escape.

Sintió un gesto a su espalda y se giró un segundo antes de que el impacto la alcanzara de lleno.

He was mobbed by necrothralls.

El golpe le vació los pulmones de aire.

The chimaeras were dead, but there were too many necrothralls, dozens of them, shoving him down into the water, tearing him apart.

Bajó la vista y, al parpadear, intercambió una consciencia con otra.

His leg twisted as teeth bit down, tearing out the tendon behind his knee.

Soren.

He was still fighting.

Helena.

His weapon was gone, but he had a knife.

Soren.

Penny was screaming behind him, but Alister held her back.

Tenía un cuchillo clavado hasta la empuñadura en el lado derecho del pecho.

Soren kept stabbing, tearing, clawing his way through, following her instruction not to stop fighting even as he was ripped apart.

Helena.

Dead fingers scrabbled across his face, finding his remaining eye.

Si se hubiera girado un segundo más tarde, le habría atravesado el corazón, pero entrecerró los ojos concentrándose y comprendió que no había provocado daños en ningún órgano vital.

His jaw was torn down, his throat left gaping.

El dolor fue lo único que hizo que Helena recobrara su propia consciencia.

Helena jerked reflexively each time a little more of him was ripped away, but the pain was all with Helena.

Actuó de inmediato: le cortó la mano al necrómata que la había apuñalado y así impidió que sacara el cuchillo.

She couldn’t feel her fingers; there was just a beacon of agony radiating up her arms.

Con la mano derecha sostuvo el arma en el sitio para que este no pudiera arrancarla y, acto seguido, le propinó una patada en la rodilla.

A warm gush of blood ran down the side of her body.

Al moverse, se le escapó un gemido de dolor y trastabilló; los bordes de la hoja se le clavaron aún más.

She thought Basilius would stab her again, but he dropped the knife into the water.

Una quimera cerró los colmillos alrededor de la pierna de Soren y le dejó una herida desgarradora.

He touched her side, fingers light across the wound.

El paladín la decapitó sin prestar atención a la herida.

Her raw nerves screamed in protest.

Lo estaban destrozando.

His fingers traced along the slit between her ribs, and without warning he shoved two of them into it.

Helena notaba las heridas, aunque no sintiera el dolor.

Helena screamed as her skin tore wider.

Esa parte del cerebro no la había logrado reanimar.

The bones bowed as he forced his fingers inside the wound, slick with her blood.

Aun así, no dejó de luchar.

“Did you know, my favourite things are wounds,” he said, the words breathless. “Wetter, hotter, and tighter than anything else.”

«Saca el cuchillo.

Helena’s legs thrashed, her broken hands scrabbling to push him away, the ruined bones grinding, but it was no use.

Cierra la herida».

She screamed and screamed but no one noticed, bashing her head against his chest until he gripped her by the throat with his free hand, his thumb shoving hard against her trachea until she stilled.

Helena se dirigió hasta una pared y se acurrucó en el agua congelada.

Her lungs seized, spasming.

Había otra quimera atacando a Sebastian y a Luc.

“Yes, just like that,” he said with an approving groan. “Don’t worry, I won’t let you die.

Por su tamaño, debía de tener algo de oso.

You’ll still be alive when I hand you over.

A Luc empezaban a fallarle las fuerzas.

Bennet is going to love you.”

La quimera era enorme.

Her consciousness had frayed to its outermost limit.

Su cuerpo era de mamífero, pero mostraba unas fauces alargadas, propias de algún reptil, y una piel tan gruesa que las armas no eran capaces de penetrarla.

Her vision blurred.

Chillaba con voz humana.

She couldn’t even breathe to scream anymore.

Helena intentó concentrarse.

She was only half aware as Soren was ripped from her mind, his body washed downriver, the connection unravelling like blood in the water.

Se mordió el labio y se preparó para sacar el cuchillo.

“One more scream.

No obstante, unos dedos se enredaron entre sus trenzas y obligaron a Helena a levantarse hasta que apenas rozaba el suelo con los pies.

You do it beauti—”

Basilius Blackthorne le dedicó una sonrisa que dejaba ver todos los dientes.

Blackthorne stumbled, gasping as if the breath had been knocked out of him.

Un reguero de sangre le caía desde la boca hasta la barbilla.

His grip on her loosened, fingers sliding free an instant before he was wrenched backwards.

Con esos dientes se había comido a su mujer y a sus hijos…

Helena dropped like a stone.

—Veo que la Llama Eterna cuenta con una nigromante —comentó con voz áspera.

The frigid cold drove her back into consciousness or she would have drowned.

Helena intentó apuñalarle el brazo con el que la agarraba, pero Blackthorne le apartó la mano con tanta fuerza que le entumeció toda la mano izquierda.

She cowered back, looking for Blackthorne in terror and spotted him being dragged by his throat through the water, a wire or rope wrapped around his neck.

La daga cayó al agua con un chapoteo.

The person dragging him wasn’t one of the Resistance.

Intentó agarrarle la muñeca, pero, en cuanto le rozó la piel con los dedos, extendió su resonancia.

It was one of the Undying.

Aunque Kaine siempre se lo había advertido: si los inmarcesibles descubrían lo que era, se mostrarían precavidos.

Immediately identifiable by the helmet and black uniform.

Antes de que pudiera establecer el contacto, Blackthorne se apartó con rapidez y cerró los dedos alrededor de los nudillos de la mano izquierda.

By the time the two were in range of each other, Blackthorne had recovered himself and lunged at his attacker.

No dejó de apretar con todas sus fuerzas, hasta que le partió los dedos como si fueran ramitas.

He’d snatched up a sword from the water and swung, going straight for the head, but the other Undying sidestepped.

Helena chilló.

Blackthorne tried again, and again.

El cuchillo que tenía en el pecho se movió y sintió una presión dolorosa en los pulmones.

His attacks were precise, the movements of a highly accomplished combat alchemist, but his opponent simply dodged.

Blackthorne contempló la mano aplastada de Helena y soltó una carcajada.

No weapon.

—Había olvidado que vosotros no os regeneráis.

No counterattack.

Entonces se fijó en la mano derecha y reparó en la extraña manera en la que sujetaba el cuchillo.

Quick and light, evading as if it were a dance, until Blackthorne left himself open for an instant.

—Creo que esta ya está rota, pero vamos a asegurarnos.

An instant was all it took.

Con una suavidad inesperada, el inmarcesible retiró la mano de Helena de la empuñadura del cuchillo y le partió la muñeca.

The Undying stepped past a blow and with his bare hand, punched through Basilius’s armour and into his chest as easily as if reaching through water.

La chica vio puntos negros y empezó a gritar de nuevo.

A pale, long-fingered hand dripped red with blood as it pulled out a gleaming piece of metal from Blackthorne’s chest cavity.

—Debería mantenerte con vida —dijo mientras le sacaba el cuchillo del pecho muy lentamente, disfrutando del resplandor de la hoja.

Blackthorne collapsed into the floodwater, vanishing.

A Helena le dolía tanto que su mente no dejaba de intercambiarse con la de Soren en busca de alguna escapatoria.

The entire fight had not even lasted a full minute.

Los necrómatas lo tenían acorralado.

In the chaos, no one else had noticed.

Había acabado con las quimeras, pero eran demasiados necrómatas, decenas de muertos que lo empujaban corriente abajo y lo estaban despedazando.

Helena tried to breathe in but choked from the pressure inside her lungs.

Uno le clavó los dientes en la pierna y le arrancó el tendón a la altura de la rodilla.

She pressed her arm against the wound, trying to prevent more air from seeping into her chest cavity.

Aun así, seguía luchando.

The necrothralls began to drop.

Aunque había perdido la guadaña, conservaba todavía un cuchillo.

A few Aspirants noticed the newcomer and seemed confused about what had happened.

Penny gritaba tras él, pero Alister la retenía.

Before they could react, they were dead.

Soren continuaba apuñalando, rompiendo y abriéndose paso a puñetazos; estaba siguiendo la orden de no dejar de luchar, a pesar de que lo estaban destrozando.

A weapon gleamed so quick that she barely saw it, just watched the bodies fall.

Unos dedos cadavéricos le tantearon la cara hasta encontrar el ojo que le quedaba.

It was Kaine.

Después, le desencajaron la mandíbula y le dejaron la garganta a la vista.

She’d never seen him fight.

Helena se estremecía de forma inconsciente cada vez que le arrancaban una parte del cuerpo, pero el dolor no cedía.

He’d never really fought with her.

No sentía los dedos, no eran más que un faro de agonía que se extendía por los brazos.

But she knew.

Notó que le caía un chorro de sangre por el costado.

There was no mistaking that brutal efficiency.

Creyó que Basilius volvería a apuñalarla, pero el inmarcesible soltó el cuchillo y pasó los dedos por la herida del costado.

He was as deadly as she’d imagined.

Helena notó el escozor en la piel sensible.

She could see the techniques he’d tried to drill into her, the fluidity that she’d lacked, how quick he was.

Entonces recorrió la puñalada que tenía entre las costillas y, sin previo aviso, introdujo dos dedos en la herida.

No movement wasted.

Helena gritó al sentir que abría la piel y le doblaba los huesos desde dentro.

The momentum of one kill led to the next.

Tenía los dedos empapados con su sangre.

Bodies fell like stars.

—¿Sabes qué?

He stalked through the water towards Helena.

No hay nada que me guste más que una herida —dijo sin aliento—.

Not a step wavering, cutting down everything that crossed his path.

Están húmedas y calientes, más que cualquier otra cosa.

When a chimaera leapt at him, he lifted his hand, and the instant it touched the creature, the body unravelled, limbs sloughing apart as if he’d ripped out all the invisible stitches assembling it.

Helena pataleó y trató de empujarlo con sus manos rotas, y, a pesar de que notó cómo giraban sus huesos destrozados, no sirvió de nada.

One minute a monster, and the next dead in the water.

Gritó y gritó, pero nadie la escuchó, así que le golpeó el pecho con la cabeza hasta que Basilius le agarró la garganta con la mano que tenía libre y presionó el pulgar contra su tráquea para que se callara.

It wasn’t combat, it was slaughter.

Sus pulmones luchaban por encontrar aire.

A numbers game.

—Sí, eso es —comentó con un gemido de aprobación—.

Minimum effort, high return.

No te preocupes, no dejaré que mueras.

It was impossible that he’d ever fought to his full potential before.

Seguirás viva cuando te entregue.

If anyone had ever fought like that, everyone would have known about it.

Bennet estará encantado contigo.

He reached into a pocket, pulling out a fistful of something and flinging it outward.

Estaba a punto de perder el conocimiento.

They looked like shimmering bits of metal, and as they flew, she felt his resonance expand, carrying them.

La vista se le nublaba.

The metal sang through the air, moving like an avian murmuration, and hit like a spray of bullets, tearing through the necrothralls’ skulls.

Ya no encontraba aire para seguir gritando.

Rather than fall, the metal stayed suspended in midair, sweeping back, dripping blood and gore.

Apenas notó que Soren desaparecía de su mente, arrastrado por la corriente; la conexión se disolvió como la sangre en el agua.

Kaine drew his hand up and they came darting back, cutting through more bodies.

—Un grito más.

A flick of his fingers and they shot out again.

Se te da estupend…

When he reached Helena, his eyes were burning with rage behind his mask, glowing bright as molten silver.

De repente, Blackthorne trastabilló y boqueó como si alguien le hubiera vaciado los pulmones.

“You idiot,” he said, and dragged her up out of the water, crushing her hard against his chest.

Sus manos perdieron fuerza y los dedos se resbalaron de su cuello un segundo antes de que él arqueara la espalda.

His resonance in the air grew heavier.

Helena cayó como una losa.

A wave that swept outwards.

El frío gélido la devolvió a la realidad; de no haber sido así, se habría ahogado.

She watched it hit the nearest necrothralls and Aspirants.

Se acurrucó en el suelo y buscó con la mirada aterrorizada a Blackthorne.

They began jerking and seizing, dropping into the water.

Vio que alguien lo arrastraba por el agua con un cable o una soga alrededor del cuello.

The necrothralls crumpled, while the chimaeras and those living were gasping as if their lungs were being compressed, clawing at their throats.

Pero la persona que lo estaba arrastrando no era miembro de la Resistencia.

Helena could still breathe, although laboriously, but everyone around her was suffocating.

Era un inmarcesible, al que reconoció de inmediato por el yelmo y el uniforme negro.

Sebastian was trying to reach Luc but collapsed into the water.

Cuando los dos estuvieron al alcance el uno del otro, Blackthorne ya se había recuperado y se abalanzó contra su atacante.

Luc was tearing gouges down his throat as his face turned blue, eyes bulging.

Había recuperado una espada del agua y la lanzó directa a la cabeza del otro inmarcesible, aunque este consiguió esquivarla.

“Stop it,” she gasped, realising that Kaine was making no distinction between the Undying and the Eternal Flame.

Blackthorne lo intentó una y otra vez.

He was killing everyone. “Stop it!

Atacaba con precisión y se movía con la destreza de un alquimista de combate experto, pero su contrincante siempre lo esquivaba.

You can’t kill them!

No llevaba armas, ni tampoco contratacaba.

Stop!”

Era rápido y ligero, se deslizaba como si estuviera danzando, hasta que Blackthorne cometió un error.

She tried to wrench away as Luc’s eyes rolled back and he slumped in the water.

Fue solo un instante, pero el atacante no necesitó más.

The invisible wave reached the walls.

El recién llegado evitó un golpe y, empleando sus propias manos, atravesó la armadura y el pecho de Basilius como si estuviera sumergiéndose en el agua.

Penny collapsed.

Una mano pálida de largos dedos y manchada de sangre extrajo un fragmento de metal resplandeciente de la caja torácica de Blackthorne.

Alister followed.

El hombre se derrumbó en el agua y desapareció.

The struggle was coming to an end.

La pelea no había durado ni un minuto.

“Stop.

En pleno caos, nadie más se había percatado.

Stop!

Helena intentó respirar, pero una presión insoportable en sus pulmones se lo impedía.

Stop!” She fought to get free. “Stop!”

Pegó el brazo contra la herida para evitar que se le escapara más aire de la caja torácica.

“Shut up,” he snarled through his helmet, letting go of her. “Wait here.”

Los necrómatas empezaron a desplomarse.

He stormed over to Sebastian and Luc, Penny and Alister and even Wagner, although she hardly cared if he died.

Unos cuantos aspirantes vieron al recién llegado, confundidos, sin entender qué estaba sucediendo.

He placed a hand on their chests, and one at the back of their heads, and she watched them jerk and start breathing again without regaining consciousness.

Antes de que pudieran reaccionar, estaban todos muertos.

She tried to stand up, but her legs wouldn’t hold her.

El arma relució tan deprisa que Helena apenas la vio; solo contempló cómo cayeron todos los cuerpos.

By the time Kaine was coming to her again, everything was swaying.

Era Kaine.

He dragged her to the far wall, where several tunnels disappeared into darkness.

Nunca lo había visto combatir, porque nunca había querido luchar con ella.

“Can’t leave them,” she rasped, trying to pull free.

Pero lo reconoció al instante.

“Shut up.” The water was only to their ankles, and there was a ladder leading up to a walkway that was shoulder height.

Esa precisión implacable era inconfundible.

“You can’t leave them,” she said, struggling. “Bring them, or I won’t go.”

Era tan letal como imaginaba.

He turned without a word and went back, kicking most of the necrothralls into the current, but pausing beside a few dead Aspirants and reanimating them.

Helena vio en directo las técnicas que había tratado de enseñarle una y otra vez, la fluidez de la que ella carecía, lo rápido que era.

They crawled to their feet and began helping to carry Luc and the others over and shoving them up onto the walkway while Kaine lifted her as gently as he could.

No desperdiciaba ni un solo movimiento.

She nearly bit through her lip at the pressure on her ribs.

El impulso de un asesinato lo conducía al siguiente.

His palms were red with her blood, but he said nothing as he swung up the ladder and scooped her up again.

Los cuerpos caían como estrellas fugaces.

The necrothralls hauled the rest of the rescue team up over their shoulders and followed.

Se abrió paso por el agua en busca de Helena.

Helena faded in and out of consciousness in the dark, briefly coming to as she heard the sound of grinding metal and a loud roar of rushing, rising water coming from the flood cathedral before they continued on.

No dudó ni un momento, se limitó a aniquilar todo lo que se interpuso en su camino.

Kaine stopped walking and kicked the wall.

Cuando se le echó encima una quimera, levantó la mano y, al tocarla, su cuerpo se descompuso.

A door almost invisible along the endless passages swung open.

Las extremidades se desprendieron como si le hubiera descosido las suturas invisibles que la mantenían unida.

He carried her into a small room.

Lo que un segundo antes era un monstruo ahora era un cadáver en el agua.

There was a table against one wall, and he laid her on it.

No era un combate, sino una masacre.

He turned away, shoving the door closed, and reached up to rip off his helmet.

Una cuestión de números: mínimo esfuerzo, máxima eficacia.

His face was twisted with fury.

Era imposible que alguien lo hubiera visto luchar así antes.

“Tell me you can last long enough for me to get a doctor.” His voice was shaking.

Si alguien lo hubiera presenciado, todo el mundo lo sabría.

She shook her head.

Metió una mano en el bolsillo y sacó un puñado de fragmentos metálicos.

He was breathing fast, but he swallowed. “Then you’ll have to tell me how.

Los lanzó por los aires.

Can you still do that?”

Al salir despedidos, Helena sintió cómo expandían la resonancia de Kaine.

“All right,” she said unsteadily, even though she wanted to pass out more than anything. “The first is—my liver.

La metralla surcó los aires moviéndose como una bandada de pájaros al unísono y acertó como si fuera una descarga de balas.

It’s where the blood is coming from.

Cada trozo de metal atravesó el cráneo de un necrómata.

I think.

En vez de caer, el metal permaneció suspendido en el aire, goteando sangre y vísceras.

There’s air—in my chest, collapsing my lung.

Kaine hizo un gesto con la mano y todos los trozos se ponían de nuevo en movimiento para atravesar más cuerpos.

After—after you—fix my liver, you can—stimulate blood generation.

Cada vez que chasqueaba los dedos, volvían a dispararse.

I don’t have the tonic, but you should be able to manage some.”

Cuando Kaine alcanzó a Helena, tenía los ojos ardientes de rabia.

He unbuckled the straps on her satchel and cut away her soaking clothes so he had clear access to the wound between her ribs that had been ripped wide.

Le brillaban como si fuera plata derretida detrás de la máscara.

She flinched, trying not to recoil as he staunched the bleeding.

—Valiente idiota estás hecha —le espetó, pero la sacó del agua sosteniéndola contra su pecho.

He listened carefully as she described what he needed to sense to identify and repair biliary ducts.

Su resonancia espesó el ambiente como una ola que se extendía hacia fuera.

Without her hands working, without resonance, it was like instructing the blind.

Helena contempló cómo atacaba a los necrómatas y a los aspirantes más cercanos.

“Shut up,” he told her when she apologised for not being sure of what was wrong.

Estos últimos empezaron a retorcerse y convulsionar, hasta que acabaron cayendo al agua.

He reached into his cloak, pulling something out. “This one’s for blood, right?

Los necrómatas se desplomaron, mientras que las quimeras y los que quedaban vivos boqueaban como si les faltara el aire, arañándose frenéticamente las gargantas.

Does it work for you?”

Helena aún podía respirar, aunque le costara, pero los demás se estaban ahogando.

He held up a familiar green-blue vial.

Sebastian se derrumbó en el agua antes de llegar a Luc, que se clavaba los dedos en la garganta, con el rostro azulado y los ojos desorbitados.

Her throat tightened and she nodded. “Yes.

—Para —jadeó Helena al darse cuenta de que Kaine no distinguía entre los inmarcesibles y la Llama Eterna.

That works for me.”

Estaba matando a todo el mundo—.

The process of siphoning the air collapsing her lung was difficult because she didn’t have the supplies for it.

¡Para!

She swallowed hard. “There’s a tube in my satchel.”

¡No los mates!

He found it, and she gingerly indicated where to numb and puncture, giving only a small whimpering gasp as it sank through the tissue and into her chest cavity.

¡Detente!

She swallowed, staring up at the ceiling overhead, able to think more clearly as breathing grew easier. “You need to look for damage to the lung tissue next, then you wash the wound and close the diaphragmatic muscle and—”

Se removió con esfuerzo para liberarse en cuanto vio que Luc ponía los ojos en blanco y se desplomaba en el agua.

His fingers brushed near the wound, and her mind stalled, careening violently.

La ola invisible alcanzó los muros.

“Don’t—don’t touch it!” The words came out a strangled scream.

Penny cayó, al igual que Alister.

She almost fell off the table, trying to get away.

La lucha había terminado.

He snatched his hand back as she collapsed and lay there, drawing sharp laboured breaths as she tried to calm down, choking back panicked sobs.

—¡Para, para, para! —Volvió a resistirse para que Kaine la soltara—.

Her heart was pounding so hard, she could feel it in her temples.

¡Para!

“He was going to—going to—” She tripped over her own tongue, trying to protectively cradle that side of her body.

—Cállate —le espetó Kaine a través del yelmo, aunque acabó soltándola—.

Keep it from being touched.

Espera aquí.

“He’s gone.” Kaine’s expression was pulled taut, a forced flatness to his entire demeanour. “He won’t ever come back.

Se acercó a ver a Sebastian y Luc, a Penny y a Alister, incluso a Wagner, aunque a Helena le importaba poco si moría o no.

Should I just cover the wound and fix your hands instead?”

Kaine les posó una mano en el pecho y otra en la nuca y, acto seguido, Helena comprobó que se movían y volvían a respirar, aunque no recobraron el conocimiento.

She shook her head. “No.

Helena intentó ponerse en pie, pero las piernas le fallaron.

I’ll stay still.

Cuando Kaine volvió a su lado, estaba empezando a marearse.

Just—” She swallowed. “Sorry.”

Kaine la arrastró hasta la pared, donde varios túneles se adentraban en la oscuridad.

The muscle in his jaw set.

—No puedes dejarlos aquí —dijo Helena con voz rasposa, intentando zafarse.

As he worked, he began telling her each time he was about to touch her, what he was about to do, his voice low, calm, and she realised he was imitating the way she used to narrate her treatment of the array.

—Cállate. —El agua apenas les llegaba a los tobillos, y ante ellos había una escalera que conducía a una pasarela que estaba a la altura del hombro.

It was the simplest part of the procedure, but she wanted to throw up because she was so sick with terror.

—No puedes dejarlos aquí —repitió ella revolviéndose—.

“There.”

Tráelos o no me iré.

The immediate danger had passed.

Kaine se giró sin pronunciar palabra.

Kaine also seemed to finally breathe.

Por el camino, empujó a los necrómatas a patadas para que se los llevara la corriente, pero se detuvo junto a unos aspirantes muertos para reanimarlos.

“Why were you there?” he finally asked.

Estos se pusieron en pie y lo ayudaron a cargar a Luc y a los demás hasta la pasarela.

She stared at him for a moment and then looked away. “The Council was going to do whatever it took to get Luc back.”

Con sumo cuidado, Kaine se encargó de llevar a Helena en brazos.

“You aren’t experienced in combat,” he said.

Ella se mordía el labio con tanta fuerza que estuvo a punto de hacerse sangre por el dolor intenso que sentía en las costillas.

His hands trembled as he wiped blood off her face. “Why would they bring you without even giving you a partner.”

Kaine tenía las manos rojas de la sangre, pero no dijo nada mientras subía la escalera y la dejaba en la parte de arriba.

“I had a partner,” she said. “She died in the fight.”

Los necrómatas se echaron al hombro al resto del equipo y lo siguieron.

“Who?”

En la oscuridad, Helena perdió y recuperó el conocimiento varias veces, y se despertó cuando oyó un chirrido de metal y el rugido estrepitoso del agua que provenía de los tanques de inundación.

“Purnell.

Siguieron avanzando.

She was an—orderly.”

Kaine se detuvo para darle una patada a la pared.

He glared at her.

Había una puerta prácticamente invisible entre las numerosas pasarelas.

“It had to be a small team; we were supposed to get in and out without being noticed.

Al abrirla, entraron en una sala pequeña.

Sofia and I weren’t supposed to fight.”

Había una mesa contra una de las paredes, y Kaine la dejó allí.

“You knew it was a suicide mission.

Luego se giró, cerró la puerta y se quitó el yelmo de un tirón.

That is what the Bayards do, they die for the Holdfasts.

Tenía el rostro agitado por la rabia.

They know nothing else.”

—Dime que puedes aguantar hasta que encuentre un médico. —Le temblaba la voz.

“Yes, but if Luc dies it’s over, for all of us.

Helena negó con la cabeza.

It was worth it to go.”

Kaine estaba jadeando, pero tragó saliva.

“And if you’d died?” He looked up, his eyes glittering with rage.

—Entonces tendrás que decirme cómo curarte.

“There’s plenty of people to replace me.

¿Puedes hacerlo?

I’ve always been expendable, remember?” She used her elbows to sit up. “I need you to fix my hands now.”

—Sí —respondió con voz trémula, aunque lo único que quería era desmayarse—.

The strain showed around his eyes. “I know.”

Lo primero que hay que arreglar… es el hígado.

She forced herself to inhale. “Start with my left.

De ahí proviene la sangre.

It won’t matter as much if it doesn’t all set right.”

Creo.

He blocked off most of the feeling from her elbow down but left enough that she could sense if he was setting it correctly, working as gently as he could.

Tengo aire… en el pecho, me está colapsando el pulmón.

The broken pieces ground together, sending a sudden pain through her arm into her shoulder, even with most of the sensation gone.

Cuando… cuando arregles… el hígado, podrás… estimular la producción de sangre.

“Good,” she choked out, dropping her head onto his shoulder as she fought back tears.

No tengo el tónico, pero deberías poder hacerlo con resonancia.

He rejoined the bones in her wrists before he worked on her hands directly.

Kaine desanudó las correas de la bolsa y le cortó la ropa empapada para poder acceder directamente a la herida que tenía entre las costillas, que estaba abierta en canal.

He had to physically move several bones back into alignment, twisting the parts that Blackthorne had mangled.

Helena se encogió de dolor, pero trató de no moverse mientras Kaine contenía la hemorragia y escuchaba atentamente sus indicaciones para identificar y reparar los conductos colédocos.

The pain without the adrenaline surge of battle bore into her.

No podía usar las manos ni la resonancia, por lo que era como guiar a un ciego.

She was sobbing into his shoulder by the time he finished aligning the bones and began fusing them.

—Cállate —le espetó cuando se disculpó por no saber exactamente en qué estaba fallando.

Her hand was swollen, purple and red from bruising when he finished.

Metió la mano en el bolsillo de la capa y sacó algo—.

He cradled it in both of his and ran his thumbs across her palm and up to her wrist, his resonance like a balm, repairing the damaged tissue and the broken blood vessels with the sweep of his thumbs, then working along each finger.

Este es para la sangre, ¿no?

He was so gentle.

¿Te servirá?

She recognised the technique.

Sostuvo en alto un frasquito con algo azul verdoso.

She hadn’t realised he’d paid attention.

Helena lo reconoció al instante.

“You could be a healer,” she finally said as he removed the block on her nerves.

Sintió que se le formaba un nudo en la garganta, pero asintió.

She flexed her hand, opening and closing.

—Sí, me sirve.

It was still sore, and fragile as though hairline-fractured. “You have a natural talent for it.”

Aún más difícil fue el proceso de sacar el aire que estaba haciendo presión sobre el pulmón, porque no tenía material para hacerlo.

“That’s one of the most ironic things anyone has ever said to me,” he said quietly.

Tragó saliva con dificultad.

He turned his attention to her other hand.

—Hay un tubo en mi bolsa.

“You can numb it all the way,” she said. “I can use my resonance now.”

Kaine lo encontró, y Helena le indicó con sumo cuidado dónde tenía que anestesiar y hacer la punción.

Working together, it was surprising how quick the process was.

Se le escapó un gemido ahogado cuando hundió el tubo en la piel para introducirlo en la caja torácica.

When he finished, he massaged her hand again, in the same way he had with the first.

Helena tragó saliva y contempló el techo que había sobre ellos.

“Don’t ever go on another mission,” he said without looking up, her hand trapped in his.

Conforme respiraba con más normalidad, su mente empezaba a despejarse.

She looked away, drawing a deep breath.

—Ahora tienes que comprobar si el tejido pulmonar ha sufrido algún daño.

“That’s not your call,” she said, slipping her hand free and standing.

Después, hay que lavar la herida y cerrar el músculo del diafragma, y…

The room swam.

Los dedos de Kaine pasaron junto a la herida y Helena se paralizó de inmediato.

She was dangerously lightheaded.

Acto seguido, se apartó con violencia.

She didn’t have a saline drip or the plasma expanders that would be on hand in the hospital.

—¡No… no la toques! —pronunció en un grito estrangulado, casi cayéndose de la mesa.

Tonic or not, she didn’t physically have the resources needed to regenerate all the blood she’d lost.

Kaine retiró la mano y se quedó observándola.

She pulled her satchel gingerly over her head, trying to be gentle with her hands as she prepared to leave.

Helena empezó a jadear, intentando controlar la respiración, aunque a veces se le escapaba algún que otro sollozo.

They’d never said goodbye before, and she didn’t see any point in starting now.

El corazón le latía tan fuerte que lo sentía retumbar en las sienes.

He blocked the door, his eyes gone cold. “Remind Crowther that if the Eternal Flame wants my continued assistance, they will keep you alive.”

—Blackthorne iba a… iba a… —Se le trabó la lengua y, siguiendo un instinto protector, intentó cubrirse la herida para que nadie la tocara.

His eyes had that cold silver gleam in them as he stared at her.

—Está muerto —dijo Kaine, que mantenía un semblante inexpresivo, con una calma deliberada—.

Her heart wavered for a moment and then turned to lead.

No va a volver.

He’d been quite clear about what she was, how he regarded her, and how much he hated her for having any hold on him.

¿Quieres que te tape la herida y te arregle las manos?

This concern, this obsession with her preservation, wasn’t about her at all.

Helena negó con la cabeza.

It was about his mother, Enid Ferron, and his failure to save her.

—No, me quedaré quieta.

To him, Helena was an opportunity to try to get it right.

Solo… —Tragó saliva—.

A consolation prize he didn’t even want but couldn’t bring himself to give up on.

Lo siento.

No wonder Crowther had been so pleased.

El chico apretó la mandíbula.

Well done, Marino.

Al reanudar la sanación, le advirtió cada vez que la tocaba y le explicaba lo que iba a hacer con voz grave y tranquila.

She knew she was supposed to accept that, but she couldn’t bear it anymore. “You’re doing this for your mother, Kaine.

Helena cayó en la cuenta de que estaba imitando lo que ella misma hizo cuando trató el sello de su espalda.

Would you really give that up because of me?”

Era la parte más sencilla de la sanación, pero Helena solo quería vomitar del miedo que sentía.

She knew that would anger him: to outright insinuate that what he felt towards her was in any way comparable to his feelings for his mother.

—Ya.

He would make a point of proving her wrong.

El peligro más inmediato había pasado.

He went very still.

Kaine también pareció respirar de nuevo.

She stepped around him, reaching for the door, but he caught her shoulders, turning her back, the expression on his face stark.

—¿Por qué has venido? —le preguntó entonces.

“She’s dead,” he said. “You are not.

Lo miró a los ojos un instante y luego apartó la mirada.

My loyalty was to those least responsible for her suffering, but if the Eternal Flame has decided that you are an affordable casualty, I will not be noble or understanding.

—El Consejo estaba dispuesto a hacer cualquier cosa por recuperar a Luc.

I can exact dual revenge.

—No tienes experiencia de combate —insistió Kaine.

I will make them pay if they get you killed.”

Le temblaban las manos mientras se limpiaba la sangre de la cara—.

She stared at him, startled.

¿Por qué te han traído sin asignarte un compañero?

She hadn’t accounted for this.

—Tenía una compañera —respondió Helena—.

She knew Kaine wasn’t a spy because of any ideological reasoning; it was purely a sense of personal interest.

Murió en combate.

He hated the Holdfasts and the Eternal Flame but he hated Morrough and the Undying more.

—¿Quién?

That fact was immutable.

—Purnell.

The source of all his motivation.

Era… camillera.

But now, because of a careless comment from her, he was re-evaluating whether the Eternal Flame served his interests.

Kaine la fulminó con la mirada.

She swallowed hard.

—Tenía que ser un equipo reducido.

She should be cold.

Debíamos entrar y salir sin que nadie se diera cuenta.

She should remind him that she would always put the Eternal Flame’s interests first.

Sofia y yo no íbamos a luchar.

If he expected more than that, he would have to wait.

—Sabíais que era una misión suicida.

And earn it.

Eso es lo que hacen los Bayard, morir por los Holdfast.

She looked up at him, willing the words to form, but they stayed trapped in her throat.

No conocen nada más.

She was so tired.

—Sí, pero, si Luc muere, será el fin para los demás.

Life had been cold for such a long time.

Merecía la pena intentarlo.

The others are hurt.

—¿Y si hubieras muerto tú? —La miró con los ojos brillantes de rabia.

You don’t even know what’s been done to Luc, and you’re wasting your time here.

—Otros podrían reemplazarme.

She flexed her hands, feeling the new tissue, focusing on it as she attempted to pull away. “I have to go.” Her voice shook.

Siempre he sido prescindible, ¿recuerdas? —Se apoyó en los codos para incorporarse—.

He wouldn’t let go.

Necesito que me arregles las manos.

He gripped her tighter. “You are not expendable.

El cansancio se hizo evidente en los ojos de Kaine.

You don’t get to push everyone away so that they’ll feel comfortable using you and letting you die.”

—Lo sé.

She shook her head.

Helena se obligó a respirar hondo.

“This is war,” she said, forcing her voice to stay steady. “It’s not some sort of tragic self-condemnation to be expendable.

—Empieza con la izquierda.

It’s a strategic liability not to be.” She met his eyes. “That was why you picked me, remember?” Her voice broke. “Well, thanks to you, I’m worth less now.

Si no queda bien, no será tan grave.

They added all these new healers after you asked for me.

Le durmió el brazo desde el codo, pero le dejó la suficiente sensibilidad para que pudiera advertir si lo estaba haciendo bien o no.

I had to train all my replacements.” She gave a bitter laugh. “You made me as expendable as I am now.

Kaine fue avanzando con sumo cuidado.

And you didn’t even want me, either.”

Los huesos rotos rechinaron unos contra otros y, a pesar de tener todo el brazo anestesiado, sintió una punzada de dolor que le llegó hasta el hombro.

He flinched, his grip loosening enough that she pulled free, turning again.

—Muy bien —consiguió decir.

He caught the door as she opened it, shoving it closed.

Dejó caer la cabeza contra su hombro y trató de contener las lágrimas.

“You are not replaceable,” he said, his hands trembling against her shoulders. “You are not required to make your death convenient.

Kaine le unió los huesos de la muñeca y, después, pasó a las manos.

You are allowed to be important to people.

Tuvo que recolocar manualmente algunos huesos y mover las partes que Blackthorne había destrozado.

The reason I’m here—the reason I’m doing any of this—is to keep you alive.

Sin la adrenalina del combate, el dolor la estaba consumiendo.

To keep you safe.

Cuando terminó de recolocarle los huesos y empezó a soldarlos, Helena estaba llorando sobre su hombro.

That was the deal.” He searched her face. “They didn’t tell you.”

Al acabar, tenía la mano hinchada y amoratada.

She shook her head, giving a broken sob and—before she let herself think—she kissed him.

Kaine la sostuvo entre las suyas y recorrió con el pulgar toda la palma hasta la muñeca; su resonancia fue como un bálsamo que iba reparando el tejido dañado y las venas partidas.

Después pasó a los dedos, siendo muy cuidadoso en todo momento.

Helena reconoció la técnica, aunque no creyó que le hubiera prestado atención.

—Podrías ser sanador —comentó cuando recuperó la sensibilidad en los nervios.

Abrió y cerró la mano.

Le seguía doliendo; la sentía frágil como si tuviera pequeñas fracturas—.

Tienes un talento natural.

—Una de las grandes ironías de la vida —repuso él en voz baja.

Pasó a la otra mano.

—Es mejor que la anestesies por completo —le explicó—.

Ya puedo usar mi resonancia.

Trabajaron juntos.

Helena se sorprendió de lo rápido que lo hicieron.

Cuando terminó, Kaine le masajeó la mano de la misma forma que había hecho con la otra.

—No vuelvas a participar en ninguna misión —ordenó sin levantar la vista, con la mano de Helena entre las suyas.

La chica apartó la mirada y respiró hondo.

—Eso no lo decides tú —replicó.

Acto seguido, retiró la mano y se puso en pie.

Todo le dio vueltas.

Estaba demasiado mareada.

No tenía suero fisiológico ni expansores de plasma, como en el hospital.

Aunque hubiera tomado el tónico, no contaba con los recursos físicos necesarios para regenerar toda la sangre que había perdido.

Se pasó la bolsa por encima de la cabeza, con cuidado de no dañarse las manos, y se preparó para irse.

Nunca se habían despedido, así que no vio motivo para empezar a hacerlo ahora.

Kaine se interpuso delante de la puerta; sus ojos se habían tornado gélidos.

—Recuérdale a Crowther que, si la Llama Eterna quiere que siga cooperando, tienen que mantenerte con vida.

La miró fijamente con ese brillo plateado y frío en los ojos.

A Helena le dio un vuelco el corazón, pero después se giró para marcharse.

Kaine le había dejado muy claro lo que era para él y lo mucho que la odiaba por tenerlo esclavo de esa forma.

Esta preocupación, esta obsesión por mantenerla con vida, no era por ella.

Era por su madre, Enid Ferron, por no haber sido capaz de salvarla.

Para él, Helena era la oportunidad de hacer bien las cosas.

Un premio de consolación que ni siquiera quería, pero del que no podía prescindir.

No le extrañaba que Crowther se hubiese mostrado tan satisfecho. «Buen trabajo, Marino».

—Todo esto lo estás haciendo por tu madre, Kaine.

¿De verdad vas a rendirte por mí?

Sabía que eso lo enfurecería: insinuar que lo que sentía por ella se parecía, si quiera un poco, a lo que había sentido por su madre.

Seguramente le dejaría claro cuánto se equivocaba.

Kaine se quedó totalmente quieto.

Ella lo rodeó para salir por la puerta, pero Kaine la sujetó por los hombros y la hizo girar para mirarla con dureza.

—Mi madre está muerta.

Tú no.

Mi lealtad residía en quienes no habían sido responsables de su sufrimiento, pero, si la Llama Eterna ha decidido que pueden permitir tu muerte, no seré noble ni comprensivo.

Puedo vengarme de ambos bandos.

Si te matan, lo pagarán caro.

Helena lo miró sobrecogida.

No había tenido esto en cuenta.

Sabía que Kaine no era espía por motivos ideológicos; lo hacía por interés propio.

Detestaba a los Holdfast y a la Llama Eterna, pero detestaba aún más a Morrough y a los inmarcesibles.

Eso no había cambiado, era lo que lo movía a seguir.

Sin embargo, después del comentario inconsciente que había hecho, Kaine parecía estar replanteándose si la Llama Eterna seguía sirviendo a sus intereses.

Helena tragó saliva.

Debería mostrarse fría, recordarle que siempre pondría primero los intereses de la Llama Eterna.

Si esperaba algo más que eso, ya podía esperar sentado.

Y ganárselo.

Lo miró, queriendo dar forma a las palabras en su garganta, pero se le quedaron atascadas.

Estaba muy cansada.

La vida había sido muy fría durante demasiado tiempo.

«Los demás están heridos.

Ni siquiera sabes lo que le han hecho a Luc, y estás aquí perdiendo el tiempo».

Flexionó las manos y sintió los nuevos tejidos.

Se centró en eso para ser capaz de alejarse.

—Tengo que irme —afirmó con voz temblorosa.

Pero Kaine no la dejó marchar.

De hecho, la sujetó con más fuerza.

—No eres prescindible.

No apartes a todo el mundo solo para que les resulte más fácil usarte y dejarte morir.

Helena negó con la cabeza.

—Estamos en guerra —dijo esforzándose por mantener un tono firme—.

Ser prescindible no es una tragedia que me autoimponga.

Si no lo eres, te conviertes en un lastre para la causa. —Lo miró a los ojos—.

Por eso me elegiste, ¿recuerdas? —Se le rompió la voz—.

Pues gracias a ti ahora valgo menos.

Como tú me necesitabas a tu lado, contrataron a otras sanadoras.

He tenido que formar a las chicas que me van a sustituir. —Se le escapó una carcajada amarga—.

Tú eres el que me ha convertido en prescindible.

Y encima ni siquiera quieres estar conmigo.

Kaine torció el gesto y se relajó apenas lo justo para que Helena intentara marcharse de nuevo.

Pero, en cuanto abrió la puerta, él la cerró de golpe.

—No eres prescindible —repitió.

Helena notó que le temblaban las manos—.

No hagas que tu muerte tenga sentido porque te han convencido de ello.

Tienes derecho a ser importante para los demás.

Estoy aquí y hago todo esto porque quiero que sigas con vida.

Quiero mantenerte a salvo.

Ese era el trato. —Buscó en su rostro—.

No te lo dijeron, ¿verdad?

Helena sacudió la cabeza y dejó escapar un sollozo.

Acto seguido, sin pensarlo dos veces, lo besó.

CHAPTER 51

Aprilis 1787

CAPÍTULO 51

KAINE CRADLED HER FACE IN HIS HANDS as he returned her kiss, pulling her closer, his arms wrapping around her.

Abrilis 1787

She was half crying as she kissed him, tracing her fingers along his face and under the curve of his jaw, trying to memorise every detail: his pulse under her fingertips, his lips pressed against hers.

Kaine le sostuvo la cara entre las manos para devolverle el beso.

The taste of him.

La atrajo hacia sí y la rodeó con los brazos.

Her eyes fluttered shut, trying to savour it all.

Helena aún seguía llorando mientras lo besaba, mientras recorría con los dedos el contorno de su rostro y la curva de su mandíbula.

This one moment.

Quiso memorizar todos los detalles: su pulso, que latía bajo las yemas de los dedos; sus labios, presionados contra los suyos; su sabor.

She could have this.

Cerró los ojos para asimilarlo todo.

She’d earned it.

Ese momento.

Then, all too soon, she forced herself to step back, pulling away. “I have to take care of the others.”

Al menos le quedaría esto.

He didn’t try to stop her again, but the rest of the team wasn’t outside the door as she’d expected; Kaine’s necrothralls had moved them deeper.

Se lo había ganado.

Her fingers trembled as she checked for pulses.

Entonces, de repente, se obligó a dar un paso atrás y se separó de él.

They were still alive, although Luc’s skin almost burned to touch.

—Tengo que atender a los demás.

“How do we get out?” she asked as she started checking for injuries, trying to work out how hurt everyone was, how much work it would take to get them conscious and moving.

Esta vez no intentó detenerla.

“Down this tunnel.

Pero al salir no encontró al resto del equipo como esperaba.

Go right, then right again, and then straight.

Los necrómatas los habían trasladado a un rincón más apartado.

There’s an upper floodgate in the far north.”

A Helena le temblaron los dedos cuando comprobó si tenían pulso.

“Where they released the chimaera?” She remembered the place.

Seguían vivos, aunque Luc ardía de fiebre.

“You’ll have to break it down, but it’ll get you out.”

—¿Cómo salimos de aquí? —preguntó mientras revisaba las lesiones.

She nodded. “You have to go before I wake them.”

Intentó identificar cuán graves estaban sus compañeros y cuánto le costaría devolverles la consciencia y ponerlos en marcha.

“I know,” he said, but he didn’t leave, lingering until she looked up.

—Por este túnel.

His eyes shone in the dark, as if there were moonlight underground.

Girad a la derecha, luego otra vez a la derecha y después todo recto.

He touched her cheek, tilting her face up and kissing her. “Use the ring, call me, if you ever need anything.”

Hay unas compuertas en la parte norte.

She wanted to say she would, but she couldn’t bring herself to.

—¿Donde soltaron a la quimera? —Recordaba ese sitio.

He was a spy that they depended on.

—Tendréis que echarlas abajo, pero podéis salir por ahí.

And she was—

Helena asintió.

Not his handler.

—Tienes que irte antes de que los despierte.

No, that role belonged to Crowther.

—Lo sé —afirmó, pero no se movió.

She was—

Se quedó allí, inmóvil, hasta que Helena alzó la vista para mirarlo.

A prison.

Sus ojos brillaban en la oscuridad, como si la luz de la luna se colara bajo la tierra.

“Go,” she said instead.

Le tocó la mejilla, le alzó la barbilla y la besó con suavidad—.

He disappeared down one of the tunnels, his necrothralls following him, as silent as wraiths.

Usa el anillo, llámame si me necesitas.

She woke Sebastian first, hoping that he’d be calm and easier to manage.

La chica quiso decir que lo haría, pero no consiguió hacerlo.

He’d also know what to do.

Kaine era el espía del que dependían.

She searched what supplies they had.

Y ella era…

She’d lost both her daggers, and everything in her satchel was contaminated with floodwater.

No era su carcelera.

Only one of the electric torches still worked, providing dim light in the darkness.

No, ese papel le correspondía a Crowther.

When he woke, Sebastian just sat silently staring at Luc’s still face while she gingerly fixed his dislocated shoulder and several shallow wounds that had already stopped bleeding on their own.

Ella era…

Finally, he looked at her.

Una prisión.

“What happened?”

—Vete —le instó en su lugar.

She shook her head. “I don’t know.

Kaine desapareció por uno de los túneles, seguido por sus necrómatas, silenciosos como espectros.

Everything went black.

Primero, despertó a Sebastian, ya que pensó que mantendría la calma y sería más fácil de manejar.

When I woke, you were all unconscious.

También sabría qué hacer.

I was afraid more of the Undying would show up, so I brought everyone here.”

Buscó entre los suministros que les quedaban.

His eyes swept pointedly over her. “Helena, I know you used necromancy.

Helena había perdido las dos dagas y todo lo que tenía en la bolsa estaba contaminado de aguas residuales.

There’s no chance you moved us all here on your own.”

Solo seguía funcionando una de las antorchas, que proyectaba una débil luz en la oscuridad.

She started to shake her head in denial.

Cuando despertó, Sebastian se incorporó en silencio y contempló la cara inerte de Luc mientras ella le recolocaba el hombro y curaba algunas heridas superficiales, que habían dejado de sangrar por el tiempo.

“You reanimated Soren.

Después, la miró.

There was no surviving the blow he took.”

—¿Qué ha pasado?

She went still.

Helena negó con la cabeza.

She didn’t know if it would be better or worse to tell Sebastian that Soren had asked her to.

—No lo sé.

“That was why he brought you, wasn’t it?

Perdí el conocimiento y, cuando desperté, todos estabais inconscientes.

I did wonder.”

Me daba miedo que aparecieran más inmarcesibles, así que os traje a todos aquí.

Helena said nothing.

Sebastian le lanzó una mirada acusatoria.

Soren’s death felt like a wound too deep to even wrap her mind around.

—Helena, sé que usaste la nigromancia.

She didn’t think she could even say his name without choking.

Es imposible que nos trajeras tú sola a todos.

“Is he still—nearby?” Sebastian’s voice was wistful.

La chica comenzó a negarlo.

Helena’s throat ached. “No.

—Reanimaste a Soren.

He—he’s gone.

Jamás habría sobrevivido a ese hachazo.

I’m sorry.”

Helena se quedó inmóvil.

There would be no holy fire to liberate Soren’s soul from his body.

No sabía si decirle que había sido Soren quien se lo pidió o si eso empeoraría las cosas.

Somewhere downriver, he would decay into the earth.

—Por eso te trajo, ¿verdad?

Lila would never see her twin again.

Ya me lo imaginaba.

Not even in the afterlife.

Ella no respondió.

Sebastian said nothing for a long moment. “We’ll tell the others we brought them here together.”

La muerte de Soren era una herida demasiado reciente para asimilarla aún.

There was blood crusted around Alister’s eyes, ears, and nose from the strain of all the transmutation he’d done.

No se sentía con fuerzas ni para pronunciar su nombre sin echarse a llorar.

She woke him slowly, but he seized into consciousness, clawing at his neck, his eyes wild as they locked on Helena.

—¿Sigue… por aquí? —La voz de Sebastian sonó esperanzadora.

“What happened?” he gasped.

Helena sintió que se le formaba un nudo en la garganta.

“We’re not sure,” Sebastian said, leaning over him. “Are you all right?

—No, ya… ya no está.

We need to move before we freeze.

Lo siento.

Luc’s sick.”

No habría fuego sagrado que liberara el alma de Soren de su cuerpo.

“Where’s Soren?”

En algún punto del río, se descompondría en la tierra, atrapado para siempre.

“Killed in combat,” Sebastian said shortly. “Marino, can you get Penny up?”

Lila jamás volvería a ver a su hermano.

Penny’s leg was wrecked, the tendons ripped out with teeth.

Ni siquiera en la otra vida.

There was no saving it.

Sebastian permaneció en silencio durante un largo rato.

Helena blocked the nerves and fused the bone so she could limp on it.

—A los demás les diremos que los trajimos aquí entre los dos.

Penny didn’t even cry when she woke, just scrubbed at her face and struggled to her feet.

Alister tenía sangre seca en las comisuras de los ojos, las orejas y la nariz, por haber abusado de la transmutación.

Wagner was unscathed.

Lo despertó con cuidado, pero, en cuanto recobró la consciencia, se llevó las manos al cuello e intentó arañárselo.

Of course he was.

Miró a Helena con los ojos desorbitados.

Coward.

—¿Qué ha pasado? —preguntó entre bocanadas de aire.

At least she didn’t have to waste any of her energy healing him.

—No lo sabemos —respondió Sebastian inclinándose sobre él—.

Helena tried to wake Luc.

¿Te encuentras bien?

His fever was searing.

Tenemos que ponernos en marcha antes de que nos quedemos congelados.

He’d somehow gotten hotter in the minutes after she’d left him.

Luc está muy mal.

She tried to cool him, but his body kept fighting it, pushing the fever higher and higher.

—¿Dónde está Soren?

She’d drugged him too much.

—Murió en combate —se limitó a decir Sebastian—.

When he regained consciousness, he screamed.

Marino, ¿puedes despertar a Penny?

The noise reverberated through the tunnels.

Penny tenía la pierna destrozada; le habían arrancado los tendones a mordiscos.

“Knock him out!” Sebastian said, lunging forward. “Keep him cold.

No había forma de salvar la extremidad.

We’ll carry him back.”

Helena anestesió los nervios y soldó el hueso para que al menos pudiese apoyarla.

It was fortunate they could smell clean air ahead, because Helena couldn’t have explained how she knew the route out.

Penny ni siquiera gritó cuando despertó.

Sebastian had an entangled medallion like Helena’s ring.

Se limitó a frotarse los ojos y se incorporó con esfuerzo.

He used it to send a pulse code to Headquarters.

Wagner no tenía ni un rasguño.

A few times, they heard sounds echoing through the tunnels.

Cómo no, el muy cobarde.

Screams.

Al menos, no tendría que gastar energías curándolo.

Roars.

Helena intentó despertar a Luc, cuya fiebre no hacía más que subir.

Splashing.

Aunque parecía imposible, el calor corporal se incrementaba por momentos.

They moved quietly.

Quiso bajarle la temperatura, pero su cuerpo la rechazaba y la fiebre escalaba, imparable.

Helena worried first whether Kaine could have gotten clear and then began to wonder if the reason they did not run into anyone was because he was lurking in the shadows.

Lo había medicado en exceso.

When they reached the locked floodgate, Alister broke through the stone wall to get past it.

Cuando por fin recobró el conocimiento, se puso a gritar, y el sonido de los gritos reverberó por los túneles.

A torrent of icy water rushed by.

—¡Déjalo inconsciente! —exclamó Sebastian acercándose—.

They struggled through, fighting to find stable footing as they clambered out.

Mantenlo frío.

A dense fog hung in the air, and a slim smuggling boat shot into view, moving silently across the water towards them.

Tendremos que cargar con él.

Sebastian sighed with relief. “Althorne.”

Por suerte, olieron el aire fresco que llegaba desde más adelante, porque Helena no podría haber explicado cómo sabía por dónde debían salir.

General Althorne glared at them from the boat as it pulled to shore.

Sebastian tenía un medallón enredado que funcionaba igual que el anillo de Helena.

His men silently slipped into the water, not even splashing as they came towards the straggling unit.

Lo usó para enviar un código al Cuartel General.

“Where’s Soren?” Althorne asked, his expression hard as Luc was carefully lifted into the boat.

De vez en cuando, oían ecos por los túneles: gritos, rugidos, chapoteos en el agua.

“Killed in combat,” Sebastian said quietly.

Avanzaron en silencio.

One of the men was lifting Penny into the boat.

Helena empezó a preocuparse por si Kaine habría logrado salir sin problemas, y luego por si el único motivo por el que no se encontraban con nadie era porque él los estaba protegiendo entre las sombras.

Alister scrambled aboard himself, smearing away the fresh blood around his eyes with shaking hands, clearly on the verge of burnout.

Cuando llegaron a las compuertas cerradas, Alister abrió un boquete en el muro de piedra.

Althorne looked at Luc, his expression a mixture of concern and relief. “We’ll need to keep him restrained until he’s cleared.”

Al hacerlo, un torrente de agua helada los inundó, pero consiguieron salir a través de la corriente con cuidado, manteniendo el equilibrio mientras trepaban.

Helena gestured towards Wagner. “We found him in a cell.

Una niebla densa los recibió al otro lado, que se apartó ante la aparición de un barco de contrabando de poca eslora.

I think Crowther wants him.

Se dirigía hacia ellos en silencio.

Don’t trust him, he killed Sofia Purnell.”

Sebastian soltó un suspiro de alivio.

Althorne jerked his head, and two of his men came over and seized Wagner’s arms.

—Althorne.

He grumbled but didn’t resist, clearly preferring Resistance captivity to the Undying.

El general Althorne los contempló con dureza mientras el barco echaba el amarre.

“You are all currently in custody for your violation of orders,” Althorne said, once the boat was pushed off.

Sus hombres descendieron al agua y acudieron al rescate del maltrecho grupo sin hacer ruido ni chapotear lo más mínimo.

There was no bite to his words.

—¿Dónde está Soren? —preguntó Althorne con el semblante tenso, vigilando cómo llevaban a Luc al interior del barco.

They’d rescued Luc; any censure for that would be a formality.

—Muerto en combate —respondió Sebastian sin añadir más.

Helena slumped against the side of the boat.

Uno de los hombres cargó en brazos a Penny.

The journey passed in a blur—docking on a concealed wharf, being herded up a staircase and into the back of a lorry.

Alister se subió a bordo por sus propios medios, aunque le temblaban las manos cuando se limpió la sangre fresca de los ojos.

When they arrived at Headquarters, Penny, Alister, and Luc were taken away to the hospital ward.

Estaba a punto de desplomarse.

Wagner was placed in a cell.

Althorne miró a Luc con una expresión que oscilaba entre la preocupación y el alivio.

Helena and Sebastian were checked, cleared of serious injury, and escorted to their rooms to be locked inside with guards stationed at the doors.

—Tendremos que mantenerlo atado hasta que lo examinen.

Helena was glad not to be kept in the hospital, even though she could have used the saline and plasma expanders.

Helena señaló hacia Wagner.

She stripped out of her wet, ruined clothing, hands shaky and trembling, and took a shower, washing away the filth of the tunnels and spring melt.

—Lo encontramos en una celda.

As the traces vanished, she grew eerily removed from what had happened, as though at some point during the battle, she’d left her body and couldn’t return to it.

Creo que Crowther lo estaba buscando.

Back in her room where everything looked familiar, it felt as if it had been a dream.

No te fíes de él, mató a Sofia Purnell.

Soren wasn’t dead.

Althorne asintió y dos de sus hombres se acercaron a apresar a Wagner.

He couldn’t be.

El hombre gruñó, pero no se resistió.

She would go out and see him sitting next to Luc in the hospital.

Era evidente que prefería estar cautivo en manos de la Resistencia.

The memory of him, dead in her arms, felt like a tear in the fabric of her mind, as if the way she’d tethered him back to life had been ripped out when the connection between them broke.

—Estáis todos bajo custodia por haber incumplido órdenes —anunció Althorne en cuanto el barco zarpó.

The person she knew and the body she’d reanimated had been tied together, and now there was a wound left.

No lo dijo con rencor.

He couldn’t be dead.

Habían salvado a Luc; cualquier castigo sería solo una formalidad.

It was a horrible dream.

Helena se dejó caer sobre la cubierta del barco.

She stared down at her hands.

El viaje se sucedió casi sin darse cuenta y, al llegar, amarraron en un muelle escondido y los hicieron subir unas escaleras y entrar en la parte trasera de un camión.

Somehow she’d expected them to be stained or blackened by her necromancy.

Cuando llegaron al Cuartel General, Penny, Alister y Luc fueron llevados directamente al hospital.

What would Sebastian tell the Council?

A Wagner lo metieron en una celda.

He’d have to tell the truth in a report.

Helena y Sebastian fueron examinados y, al confirmar que no tenían ninguna herida grave, los escoltaron a sus habitaciones.

Once the truth came out, there’d be consequences.

Allí los encerraron bajo llave y un par de guardias montaron vigilancia en la puerta.

It would have been a lesser crime to have murdered Soren.

A Helena no le hizo gracia estar confinada en el hospital, aunque allí disponía de suero y expansores de plasma.

Murder was only a mortal crime; necromancy was a crime upon this life and the afterlife.

Con manos temblorosas, se quitó los ropajes mojados y hechos jirones, y se dio una ducha para deshacerse de la suciedad de los túneles y la nieve derretida.

She packed away all her possessions in her trunk and sat waiting.

Cuando desapareció todo rastro de lo vivido, se sintió extrañamente desconectada, como si en algún momento de la batalla hubiera abandonado su cuerpo y no fuese capaz de regresar.

There was a loud banging on the door.

Ahora que volvía a estar en su habitación, le parecía que todo había sido un sueño.

She stood, ready.

Soren no estaba muerto.

“Helena!

Era imposible.

Helena!

Cuando saliera de allí, lo vería en el hospital, sentado al lado de Luc.

There’s something wrong with Luc!” It was Elain outside. “We need you in the hospital!”

Al recordarlo muerto en sus brazos, notó cómo se desgarraba la tela de su mente, como si el hilo que le había devuelto a la vida se hubiese roto en cuanto desapareció la conexión entre ambos.

All thoughts of arrest vanished.

La persona que conocía y el cuerpo que había reanimado estaban tan unidos que su partida le había causado un daño físico.

“What’s wrong?” Helena opened the door, and the guards stepped back to let her out.

No podía estar muerto.

She rushed towards the lifts with Elain.

Había sido una pesadilla.

“We’ve done all the examinations and doubled-checked for talismans, and he’s clear.

Se contempló las manos.

But his organs—they’re all poisoned.

Por algún motivo, esperaba que estuvieran manchadas o sucias por haber usado la nigromancia.

I don’t know what they could have done.

¿Qué diría Sebastian en el Consejo?

We tried reversing the damage, but they won’t regenerate.

Tendría que contar la verdad en su informe.

We were trying to get his fever down and Pace had me wake him, but he started screaming.

En cuanto saliera a la luz, habría consecuencias.

Now he won’t stop, and he doesn’t let anyone near.

Habría cometido un delito menor si hubiera asesinado a Soren.

He’s hurting himself.”

El asesinato se consideraba un crimen mortal, mientras que la nigromancia era un crimen en esta vida y también en la siguiente.

Luc was in a quarantine room at the far end of the hospital.

Helena guardó todas sus pertenencias en su baúl y esperó sentada.

She heard him before she saw him.

Entonces escuchó que alguien llamaba a la puerta.

His eyes were deranged, his face gaunt with scarlet stains in the cheeks.

Se puso en pie, preparada.

There was a ripple of heat coming off him as if he were molten gold.

—¡Helena!

Ilva was standing helplessly in the doorway, along with Althorne, Maier, Pace, and several medics.

¡Helena!

Ilva kept trying to talk to him, but Luc didn’t seem to hear anything.

¡A Luc le pasa algo! —Era Elain la que estaba fuera—.

The screaming faded as his throat stripped itself raw.

¡Te necesitamos en el hospital!

He’d seemingly forgotten how a body worked.

El temor a que la apresaran se esfumó por completo.

He seized, his arms and legs and fingers and head all tilting into bizarre angles, and then he slammed himself into the wall.

—¿Qué ha pasado? —Helena abrió la puerta y los guardias retrocedieron para dejarla salir.

“I brought Helena,” Elain said breathlessly.

Corrió junto a Elain hacia los ascensores.

Luc’s head swivelled.

—Hemos hecho todas las pruebas pertinentes y nos hemos asegurado de que no lleva ningún talismán.

He stared at Helena.

Pero sus órganos… están contaminados.

His eyes seemed to grow, bulging from their sockets, head weaving like a snake.

No sé qué le han hecho.

“Hel—” he croaked.

Hemos intentado revertir los daños, pero no se regeneran.

He reached for her.

Estábamos tratando de bajar la fiebre cuando Pace me pidió que lo despertara, pero entonces empezó a gritar.

His fingers looked broken, but he didn’t seem to notice. “Hel—”

Y ahora no para, ni tampoco deja que nadie se acerque.

“Careful, he’s been violent,” she dimly heard Pace say.

Se está haciendo daño a sí mismo.

She paid no mind.

Luc estaba en una sala de cuarentena al fondo del hospital.

She reached out, laced their fingers together, and touched the side of his face with her knuckles.

Lo escuchó antes de llegar.

His skin was so hot, it almost burned.

Tenía los ojos desorbitados, la cara demacrada y las mejillas llenas de arañazos, cubiertas de sangre.

He somehow bent his fingers, not seeming to notice the pain, clutching her hand, pulling her close.

Irradiaba calor, como si todo él fuese oro derretido.

“I’m here.

Ilva se encontraba en la puerta sin saber qué hacer, junto a Althorne, Maier, Pace y otros médicos.

What’s wrong?” She numbed his hand, setting his fingers quickly.

Aunque Ilva no paraba de hablarle, Luc parecía no escuchar nada.

His eyes had gone out of focus, and he started shuddering. “Out—” he moaned, shaking his head. “Inside—”

Los gritos cesaron cuando se desgarró la garganta hasta dejarla en carne viva.

She pressed her hand against his forehead, ignoring the way his skin scalded her hand, letting her resonance flow into him, trying to find the source of what was wrong.

Era como si hubiera olvidado cómo funcionaba su propio cuerpo.

What was she missing?

Sufrió una convulsión en la que los brazos, las piernas, los dedos y la cabeza se le doblaron en ángulos imposibles y, acto seguido, se lanzó contra la pared.

“Hel—” Luc was saying again.

—He traído a Helena —dijo Elain sin aliento.

Pain exploded through her chest.

Luc giró la cabeza y la miró fijamente.

The world went careening, spinning.

Abrió tanto los ojos que parecía que iban a salírsele de las órbitas.

Vicious red burst across her vision, slamming into the back of her head.

Meneó la cabeza como si fuera una serpiente.

An endless ringing filled her ears.

—Hel… —pronunció como un graznido.

She struggled to focus her eyes.

Estiró la mano hacia ella; parecía que se había roto los dedos, pero no le importaba—.

She couldn’t breathe.

Hel…

She clutched at her chest.

—Ten cuidado, se comporta de forma violenta —escuchó que decía Pace.

Noises were elongated.

No le prestó atención.

Faces loomed over her.

Helena extendió la mano y entrelazó los dedos con los suyos.

Something grabbed her.

Luego le acarició el dorso de la cara con los nudillos.

She gave a panicked scream, going for her knives, but they weren’t there.

Tenía la piel tan caliente que era como si estuviera ardiendo.

She clawed wildly to free herself.

Aun estando rotos, Luc consiguió doblar los dedos, sin percatarse del dolor.

“Calm down, Marino,” Matron Pace was saying. “You’re all right, just a bad scare.

Le agarró la mano y la acercó hacia sí.

Knocked your breath out.”

—Estoy aquí.

The raw terror ebbed.

Dime qué es lo que sucede —dijo mientras le anestesió la mano y le arregló los dedos en un momento.

The room came slowly back into view.

Luc tenía la mirada perdida y había empezado a estremecerse.

She was on the floor, breathing raggedly, pain consuming her chest as she tried to make sense of what had happened.

—Sácalo… —gimió sacudiendo la cabeza—.

Luc was on the other side of the room.

De dentro…

His expression had turned scorchingly lucid.

Helena posó la mano en su frente, ignorando el calor que desprendía su piel, y dejó que la resonancia se introdujera en su cuerpo, buscando el origen del malestar.

“You—” His eyes were suddenly clear and burning. “You used necromancy on Soren.”

¿Qué se le había escapado?

The accusation hung in the air like the lull between lightning and thunder.

—Hel… —dijo Luc de nuevo.

Everyone froze.

De repente, un dolor punzante le atravesó el pecho.

Helena pushed herself upright.

El mundo dio vueltas.

“I’m sorry,” she rasped, struggling to speak.

Todo se tiñó de un rojo sangriento que inundó su cerebro.

Her lungs were seizing for air, sending jolts of pain through her ribs.

Un pitido agudo resonaba en sus oídos.

She knelt and almost doubled over on the floor of the hospital. “I tried to heal him.

Intentó enfocar la vista, pero no podía respirar.

I’m sorry.”

Se llevó la mano al pecho.

“He was alive.

Los sonidos se ralentizaban y las caras a su alrededor se deformaban.

Why didn’t you just heal him?” Luc’s voice was racked with grief.

Sintió que alguien la sujetaba.

She couldn’t breathe enough to explain herself, to describe how quickly Soren was gone, that he’d known he’d die, and that he’d asked her to do it.

Helena soltó un grito de pánico y buscó sus cuchillos, pero no los tenía.

“I’m sorry, Luc.”

Arañó el aire con desesperación para liberarse.

“Get out …” He wasn’t looking at her anymore.

—Tranquila, Marino —le decía la enfermera Pace—.

His gaze lost focus, and he swayed.

Estás bien, solo fue un susto.

“Luc, you’re sick—”

Te has quedado sin respiración.

“Get out!” He closed his eyes, starting to shudder again, his breathing coming faster and faster as if being in the same room with her was about to drive him mad. “Get out!

El miedo la embargó por completo.

Get out!

Pero poco a poco la habitación volvió a su forma natural.

Get out!”

Estaba en el suelo, respirando con dificultad.

He started clawing at his chest, screaming, tearing grooves into his skin as if trying to tear his own heart out.

El dolor del pecho la consumía por dentro, pero intentó darle sentido a lo que había pasado.

“Luc?” another voice broke in.

Luc estaba en la pared opuesta.

Lila stood in the doorway, a crutch under one arm.

De repente, su expresión mostraba una lucidez absoluta.

Rhea was beside her, helping her walk.

—Tú… —Tenía los ojos claros y ardientes—.

The scars on Lila’s face and chest showed vividly where she was stitched together.

Usaste la nigromancia en Soren.

Luc’s eyes shot open at the sound of her voice.

La acusación flotó en el aire como la calma que precede a la tempestad.

“Lila …” he said, his voice both grief-stricken and filled with relief, as if he hadn’t believed she was still alive until that moment.

Todo el mundo se quedó muy quieto.

Several people tried to hold her back, murmurs of Careful, but Lila let go of her mother, reaching desperately towards Luc.

Helena se puso en pie.

She let her crutch fall and toppled into his arms, clinging to him.

—Lo siento —expresó con voz rasgada; le costaba hablar.

“I told you to run,” Lila was saying, clutching him close.

Sus pulmones se esforzaban por respirar, pero le dolían las costillas.

His hands were shaking as he touched the laceration running down her face.

Cayó de rodillas y estuvo a punto de vomitar sobre el suelo del hospital—.

Lila brushed across the gouges he’d clawed in his chest. “What did they do to you?”

Intenté curarlo.

He just shook his head and pulled her closer, burying his head against her shoulder, arms wrapped around her.

Lo siento.

It was painfully intimate.

—Estaba vivo.

If there had been any doubts about whether or why Luc had handed himself over, they were all gone now.

¿Por qué no lo curaste? —La voz de Luc sonaba desgarrada por el dolor.

There was a touch at Helena’s elbow.

No había respirado lo suficiente para explicarse, para describir lo rápido que murió Soren, que incluso él mismo sabía que moriría y le había pedido que lo hiciera.

She looked up and found Ilva, who nodded towards the door.

—Lo siento, Luc.

Helena pushed herself to her feet and slipped out before Luc noticed her again.

—Fuera… —Ya ni siquiera la miraba.

When she passed Rhea, she looked away.

Tenía la mirada perdida y se tambaleaba.

It was Lila who coaxed Luc into bed, who persuaded him to let Pace and Elain examine him again, to accept an intravenous drip in his arm, and take the medicine needed to bring his fever down.

—Luc, estás enfermo…

Helena sat on a hospital bed in the main room, an intravenous drip in her arm, while Elain fixed a fracture in her sternum and spread a salve across the bruise that spanned most of her chest, then treated the back of her head, where she’d hit the far wall.

—¡Fuera! —Cerró los ojos con fuerza y, de nuevo, empezó a temblar.

It wasn’t the first time Helena had been injured by a patient, but it felt different.

Cada vez respiraba más rápido, como si estar en la misma habitación que Helena lo estuviera sacando de quicio—.

Luc was never going to forgive her for what she’d done to Soren.

¡Fuera!

She’d broken him.

¡Fuera!

The curtain around the hospital bed rustled, and Ilva stepped through.

¡Fuera!

Elain lingered until Ilva glared, and then the healer fled.

Empezó a arañarse el pecho entre alaridos, abriendo surcos en la piel como si quisiera arrancarse el corazón con las manos.

Helena closed her shirt and didn’t look up.

—¿Luc? —interrumpió otra voz.

“We’re taking reports on what happened,” Ilva said, her tone unreadable.

Lila estaba en la puerta, apoyada en una muleta, y Rhea a su lado para ayudarla a caminar.

Helena sat numbly.

En la cara y en el pecho se distinguían perfectamente los puntos de sutura de sus cicatrices.

Would they put her on trial now?

Luc abrió los ojos con asombro al escucharla.

Or would it wait until after the war?

—Lila… —susurró, con la voz rota por el dolor y un alivio profundo, como si hasta ese momento no hubiera creído que ella siguiera viva.

“What have you heard?” she asked in a dull voice.

Algunos intentaron detenerla, advirtiéndole en voz baja que tuviera cuidado, pero Lila se separó de su madre y corrió hacia Luc desesperada.

Ilva cleared her throat. “Luc is delirious, his version of events hardly reliable given that he was not only severely injured but also heavily drugged.

En cuanto soltó la muleta, se dejó caer en sus brazos, apoyándose con fuerza en él.

Alister and Penny both gave statements that Soren Bayard died protecting them.

—Te dije que corrieras —le dijo abrazada a él.

Sebastian Bayard—” Ilva paused for a moment. “Sebastian corroborates this, and claims that the two of you managed to drag the others to safety after the rising floodwater washed away a large number of the attacking forces.”

A Luc le temblaban las manos cuando acarició el corte que le atravesaba a Lila la cara.

“And?” Helena asked.

Lila tocó con suavidad los rasguños que se había provocado él mismo en el pecho—.

“Lucien—hallucinated Soren Bayard’s alleged reanimation.

¿Qué te han hecho?

Perhaps Soren fell briefly.

Luc negó con la cabeza y la abrazó con más fuerza.

In the confusion of a battle, it is impossible to know.

Enterró la cabeza en su hombro mientras la rodeaba con los brazos.

The point is, this was a heroic rescue.

Fue un momento tan íntimo que dolía contemplarlo.

The Principate was saved though the price was great.

Si quedaba alguna duda de por qué Luc se había entregado, se disipó en ese instante.

Sol’s will was done.”

Alguien tocó el codo de Helena.

Helena knew she was supposed to be grateful, but she also knew the lie wasn’t for her sake.

Cuando levantó la vista, vio que Ilva le señalaba la puerta con un gesto.

It was all for the story.

Ella se puso en pie y se escabulló en silencio antes de que Luc reparara en su presencia de nuevo.

It didn’t matter what had really happened, only what people believed.

Cuando pasó junto a Rhea, la mujer apartó la mirada, evitándola.

“The obligations of Soren and Sebastian’s vows supersede any orders by the Council,” Ilva said. “Alister and Penny were obeying the orders of their direct superiors.

Al final, Lila logró que Luc se metiera en la cama y aceptara que Pace y Elain lo examinaran de nuevo.

You would have a reprimand on your military record for your participation, but as a healer you’re not part of the military.

Incluso accedió a que le pusieran una vía intravenosa en el brazo y a tomar la medicina que le bajaría la fiebre.

Matias will be the one to decide what sort of reprimand you deserve.

Helena se sentó en una camilla de la sala principal del hospital con una vía intravenosa en el brazo, mientras Elain le arreglaba una fractura del esternón y extendía un bálsamo sobre el moratón que le ocupaba todo el pecho.

Until then, you’ll be off duty.

Por último, le trató la parte posterior de la cabeza, donde se había golpeado al chocar con la pared.

I believe it would be best if you stay out of sight until the official story has circulated.”

No era la primera vez que un paciente le causaba alguna lesión, pero esta vez todo era distinto.

Helena went back to her room and collapsed into her bed, exhaustion rolling over her like a wave.

Luc jamás la perdonaría por lo que le había hecho a Soren.

It was dark oblivion at first, but then the landscape of her mind morphed.

Lo había dejado destrozado.

She was sinking, down, down.

La cortina que envolvía la camilla se apartó para dar paso a Ilva.

There were teeth sinking into her.

Elain permaneció allí hasta que la mano derecha del principado la fulminó con la mirada; entonces huyó.

Hands clawing, curling around her limbs, tearing her apart.

Helena se cerró la camisa sin levantar la mirada.

She kept fighting.

—Estamos recibiendo los informes de lo ocurrido —comunicó Ilva sin emoción alguna.

Cold fingers carving gouges through her flesh, stabbing into her bones.

Helena no se inmutó.

She tried to fight.

¿La llevarían a juicio ahora?

The weight bore down on her.

¿O esperarían a que la guerra terminara?

Her bones cracked.

—¿Qué te han contado? —preguntó en voz baja.

Teeth sank into her flesh.

Ilva carraspeó.

The tendon behind her knee ripped out.

—Luc ha perdido la razón.

Wet hands found her mouth, clawing in so deep she couldn’t bite down.

No podemos fiarnos de su versión de los hechos, dado que no solo está gravemente herido, sino que además está muy medicado.

Her jaw gave way, ripping until her throat tore open.

Alister y Penny han declarado que Soren Bayard murió protegiéndolos.

She was still fighting as water closed over her head.

Sebastian Bayard… —se detuvo un momento—.

Helena started violently awake, gasping to breathe, hands clutching at her open throat.

Sebastian Bayard lo ha corroborado, y afirma que fuisteis vosotros dos quienes pusisteis a salvo a los demás cuando la corriente de agua arrastró a la gran mayoría de los atacantes.

Just a dream, just a dream, she tried to tell her pounding heart.

—¿Y qué más? —insistió Helena.

Not really a dream, though.

—Lucien… ha debido de alucinar con la supuesta reanimación de Soren Bayard.

A memory.

Quizá solo cayó al suelo por un instante.

Soren’s memories postmortem were lodged inside her consciousness as though they were her own.

Es imposible saberlo en el caos de una batalla.

Bright and lurid in all their details.

La cuestión es que habéis llevado a cabo un rescate heroico.

She hadn’t known necromancy was like that.

Habéis salvado al principado, aunque hemos pagado un precio muy alto.

That she would never be free of the person she brought back.

Es la voluntad de Sol.

No wonder necromancers went mad.

Helena sabía que debía sentirse agradecida, pero también era consciente de que no estaban mintiendo para protegerla.

Who could stay sane with the minds of the dead inside them?

Todo formaba parte de la historia oficial.

The place where Soren had been was like a pit of festering guilt.

Daba igual qué hubiera sucedido en realidad, lo importante era lo que creyese la gente.

Her body and mind had been cored, and now something dead and rotting was left there.

—Los juramentos de Soren y Sebastian están por encima de las órdenes del Consejo —prosiguió Ilva—.

Everyone always talked of what a curse necromancy was.

Alister y Penny solo obedecían a un superior directo.

Warned against it and its consequences, but Helena had been so convinced of its necessity, and so distracted by the eternal consequences, that she’d never paused to consider there being immediate ones.

Tú recibirás una amonestación en tu expediente militar, pero, como eres sanadora, no formas parte del ejército.

She lay there, still feeling phantom fingers tearing her apart; her body was unutterably cold, reliving the cold, snowmelt water.

Matias será quien decida qué castigo mereces.

She pulled more blankets onto herself, stealing Lila’s bedding, and huddled, trying to sleep, to escape from the deadness Soren had left inside her.

Hasta entonces, estarás fuera de servicio.

Every time she closed her eyes, Soren’s final memories and sensations flashed through her mind.

Creo que lo mejor es que te mantengas al margen hasta que hagamos circular la historia oficial.

She hadn’t brought back his ability to feel pain or emotions, but her own mind dutifully tried to fill in those blanks, phantom sensation and terror rippling through her until her mind threatened to fissure, splitting between two realities.

Helena volvió a su habitación y se dejó caer sobre la cama.

It was only pain that drew her back into herself.

El cansancio la envolvió como una ola imparable.

She kept pinching at her skin, scratching at it.

Al principio solo hubo oscuridad y olvido, pero después el paisaje de su mente se fue transformando.

It wasn’t intense enough.

Se estaba hundiendo, cada vez más profundo.

She needed something stronger.

Unos dientes mordieron su piel, unas manos la arañaban, aferrándose a sus extremidades y destrozándola.

She blinked and found herself holding one of Lila’s knives, a second away from shoving it through her left forearm.

Aun así, Helena no dejó de luchar.

She dropped it and fled the room, wandering half blindly through the empty hallways of the Tower.

Unos dedos fríos rasgaron su carne y se clavaron en sus huesos.

It was night, quiet; almost everyone was asleep.

Intentó resistirse, pero era demasiado.

It was so eerily still.

Sintió cómo se le partían los huesos, cómo los dientes penetraban en la carne.

She was consumed with a sort of mania.

El tendón de la rodilla cedió.

She stumbled outside, hoping that the clear air would help centre her.

En la boca, unas manos húmedas se metieron tan al fondo que no podía cerrarla.

Lumithia hung overhead, bright as a white sun in the black abyss.

La mandíbula se fracturó, dejando la garganta al descubierto.

Helena’s eyes throbbed just looking up at her.

Todavía estaba luchando cuando quedó sumergida bajo el agua.

The Ascendance always put everything on edge, but Helena was already on edge.

Helena se despertó de repente, luchando por respirar mientras se arañaba la garganta con las manos.

Ascendance had shoved her right over.

«Solo ha sido un sueño.

She closed her eyes and she was drowning again, nails dragging welts across her skin.

Un sueño, eso es todo», trató de decirle a su corazón desbocado.

Kaine.

Pero no había sido un sueño, sino un recuerdo.

Kaine would know what was wrong.

Los recuerdos post mortem de Soren estaban grabados a fuego en su mente como si fueran propios: claros, lúcidos, cargados de detalles.

He’d understand.

No sabía que la nigromancia era así, que jamás se libraría de la persona que había reanimado.

He used necromancy; he must know how to deal with this.

No le extrañaba que los nigromantes se volvieran locos.

Without pausing to think, she headed for the Outpost.

¿Cómo podían mantener la cordura si tenían en su interior la mente de los muertos?

The destination was deliriously urgent.

El hueco que había dejado Soren se había convertido en un pozo de culpa infecta.

Curfew would be soon.

Helena intentó con toda el alma reanimarlo, y ahora solo le quedaba algo muerto y putrefacto.

She had to get through the checkpoints.

Todo el mundo decía que la nigromancia era una maldición y advertían sobre sus consecuencias, pero en ese momento Helena estaba tan convencida de que la necesitaban, tan absorta en el futuro, que no se había parado a pensar en cuánto le afectaría en el presente.

The streets of the city were like silver ribbons gleaming under full Ascendance, the shadows like teeth.

Permaneció tendida en la cama, aunque aún sentía los dedos fantasmas que la despedazaban y el frío implacable de la nieve derretida.

Just a little farther, she kept telling herself with every step.

Le robó las mantas a Lila y se acurrucó bajo ellas para intentar dormir y huir de la falta de vida que Soren le hacía sentir en su interior.

Until she was across the bridge, the river high and roaring beneath her, the tenement looming in front of her.

Cada vez que cerraba los ojos, veía en su mente los últimos recuerdos y sensaciones de Soren.

It was only when she reached the steps that she stopped to think.

A pesar de que no había recuperado su capacidad de sentir dolor o emociones, su propia mente se encargaba de llenar esos vacíos con un terror fantasma que la hacía estremecer hasta tal punto que parecía que su mente se rompía, dividida en dos realidades.

She’d promised Kaine she would never come to the Outpost unless there was a Resistance emergency.

Lo único que la anclaba al presente era el dolor, así que empezó a pellizcarse y a arañarse.

He was a spy.

No era suficiente; necesitaba algo más intenso.

It was dangerous for him.

Parpadeó y se descubrió a sí misma sosteniendo uno de los cuchillos de Lila, a unos milímetros de clavárselo en el antebrazo.

She’d given her word.

Lo dejó caer y salió corriendo de la habitación, aunque apenas veía en los pasillos desiertos de la Torre.

She’d risk his cover—endanger him.

Era de noche y reinaba un silencio sepulcral; casi todos ya se habían ido a dormir.

She turned away.

La calma le resultó escalofriante, pero a ella la consumía una obsesión implacable.

Without a destination, her focus fractured.

Salió a trompicones, con la esperanza de que el aire fresco le devolviera la cordura.

Soren.

Lumitia pendía en el cielo, brillante como un sol blanco en medio de un abismo negro.

Helena.

A Helena le dolieron los ojos con solo mirarla.

Soren.

La sublimación siempre ponía nervioso a cualquiera, pero Helena ya estaba al borde de la locura.

She felt her jaw give way, cold air and blood as her oesophagus tore open.

La sublimación solo lo empeoraba.

Fingers gouging into her eye sockets.

Cerró los ojos y sintió que se ahogaba de nuevo, que unas uñas le hacían surcos en la piel.

Water closing over her head.

Kaine.

She was drowning but couldn’t die, so she just kept drowning.

Kaine sabría qué le ocurría. Él lo entendería.

When her consciousness found her again, she was lying on the ground.

Usaba la nigromancia, así que debía de conocer cómo ayudarla.

The black sky, dark as ink, loomed overhead as Lumithia bore down, a scorching cold in Helena’s resonance.

Sin pensarlo dos veces, se dirigió al Reducto.

“Marino, what have you done to yourself?”

En realidad, debía llegar allí en tiempo récord, ya que quedaba poco para el toque de queda y todavía tenía que pasar por el puesto de control.

She was barely conscious of being lifted off the ground.

Las calles de la ciudad parecían lazos plateados bajo el brillo de la sublimación plena, pero las sombras eran como colmillos al acecho.

Hot hands touching her face and forehead, driving away the drowning cold.

«Un poco más allá», se repetía con cada paso.

She burrowed into the heat.

Hasta que cruzó el puente, donde el río rugía bajo sus pies cargado de agua, y los apartamentos surgieron ante ella.

She was delirious.

No se detuvo a pensar hasta que llegó a los escalones.

Truly delirious now, because Kaine was there with a giant winged dog standing behind him.

Le había prometido a Kaine que no volvería al Reducto a menos que hubiera alguna emergencia.

She’d never had a hallucination before, but all things considered, it was oddly pleasant.

Era un espía; su vida corría peligro.

Kaine was like a furnace, and when she buried herself in his arms, face pressed against his chest, she could scarcely feel the cold dead fingers anymore.

Helena le había dado su palabra de que no se acercaría por allí salvo que se lo ordenara la Llama Eterna.

“Soren Bayard died and I—I brought him back, but the other necrothralls tore him to pieces.

De repente fue consciente de que había puesto en peligro su tapadera, y también a él.

I can’t stop remembering how it felt.

Se dio la vuelta.

I think he took part of me with him.

Al no tener adónde ir, perdió la concentración.

How do you do it again and again without going insane?

Soren.

Is it like this forever?”

Helena.

One of his hands tilted her head back so she could see his eyes.

Soren.

In the moonlight, the grey glowed almost as bright as Lumithia, his hair gleaming that same colour.

Sintió que se le desencajaba la mandíbula, que el aire frío y la sangre entraban en su esófago desgarrado.

“Had you ever used necromancy before?”

Unos dedos invisibles se le metieron en los ojos.

She shook her head.

El agua la estaba sumergiendo.

“I don’t suppose anyone told you how to do it, did they?” He exhaled, the back of his fingers pressing against her forehead. “You had the shit luck of knowing him, too.

Se estaba ahogando, pero no moría.

You’re going into shock.”

Seguía ahogándose atrapada en un bucle infinito.

A hysterical laugh bubbled up from her.

Cuando recobró el conocimiento, estaba tendida en el suelo.

Of course no one had told her how to perform necromancy.

El cielo negro, oscuro como la tinta, se cernía sobre ella.

He shushed her, pulling her back against his chest, warding off the way her skin crawled with the memory of decaying fingers burrowing into it. “You tried to bring him back, didn’t you?

Sin embargo, la luz de Lumitia seguía emitiendo un frío punzante que quemaba su resonancia.

Idiot.

—Marino, ¿qué te has hecho a ti misma?

You’re freezing cold.”

Apenas fue consciente de que la alzaban del suelo.

She didn’t struggle as he half carried her towards his giant dog.

Unas manos cálidas le tocaron la cara y la frente alejando el frío que la asfixiaba.

On closer inspection, it wasn’t a dog, but a wolf with bright-yellow eyes, and it was the size of a warhorse, with wings the size of—

Se acurrucó contra ese calor.

She didn’t know of anything on earth with wings that large.

Había perdido la cabeza.

Kaine pushed her up and set her on a saddle cinched behind the wings, and then swung atop behind her.

Esta vez de verdad, porque Kaine estaba delante de ella acompañado de un enorme perro con alas.

Helena’s eyes fluttered shut as she sagged against him, tensing at the sensation of icy-cold fingers tearing open her skin.

Helena nunca había sufrido alucinaciones, pero, dadas las circunstancias, aquella resultaba extrañamente reconfortante.

The creature hunched down, muscles rippling beneath thick fur.

Kaine era como un horno y, cuando se hundió en sus brazos y posó la cara en su pecho, dejó de sentir los dedos fríos y muertos de sus pesadillas.

There was a lurch, then a sickening jerk that nearly threw Helena off.

—Soren Bayard murió y… y lo traje de vuelta, pero los demás necrómatas lo despedazaron.

Without warning, they were airborne.

No dejo de revivir lo que sintió.

Wind stung across her face, and her eyes rolled back.

Creo que se llevó una parte de mí consigo.

She was barely conscious of anything except Kaine behind her and the cold wind screaming in her ears.

¿Cómo lo haces para soportarlo sin volverte loco?

Then she was sliding down, her legs giving out, and Kaine caught her before she hit the ground.

¿Siempre estaré así?

They were standing somewhere so high up, the night so bright, that she could see beyond the mountains.

Kaine le levantó la barbilla con una mano para mirarla a los ojos.

She’d never been so high.

A la luz de la luna, el color gris resplandecía casi tanto como la propia Lumitia, y su cabello brillaba con el mismo tono plateado.

She looked around.

—¿Habías usado la nigromancia alguna vez? —Ella negó con la cabeza—.

She was on a balcony and alone with Kaine.

Y supongo que nadie te explicó cómo hacerlo, ¿verdad? —Exhaló el aire con lentitud y comprobó la temperatura de su frente con el dorso de la mano—.

For the first time in years, she felt a sense of distance from it all, looking down onto the East Island, cratered by years of war, cast in moonlight.

Tuviste suerte de que fuera alguien conocido.

The air was thin, as if she were back in the mountains, the world dreamily still.

Estás entrando en shock.

She held out a hand, letting the silver coat her skin.

A Helena se le escapó una risa nerviosa.

“Do you think this is what my subconscious thinks I want?” she asked, peering towards the light of the Alchemy Tower’s beacon gleaming like a small golden sun. “To run away from the war with you?”

Por supuesto que nadie le había contado cómo funcionaba la nigromancia.

Kaine’s expression was unreadable as he pulled her back from the railing.

Kaine le chistó y la atrajo contra su pecho para evitar que el recuerdo de unos dedos putrefactos clavándose en su piel le erizara todo el vello del cuerpo.

There was a dark doorway, and he led her through it and into a hallway.

—Intentaste resucitarlo, ¿verdad?

After the silver brightness of the city, her eyes struggled to adjust.

Idiota.

“What do you want?” he asked.

Estás congelada.

His voice seemed to come from the darkness.

Helena no se resistió cuando la acercó a su perro gigante.

Her eyes burned and she reached, feeling the wall under her fingertips.

En realidad, ahora que lo veía de cerca, no era un perro, sino un lobo de ojos brillantes y amarillentos, pero tenía el tamaño de un caballo de guerra y las alas de una…

“I don’t want to always be alone,” she said.

No conocía ningún animal que tuviera unas alas así de grandes.

It was easier to be honest in the dark. “I want to love someone without feeling like if they know, it’ll end up hurting them.

Kaine la alzó y la sentó sobre la montura, justo detrás de las alas, y luego se aupó para colocarse a su espalda.

People who love me always die.

Helena cerró los ojos y se apoyó en su cuerpo, aunque un escalofrío la hizo encogerse al sentir de nuevo los dedos gélidos desgarrándole la piel.

No matter what I do, it’s never enough to save them.

La criatura tomó impulso; sus músculos se le tensaron bajo el espeso pelaje y, de repente, se lanzó hacia delante con su salto que casi hizo que Helena cayera.

I have to love everyone from a distance, and I’m so lonely.”

Y, sin más, estaban volando.

Her eyes blurred, and then the darkness fell away, revealing a large room with a roaring fire.

El viento le azotaba la cara con fuerza.

The place was lavish.

Sintió que los ojos se le volvían hacia atrás.

The Holdfasts’ city residence had once been like this, filled with gilded furniture that glittered in the firelight.

Apenas era consciente de nada más salvo de que Kaine estaba a su espalda y el frío viento rugía en sus oídos.

It was elegant but impersonal.

Entonces empezó a resbalarse, las piernas le flaquearon, y Kaine la sostuvo antes de que cayera.

There wasn’t anything to make the place feel lived-in.

Volaban a tanta altura y la luna emitía una luz tan intensa que se veía incluso más allá de las montañas.

She looked back; Kaine was standing behind her.

Jamás había estado tan alto.

His black clothes were limned by the glowing firelight, adding a flush of gold and ember red to his almost monochrome appearance.

Miró a su alrededor.

He still had that otherworldly glow about him.

Estaba en un balcón, a solas con Kaine.

“You don’t have to be alone,” he said.

Por primera vez en años, sentía una leve distancia de todo lo que la atormentaba.

She looked down, wanting to fall headlong into the fantasy of believing that; to feel good for a little while, and tell herself it would do no harm.

Desde allí, la isla Este se extendía a lo lejos, destrozada tras tantos años de guerra, iluminada bajo la luz de la luna.

But she knew that was a lie.

El aire era escaso, como si estuvieran en las montañas, y el mundo parecía sumido en un silencio de ensueño.

Her mind was never quiet enough to let her enjoy anything without thinking about its consequences.

Helena extendió la mano para que la luz plateada bañara su piel.

“Why?

—¿Crees que esto es lo que quiere mi subconsciente? —preguntó, y se asomó para ver el faro de la Torre de Alquimia, que brillaba como un sol dorado en miniatura—.

Because of you?” she asked bitterly, going towards the fire instead, sinking onto her knees in front of it.

¿Escapar de la guerra contigo?

She couldn’t think she was drowning here.

Kaine mostró una expresión indescifrable cuando la apartó de la barandilla.

She shook her head. “I don’t get to care about you.”

Detrás de ellos había una puerta oscura, y él la guio para atravesarla y salir al pasillo.

Her chest clenched, fingers curling into fists. “If I care about you—I won’t be able to use you.

Tras el brillo plateado de la ciudad, sus ojos tuvieron que adaptarse a la oscuridad.

And you’re the only hope I have of keeping everyone else alive.”

—¿Y qué es lo que quieres? —preguntó Kaine.

She curled in on herself, staring at the dancing flames.

La voz parecía provenir de la penumbra.

Somewhere on the Outpost, she was lying on the ground, going into shock, possibly freezing to death.

Helena sintió que le ardían los ojos y extendió una mano para palpar la pared con las yemas de los dedos.

“Then use me,” Kaine said.

—Quiero dejar de estar siempre sola —confesó.

He was right next to her.

Era más fácil ser sincera en la oscuridad—.

He pulled her close and tried to kiss her.

Quiero amar a alguien sin pensar que, si lo descubrieran, acabaría sufriendo.

She jerked away. “No!

La gente que me quiere siempre muere.

No, I can’t.” She shook her head.

Da igual lo que haga, nunca consigo salvarlos.

Wake up, Helena. “I don’t want to do that to you.

Tengo que querer a todo el mundo desde la distancia, y me siento muy sola.

You don’t—deserve that.

La vista se le nubló, pero entonces la oscuridad se desvaneció dando paso a una habitación enorme iluminada por el fuego de una chimenea.

I can take care of myself.”

Era una casa fastuosa.

He wouldn’t let go.

La residencia de los Holdfast en la ciudad había sido así, repleta de muebles dorados que refulgían bajo las llamas.

“You don’t have to push me away to protect me,” he said in a hard, familiar voice. “I can take it.

Pero, aunque era elegante, carecía de personalidad.

You can stop being lonely.

No había nada que indicara que alguien vivía en ese sitio.

I won’t misunderstand.

Miró hacia atrás; Kaine estaba allí.

I know you just want someone to be with.”

La luz de la chimenea delineaba su figura, tiñendo de tonos dorados y rojizos su ropa oscura.

She looked for a door.

Aún tenía ese brillo etéreo.

An escape.

—No tienes por qué estar sola —dijo.

He didn’t let go. “Helena …”

Helena bajó la vista y deseó con todo su corazón poder recrearse en esa fantasía, sentirse un instante en calma y convencerse a sí misma de que no le haría daño.

She stilled at her name.

Sin embargo, sabía que era mentira.

“I’m alone, too,” he said.

Su mente nunca se relajaba lo suficiente para disfrutar de algo sin pensar en las consecuencias.

A lump rose in her throat, her heart pounding. “But I don’t want to hurt you, you don’t deserve—”

—¿Por qué?

He kissed her, swallowing her objections.

¿Lo dices por ti? —preguntó con amargura.

She didn’t struggle when he pulled her into his arms.

Se dirigió al fuego y se dejó caer de rodillas frente a la chimenea.

The heat of the fire faded until there was only the heat of him, his lips warm against hers, his hands cradling her face.

Allí no podía pensar que se estaba ahogando.

Then there was the softness of a bed beneath her back, pillows and sheets, and she pulled him closer, fingers seeking the buttons on his coat and unfastening them, but he caught her hands in his, holding them captive against his chest, and drew back.

Negó con la cabeza—.

He tilted her face into the light.

No puedo preocuparme por ti. —Apretó el puño—.

She stared dazedly at him as he pressed the back of his hand against her forehead and tucked her in as if she were sick and needed nursing.

Si me preocupo por ti, no podré usarte.

When she tried to sit up, he sat down next to her and let her huddle close, face buried against his chest.

Y eres la única esperanza que tengo para mantener con vida a todos los demás.

“Necromancy doesn’t—bring someone back …” he said, “but that can be hard to remember in the moment.

Se encogió sobre sí misma y se quedó mirando cómo danzaban las llamas.

When it’s someone you know, when you can feel the span of their loss, it’s instinctive to think it costs that much to bring them back.

En algún lugar del Reducto, Helena seguiría tumbaba en el suelo, habría entrado en shock y seguramente se estuviera muriendo de frío.

What you did with Bayard was put a part of yourself into reanimating him.

—Pues úsame —repuso Kaine.

In other circumstances, you could have reversed it, untethered yourself, but he took all of it with him when he was destroyed.”

Estaba a su lado.

There was a pause.

Se acercó e intentó besarla, pero Helena se apartó.

“You’ll recover, but it’ll leave a scar.

—¡No!

You just have to stay grounded until your mind learns not to go there.

No, no puedo. —Sacudió la cabeza. «Despierta, Helena»—.

Lucky for you, animancy should help with that.”

No quiero hacerte eso.

“Did this ever happen to you?”

No…, tú no te lo mereces.

He was silent for a minute. “Something similar once, but it was a long time ago.”

Puedo cuidar de mí misma.

Helena curled closer to him, listening to his heartbeat.

Kaine no la soltó.

He was alive.

—No tienes que alejarte de mí para protegerme —afirmó en un tono duro que a ella le resultaba familiar—.

She had kept him alive.

Podré soportarlo.

She found his hand, pulling it up near her chin, holding it in both of hers, tracing the ridges of his knuckles, lacing her fingers along them.

Puedes dejar de sentirte sola.

Just holding on.

No voy a malinterpretar lo que somos.

She lifted her head to look at him.

Sé que solo quieres tener a alguien con quien estar.

He didn’t move, not even when she let go of his hand to reach up and touch his face.

Helena buscó una puerta, una escapatoria, pero Kaine no la soltaba.

Or when she shifted near enough to brush her lips against his cheek.

—Helena… —Se quedó petrificada al oír su nombre pronunciado en sus labios—.

Her fingers traced across his cheekbones, and she kissed his temple and his forehead.

Yo también me siento solo.

Then, hesitantly, she pulled him closer and kissed him on the mouth.

Ella notó que se le formaba un nudo en la garganta; su corazón latía con fuerza.

He was fire to touch.

—Pero no quiero hacerte daño, no te mereces…

She kissed him slowly until his arms slid around her back and he returned it.

La besó y acalló todas sus objeciones.

She didn’t know if what she was doing was holding on or letting go.

Helena no se resistió cuando la sostuvo en sus brazos.

The first thing his fingers found were the pins in her hair.

El calor del fuego desapareció al sentir su calidez, sus labios calientes sobre los suyos, sus manos acunándole la cara.

Her braids tumbled down her back, his fingers combing through them until her hair was loose.

Entonces sintió la suavidad de una cama bajo su espalda, almohadas y sábanas, y atrajo a Kaine hacia sí.

His hand tangled through it as he kissed her again.

Buscó con los dedos los botones de su abrigo y los desabrochó, pero él le cogió las manos entre las suyas y las sostuvo cerca del pecho.

The kisses were slow.

Se separó de ella y le alzó la cara hacia la luz.

It wasn’t seething or rushed or guilty, but it was still desperate, because he always made her desperate.

Helena lo contempló desconcertada mientras Kaine le posaba el dorso de la mano en la frente y le remetía las mantas como si estuviera enferma y necesitara cuidados.

She kissed him the way she’d wanted to.

Cuando intentó levantarse, él se sentó a su lado y la abrazó fuerte, hundiéndole la cara en el pecho.

The way she’d secretly wished she could.

—La nigromancia no… no resucita a nadie —le explicó—, pero en esos momentos cuesta recordarlo.

She could have this.

Cuando se trata de alguien que conoces, cuando sabes lo que te afectará su pérdida, crees que reanimarlo te compensará.

Once.

A Bayard le diste una parte de ti misma cuando lo reanimaste.

She gave a low sob.

En otras circunstancias, podrías haberlo revertido para separarte de él, pero Bayard se lo llevó consigo cuando murió.

He paused, but she held on, not letting him go.

Hizo una pausa.

“This—is the way I wanted it to be,” she admitted. “With you.

—Te recuperarás, aunque te dejará cicatriz.

I wanted it to be like this with you.”

Tienes que mantenerte cuerda hasta que tu mente comprenda que no puede recrearse en ese momento.

He went very still.

Por suerte, la animancia ayuda en estos casos.

“I’m sorry.

—¿A ti te ha pasado alguna vez?

I’m sorry it wasn’t,” he finally said, pulling her closer.

Él se quedó en silencio unos instantes.

Had he ever actually been like this?

—Me pasó algo similar, pero fue hace mucho.

She wondered sometimes how much of her drunken memory of kissing him was real.

Helena se hizo un ovillo a su lado y escuchó el latido de su corazón.

Or if she’d invented all the intimacy to replay when her life felt too void of any tenderness.

Estaba vivo.

“It doesn’t matter,” she said, resting her head on his shoulder.

Lo había mantenido con vida.

“Yes, it does.

Encontró su mano y se la acercó a la barbilla.

Let me give you this now.” He drew her face to his and kissed her.

La sostuvo con ambas manos y trazó el contorno de sus nudillos.

Slow and intent.

Después entrelazó los dedos con los suyos y se quedó así.

Like a star, he was glittering and ice-cold from afar, but when the space was bridged, the heat of him was endless.

Levantó la cabeza para mirarlo.

His lips didn’t leave hers as his hands found the buttons on her shirt and underclothes, unfastening them slowly this time.

Kaine no se movió, ni siquiera cuando Helena le soltó la mano para tocarle la cara.

The fabric whispered across her skin as his fingers traced along her spine.

O cuando se giró un poco para rozarle la mejilla con los labios.

His mouth followed the curve of her collarbones, fingers drawing her head back so he could taste the dip of her throat.

Después, le acarició la mandíbula y le posó un beso en la sien y otro en la frente.

She fumbled at his clothes.

Después, algo vacilante, se acercó un poco más y le dio un beso en la boca.

Her fingers were unsteady, but there was no rush this time.

Estaba ardiendo al tacto.

She managed the buttons one by one.

Helena lo besó lentamente, hasta que Kaine la envolvió con los brazos y le devolvió el beso.

He was unfathomably gentle.

No tuvo claro si se estaba aferrando a él o dejándolo marchar.

His touch light, and yet it made her feel as though a flame were kindled inside her, a desire that made her ache.

Lo primero que encontraron los dedos de Kaine fueron las horquillas de su cabello y se las quitó.

It wasn’t too fast, or too much before she was ready.

Las trenzas se desplegaron a su espalda y sus dedos las peinaron hasta que tuvo todo el cabello suelto y enmarañado.

He went as slowly as she wanted him to.

La volvió a besar.

When he pushed inside her, his eyes were fastened on her face. “Is this all right?

Eran besos lentos.

Is it good for you?”

No estaban envueltos en desdén, en prisa o en culpa, pero aun así eran desesperados, porque Kaine siempre la hacía sentir así.

She gave a gasp and nodded.

Lo estaba besando como siempre había querido hacerlo.

Because it was good this time.

Como siempre había deseado en secreto poder hacerlo.

“It’s good.

Podía disfrutar de esto.

Don’t stop,” she said, gripping him by the shoulders, pulling him nearer.

Al menos por esta vez.

She could feel the scars of the array spanned beneath her fingers.

Se le escapó un sollozo.

She didn’t know how he could be so calm with all that power humming beneath the surface of his skin.

Kaine se detuvo, pero la chica no permitió que se alejara.

His forearms were around her head as though framing her, his fingers laced in her hair.

—Así… así me habría gustado que fuese —admitió—.

When he started to move, he pressed his forehead against hers, their breath intermingling.

Contigo.

When he kissed her, it felt like the beginning of something that could be eternal.

Me habría gustado que la primera vez hubiese sido parecido.

It happened so gradually, she almost forgot that there was more to it.

Kaine se quedó muy quieto.

They could have stayed like that, lost in each other, and it would have been more than enough.

—Lo siento.

She breathed in against his neck, tasting his skin with the tip of her tongue, memorising his scent, the feel of him in her arms.

Siento que no fuera así —dijo al fin, y la atrajo hacia su cuerpo.

The world beyond them had ceased to exist.

¿Se había comportado de esa manera alguna vez?

He knew how to trail his fingers across her skin so that she was gasping, kiss her so that her legs wrapped tight around his hips, and move so slowly that, at first, she didn’t notice the coiling tension inside her.

A veces se preguntaba si era real el recuerdo de cuando lo había besado estando borracha.

That lurking hunger.

O si se había imaginado aquella intimidad para sentirla cuando su vida careciera de ternura.

But of course there was more, and Kaine was looking for it.

—No importa —repuso apoyando la cabeza en su hombro.

All his meticulous attention to when her breath caught, what angle made her hips rise in response, when she caught her lip between her teeth to hold back a low moan, body shuddering.

—Claro que importa.

He entwined their fingers and noticed when she gripped him, squeezing so tight her nails bit into his knuckles, breath growing short.

Déjame que te lo dé ahora. —Acercó la cara de Helena a la suya y le dio un beso lento e intencionado.

The pace and friction and contact increased, growing into something larger and deeper than comfort.

Como si fuera una estrella, Kaine brillaba y se mostraba frío como el hielo cuando estaba lejos, pero, al acortarse las distancias, desprendía un calor infinito.

When he slid his hand between her legs, she instantly flinched away.

No despegó los labios de los de Helena mientras buscaba los botones de su camisa y el resto de la ropa; esta vez los desabrochó despacio.

The comfort vanished.

La tela emitió un susurro al tiempo que sus dedos recorrían su piel.

She went cold all over, trying to twist, wanting to escape, turning her face away.

Con la boca siguió la curva de su clavícula, y le echó la cabeza hacia atrás para saborear la hendidura de su garganta.

“No.” She tried not to panic, but this was all a mistake. “No, don’t.”

Helena le quitó la ropa con torpeza.

He withdrew his hand and cradled her face, kissing her. “You get this part.

Le temblaban las manos, pero esta vez no tenía prisa.

This is yours.”

Consiguió desabrocharle los botones uno a uno.

She shook her head. “No.

La trató con una ternura inconmensurable.

It’s not.” She drew in on herself, chin down, speaking rapidly. “When I became a healer, I had to promise I wouldn’t ever—I took the vows—and—and then you said—about Luc, if he knew.

La tocaba con suavidad y, aun así, hacía que una llama ardiera en su interior, un deseo que le dolía.

I can’t stop thinking about that.

No fue demasiado rápido ni brusco, y esperó a que estuviera preparada.

That—that I’m a whore—”

Era todo tan lento como ella quería.

Her voice failed.

Cuando la penetró, la miró fijamente a los ojos.

“I’m sorry.” His hand still entwined with hers tightened. “I’m so sorry.

—¿Está bien?

I ruined so much of this for you.

¿Te gusta?

This is how it’s supposed to be.

Helena gimió y asintió.

Let me give this to you now.”

Porque esta vez así era.

She didn’t move, her heart pounding against her ribs.

—Me gusta.

“Please, Helena.”

No pares —respondió agarrándolo por los hombros para pegarse aún más a él.

She gave the barest nod.

Sintió bajo los dedos las cicatrices del sello que tenía en la espalda.

“Close your eyes.” His breath whispered against her cheek.

No sabía cómo podía mostrarse tan tranquilo con todo el poder que rezumaba bajo su piel.

Her eyes fluttered closed as he kissed her.

Kaine colocó los antebrazos a cada lado de su cabeza, como si la encerrara, y entrelazó los dedos en su pelo.

Without being able to see, her focus was on the sensations, the feeling of his body pressed against hers.

Cuando empezó a moverse, presionó la frente con la suya; sus respiraciones se entremezclaron.

The movement of air across her skin.

Al besarla, fue como si comenzara algo que podía ser eterno.

When his lips brushed against the pulse-point of her throat, she moaned.

Sucedió tan despacio que Helena estuvo a punto de olvidar que iba a más.

His palm cupped her breast, stroking as he started to move.

Podrían haberse quedado así, perdidos el uno en el otro, y también habría sido suficiente.

He kissed her as he slid his hand between their bodies again, deepening the kiss until her jaw loosened, mouth slack, and pleasure flooded through her, so intense her spine bowed.

Respiró en su cuello y saboreó su piel con la punta de la lengua.

She gave a ragged gasp against his lips.

Memorizó su aroma y cómo era tenerlo en sus brazos.

She was being wound up, fire igniting, growing, running outwards along her nerves, through her arms and legs until her fingers twisted, tangling in the sheets.

El mundo exterior dejó de existir.

Every time he moved or his lips found some new sensitive place, the tension ratcheted inside her, notch by notch, until she was on the verge of fracturing open.

Kaine sabía cómo acariciarla con los dedos para dejarla sin respiración, besarla de tal forma que apretara las piernas alrededor de sus caderas, y moverse tan lentamente que, al principio, Helena no se percató de la tensión que se acumulaba en sus entrañas.

Her breath caught inside her lungs as she struggled, trying to hold herself together, overcome by the terror that she would break apart.

Esa voracidad acechante.

She couldn’t.

Pero, por supuesto, aquello iba a más, y Kaine quería conseguirlo.

If she broke, there would never be anyone to pick up the pieces.

Centró toda su atención en observar cuándo se quedaba sin aliento, qué ángulo la hacía arquear la espalda, cuándo se mordía el labio para contener un gemido, en qué momentos se estremecía.

“I can’t—” she finally gasped out.

Entrelazó los dedos con los suyos y notó que Helena lo abrazaba más fuerte, tanto que le clavaba las uñas en los nudillos.

“Helena.” Kaine’s lips brushed across her cheek and temple, his breath ragged. “You get to have this.

Empezó a jadear más rápido.

You’re allowed to feel good things.

Aumentó el ritmo, la fricción y el contacto, hasta generar una sensación más intensa y profunda que la comodidad.

Don’t be alone.

Cuando Kaine deslizó la mano entre sus piernas, Helena se removió.

Have this with me.”

Desapareció esa comodidad.

He pulled her leg up with one arm, deepening and shifting the angle, drawing the tension higher, and crushed their bodies together, kissing her.

Se quedó helada e intentó retorcerse, deseando escapar.

Her eyes shot open.

Apartó la mirada.

She stared up at him as her whole world shattered into shards of silver.

—No. —No quería sucumbir al pánico, pero eso era un error—.

“Oh gods—” She sobbed the words out.

No sigas.

Her fingernails sank into his arms. “Oh—oh—oh …”

Kaine apartó la mano y le sostuvo la cara para darle un beso.

She came apart under him, and he watched every moment of it.

—Te lo mereces.

As she lay panting, trying to catch her breath, his speed increased.

Esto es para ti.

Gripping her closer, tighter, his expression going tense.

Helena negó con la cabeza.

When he came, his mask slipped.

—No, no es cierto. —Se encogió sobre sí misma y bajó la barbilla.

He met her eyes for a moment before he buried his face against her shoulder, and she saw all the heartbreak in him.

Empezó a hablar deprisa—: Cuando me hice sanadora, prometí que nunca… Hice un juramento… y… y cuando dijiste… lo de Luc… Si lo supiera.

Afterwards he held her close, not letting go.

No puedo dejar de pensar en eso.

She looked up.

Que… que soy una puta…

He was watching her, his expression distant, his emotions carefully hidden away.

Le falló la voz.

She reached up and ran a finger along his cheek, looking for any trace of that boy who’d first greeted her at the Outpost, but there was so little of him remaining.

—Perdóname. —Kaine aún tenía su mano entrelazada con la suya—.

Even his hair was all silver now.

Siento mucho haberte arruinado esta experiencia.

“I think I’ve nearly memorised you,” she said. “Especially your eyes.

Así es como debería haber sido.

I think I learned to read them first.”

Déjame que te lo dé ahora.

The corner of his mouth twitched, and he caught her hand, capturing it against his chest.

Helena no se movió; el corazón le retumbaba en las costillas.

“I memorised yours, too,” he said after a moment, and then sighed, looking away. “I should have known—the moment I looked into your eyes, I should have known I would never win against you.”

—Helena, por favor.

She gave a small smile, struggling to stay awake, afraid it might all fade away if she did. “I’ve always thought my eyes were my best feature.”

Se limitó a asentir.

“One of them,” he said quietly.

—Cierra los ojos —susurró contra su mejilla.

Helena cerró los ojos y permitió que la besara.

Ahora que no veía, podía centrarse en otras sensaciones: el peso de su cuerpo sobre el suyo, cómo se movía el aire sobre su piel.

Cuando le rozó con los labios el punto de la garganta donde latía su corazón, se le escapó un gemido.

Kaine le acarició los senos y empezó a moverse de nuevo.

La siguió besando mientras deslizaba de nuevo la mano entre sus cuerpos y la besó con más pasión hasta que ella relajó la mandíbula y la boca, y dejó que el placer la embargara de una forma tan intensa que arqueó la espalda.

Gimió con aspereza contra sus labios.

Cada vez estaba más excitada; el fuego se encendía, crecía y se extendía por todas sus terminaciones nerviosas, por los brazos y las piernas, hasta que cerró los dedos, enredando las sábanas en el puño.

Cuando Kaine se movía, cuando sus labios encontraban algún punto sensible, Helena sentía que se soltaba la tensión, nudo a nudo, hasta que estuvo a punto de deshacerse.

Se le cortó la respiración cuando luchó, tratando de recomponerse y superar el miedo a romperse.

No podía hacerlo.

Si se rompía, nadie recogería los pedazos.

—No puedo… —dijo entre jadeos.

—Helena. —Los labios de Kaine le acariciaron la mejilla, la sien; respiraba de forma entrecortada—.

Puedes disfrutar de la vida.

Tienes derecho a sentir cosas buenas, a no estar sola.

Compártelo conmigo.

Kaine le levantó una pierna para que la penetración fuese más profunda y con un ángulo distinto.

La tensión fue en aumento.

Apretó su cuerpo contra el suyo y la besó de nuevo.

Helena abrió los ojos de par en par y lo miró mientras su mundo se hacía trizas en esquirlas de color plata.

—Por Dios… —gimió, clavando las uñas en sus brazos—.

Ah…, ah…, ah…

Llegó al orgasmo bajo su cuerpo, y él la observó hasta el último segundo.

Helena seguía tumbada, intentando recobrar el aliento, cuando Kaine aumentó la velocidad.

La atrajo más hacia sí y vio que se tensaba.

Cuando alcanzó el clímax, se le cayó la máscara y, por un instante, la miró a los ojos.

Aunque después enterró la cara en su hombro, ella llegó a ver todo el dolor que sentía.

Cuando acabó, la abrazó con fuerza para no dejarla marchar.

Helena alzó la mirada.

Kaine la estaba contemplando con expresión distante; estaba ocultando sus sentimientos.

Estiró la mano y le pasó un dedo por la mejilla, en busca de algún rastro del chico que la había recibido en el Reducto la primera vez.

Sin embargo, ya quedaba poco de él.

Hasta su cabello se había tornado plateado.

—Creo que te he memorizado casi por completo —comentó—.

Sobre todo, los ojos.

Creo que he aprendido a interpretarlos.

Kaine curvó las comisuras de los labios y le cogió la mano para llevársela al pecho.

—Yo también he memorizado los tuyos —dijo al cabo de un rato.

Después suspiró y apartó la mirada—.

Debería haberlo sabido en cuanto te miré a los ojos.

Debería haber sabido que jamás ganaría frente a ti.

La chica esbozó una leve sonrisa; le costaba mantenerse despierta.

Le daba miedo que todo se esfumara mientras dormía.

—Siempre pensé que los ojos eran mi mejor atributo.

—Uno de ellos —respondió Kaine en un susurro.

CHAPTER 52

Aprilis 1787

CAPÍTULO 52

WHEN HELENA WOKE, SHE FOUND HERSELF IN a large bed, in a large room, and through the windows, the Novis Mountains were arrayed around them, gilded by a golden sunrise.

Abrilis 1787

She was tangled in juniper-scented sheets and wrapped up in Kaine’s arms, and she had no memory of how she’d gotten there.

Cuando Helena despertó, se descubrió a sí misma en una cama enorme, se encontraba en una gran habitación y, al otro lado de las ventanas, se alzaban las montañas Novis, bañadas por la luz dorada del amanecer.

She glanced around the room again.

Estaba envuelta en sábanas con olor a enebro y en los brazos de Kaine.

From the angle of the city, she could tell she was on the West Island.

No recordaba cómo había llegado hasta allí.

Probably one of the towers so immense they often disappeared into the clouds.

Volvió a mirar la habitación.

She’d always imagined Kaine on an estate or in one of the old houses in the city.

Por el ángulo de la ciudad, supo que estaba en la isla Oeste.

Why would he be somewhere like this?

Seguramente se tratara de una de las torres tan alargadas que desaparecían entre las nubes.

He lay, arms wrapped possessively around her as though he were keeping her from being stolen, features relaxed in sleep.

Siempre había dado por sentado que Kaine viviría en una finca en las afueras o en una de esas casas antiguas de la ciudad.

She studied him.

¿Por qué preferiría estar en un sitio como ese?

What had she done?

Él estaba tumbado; sus brazos la envolvían posesivamente, como si así no pudieran robársela, aunque mantenía un semblante plácido mientras dormía.

Kaine Ferron was a dragon, like his family before him.

Helena lo observó detenidamente.

Possessive to the point of self-annihilation.

¿Qué le había hecho?

Isolated and deadly, and now he held her in his arms as if she were his.

Kaine Ferron era un dragón, como todos sus antepasados.

The temptation to give in, to let him have her, and to love him for it terrified her.

Posesivo hasta la autodestrucción.

Her need to love people and her desperate longing for them to love her back—she had given that up, locked it away and buried it, giving its place to the coldness of logic, realism, and the necessary choices of war.

Ermitaño y letal, pero la sostenía entre sus brazos como si fuera de su propiedad.

This could only lead to ruin.

Helena sintió pavor al notar la tentación de ceder, de permitir que la tuviera y de amarlo.

She had to be gone before he woke.

La necesidad de amar a los demás y ese anhelo desesperado por que la correspondieran… Hacía mucho que se había rendido, había guardado ese sentimiento bajo llave y lo había enterrado para dar paso a la frialdad de la lógica, al realismo y a las elecciones prácticas de la guerra.

She tried to slip away as she had before, but this time his eyes snapped open.

Esto la iba a llevar a la ruina.

He pulled her back immediately but then caught sight of her terrified expression.

Tenía que marcharse antes de que Kaine despertara.

His eyes flickered, and he let go.

Intentó despegarse tal como había hecho en otras ocasiones, pero esta vez Kaine abrió los ojos.

She went still.

En un primer momento, la atrajo hacia sí, pero entonces vio su expresión temerosa.

The fear and anger that he’d inspired a year earlier had all but disappeared.

Parpadeó un par de veces y la dejó marchar.

The danger was still there, cast in sharper relief now that she had seen how lethal he was.

Helena se quedó donde estaba.

Yet somehow knowing it made her less frightened.

El miedo y la rabia que él le inspiraba el año anterior se habían desvanecido por completo.

Now she knew how much he was holding back.

Aún percibía el peligro, tal vez incluso con más nitidez, pues sabía lo letal que era.

Despite everything he’d achieved, this was Kaine Ferron using restraint.

Sin embargo, de alguna manera, saberlo hacía que le diera menos miedo.

“This was a mistake,” she said. “I shouldn’t have come here.”

Ahora sabía además lo mucho que se había contenido.

His throat dipped as he looked away.

A pesar de todo lo que había conseguido, Kaine Ferron se estaba controlando.

“Don’t worry,” he said quietly. “This won’t complicate anything for you.

—Esto ha sido un error —dijo Helena—.

You wanted someone to be with, and I was available.

No debería haber venido aquí.

I know it didn’t mean anything.”

Kaine tragó saliva y desvió la mirada.

Helena’s breath caught, and she swallowed.

—No te preocupes —repuso con calma—.

He wasn’t just someone.

No te complicaré las cosas.

To her, he was—

Querías estar con alguien y yo estaba disponible.

That was the mistake of it, what she was so scared of.

Sé que no significó nada.

Before she could even begin to invent a lie, something must have shown in her face.

Al oírlo, Helena contuvo la respiración y tragó saliva.

Her eyes always betrayed her.

Kaine no era alguien sin más.

Because his expression was withdrawn, and then, in an instant, triumph flashed across his face and he reached for her again.

Para ella era…

Hunger and heat splintered the air like lightning.

Ese era el mayor error de todo, lo que la aterraba.

Before she could bolt, he pulled her back to him and his lips found hers, and all her fears and guilt and resolution became lost to her.

Antes de que pudiera esbozar una mentira para protegerse, algo en su rostro la traicionó.

All she could think of was how much she wanted to be there, being touched by him.

Sus ojos siempre la delataban.

He was fire, and she was already consumed.

Porque Kaine, cuyo semblante parecía abatido, adoptó una expresión de triunfo.

“You’re mine,” he said against her lips, his fingers sliding along her throat, tangling in her hair, holding her fast as he dragged her nearer.

Volvió a atraerla hacia sí con una voracidad y una pasión que atravesó el aire como un relámpago.

It was not like the previous night.

Sin posibilidad de huir, Helena regresó a sus brazos, y los labios de Kaine buscaron los suyos.

It wasn’t comfort.

Cualquier rastro de miedo, culpa o decisión se deshizo en el aire.

It was claiming.

Lo único en lo que pensaba era en lo mucho que deseaba estar allí, en que él la tocara.

His mouth was hot on her lips, his teeth nipping possessively along her jaw and her throat, over her shoulders.

Kaine era puro fuego, y ella ya se había consumido.

She tangled her fingers in his hair, arching into his touch.

—Eres mía —murmuró contra sus labios.

She tried not to cry from how desperately she wanted him, and how grateful she was that she didn’t have to ask.

Deslizó los dedos por su garganta y los enredó entre los mechones de cabello, acercándola todavía más.

He pulled her closer, arms entwined around her as he aligned himself and sank into her with a sharp thrust, his breath burning along her neck.

No fue como la noche anterior.

He was exacting.

No se trató de un acto de consuelo, sino de dominación.

Determined to prove to her that this was where she belonged, to ensure that she could never deny what he made her feel.

Helena sintió la boca ardiente de Kaine sobre sus labios, y después sus dientes dándole mordiscos en la mandíbula y en la garganta, también en los hombros.

She could feel his resonance along her nerves.

Ella enredó los dedos en su cabello y arqueó la espalda bajo sus manos.

He made no effort to hide the way he attuned himself to her, overwhelming her with sensation and pleasure all at once.

Intentó no gemir de lo desesperadamente que lo deseaba, agradecida de no tener que pedirlo.

In the moment his control slipped and his expression was laid bare again, there was no more heartbreak; he was possessive and triumphant.

Kaine la acercó a su cuerpo, la envolvió con los brazos y se colocó encima.

He pulled her close, crushing her to his chest. “You’re mine.

Cuando se hundió en su interior con una fuerte embestida, Helena sintió su aliento caliente en el cuello.

You swore yourself to me.

La poseyó con dureza, como si quisiera demostrarle que ahí era donde debía estar, como si necesitara asegurarle que nunca podría negar cómo la hacía sentir.

Now and after the war.

Helena sentía su resonancia vibrando en sus propias terminaciones nerviosas.

I’m going to take care of you.

Kaine no se molestó en ocultarlo: estaba sintonizado con ella, y eso le provocaba unas sensaciones y un placer desbordantes.

I’m not going to let anyone hurt you.

Cuando Kaine se dejó llevar y su rostro volvió a mostrar sus emociones al desnudo, ya no había un corazón roto, sino una declaración de posesión y triunfo.

You don’t have to be lonely.

La atrajo hacia sí, apretándola contra su pecho.

Because you’re mine.”

—Eres mía.

Helena knew she should go, but she had lost herself there.

Juraste serlo.

She was locked in the dangerous embrace of Kaine Ferron, and it felt like home.

Ahora y después de la guerra.

She slept in his arms, nearly dead to the world, waking only briefly when his fingers trailed along her shoulder.

Yo me encargaré de cuidar de ti.

She looked up, found him watching her, his eyes dark.

No permitiré que nadie te haga daño.

She arched into his touch and dropped a kiss over his heart.

No tienes por qué sentirte sola.

He picked up her hand, and she felt his resonance in her fingers as she fell asleep.

Porque eres mía.

When she woke again, it was nearly evening, and the mountains had turned purple with dusk, gilded a burnished red as Sol began his descent.

Helena sabía que debía marcharse, pero se perdió en el momento.

Kaine was dressed, but he was just sitting beside her, watching her sleep, her fingers laced in his, as if there was nothing else to do.

Estaba atrapada en el peligroso abrazo de Kaine Ferron, y se sentía como si estuviera en casa.

“How are you here?” she asked, dazed with exhaustion.

Se durmió entre sus brazos, como si el mundo hubiera dejado de existir, y solo despertó un instante al sentir sus dedos acariciándole el hombro.

She somehow felt more tired than she ever had before, as if her body had finally remembered how to sleep and now intended to recover all the years of deprivation.

Cuando alzó la vista, lo vio observándola con los ojos oscurecidos.

He raised an eyebrow. “I live here.

Helena se acurrucó bajo esa caricia y lo besó ahí donde latía su corazón.

Did you think my primary residence was the Outpost panic room?”

Cuando Kaine le tomó la mano, Helena sintió su resonancia en sus propios dedos y volvió a quedarse dormida.

She shook her head, rolling onto her back.

Al despertarse de nuevo, estaba a punto de hacerse de noche y las montañas se habían teñido de un morado y un rojo bruñido que marcaban el descenso de Sol.

Her hands didn’t hurt at all anymore. “No, but how are you able to spend a whole day in bed with me?

Kaine estaba vestido, pero seguía sentado a su lado, mirándola dormir con los dedos entrelazados con los suyos, como si no tuviera nada más que hacer.

Aren’t you a general or something?

—¿Cómo es posible que estés aquí? —preguntó Helena, entre perpleja y exhausta.

Don’t you have meetings, or crimes to commit?”

Por algún motivo, se sentía más cansada que antes, como si su cuerpo, al fin, hubiera recordado cómo se dormía y ahora pretendiera recuperar todos los años de privación.

Rather than answer, he leaned over her until she was stretched out beneath him.

Kaine arqueó una ceja.

His longer arms pinned her hands above her head, and he kissed her.

—Vivo aquí.

“I’m off duty,” he finally said when she was breathless. “A concept I fear no one has ever acquainted you with.”

¿Pensabas que mi residencia habitual era la habitación del pánico del Reducto?

She rolled her eyes. “But why do you live here?

Helena negó con la cabeza y se quedó tumbada de espaldas.

I thought old families had property.”

Ya no le dolían las manos.

He let go then and sat up, looking out at the view. “My mother was tortured at our country estate, and all the staff murdered.

—No, pero ¿cómo es posible que puedas pasar un día entero en la cama conmigo?

We moved to the city residence, and that’s where she died.

¿No eres general o algo así?

I wanted somewhere else to go, away from it all.”

¿No tienes reuniones o crímenes que cometer?

Helena sat up.

En lugar de responder, Kaine se le echó encima hasta dejarla tendida bajo su cuerpo.

“I’m sorry, I shouldn’t have asked, I just never imagined you high like this,” she said, reaching up and resting a hand on his cheek.

Con sus brazos alargados, le sostuvo las manos por encima de la cabeza y luego la besó.

He dropped his head against her palm and closed his eyes for a moment, the strands of his hair falling across her fingertips.

—Estoy de descanso —contestó mientras la dejaba sin respiración—.

Then he abruptly lifted his head. “Well, it’s mostly practical.

Un concepto que me temo que nadie te ha explicado. —Entonces la soltó y se sentó para admirar las vistas—.

Amaris flies better from the roof.

A mi madre la torturaron en nuestra casa de las afueras, y también asesinaron allí a nuestros empleados.

She’s better at it now, but it used to be hard for her to get airborne.”

Después, nos trasladamos a nuestra residencia de la ciudad, y ahí fue donde murió.

“Amaris?” Helena repeated slowly.

Quería ir a un sitio distinto, que estuviera alejado de todo eso.

“The chimaera.

Helena se incorporó.

You saw her last night.”

—Lo siento, no debería haber preguntado.

She blinked at him, a memory of an impossibly enormous, winged wolf resurfacing. “I thought … I’d hallucinated.”

Simplemente jamás te imaginé viviendo a esta altura —comentó.

He gave her a look. “I told you I was getting a chimaera.”

Luego estiró la mano y la posó en su mejilla.

“Well, yes, but I assumed it was something—smaller, and you never mentioned it again.

Kaine apoyó la cabeza en la palma de su mano y cerró los ojos durante un instante; los mechones de su cabello le rozaron las yemas de los dedos.

I assumed it had died.”

Sin embargo, levantó la cabeza de repente.

He shrugged. “Well, she was small at first.

—Bueno, es lo más práctico.

About the size of a foal when she arrived.”

Amaris echa a volar desde la azotea.

“What is she?”

Ahora se le da mejor, pero le ha costado mucho aprender a hacerlo.

“Bennet isn’t forthcoming about such things.

—¿Amaris? —repitió Helena lentamente.

A lot of Northern wolf and some kind of destrier.

—La quimera.

I don’t know where he got the wings, though.”

La viste anoche.

“And she’s—tame?”

Helena parpadeó un par de veces.

He shook his head. “No.

El recuerdo de un lobo alado, de proporciones imposibles, resurgió en su mente.

Just fond of me, but you should meet her.

—Creía que… estaba alucinando.

I meant to introduce you, but the moment never seemed right.

Kaine la miró fijamente.

Come on.”

—Te dije que me iban a dar una quimera.

Helena didn’t move, not wanting to go anywhere yet.

—Bueno, sí, pero di por hecho que sería algo… más pequeño, y, como no volviste a mencionarlo, supuse que habría muerto.

Everything was so different between them now.

Kaine se encogió de hombros.

The tension and wariness finally absent.

—Bueno, al principio era pequeña.

She’d never known him outside of that context, even as children.

Cuando llegó, tenía el tamaño de un potro.

Secreted away from the rest of the world, she felt that she could finally see him for his own sake, rather than only through the lens of the Eternal Flame’s interests.

—¿Qué es en realidad?

Glancing around the impersonal rooms, she could see them for what they were, a place to exist.

—Bennet no nos ha dado muchos datos al respecto.

There was not a single item of personal significance.

Tiene mucha genética de lobo norteño mezclada con algo de caballo de guerra.

Temporary.

Aunque no sé de dónde sacó las alas.

Uncommitted.

—¿Y está… domada?

“When did you realise that I didn’t know you were supposed to die?” she asked rather than stand.

El chico negó con la cabeza.

He released a long breath. “The first time you arrived on the Outpost.

—No, simplemente me ha cogido cariño, pero deberías conocerla.

I could tell by the way you looked, you thought it really was forever.”

Hacía tiempo que quería presentártela, pero nunca encontré el momento oportuno.

Her throat tightened.

Ven conmigo.

He looked away. “It was—funny at first.

Helena no se movió, todavía no quería ir a ninguna parte.

I kept waiting for you to catch on.”

Algo había cambiado entre ellos: la tensión y la cautela se habían desvanecido por completo.

Heat spread across the back of her neck.

Nunca se habían tratado con suavidad, ni siquiera cuando eran más jóvenes.

“I thought that when I pointed out that you should’ve known about my punishment, you’d realise it was a setup, but you didn’t.

Alejados del resto del mundo, Helena sentía que por fin podía verlo tal como era, y no a través del filtro impuesto por los intereses de la Llama Eterna.

Then I assumed that it would have been explained to you by that evening or the next day, but you just kept coming back.

A pesar de estar en una habitación impersonal, a Helena le parecía que era justamente el sitio donde podían existir.

I figured there must be something else they wanted, but it was clear by then they weren’t going to tell you.

No había ni un solo objeto que tuviera un significado especial.

I almost did, a few times, but—” He sighed. “—I suppose I enjoyed the way you wanted to save me.”

Era algo temporal, sin ataduras.

She nodded slowly, fingers running along the seam of the linen sheet. “Crowther talked so much about the long term and making sure you didn’t lose interest, and how I had to keep it secret, that no one could know.

—¿Cuándo te diste cuenta de que no sabía que debías morir? —preguntó en vez de ponerse en pie.

I thought they trusted me.” She was quiet for a moment. “Ilva told me just before the solstice.

Kaine soltó un largo suspiro.

You probably realised.”

—El primer día que fuiste al Reducto.

She took his silence for confirmation.

Por la cara que pusiste, supe que tú creías que era para siempre.

There was a pause as she remembered something. “Kaine, I don’t think your father’s dead.”

La chica sintió que se le cerraba la garganta.

Kaine looked at her sharply. “What?”

Kaine apartó la mirada.

“When we rescued Luc, there was a lich.

—Al principio me pareció… divertido.

He told Sebastian that he was Atreus.

Estuve esperando a que te dieras cuenta. —Helena sintió que se le ruborizaba el cuello—.

He was guarding the door to the room Luc was in.”

Cuando te dije que deberías haber sabido que me castigarían, pensé que comprenderías que todo era una farsa, pero no lo hiciste.

“No,” Kaine said, his voice shaking. “No.

Luego supuse que te lo contarían esa misma noche o al día siguiente, pero tú seguiste viniendo.

He died.

Imaginé que tus superiores querrían algo más, aunque para entonces ya era evidente que no te lo estaban contando todo.

If he were still alive, he would have come back.

Yo estuve a punto de hacerlo un par de veces, pero… —suspiró—.

For my mother.”

Supongo que estaba disfrutando de que quisieras salvarme.

His pupils had shrunken into sharp points of black, the denial stark.

Helena asintió con pesadez y, con los dedos, acarició la costura de la sábana de lino.

“He was a lich,” she said as gently as she could. “Would he have wanted her to see him like that?”

—Crowther hizo mucho hincapié en los objetivos a largo plazo, en que debía asegurarme de que tú no perdieras el interés y en que todo era secreto, que nadie podía saberlo.

He started to speak several times as if to protest but then stopped. “What happened?”

Pensaba que confiaban en mí. —Se quedó callada unos segundos—.

“Soren and Sebastian killed him.

Ilva me lo contó poco antes del solsticio.

He was between us and Luc.

Supongo que te diste cuenta.

We didn’t have time to find the talisman, though.

Ella tomó su silencio como una confirmación.

You didn’t know he was Undying?”

Se produjo una pausa en la que recordó algo más.

He shook his head. “I thought he was arrested before all that began.” He drew a scoffing breath, his expression growing bitter. “So in the end, he didn’t even manage to die for her.”

—Kaine, creo que tu padre no está muerto.

“Your mother?”

La miró con intensidad.

He nodded slowly. “It was all because of her.

—¿Cómo?

I know what people said about them, about why he married her, but he—adored her.

—Cuando rescatamos a Luc, había un liche.

She was life itself to him.

Le dijo a Sebastian que se llamaba Atreus.

When I was born and she was sick, he grew obsessed with keeping her well, not allowing visitors or any potential disease near her.

Estaba custodiando la puerta de la habitación donde lo tenían retenido.

Morrough claimed he could cure her, that she’d live forever.”

—No —replicó Kaine con voz trémula—.

“He must not know what happened after he was arrested,” Helena said.

No.

There was a strained look in Kaine’s eyes. “Likely not.”

Mi padre murió.

“If he knew, do you think—?”

Si siguiera con vida, habría regresado.

Kaine shook his head. “I’m sure he’d blame me.

Por mi madre.

He always did.” There was a pause, and he looked over at her. “Speaking of dying, or rather, not dying … would you mind telling me why I haven’t?”

Las pupilas se le habían contraído hasta formar unos puntos nítidos de color negro.

Helena suddenly found the thread count of the sheets fascinating.

Se negaba a creerlo.

“It was a failed experiment.

—Era un liche —repitió Helena con todo el tacto posible—.

Bennet spent weeks trying to heal it, and everything he did made it worse.

¿Habría querido verla en ese estado?

When it was finally deemed a failure, he tried to scrap my body, but the array was pulling so much energy from the talisman, he couldn’t touch it.

Kaine abrió la boca en varias ocasiones, como si quisiera protestar, pero después pareció pensarlo mejor.

He assumed that eventually the energy would run out, or my body would incinerate around it, so they sent me home, because they didn’t want the potential fallout to contaminate the new lab.

—¿Qué sucedió?

“Since my miraculous recovery, Bennet’s tried to repeat the experiment.

—Soren y Sebastian lo mataron.

Every subject has died, slowly and terribly, and Bennet cannot find any explanation for why I alone survived.

Se interpuso entre nosotros y Luc.

You are the only person who has never questioned my survival, and I would like to know why.”

Pero no tuvimos tiempo de arrancarle el talismán.

There was a long pause.

¿No sabías que era un inmarcesible?

Helena cleared her throat. “I had this amulet of the Holdfasts’.

Él negó con la cabeza.

A holy relic, you could say.

—Creía que lo habían arrestado antes de que comenzara la guerra. —Cogió aire con una mueca sarcástica; su expresión se volvió amarga—.

Ilva gave it to me when I became a healer, and it helped.”

Así que, al final, ni siquiera fue capaz de morir por ella.

“Helped?” The scepticism in his voice was heavy.

—¿Por tu madre?

“I could—work longer.” She avoided his eyes. “I didn’t get tired or—burn out when I had it.

Kaine asintió.

When you were injured, you’d deteriorated so much that the array was using more energy and resources than you had.

—Lo hizo por ella.

I thought since it had helped me maybe it would work for you, too, give you enough strength to recover.”

Sé lo que la gente decía de ellos, los motivos por los que se casaron, pero en realidad mi padre… la adoraba.

His eyebrows rose. “What kind of relic would have the power to do that?”

Era lo único que le daba sentido a su vida.

She coughed.

Cuando nací y ella se puso enferma, se obsesionó con protegerla.

She should probably lie, given that telling the truth was possibly treason.

No permitía visitas ni nada que alterara su descanso.

But she couldn’t think of a lie to tell.

Morrough le prometió que la curaría y viviría para siempre.

She’d already committed treason anyway.

—Entonces no sabrá todo lo que sucedió después de que lo arrestaran —repuso Helena.

“The Stone of the Heavens,” she said. “I didn’t know that’s what it was, and it’s not—really what the stories said.

Los ojos de Kaine reflejaron un cansancio profundo.

It was something made by the Necromancer, but Orion ended up with it, and people just assumed it was heaven-sent.”

—Probablemente no.

“And they gave it to you?” Kaine’s eyes were narrowed.

—De haberlo sabido, ¿crees que…?

“Apparently, it—chose me.

Kaine negó con la cabeza.

It doesn’t work for most people.”

—Estoy seguro de que me culpa a mí.

Kaine had his hands on his hips. “And that’s how you healed me?”

Como siempre. —Se produjo un silencio, y después le lanzó una mirada a Helena—.

She gave a tight nod. “That’s how I healed you.”

Hablando de morir, o más bien de lo contrario, ¿podrías explicarme por qué sigo vivo?

He was silent for a long time.

De repente, a Helena le pareció fascinante contar los hilos de la sábana.

She couldn’t read his expression, couldn’t tell if he believed her.

—El sello era un experimento fallido.

“Where is it now?”

Bennet se pasó semanas tratando de arreglarlo, pero no hizo más que empeorar la situación.

“Gone,” she said, averting her eyes. “It’s gone now.”

Cuando finalmente aceptó su derrota, quiso arrancármelo del cuerpo, pero el sello consumía tanta energía del talismán que era incapaz de tocarlo.

He sighed. “Well, I suppose it makes sense they wouldn’t let you keep it, if I’m what you used it on.”

Dio por hecho que la energía se agotaría en algún momento, o que mi cuerpo acabaría descomponiéndose, y por eso me mandaron a casa, porque no querían que las posibles consecuencias contaminaran el laboratorio recién estrenado.

She forced a self-deprecating smile.

»Como me he recuperado milagrosamente, Bennet está intentando repetir el experimento.

It was probably best he thought that. “Ilva wasn’t pleased.”

Hasta ahora, todos los sujetos han muerto, de una forma lenta y horrible, y no logra entender por qué soy el único que ha sobrevivido.

“I imagine not.

Tú eres la única persona que nunca ha cuestionado que saliera adelante, y me gustaría saber por qué.

Were there any other repercussions?”

Se hizo un silencio que Helena rompió aclarándose la garganta.

“Well, I was supposed t—” She swallowed. “—to kill you, but I got out of that.

—Tenía un amuleto de los Holdfast.

So I guess it all worked out in the end.”

Podríamos decir que era una reliquia sagrada.

She managed another smile, but he did not return it.

Ilva me lo regaló cuando me hice sanadora.

His expression had gone cold and empty. “This is your idea of things working out?”

Y me ayudaba.

Her face fell, and just as suddenly it was all back: the reality of all that existed between them.

—¿Te ayudaba? —La incredulidad era evidente en su voz.

That he would have preferred it if she’d killed him; that that was what he’d wanted.

—Me permitía… trabajar más horas —respondió esquivando su mirada—.

Instead she was sitting on his bed, smiling over how it had worked out so nicely for everyone else now that she had him on a leash.

No me cansaba ni… se desgastaba mi poder cuando lo tenía.

“No, no, of course not.

Tus heridas eran tan graves que te estabas deteriorando más rápido de lo que tu cuerpo podía sostener.

Sorry.”

El sello estaba drenando toda tu energía.

She drew back, turning, trying to find her clothes.

Como a mí me había funcionado, supuse que a ti también podría ayudarte, que te daría fuerzas para recuperarte.

“What are you doing?” Kaine leaned forward and caught her by the ankle before she was halfway across the bed.

Kaine elevó las cejas.

“I think I should go now,” she muttered, her throat tight, trying to slip free.

—¿Qué reliquia tiene semejante poder?

“Why?”

Helena carraspeó.

Her heart was in her throat. “I know you didn’t want any of this; I didn’t mean to act like it was all fine.”

Debería mentir, puesto que decir la verdad podía considerarse traición.

His expression hardened, and he dragged her back across the bed.

Sin embargo, no se le ocurría ninguna mentira.

She tried desperately to get free. “Can I—at least put my clothes on before you get angry?

Además, ya había cometido traición.

Please.”

—La Gema de los Cielos —contestó—.

He stared at her. “I wasn’t talking about me.

Yo no sabía lo que era, y en realidad no es… lo que cuentan las historias.

I was talking about you.”

Fue el Nigromante quien la creó, pero Orion se la arrebató y la gente asumió que había sido un regalo de los cielos.

“Me?” She was confused enough that she stopped struggling.

—¿Y te la dieron a ti? —Kaine entornó los ojos.

“Yes.

—Por lo visto, me… eligió.

You.

No funciona con la mayoría de las personas.

The Resistance has latched on to you like a parasite, and you think it’s all worked out because they’re kind enough to keep you alive while they eat you?”

Kaine tenía los brazos cruzados.

“It’s not like that,” she said sharply.

—¿Y así me curaste?

“Six years in a war hospital.

Helena se limitó a asentir.

How many people have you saved for them?

—Así te curé.

I doubt you know.

El chico quedó en silencio durante un largo rato.

But was that enough for them?

Helena no consiguió descifrar su expresión, no tenía forma de saber si la creía o no.

No.

—¿Y dónde está la gema ahora?

The moment there was another advantage to gain, they sold you for the ports.

—No la tengo —respondió evitando su mirada—.

I’ve seen workhorses treated better; they would have turned you into glue once you weren’t good for anything else.” He sneered. “But I suppose that’s how it’s always been.

Ya no.

It’s only the war stallions like the Bayards who are retired to the countryside.”

Kaine suspiró.

“Shut up,” she said, kicking sharply and freeing herself.

—Bueno, supongo que tiene sentido que no te dejaran quedártela después de haberla usado conmigo.

Her face was hot with anger. “You think I don’t know I’m expendable?

La chica forzó una sonrisa culpable.

When you see fit to remind me of it at every turn?

Quizá era mejor que pensase eso.

Well, you don’t have any right to be angry about that, when you’re just as much a part of it as any of them.

—Ilva no estaba muy contenta.

You knew what was happening, and that I didn’t, and you still chose to be as cruel as you were.

—Supongo que no.

At least Ilva and Crowther manipulated me for a reason.” She looked away from him. “When were you even that kind?”

¿Sufriste alguna consecuencia?

He was silent.

—Bueno, tenía que m… —tragó saliva— matarte, pero finalmente me libré de hacerlo.

She looked away.

Así que al final todo se ha arreglado.

“I’m sorry,” he said after a moment.

Consiguió esbozar otra sonrisa, pero Kaine no la correspondió.

She gave a mirthless laugh. “Yes, you’ve apologised before, but you don’t change, so it doesn’t really mean anything.”

Su expresión se endureció, tornándose distante, vacía.

“You’re right.”

—¿De verdad crees que lo hemos arreglado?

He sat down on the edge of the bed and pressed his face into his hands. “I’m sorry for that, too.

La cara de Helena se descompuso y, de repente, lo recordó: esa realidad que se interponía entre ambos.

I never meant for any of it to go so far.

Que él habría preferido que ella lo matase, que eso era lo que él había querido.

I knew the mission you’d been sent with, and I was sure I’d be immune, but realising it was all real for you—when it would work, and I’d find myself falling for the trap I’d chosen—I’d do whatever it took to make you stop.

En cambio, estaba sentada en su cama, diciendo con una sonrisa que todo había salido bien porque había conseguido atarlo a la vida.

It hadn’t occurred to me that they wouldn’t tell you.”

—No, no quería decir eso.

She bit the inside of her lip. “They thought I’d be more convincing that way.”

Lo siento.

He nodded slowly. “I thought if I was just cruel enough, you’d give up.

Se apartó y se giró para buscar su ropa.

That you’d have a limit, that once I found it, you’d stop—finding ways to emotionally blindside me.” He gave a low sigh. “I spent such a long time waiting to be betrayed, I didn’t want to care when it happened.

—¿Qué estás haciendo? —Kaine se inclinó y la cogió por el tobillo antes de que se levantara de la cama.

I was trying to hurt you, but I am so sorry that I did.”

—Creo que debería irme ya —masculló Helena con un nudo en la garganta mientras intentaba liberarse de su agarre.

She stared out at the horizon, shaking her head slowly. “I don’t know why I kept trying.

—¿Por qué?

You just had these moments when I could see how little of you was real.

Helena tenía el corazón en un puño.

When you’d forget to pretend, you always seemed so lonely.

—Sé que no querías nada de esto.

And I was lonely, too.” She looked down at the scar in her palm. “I used to think that we were the reverse of each other.

No pretendía fingir que todo iba bien.

Now—” She looked at him and extended her hand. “—I can’t help feeling like we’re mostly the same.”

La expresión de Kaine se endureció, y la arrastró de nuevo hacia la cama.

He entwined his fingers with hers and pulled her close, and this time she let him take her into his arms, his face buried in the curve of her neck.

Helena trató desesperadamente de librarse de su agarre.

Life was not cold.

—¿Me dejas al menos… ponerme la ropa antes de enfadarte, por favor?

Then he sat back enough to look at her.

Kaine la miró con intensidad.

She watched the way his eyes moved, taking her in piece by piece as if he didn’t want to miss a single detail.

—No me refería a mí.

His hands slid up around her throat, warm and possessive, thumb covering the scar below her jaw as he kissed between her eyes. “You’re a far better person than I am.

Estaba hablando de ti.

This world doesn’t deserve you at all.”

—¿De mí? —Le resultó tan desconcertante que dejó de resistirse.

She shook her head. “I could survive without having to go as far as you did.

—Sí, de ti.

That doesn’t make me better.”

La Resistencia se te ha enganchado como un parásito y tú crees que todo ha salido bien porque son lo bastante generosos de permitirte vivir mientras te devoran por dentro.

“You keep people alive.

—No es así —replicó Helena con dureza.

You touch them and your instinct is to save them, no matter who they are or what they’ve done to you.

—Seis años en un hospital de guerra.

That is not a trait we share.

¿A cuántas personas has salvado para la causa?

It’s far more difficult than calculating all the ways to kill someone.

Dudo que lo sepas.

And it costs you more.”

Pero ¿les parece suficiente?

Their foreheads touched, and she closed her eyes.

No.

It was as though their souls were touching, too.

En cuanto hubo otra manera de aprovecharse de ti, te vendieron al mejor postor.

She wanted to spend her life lost in that moment, but she’d been gone for a day, and no one knew where she was.

Incluso a los caballos de tiro se les trata mejor; deberían haberte convertido en pegamento cuando ya no les serviste para nada más. —Soltó un bufido de desdén—.

She couldn’t stay.

Pero supongo que siempre ha sido así.

“I have to go back.”

Los únicos que disfrutan de una jubilación en el campo son los sementales de guerra como los Bayard.

He didn’t let go. “You should eat.”

—Cállate —le espetó Helena, y propinó una patada para soltarse.

“I have to go,” she said firmly, trying to rise.

Tenía la cara encendida de rabia—.

“Take a bath,” he said, catching her waist. “I’ll order something to be brought up.

¿Crees que no sé que soy prescindible?

Anything you want.”

Tú te has encargado de recordármelo cada vez que has tenido una oportunidad.

“Kaine.” She pulled his hands off. “You can’t keep me here.

Pero no tienes ningún derecho a enfadarte por ello, porque has formado parte de todo esto desde el principio.

I have to go.”

Tú sabías lo que estaba pasando y yo no, y aun así decidiste seguir siendo cruel.

His expression flickered, just enough to reveal a shard of possessiveness, something ravenous and desperate.

Al menos, Ilva y Crowther me manipularon por un motivo. —Apartó la mirada—.

Then it vanished and he let her stand, resignation sweeping across his face.

¿Tú cuándo te has mostrado así de generoso?

She reached out, her fingers brushing back his hair. “Don’t worry.

Kaine se quedó callado.

I’m always going to come back to you.”

Helena se giró.

—Perdóname —dijo él tras unos instantes.

Ella no pudo más que reír, sin alegría.

—Sí, ya te has disculpado, pero no cambias, así que no significa nada.

—Tienes razón.

Se sentó al borde de la cama y se tapó el rostro con las manos.

—También te pido disculpas por eso.

Nunca quise que esto llegara tan lejos.

Sabía la misión a la que te habían enviado, y yo estaba convencido de que sería inmune, pero al darme cuenta de que para ti era real, cuando vi que estaba funcionando y que estaba cayendo en mi propia trampa, hice todo lo posible para que te alejaras.

No se me pasó por la cabeza que tus superiores no te avisarían.

Helena se mordió el labio.

—Creyeron que así sería más convincente.

Kaine asintió con pesar.

—Pensé que, si te trataba con crueldad, te rendirías.

Que tendrías un límite y que, cuando lo alcanzaras, dejarías de… abrirte paso por mis emociones. —Se le escapó un suspiro—.

Me he pasado tanto tiempo esperando que me traicionaras que no quería que me importase cuando sucediera.

Quería hacerte daño, pero siento habértelo hecho.

Helena se quedó contemplando el horizonte y sacudió la cabeza lentamente.

—No sé por qué seguí intentándolo.

Hubo momentos en los que vi claramente que toda esa fachada era mentira.

Cuando se te olvidaba fingir, siempre parecías sentirte muy solo.

Y yo también. —Bajó la vista hacia la cicatriz que tenía en la palma de la mano—.

Antes creía que éramos totalmente opuestos.

Ahora… —lo miró y extendió una mano—, no puedo evitar pensar que somos prácticamente iguales.

Kaine entrelazó sus dedos con los de ella y la atrajo hacia sí.

Esta vez, Helena se dejó caer en sus brazos para que Kaine enterrara su rostro en el hueco de su cuello.

La vida no era fría.

Después, se enderezó para mirarla.

Helena observó cómo sus ojos recorrían cada detalle de su cuerpo, como si no quisieran perderse nada.

Kaine le envolvió la garganta con la mano en un gesto pasional y posesivo, y luego le acarició la cicatriz que tenía debajo de la mandíbula antes de darle un beso en la frente.

—Tú eres mucho mejor persona que yo.

El mundo no te merece.

Helena negó con la cabeza.

—Podría sobrevivir sin llegar tan lejos como tú.

Eso no me hace mejor.

—Mantienes con vida a la gente.

Nada más tocarlos, tu instinto es salvarlos, sin importar quiénes sean o lo que te hayan hecho.

Esa cualidad no la compartimos.

Es mucho más compleja que pensar en todas las formas en las que podrías asesinar a alguien.

Y te pasa una mayor factura.

Sus frentes se tocaron, y Helena cerró los ojos.

Era como si sus almas se estuvieran rozando.

Quería quedarse ahí, absorta en ese momento, pero ya había desaparecido un día entero, y nadie sabía dónde estaba.

No podía hacerlo.

—Tengo que volver.

Kaine no la soltó.

—Deberías comer algo.

—He de irme —repitió con firmeza e hizo amago de levantarse.

—Date un baño —le pidió tomándola de la muñeca—.

Pediré que te suban algo de comer, lo que quieras.

—Kaine —apartó sus manos—, no puedes encerrarme aquí.

Tengo que marcharme.

Dudó un instante, lo justo para mostrar un atisbo de instinto posesivo, algo voraz y desesperado.

Pero se desvaneció y la dejó ponerse en pie con resignación.

Helena estiró la mano y le apartó unos mechones de la cara.

—No te preocupes.

Siempre volveré a ti.

CHAPTER 53

Aprilis 1787

CAPÍTULO 53

KAINE’S CHIMAERA WAS SOMEHOW EVEN LARGER WHEN encountered lucid.

Abrilis 1787

When Helena was dressed and ready to leave, rather than be smuggled through the city, Kaine led her to the high open roof.

Una vez recuperada la lucidez, la quimera de Kaine se le antojó aún más grande.

The creature stood, stretching and yawning, baring fangs longer than Helena’s fingers, wings spreading so wide they nearly blanketed the rooftop.

Cuando Helena terminó de vestirse y estuvo ya lista para marcharse, en vez de volver a la ciudad de forma discreta, Kaine la llevó a la azotea.

The chimaera cantered stiffly towards Kaine, eerie yellow eyes watching Helena, the whites showing, muzzle curled in warning.

Allí estaba la criatura, estirándose y bostezando, dejando a la vista unos colmillos más largos que los dedos de Helena.

“Be nice, Amaris,” Kaine said chidingly, scratching the chimaera behind her ears.

Las alas se desplegaban de tal modo que ocupaban casi toda la superficie de la azotea.

Amaris drooped her head, her lip still curling to the gums, eyes fastened on Helena.

La quimera fue hasta Kaine al trote y abrió sus escalofriantes ojos amarillentos para observar a Helena; torció el hocico en señal de advertencia.

It was for the best that Helena had been delirious the night before; she would never have climbed on that animal knowing it was real.

—Amaris, pórtate bien —la reprendió Kaine al tiempo que le rascaba por detrás de las orejas.

Kaine patted the wolfen monster and then knelt, running his hands up and down a foreleg.

Amaris dejó caer la cabeza, pero siguió enseñando las encías sin apartar la vista de Helena.

Helena could see the horse shape of the leg, but it ended in a paw with huge talon-like claws.

Fue una bendición que la noche anterior Helena hubiera estado delirando; jamás se habría atrevido a montarse sobre esa criatura de haber sabido que era real.

She backed away, giving more space.

Kaine acarició al monstruo lobuno y después se arrodilló para masajearle la pata delantera.

Despite Kaine’s desire that they all be friends, it was obvious that Amaris did not like anyone but him.

La chica vio que tenía patas de caballo, pero acababan en unas garras enormes.

“She’s not growling at you,” Kaine said before Helena could take another step back. “Bennet spliced the legs wrong when he made her.

Helena dio un paso hacia atrás para darle más espacio.

Whenever she grows, the nerves get stretched out, and I have to fix them.”

A pesar de que Kaine quería que se hiciesen amigas, era evidente que a Amaris no le caía bien nadie salvo su dueño.

“What do you mean?” Helena watched.

—No está gruñendo por ti —le explicó Kaine antes de que Helena retrocediera un poco más—.

She could tell he was using his resonance as his fingers brushed along the length of the foreleg.

Bennet ensambló mal las patas cuando la creó.

“Bennet only cares about the aesthetics when it comes to the chimaeras.

Cuando crece, se le estiran los nervios y tengo que arreglarlos.

He forces things to fit together even when they shouldn’t.

—¿A qué te refieres? —Helena lo observó con atención.

The reason the chimaeras are so dangerous is that they’re all rabid with pain.

Se percató de que estaba usando la resonancia mientras le masajeaba la pata delantera.

They usually die because the stress kills them.

—A Bennet solo le interesa la parte estética de las quimeras.

When Amaris arrived, she bit me about fifty times during the first week.

Une piezas a la fuerza, sin importarle la funcionalidad.

You may recall that my back was still in tatters at the time.

Las quimeras son tan peligrosas porque están rabiando de dolor.

I nearly snapped her neck after the tenth time, but I thought, I’m in so much pain I’d love to bite someone.

Mueren del estrés que sufren.

Why would it be different for her?

Cuando me dieron a Amaris, me mordió unas cincuenta veces la primera semana.

She was all puppy then, but legs like a foal.

Tal vez recuerdes que por aquel entonces todavía tenía la espalda destrozada.

Constantly tripping and breaking her wings.” He glanced back at Helena. “I had a notion of the taming capacity of pain relief, and you’d mentioned how flawed the transmutations were, so I tried to fix what I could.

Estuve a punto de partirle el cuello al décimo mordisco, pero pensé: «A mí me duele también tanto que me encantaría morder a alguien.

Once she realised I wasn’t there to hurt her, she stopped biting.”

¿Por qué no va a hacer ella lo mismo?».

He straightened and patted Amaris just below a huge wing.

Por entonces era un cachorro, pero parecía un potro.

The feathers were as long as Helena’s arms.

Se tropezaba y se rompía las alas una y otra vez. —Volvió la vista hacia Helena—.

He rubbed his knuckles between Amaris’s eyes. “She warmed up to me after that.

Para entonces ya había aprendido la contención del alivio del dolor, y tú me habías comentado los numerosos defectos que tenían las transmutaciones, así que intenté arreglar todo lo que pude.

She’s the only survivor of the whole batch.

Cuando Amaris comprendió que no iba a hacerle daño, dejó de morderme.

Bennet tried to take her back, wanted to see why she’d worked.

Se enderezó y acarició a la quimera por debajo de un ala enorme.

She nearly took his head off.

Las plumas eran del tamaño del brazo de Helena.

Didn’t you?”

Kaine frotó los nudillos entre los ojos de Amaris.

He rumpled the thick fur.

—Y, después, me fue cogiendo cariño.

“Come meet her, she’ll be nice now.” He gestured Helena over.

Es la única superviviente de toda su camada.

He took her hand and let Amaris sniff it.

Bennet quiso que se la devolviera para ver por qué había salido bien.

Her teeth remained bared, but her tail slowly began to swing and her wings relaxed.

Estuvo a punto de arrancarle la cabeza, ¿verdad? —Le desordenó el espeso pelaje—.

He guided Helena to bury her fingers in the thick fur and scratch behind an enormous, pricked ear.

Ven a conocerla, se portará bien.

Helena could feel his eyes on her as she tentatively let her resonance creep in.

Le indicó a Helena que se acercara, la cogió de la mano y dejó que Amaris la olfateara.

Amaris trembled but didn’t move or snarl.

La quimera siguió enseñando los dientes, pero empezó a mover la cola y relajó las alas.

She could feel how haphazardly assembled Amaris was, bones and tissue not meant to be combined but forced together nonetheless.

Kaine hizo que Helena enterrara los dedos en el espeso pelaje y rascara por detrás de una oreja enorme y puntiaguda.

Unlike the chimaeras she’d examined in her lab, it was clear someone had tried to correct the excessive flaws, to properly join the muscles, smooth the bone fusions and misjoined ligaments, to block off nerves that caused nothing but pain.

Helena notó que Kaine no dejaba de mirarla mientras permitía que la resonancia se extendiera hacia el cuerpo de la quimera.

She tried to imagine this monster as a puppy, a foal, a hatchling.

Amaris se estremeció, pero no se movió ni gruñó.

Innocent and juvenile and then—

Sintió lo mal ensamblada que estaba Amaris; tenía huesos y tejidos que no deberían estar juntos pero que estaban unidos a la fuerza.

Pain and mutilation.

A diferencia de las quimeras que había examinado en el laboratorio, era evidente que alguien había intentado corregir los fallos más graves: coser bien los músculos, suavizar las articulaciones y los ligamentos cruzados, bloquear los nervios para que no sintiera tanto dolor…

Of course the chimaeras were savage.

Intentó imaginar a ese monstruo de cachorro, como un potro o un polluelo.

How could anything endure so much hurt and not learn only to bite?

Inocente y joven, y entonces…

“You’ve done remarkable work on her,” she said, her mouth dry. “Is this how you learned to heal?”

Dolor y mutilación.

“I suppose it was some good practice.”

Por supuesto que las quimeras eran salvajes.

He looked out over the city, spread below like a glittering crown.

¿Cómo iban a soportar tanto dolor sin aprender a morder?

Lumithia had yet to rise, leaving whole swaths of the East Island in darkness, but the Alchemy Tower stood above it all, its beacon ever burning.

—Has hecho un trabajo excepcional —dijo con la boca seca—.

“We should go now.

¿Así es como aprendiste a sanar?

It’s dark enough to fly without being sighted.”

—Supongo que me sirvió de práctica.

IT WAS ONE THING TO pet Amaris; it was quite another to mount her.

Kaine contempló la ciudad, que se extendía como una corona resplandeciente.

Helena was certain the wolf could bite her in half if so inclined.

Lumitia todavía no había salido, por lo que había franjas en la isla Este que permanecían a oscuras.

Kaine stood at Amaris’s head, scratching her ears, while Helena grasped the leather harness and clambered up.

Sin embargo, la Torre de Alquimia se alzaba sobre todo lo demás, con su faro siempre brillante.

It took an embarrassingly long time, like scaling a furry mountain.

—Tenemos que irnos ya.

Helena was worried about kneeing or elbowing Amaris and struggled to get a good grip.

Está tan oscuro que podemos pasar desapercibidos.

Kaine swung up behind her in one easy movement.

Una cosa era acariciar a Amaris y otra muy distinta ir subida sobre su lomo.

He was barely seated before Amaris leapt off the roof.

Helena estaba convencida de que, si quisiera, el lobo podría partirla por la mitad con los dientes.

They plummeted straight down and then the huge wings spread out, catching the air and carrying them skywards.

Kaine se quedó junto a la cabeza de Amaris, para rascarle detrás de las orejas, mientras Helena se agarraba al arnés de cuero y se subía a la montura.

Kaine flew Amaris so high, the air grew thin.

Tardó tanto tiempo en hacerlo que empezó a darle vergüenza; era como escalar una montaña peluda.

They kept their distance from the city and towers, flying near the mountains until they reached the dam.

Helena temía darle un rodillazo o un codazo, así que no sabía cómo colocarse.

Amaris banked sharply, so fast the Outpost blurred and the wind from her wings rattled the windows as they sped past.

Kaine se montó de un salto a su espalda.

One of the factories had a large open roof that they landed on.

Apenas se había sentado cuando Amaris saltó del tejado.

Helena’s legs scarcely held her as she slid off, desperately grateful for solid ground and convinced that humans were not meant to fly, and it was an abomination for them to do so.

En un primer momento, se desplomaron hacia el suelo, pero entonces desplegó esas enormes alas para aprovechar una corriente de aire llevándolos hacia los cielos.

She tried to appear grateful and not look too green as she scuttled away from the chimaera.

Amaris volaba tan alto que el oxígeno comenzó a escasear.

Kaine followed her.

Mantuvieron distancia con la ciudad y las torres, y volaron junto a las montañas hasta la presa.

Now that the introduction to Amaris and the journey were over, there was an undeniable look of resentment in his eyes again, as if letting her return to Headquarters was not yet something he was convinced of.

La quimera descendió a tal velocidad que el Reducto pasó como un borrón y las ráfagas que provocaron sus alas hicieron vibrar las ventanas del edificio.

Helena pretended not to notice as she headed for the gate, but it only made his mood darken.

Aterrizaron en el patio de una de las fábricas.

Finally, she stopped. “What is it?”

Cuando se bajó, Helena sintió que las piernas la sostenían a duras penas y agradeció de corazón que hubiera un suelo firme bajo sus pies.

“Don’t go,” he said softly.

Quedó convencida de que los humanos no estaban hechos para volar y que hacerlo era una abominación.

“You know I have to.”

Trató de parecer agradecida en vez de a punto de vomitar, pero se alejó de la quimera.

He shook his head. “No, I don’t.

Kaine la siguió.

They don’t care about you.”

Ahora que le había presentado a Amaris y el viaje había terminado, volvía a haber cierto brillo de resentimiento en sus ojos, como si todavía no tuviera muy claro si debía dejarla regresar al Cuartel General.

The words were like a raw nerve being plucked.

Helena fingió no darse cuenta mientras se acercaba a la cancela, pero eso solo consiguió ponerlo de peor humor.

The pain hummed inside her.

Al final se detuvo.

Before, she would have denied it, because Luc was there and he would never turn on her, but that was no longer true.

—¿Qué sucede?

Still, she was unmoved.

—No te vayas —expresó en tono suave.

She shook her head. “We can’t let the Undying win.

—Sabes que tengo que irme.

There is too much at stake.

El chico negó con la cabeza.

I have to go where I can do good.”

—No, no es cierto.

A look of fury joined his resentment. “No, you don’t.

No les importas.

It doesn’t matter how many times you break yourself, the gods don’t care.

Las palabras le dolieron como si hubieran tocado un nervio.

There’s no reward.

El dolor resonó por todo su cuerpo.

This”—he threw his hand out, gesturing at the city, the mountains, and the black sky that Lumithia now radiated down from—“is the Abyss.

En el pasado lo habría negado, porque tenía a Luc y él jamás le habría dado la espalda, pero ese ya no era el caso.

We’re already in it.

Sin embargo, no cedió.

None of it matters.

Negó con firmeza.

Sacrifice and pain, the universe does not care.”

—No podemos permitir que ganen los inmarcesibles.

“You’re wrong,” she said.

Nos jugamos demasiado.

He opened his mouth to argue, to offer an endless list of examples of how cold and uncaring the world was, but she didn’t need to be told.

Tengo que ir adonde sirva de algo.

“You’re wrong because I’m part of the universe,” she said. “A tiny piece, I admit, maybe never an important or mathematically significant one, but still a piece.

La furia se sumó al resentimiento en los ojos de Kaine.

You and I are not separate from it.

—No, no es cierto.

No one is.

Da igual cuántas veces te rompas, a los dioses no les importa.

It matters to me, everyone who’s died and everyone who will, and everyone who suffers.

No habrá recompensa.

As long as I exist, I will always care.

Esto… —señaló con una mano la ciudad, las montañas y el firmamento negro desde el que refulgía Lumitia—, esto es el Abismo.

And that means that part of the universe does.” She smiled at him. “Doesn’t that make it all a little brighter?”

Ya estamos dentro.

He looked despairing.

Todo lo demás da igual.

She gave a helpless shrug. “I want to do good in the world.

Al universo le importa un comino el sacrificio y el dolor.

That was what my father wanted most for me.” She looked down at her hands. “I know most people won’t think I have.

—Te equivocas —replicó Helena.

I’ve done things now that I don’t think I’m supposed to be forgiven for.

Kaine abrió la boca para protestar, para enumerar una lista interminable de ejemplos que confirmaban que el mundo era frío y ajeno, pero ella no necesitaba oírlo.

But I want to be remembered as someone who tried at least.”

—Te equivocas porque yo formo parte del universo —siguió—.

She stepped back, but he caught her.

Un trocito de nada, es cierto, tal vez insignificante en términos matemáticos, pero formo parte de igual forma.

“Helena—”

Tú y yo no somos ajenos a nada.

She pulled free. “Be careful, Kaine.

Nadie lo es.

Don’t die.”

A mí me importan las personas que han muerto y las que morirán, y también los que sufren.

“CROWTHER’S LOOKING FOR YOU,” THE gatehouse guard said as he let her in.

Me importarán mientras siga con vida.

Helena nodded and headed to the Tower.

Y eso significa que a esa parte del universo le importa. —Le dedicó una sonrisa—.

Crowther was seated in his office, his right arm strapped to his body as if it were paralysed again, and he looked at Helena with a degree of disgust unlike anything she’d ever seen before.

¿No te parece un poco más alentador?

It reminded her of how the guild students used to look at her, but intensified by magnitudes.

Parecía desolado.

The fingers of his right arm were squeezed into a fist.

Aun así, Helena se encogió de hombros.

Which meant it still worked and he was intentionally depriving himself of it.

—Quiero hacer el bien en este mundo.

It took her a moment to understand.

Eso es lo que quería mi padre por encima de todo. —Se miró las manos—.

This was because she was a necromancer now.

Sé que la mayoría de la gente no lo valorará.

“I was told you wanted me,” she said, pretending not to notice his expression.

He hecho cosas que dudo que me perdonen.

“Hours ago,” he said through clenched teeth.

Pero me gustaría que me recordaran como alguien que lo intentó, al menos.

“I’m here now.”

Dio un paso hacia atrás, pero Kaine le tomó la mano.

Crowther snapped the ignition rings on his left hand, and a deep red orb of flames filled his hand before his fingers squeezed into a fist, skin glowing for a moment before the light extinguished. “The prisoner you brought back refuses to cooperate without you, and Ilva …” His expression twisted with fury. “Ilva insists on a light touch until we know who he is.

—Helena…

I have wasted an entire day waiting for you.

Ella se zafó.

Where were you?”

—Ten cuidado, Kaine.

Helena avoided his eyes. “Ilva said it would be best to keep out of sight until the official story had circulated.”

No mueras.

“That’s not what I asked.”

—Crowther te está buscando —le dijo el guardia de la entrada al dejarla pasar.

Helena set her jaw and met his eyes. “I was with Ferron, but I’m sure you already worked that out.”

Helena asintió y se dirigió hacia la Torre.

He gave a scathing laugh that made her scalp crawl.

Crowther se encontraba en su despacho.

The venom in his expression was so shocking, it was as if she were not even human anymore.

Tenía el brazo atado al cuerpo, como si se le hubiera paralizado de nuevo, y miró a Helena con un asco que jamás había visto en él.

“It’s not as if I wanted to use necromancy,” she said, deciding to drag the unspoken source of his fury into the open. “There was no other way.

Le recordó a cómo la miraban los alumnos del gremio, aunque de una manera mucho más intensa.

Soren wasn’t near recovered enough for a mission like that.

Los dedos del brazo derecho formaban un puño, lo que significaba que aún le funcionaba, pero que había decidido privarse de ese movimiento.

What was I supposed to do?

Tardó unos instantes en entenderlo.

Let Luc die?”

Lo hacía porque Helena era ahora una nigromante.

“What were you supposed to do?” he repeated slowly, standing. “You were supposed to stay in Headquarters.

—Me han dicho que querías verme —afirmó como si no se hubiera percatado de su expresión.

You have one job, Marino, and that is to stay alive and intact so that Ferron can have his weekly proof of life.

—Hace horas —respondió Crowther entre dientes.

But it seems I have expected too much of your skills of deduction, so let me be crystal-clear: Unless you are liaising, you will not set foot outside of Headquarters ever again.

—Pues aquí estoy.

The only reason I am not having you thrown in prison to stand trial for necromancy is because you now exist to keep Ferron in line.”

Crowther chasqueó los anillos de ignición de la mano izquierda y un orbe de llamas relamió sus dedos hasta que los cerró en un puño; la piel centelleó unos segundos antes de que la luz se apagara.

Helena’s throat closed. “It was your plan.

—El prisionero que trajisteis de vuelta se niega a cooperar si no estás presente, e Ilva… —Su expresión se tornó lívida de rabia—.

I was working with what I had.”

Ilva insiste en que seamos cuidadosos hasta que sepamos quién es.

Crowther’s eyes bulged. “My plan?”

He perdido un día entero esperándote.

“It was your informant from the hospital who gave Soren all the information.

¿Dónde estabas?

Where else would Purnell—”

Helena no lo miró a los ojos.

Before she could finish the question, the door burst open, and a boy flew into the room.

—Ilva me dijo que me mantuviera al margen hasta que hicierais circular la historia oficial.

“Where’s Sofia?

—Eso no es lo que te he preguntado.

I tried to find her, but no one will talk to me.

La chica lo miró a los ojos con la mandíbula en tensión.

Where is she?”

—Estaba con Ferron, pero estoy convencida de que eso ya te lo habías imaginado.

It was Ivy, her face dirty, hair tucked up in a cap.

El hombre dejó escapar una carcajada de desprecio que le puso el vello de punta.

Crowther’s gaze slid to Helena. “Marino, perhaps you’d like to tell Ivy here where her older sister, Sofia Purnell, is?”

La miraba con tal animosidad que parecía que Helena había dejado de ser humana.

Ivy turned, and Helena noticed then the resemblance between the hospital orderly and Crowther’s little protégée.

—No fui yo la que quiso usar la nigromancia —explicó, decidida a sonsacarle el origen de su furia—.

A few years apart, different colouring, and Ivy’s features were sharp and foxlike where Sofia was soft.

No había otra opción.

But as she looked, Helena could see the likeness.

Soren no se había recuperado lo suficiente como para embarcarse en una misión así.

“Your sister?” Helena said, her voice straining. “Sofia was your sister?”

¿Qué querías que hiciera?

Beneath the dirt, all colour drained from Ivy’s face.

¿Que dejara morir a Luc?

“Sofia was part of the rescue team that saved Luc.

—¿Que qué quería que hicieras? —repitió lentamente, y se puso en pie—.

She showed us the route through the tunnels to the prison, but during the escape, she was caught in the flood current.

Tendrías que haberte quedado en el Cuartel General.

I thought—I thought”—Helena looked at Crowther—“you sent her.

Solo tenías que hacer una cosa, Marino, y era seguir sana y salva para que Ferron tuviera una prueba de que sigues con vida todas las semanas.

You didn’t send her?”

Pero se ve que he sobrestimado tus capacidades de deducción, así que te lo voy a dejar claro: a menos que estés mandando algún mensaje, no puedes volver a salir del Cuartel General bajo ningún concepto.

Ivy stared at Helena for a moment and then screamed.

El único motivo por el que no te he metido en la cárcel para juzgarte por nigromancia es porque te necesito para mantener a Ferron de nuestra parte.

Helena had never heard such a sound from anyone.

Helena notó que se le hacía un nudo en la garganta.

It exploded out of the girl, so sharp it felt as though the lightbulbs might shatter.

—Tú ideaste ese plan.

White rage swept across Ivy’s face.

Estaba trabajando con lo que tenía.

Helena braced herself, but Ivy whirled on Crowther. “You promised to protect her if I did everything you said!

A Crowther se le salieron los ojos de las órbitas.

She wasn’t supposed to work for you.

—¿Yo?

She was just supposed to be safe!”

—Fue tu informante del hospital la que le dio a Soren toda esa información.

She lunged at him, going right over the desk, as if she intended to claw his eyes out, but before her fingers reached him, a burst of flames materialised and slammed her into the wall.

¿De dónde sacó Purnell si no…?

Ivy hit the floor, and books toppled from the shelves onto her, catching fire as they rained down.

Antes de que Helena pudiera terminar la pregunta, la puerta se abrió de par en par y una chica irrumpió en el despacho.

Crowther had moved, darting like a cat.

—¿Dónde está Sofia?

His years of combat experience showing as he closed in on Ivy.

He intentado buscarla y nadie me dice nada.

“I never told her about tunnels or waterways, or any prison,” Crowther said as his hand clenched in a fist, the fire vanishing. “If she knew that information, it was from your indiscretion.

¿Dónde está?

I warned you to tell her nothing, but you had to talk about all the ways you could travel through the city unseen.

Era Ivy.

Are you glad you impressed her now?

Su rostro estaba sucio y su cabello recogido en una cofia.

I’m sure you made it sound so easy.”

Los ojos de Crowther se posaron sobre Helena.

Helena expected Ivy to spring up, but the girl just stayed there on the floor.

—Marino, ¿quieres decirle a Ivy dónde se encuentra su hermana mayor, Sofia Purnell?

“I wanted her to know the ways out.

Cuando Ivy se giró, Helena se percató del parecido entre la camillera del hospital y la pequeña protegida de Crowther.

I showed her the map and told her about the prison so she wouldn’t go that way,” Ivy said, her voice a whimpering sob.

Aunque se diferenciaban en unos años y en el color del cabello, los rasgos de Ivy eran más marcados y afilados, mientras que Sofia parecía más amable.

“If you had listened to me, she’d be alive,” Crowther said, his voice callous. “I upheld my end of the deal; none of this is my fault.” He kicked her. “Now get out of my sight.

Aun así, resultaba evidente que eran hermanas.

If Lucien Holdfast had been killed in that ridiculous rescue, I would have blamed you.”

—¿Era tu hermana? —dijo Helena con voz estrangulada—.

Ivy picked herself up off the floor without a word, but as she slipped through the door, she looked back for an instant, and there was murder in her eyes.

¿Sofia era tu hermana?

When she was gone, Crowther stepped over and pulled out a radio from inside his desk, holding the transceiver up as it crackled to life.

Ivy palideció bajo toda la suciedad del rostro.

Helena recognised the voice of the guard.

—Sofia formaba parte del equipo de rescate que salvó a Luc.

One of the higher-ups.

Fue ella la que nos mostró la ruta a través de los túneles que llevaban a la prisión, pero, cuando escapamos, la arrastró la corriente.

The string of jargon that Crowther muttered was nearly incomprehensible, but Helena did pick up two phrases: “extremely dangerous” and “neutralised.”

Pensé… pensé… —Helena miró a Crowther— que tú la habías enviado.

He set the transceiver down and looked around his charred office.

¿No fuiste tú?

“Is that really necessary?” Helena asked.

Ivy miró a Helena fijamente y después se puso a gritar.

Crowther looked up. “You’ve seen what she’s capable of.

Helena jamás había escuchado un grito así.

Without her sister keeping her in check, Ivy is of no use.

Fue como si estallara algo en su interior, tan agudo que pareció que las bombillas a su alrededor iban a estallar.

Bear in mind, that rule applies to Ferron as well.”

Una rabia lívida recorrió el rostro de Ivy.

His eyes raked over her in disgust, as if he could see every place Kaine had touched her. “I would strongly advise keeping yourself alive, Marino.”

Helena se preparó para el golpe, pero la chica se giró hacia Crowther.

WHEN HELENA SAW WAGNER, HE smiled at her, but all she could think of was the terror in Sofia’s face as he shoved her towards the necrothralls.

—¡Me prometiste que la protegerías si hacía todo lo que pedías!

A translator had been found, a rheumy old man named Hotten who worked in the kitchens.

Ella no debería haber trabajado para ti.

His son had been a graduate of the Alchemy Institute and died early in the war.

¡Solo tenías que mantenerla a salvo!

“Now then,” Crowther said as they entered the cell.

Se abalanzó sobre él por encima del escritorio, como si quisiera arrancarle los ojos, pero, antes de que sus dedos lo rozaran, un estallido de llamas la arrojó contra la pared.

All his anger had vanished, and he was almost convincingly convivial. “Why are you so important?”

Ivy cayó al suelo, y los libros de los estantes se desplomaron encima, incendiándose en su caída.

Hotten translated.

Crowther se movió con la agilidad de un gato.

Hevgotian was a low West dialect that had a folky cadence and very round-sounding words.

Sus años de experiencia en combate se notaron cuando se abalanzó sobre Ivy.

Wagner gave a few long-winded answers that Hotten summarised after trying and failing to keep up.

—Nunca le hablé de túneles ni alcantarillados, ni tampoco de prisiones —le dijo Crowther.

“He knew Morrough in Hevgoss.

Cerró la mano e hizo desaparecer el fuego—.

Morrough was given a prison unit, sector four criminals.

Si se enteró de todo aquello fue por tu indiscreción.

Wagner was a guard,” Hotten translated slowly.

Te advertí que no le contaras nada, pero quisiste impresionarla contándole cómo viajabas por la ciudad sin que nadie te viera.

The only thing Hevgoss liked more than expansionist war was their prison population.

¿Te sientes ahora orgullosa?

It was vast, multigenerational, and the source of their labour force and the bulk of their military.

Seguro que le mostraste lo fácil que era.

Sector four criminals were usually political prisoners, sentenced to four generations of imprisonment, lifetime after lifetime of indentured servitude that only their great-great-grandchildren would have a chance of escaping.

Helena creyó que Ivy se pondría en pie, pero se limitó a quedarse en el suelo.

Labour sentences were passed down for almost any infraction, lasting anywhere from days to generations.

—Solo quería que supiera salir de la ciudad.

Much of their low-ranked military was composed of sector one and two criminals, who were promised pardons in exchange for a successful military record.

Le enseñé el mapa y le hablé de la prisión para que no fuera en esa dirección —replicó Ivy, a quien le sobrevino un sollozo.

Whenever there were labour shortages, or rumours of political or economic instability within the country, Hevgoss had a habit of going to war, stretching their borders to encompass some new population to refill their prisons.

—Si me hubieras hecho caso, seguiría viva —repuso Crowther con voz cruel—.

Officially Hevgotian prisons were all state-run, but that didn’t prevent the “rental” of prisoners when it suited them to whoever could pay.

Yo he mantenido el trato, y nada de esto es culpa mía. —Le dio una patada—.

Slavery was illegal on the Northern continent, so Hevgoss had reinvented it.

Quítate de mi vista.

“Morrough had made a deal with the militocrats.

Si Lucien Holdfast hubiese muerto en ese rescate absurdo, tú tendrías la culpa.

He was trying to find a way of controlling the power of life.

Ivy se levantó del suelo sin pronunciar palabra, pero, cuando atravesó la puerta, se giró un instante con un brillo asesino en los ojos.

He said that mastering it, harvesting it, was the key to immortality.

Cuando desapareció, Crowther se dio la vuelta y sacó un transmisor de un cajón de su escritorio.

He promised the leaders that he’d teach it to them if they provided him with the materials to test it, but the prisoners”—Wagner shrugged—“were resistant.

Emitió un estallido de estática al encenderse y, después, Helena reconoció la voz del guardia.

They didn’t want to cooperate.

Era uno de rango superior.

They knew they would die.”

Crowther musitó una jerga prácticamente ininteligible, pero la chica comprendió algunas palabras: «muy peligrosa» y «neutralizar».

Wagner smiled as he recounted this, as though the story evoked fond memories.

Luego guardó el transmisor y miró las quemaduras que había ocasionado en su despacho.

“My job was to deliver the prisoners each day and take them back at night, but there were never any to take back when he was done with them.

—¿De verdad es necesario? —preguntó Helena.

Morrough was friendly to me.

Crowther levantó la mirada.

He would talk to me, tell me his frustrations.

—Ya has visto de lo que es capaz.

The energy, you see, could not be taken by force; it had to be given willingly.

Ahora que no está su hermana para mantenerla a raya, Ivy no me sirve de nada.

He had already found many tricks to get it, but when the prisoners were dead, the energy, he said, remembered.

Recuerda que esa misma regla se aplica a Ferron. —La miró de arriba abajo con repugnancia, como si pudiera ver todos los sitios en los que Kaine la había tocado—.

They would lash out.

Te aconsejo encarecidamente que te mantengas con vida, Marino.

Resist, so that it was difficult even for him to control.”

Cuando Helena vio a Wagner, este le sonrió, pero lo único en lo que pensaba ella era en el rostro aterrorizado de Sofia cuando la empujó hacia los necrómatas.

Helena and Crowther shared a quick glance.

Habían encontrado un intérprete: un anciano artrítico llamado Hotten que trabajaba en las cocinas.

Clearly Crowther was also acquainted with the true story of Orion’s victory against the Necromancer.

Su hijo era graduado en la Academia de Alquimia y había muerto al comienzo de la guerra.

“It was my idea that solved it.” Wagner thumped his chest. “My father, he was a warden, so was my grandfather.

—Muy bien —dijo Crowther cuando entraron en la celda.

Prison uprisings are a dangerous thing.

Había hecho desaparecer toda su rabia e incluso parecía simpático—, ¿por qué eres tan importante?

There are prisons the size of towns.

Hotten lo tradujo.

To keep order, it is important that the guards are not the enemy.

El hevgotiano era un dialecto del occidente meridional que tenía una cadencia particular y en el que se pronunciaban las palabras con cierto ritmo.

Instead, you make the prisoners think their trouble is other prisoners, a different unit or sector.

Wagner habló sin pausa y Hotten tuvo que resumir después de tratar, sin éxito, de interpretar simultáneamente.

Those prisoners are the reason this prisoner has less; the rules they hate are those prisoners’ fault.

—Conoció a Morrough en Hevgoss.

By making privileges always at the expense of others, the prisoners forget who has made those rules.

A Morrough se le concedió una unidad de la prisión, los criminales del sector cuatro.

Morrough liked this idea.

Wagner trabajaba allí de guardia —tradujo Hotten con voz pausada.

To take the souls, he must make the prisoners blame someone else.

Hevgoss adoraba, por encima de todo, sus guerras expansionistas y su población encarcelada.

Even after the energy was taken, the blame must continue to be misdirected.”

Esta última era numerosa, abarcaba varias generaciones y constituía tanto la mano de obra como el grueso de su ejército.

Wagner looked from Helena to Crowther, seeming to expect their awe.

Los criminales del sector cuatro solían ser presos políticos, condenados a cuatro generaciones de prisión; una vida tras otra dedicadas a la servidumbre, de la que solo escaparían sus tataranietos.

“He succeeded in this, I presume,” Crowther said.

Las penas de trabajos forzosos se heredaban a la más mínima infracción, y podían prolongarse por días o por generaciones enteras.

Wagner nodded. “He stopped trying to contain or bind the energy to himself.

La mayor parte de los rangos inferiores de su ejército se componía de criminales de los sectores uno y dos, a los que se les prometía el perdón a cambio de una destacada carrera militar.

Instead he used another prisoner inside the array.” He spread his hands wide. “He had a strange alchemy.

Cada vez que escaseaba la mano de obra o había rumores de inestabilidad política o económica, Hevgoss respondía con la guerra para ampliar sus fronteras y así hacerse con más población que llenara sus prisiones.

With his power, he pulled the energy out and bound them to the soul of a chosen prisoner.

En teoría, las cárceles hevgotianas estaban bajo el control estatal, pero eso no evitaba que «alquilaran» presos a quienes quisieran pagar por ellos.

The other prisoner would suffer all the anger, and Morrough took the power.”

La esclavitud era ilegal en el continente Norte, así que Hevgoss la había reinventado.

“But how would he control it,” Helena said, “if the souls—the energy is bound to someone else?”

—Morrough había hecho un trato con los militócratas.

“With his bones,” Wagner said, raising his eyebrows. “I saw it.

Buscaba controlar el poder de la vida.

He used his alchemy to contain all the souls inside pieces of his own bones.

Dijo que dominarlo y recolectarlo era la clave para la inmortalidad.

It was strange, but if a piece stayed with the prisoner in the array, they could not die, even if they tried.

Prometió a los líderes que les enseñaría a hacerlo si le entregaban los materiales para realizar las pruebas, pero los prisioneros —Wagner se encogió de hombros— se resistieron.

Then Morrough could keep the power.”

No querían cooperar.

The phylacteries.

Sabían que morirían.

It was exactly what Kaine had described.

Wagner sonrió al contarlo, como si reviviera un recuerdo que le parecía reconfortante.

“The souls of the others, they would feel that life, they would try to resist, but the prisoner could not be killed.

—Mi trabajo consistía en llevar a los prisioneros por la mañana y traerlos de vuelta por la noche, pero, cuando terminaba con ellos, no quedaba ninguno con vida.

Still … slowly their mind would—” Wagner touched the sides of his head, pulling invisible strings as though unravelling something.

Morrough me trató con respeto.

“Are you saying that the Undying are just a power source for Morrough?” Helena said slowly.

Me hablaba, me contaba sus frustraciones.

“Yes!

Veréis, la energía no se puede otorgar a la fuerza, hay que darla voluntariamente.

That is what he called them.

Ya había descubierto muchos trucos para conseguirla, pero, según decía, cuando los prisioneros morían, la energía lo recordaba, se resistía, atacaba.

Undying.

Por eso le resultaba tan difícil controlarla.

Not living or dead.”

Helena y Crowther compartieron una mirada cómplice.

Crowther placed paper and pen down in front of Wagner, indicating that he sketch as much of the procedure and array as possible.

Era evidente que Crowther también conocía la verdadera historia de la victoria de Orion contra el Nigromante.

It was clear that Wagner was no alchemist, or artist, but he’d seen the process done at least a few times.

—Lo resolvió gracias a mi idea. —Wagner hinchó el pecho—.

He sketched a massive array unlike anything Helena had ever seen.

Mi padre fue guardia, al igual que mi abuelo.

Neither celestial nor elemental, it had nine source points, and in the centre a platform was suspended by which Morrough could access the body of the prisoner designated to survive.

Los levantamientos en las cárceles son muy peligrosos, algunas prisiones son del tamaño de ciudades.

The sacrificial victims were placed on the nine points.

Para mantener el orden, es vital que los guardias no sean vistos como el enemigo, así que convencemos a los prisioneros de que el problema son otros prisioneros, una unidad o un sector distinto.

Morrough would open the chest cavity of the chosen recipient prisoner and place a piece of one of his own bones inside as the final component of the array.

Esos prisioneros son los culpables de que ellos tengan menos; las normas que odian fueron establecidas por culpa de esos prisioneros.

After somehow tethering their life force to that bone, he would activate the array.

Al conceder privilegios a costa de otros, los prisioneros olvidan quién firmó esas normas.

The array created a pull so terrible that the sacrifices shrivelled into husks, stripped of life until it was drawn into the recipient, trapping their soul beneath the layers and layers of the others, like an insect trapped in a spiderweb.

A Morrough le gustó esa idea.

Morrough would cut off a shard of the bone, coat it in lumithium, and leave it inside the prisoner’s body.

Para capturar almas, debía hacer que los prisioneros culparan a otra persona.

Then he’d place the rest back inside his own.

Incluso después de que les arrebatara la energía, la culpa tenía que redirigirse.

The information fell in line with what they knew, but Helena’s mind refused to believe that such a thing could be possible.

Wagner miró a Helena y luego a Crowther, como si esperara que se hubieran quedado sin palabras.

Ilva’s story about the first Necromancer had been horrifying enough, manipulating and deceiving a multitude, but the scale made it impersonal.

—Entiendo que le salió bien —comentó Crowther.

This process was so intimate and intentional.

Wagner asintió.

The repetition.

—Dejó de intentar contener o unir la energía a su cuerpo.

The scope.

En su lugar, empleaba a otro prisionero dentro del sello. —Extendió las manos a ambos lados—.

Nine victims, over and over, tearing bone shard after bone shard each time.

Poseía una alquimia muy rara.

For power.

A través de su poder, extraía la energía y la ataba al alma de un prisionero.

For immortality.

El otro prisionero absorbía toda la rabia y Morrough se quedaba con el poder.

This was how Kaine had been made.

—Pero ¿cómo lo controlaba si las almas…, si la energía estaba atada a otra persona? —preguntó Helena.

“How did you survive so long, knowing all this?” Crowther asked Wagner.

—Con sus huesos —respondió Wagner con las cejas arqueadas—.

Wagner smiled. “He was a selfish man.

Lo vi con mis propios ojos.

The lives of others were, to him, a resource.

Usaba su alquimia para contener las almas dentro de esquirlas de sus propios huesos.

I am no fool.

Era extraño, pero, si una esquirla estaba en el sello junto al prisionero, este no podía morir ni aunque quisiera.

When it was a success, I ran.

Y, después, Morrough podía quedarse con el poder.

I knew he would try to find me someday.

Las filacterias.

He would not share credit in his great discovery.

Era exactamente lo que Kaine había descrito.

I thought he had forgotten, until I woke up in Paladia.

—Las almas de los demás… podían percibir esa vida, intentarían resistirse, pero el prisionero no podría morir.

Now the world will know of me.”

Aun así… sus mentes empezaban a… —Wagner se tocó las sienes y tiró de unos hilos invisibles como si desenrollara algo.

He smiled craftily at Crowther, clearly anticipating being used by the Resistance to counter Morrough’s claims of power and scientific genius, but Helena couldn’t imagine anyone caring whose idea it was; Morrough was the one with the power and ability.

—¿Quieres decir que los inmarcesibles solo son una fuente de poder para Morrough? —preguntó Helena.

“How are all the Undying able to use necromancy?” she asked.

—¡Sí!

Hotten translated the question.

Así es como los llamaba: inmarcesibles.

“Accident,” Wagner said with a barking laugh. “He never knew why.”

Ni vivos ni muertos.

ONCE THE INTERVIEW WITH WAGNER was over, Helena was left at a loose end.

Crowther colocó un papel y un boli delante de Wagner y le ordenó que dibujara el procedimiento y el sello con la mayor exactitud posible.

Headquarters security was thrown into chaos after the guards failed to apprehend Ivy.

Quedó claro que Wagner no era ni alquimista ni dibujante, pero había presenciado cómo se realizaba el procedimiento varias veces.

Any information Ivy knew was now considered compromised.

Esbozó un sello enorme que Helena jamás había visto.

Crowther immediately moved the prisoners under the Alchemy Tower to a different location, somewhere south of Headquarters, and a team of alchemists went down into the warren of tunnels, trying to seal them off to keep Ivy from sneaking back in.

No era ni celestial ni elemental, tenía nueve puntos de referencia y, en el centro, había una plataforma en suspensión desde la que Morrough tenía acceso al cuerpo del prisionero destinado a sobrevivir.

But when Ilva and Althorne went with Crowther for a follow-up interrogation, Wagner was found dead, hacked to bits by the reanimated corpses of the two guards stationed outside his cell.

Las víctimas del sacrificio se disponían en las nueve puntas.

The remains had been assembled to read: CROWTHER NEXT.

Morrough abría la cavidad torácica del prisionero elegido como receptor y colocaba una esquirla de alguno de sus huesos en su interior; ese era el último componente del sello.

Luc was still in the hospital, under constant watch.

De alguna forma, conseguía canalizar la fuerza vital de los prisioneros en ese hueso y, después, activaba el sello.

Information about his condition was kept carefully controlled.

El sello creaba una atracción tan poderosa que los sacrificados quedaban como cascarones vacíos, desprovistos de una vida que se introducía en el receptor.

According to the daily reports, he was recovering and only needed a few more days before he’d be transferred to his rooms.

Su alma era atrapada bajo las capas y capas de los demás, como un insecto en una telaraña.

Elain was the only healer allowed to go in to see him.

Después, Morrough cortaba un fragmento del hueso, lo bañaba en lumitio y lo dejaba en el interior del cuerpo del prisionero.

She was tight-lipped for the first time in her life.

El resto del hueso lo introducía en su propio cuerpo.

She would hurry in and out, retrieving medicine from the supply room, talking to Pace in a hushed voice, and then hurrying back.

Esta información iba en la misma línea de lo que ya conocían, pero la mente de Helena se negaba a creer que algo así fuera posible.

Helena covered Elain’s usual shifts.

La historia que Ilva le había contado sobre el primer Nigromante ya le había parecido espantosa, pues había manipulado y engañado a muchas personas, pero la magnitud de sus actos hacía que fuese algo impersonal.

Among those patients was Penny, whose leg had been too damaged for healing and had been amputated at the knee.

Sin embargo, este proceso a pequeña escala se le antojó más íntimo e intencionado.

Alister was sitting at her bedside, keeping her company when Helena pushed back the curtains.

La repetición.

Helena was surprised at first that Penny had so few visitors, but then she remembered that, aside from Alister, Luc and Lila were the only ones left.

El alcance.

All the rest were still being searched for beneath the rubble.

Nueve víctimas, una y otra vez, arrancando esquirlas de hueso una tras otra.

“I should go,” Alister said, standing up. “The tribunal has follow-up questions.”

En busca del poder.

Penny nodded wordlessly, her fingers clutching the blankets on her lap.

En busca de la inmortalidad.

“What tribunal?” Helena asked, sitting down when Alister had gone. “You two aren’t being punished for saving Luc, are you?”

Así había creado a Kaine.

Penny shook her head, picking at a lump in the thread of the linen sheets. “No.

—¿Cómo es posible que sobrevivieras tanto si sabías todo esto? —le preguntó Crowther a Wagner.

We just got a reprimand.

Este sonrió.

I’m even supposed to get two medals.

—Es un hombre egoísta.

The tribunal’s for Lila.”

Para él, las vidas ajenas son un mero recurso.

Helena looked up sharply. “What do you mean?”

No soy idiota.

“They’re replacing Lila with Sebastian as paladin primary,” Penny said without looking up. “Lila’s probably going to be stripped of rank for compromising Luc’s safety.”

Cuando vi que tenía éxito, salí huyendo.

“You can’t be serious,” Helena said. “Lila has saved Luc’s life more times than—”

Sabía que intentaría encontrarme algún día.

“I know,” Penny said sharply. “We all know, but they’re not going to do anything to Luc—he’s Principate.

No querría compartir el reconocimiento por ese gran descubrimiento.

So Lila takes the fall.

Pensé que se había olvidado de mí, hasta que un día desperté en Paladia.

People have been complaining for a while—I mean, they always were, because she’s a girl and paladins are supposed to be boys—but Lila always outweighed the risk before, but after that last time with the chimaera, and now … the higher-ups see her as a liability for him.

Pero ahora el mundo conocerá mi nombre.

They think that if it hadn’t been for her, Luc wouldn’t have been captured.”

Sonrió con astucia.

“But—”

Era evidente que estaba convencido de que la Resistencia lo usaría para rebatir las reivindicaciones de poder y saber científico de Morrough.

“They’ve been doing interviews, and the thing is,” Penny continued, looking a mixture of guilt-stricken and resigned, “we all knew.

No obstante, Helena sabía que a nadie le importaría de quién había sido la idea, pues Morrough era quien ostentaba el poder y la habilidad de hacerlo.

I mean he tried to be subtle about it, but you could tell just looking.

—¿Por qué todos los inmarcesibles son capaces de usar la nigromancia? —preguntó.

Especially lately, everyone thought it was all going to be over soon.

Hotten tradujo la pregunta.

I think Luc thought it’d be fine because no one cared when it was his dad and Sebastian.

—Un accidente —respondió Wagner con una carcajada—.

But there’s always more rules for us girls, and no one under oath can say that Luc’s not compromised.

Nunca supo por qué.

Could you?”

Una vez finalizado el interrogatorio, Helena se quedó sin saber qué hacer.

Helena looked away.

La seguridad del Cuartel General se desmoronó cuando los guardias no fueron capaces de apresar a Ivy.

Poor Lila.

Toda la información que conocía la chica pasó a ser considerada comprometida.

She’d straddled the impossibility of her role for years, rarely making a mistake, but now she was left paying for Luc’s.

Crowther no tardó en trasladar a los prisioneros de los sótanos de la Torre de Alquimia a otra ubicación, algún lugar al sur del Cuartel General, y un equipo de alquimistas bajó al laberinto de túneles y se dedicó a sellarlos para que Ivy no pudiera volver a entrar.

What would happen?

Sin embargo, cuando Ilva y Althorne se reunieron con Crowther para continuar con el interrogatorio, encontraron a Wagner muerto, despedazado, junto a los cadáveres reanimados de los guardias apostados a las puertas de la celda.

Helena swallowed hard, forcing herself to focus on the task at hand.

Los restos estaban dispuestos de forma que se leía: Crowther el siguiente.

There wasn’t anything they could do about the tribunal. “How’s the leg?”

Luc seguía ingresado en el hospital bajo vigilancia constante.

Penny seemed to shrink. “Fine,” she said too quickly.

Nadie daba detalles concretos de su estado.

Helena reached out slowly. “You know, sometimes the nerve endings don’t realise the amputation has happened, and it can make you feel like the leg’s still there and in pain.

Según los informes diarios, se estaba recuperando y en unos días lo trasladarían a sus aposentos.

I can use my resonance to block it so it doesn’t feel that way.”

Elain era la única sanadora con permiso para entrar a verlo.

“Really?” Penny’s voice had a hint of desperation.

Por primera vez en su vida, se mostraba reservada.

Helena set to work, but even this made her think about Lila.

Iba de un lado a otro con prisa, cogía medicinas de la sala de suministros, hablaba con Pace entre susurros y se apresuraba a volver.

As far as lost limbs went, it was a good amputation.

Helena quedó a cargo de los turnos de Elain.

Maier had been able to salvage as much of the leg as possible and perform a clean cut, without the rush of an emergency. “You know, you might be able to get a prosthetic.”

Entre esos pacientes se encontraba Penny, cuya pierna había sufrido tantos daños que tuvieron que amputársela a la altura de la rodilla.

“I don’t think my repertoire is good enough for much,” Penny said with a bitter smile, but the strain in her expression was already clearing. “Maybe a basic one, though, so I can stay on, maybe man the radios.

Cuando Helena descorrió las cortinas, Alister estaba sentado al lado de su cama haciéndole compañía.

I don’t want to get sent off.”

Al principio, le sorprendió que tuviera tan pocas visitas, pero entonces recordó que los únicos que quedaban vivos eran Alister, Luc y Lila.

“The forge-masters are very talented.

Todos los demás seguían enterrados bajo los escombros.

Titanium bonds well for most people, and it’s a lot lighter than the old models.”

—Tengo que irme —dijo Alister, que se puso en pie—.

“I guess we’ll see,” Penny said.

El tribunal quiere hacernos más preguntas.

There was silence while Helena worked, and then Penny spoke again. “Is it true, what Luc said?

Penny asintió sin pronunciar palabra; tenía los dedos cerrados alrededor de las mantas que le cubrían el regazo.

When Soren came to save Alister and me, was he dead?”

—¿Qué tribunal? —preguntó Helena al sentarse donde había estado Alister—.

Helena flinched as if she’d been kicked through the skull, Soren’s name striking like an anvil.

No os van a castigar por salvar a Luc, ¿no?

She was drowning again.

Penny negó con la cabeza y enredó con el dedo un hilo de las sábanas de lino.

Penny’s leg wavered in Helena’s vision.

—No, solo recibiremos una reprimenda.

“When I first heard the rumour, I thought it was ridiculous.

A mí me van a dar incluso dos medallas.

I was sure I would have noticed if he was dead.

El tribunal es por Lila.

But sitting here, I keep thinking about it, the way he didn’t stop fighting no matter what they did to him.

Helena levantó la vista de inmediato.

He never screamed—not even when they started tearing him apart.” Penny’s voice shook. “I think I’d rather believe he was dead.”

—¿De qué estás hablando?

Helena’s skin crawled as if those cold fingers were dragging across it.

—Van a nombrar a Sebastian paladín primero en vez de Lila —le contó Penny sin mirarla—.

She blinked, pushing the thoughts and memories of Soren back and away, again wilfully forcing her consciousness to swerve around the wound that his memory evoked.

Lo más probable es que degraden a Lila por haber puesto en peligro la seguridad de Luc.

She knew better than to outright confess.

—¿Lo dices en serio?

She bit her lip for a moment. “Soren said we had to do anything, no matter what it took, to save Luc.”

Lila le ha salvado la vida a Luc más veces que…

Penny was quiet for a long time. “I don’t know how to feel.

—Lo sé —intervino Penny—.

I know I’d be dead if he hadn’t come right then … but—” Her lips trembled. “—what if that was a test?

Todos lo sabemos, pero a Luc no pueden hacerle nada… Es el principado.

All these years of fighting the good fight, but then in the final moment, instead of staying true, we chose the easy way.”

Así que Lila tiene que asumir la culpa.

Helena was glad that she was nearly done working on Penny’s leg, because the conversation was making her hands shake.

La gente lleva un tiempo quejándose… Bueno, siempre se han quejado, porque es una chica y los paladines suelen ser hombres, pero con Lila merecía la pena el riesgo.

Easy.

Sin embargo, después de lo que pasó con la quimera y esto…, los jefes consideran que lo vuelve más vulnerable.

She hated that word.

Creen que, si no hubiera sido por ella, jamás habrían capturado a Luc.

She swallowed hard. “If one person’s actions are enough to damn everyone, then the gods are terrible, and Sol is the worst of all.”

—Pero…

“You don’t mean that,” Penny said sharply, catching her by the wrist, clutching at it until her fingers bit into her skin. “Look at me, Helena.

Penny siguió hablando con una mezcla de culpa y resignación.

You don’t mean that.

—Han estado interrogándonos, y el caso es que todos lo sabíamos.

It works the other way, too.

Luc intentaba ser discreto, pero se notaba solo con verlos.

Orion passed the test, and think of all the blessings that came from that.”

Sobre todo, en los últimos meses, cuando pensábamos que la guerra estaba a punto de acabar.

Penny seemed desperate to convince her.

Creo que Luc pensó que ya no importaba, que no pasaría nada.

“I remember when you first came here.

Después de todo, nunca le reprocharon nada a su padre ni a Sebastian.

We were in the same dorm.

Pero para las chicas siempre hay más reglas, y nadie que esté bajo juramento puede decir que a Luc no le afecta lo que le ocurra a Lila.

You said that Paladia was the most beautiful place in the whole world.

¿Tú podrías?

The Shining City, you called it.

Helena desvió su mirada.

You said that in Etras people didn’t really believe in the gods, but here in the North, you understood why they did, because how else could a place be so beautiful.

Pobre Lila.

Don’t you remember that?”

Había sorteado las dificultades de su rango durante años, apenas había cometido un error, pero al final iba a pagar los de Luc.

She found Helena’s hand and squeezed it. “That’s what you said.

¿Qué pasaría entonces?

I think you still believe that, deep down.

La chica tragó saliva con dificultad y se obligó a centrarse en la tarea que tenía entre manos.

You were just—you were just scared and you—made a mistake, but you can repent.

No podían hacer nada respecto al tribunal.

If you talk to the Falcon, he makes it all so clear.

—¿Cómo tienes la pierna?

The journey, all the suffering, it’s what we need.

Penny pareció encogerse.

How else can we be purified?

—Bien —respondió demasiado rápido.

Even—even when it’s hard, we have to be grateful for it, because that’s what makes us pure.”

Helena se acercó lentamente.

Penny was smiling at Helena, fervently trying to convince her. “That’s why it’s better for all of us to die true to what we believe than to live on by betraying and corrupting ourselves.

—Verás, a veces las terminaciones nerviosas no se dan cuenta de que ha habido una amputación.

I know you meant well, saving us, but you should have trusted Sol.”

Siguen enviando señales como si la pierna aún estuviera ahí, y por eso te duele.

Helena pulled her hand free. “Penny, if I thought we’d all die, I wouldn’t be so afraid of losing.

Puedo usar la resonancia para bloquearlas y así dejarás de sentir el dolor.

What they’ll do to us if we lose will be far worse than death.” She shook her head. “There will be nothing purifying about it.”

—¿De verdad? —La voz de Penny sonó algo desesperada.

EVEN AFTER DAYS OF CHELATING treatment, Lila’s resonance failed to return.

La sanadora empezó a trabajar, pero no pudo dejar de pensar en Lila.

The Council was trying to keep the news quiet, not wanting to cause a panic.

La amputación había sido limpia.

The chelators were supposed to sequester the metal in Lila’s blood to flush it out, but it wasn’t working as effectively as expected.

Maier había conseguido conservar gran parte de la extremidad y el corte era perfecto, ya que no se había visto presionado por la urgencia propia de una emergencia.

Shiseo had said nothing about the message Helena had sent him to the Outpost with, asked no questions, but he’d looked very relieved the first time she returned to the lab.

—¿Sabes qué?

It communicated more than words could.

Tal vez puedas ponerte una prótesis.

They spent days analysing and re-analysing the shards and new samples of Lila’s blood, trying to determine what they were missing.

—Creo que mi repertorio no es lo suficientemente bueno como para eso —respondió Penny con una sonrisa amarga, pero empezó a aligerarse el cansancio de su rostro—.

Every time Helena had to leave for a shift, she always returned to find Shiseo still working.

Aunque quizá pida una básica.

He finally fell asleep, slumped over the workstation.

Así podría seguir trabajando, tal vez en las transmisiones.

Helena sat quietly, watching a flame under the glass alembic before her, steam rising in the cucurbit, collecting in the ambix and running down the tube into a vial beside it.

No quiero que me despidan.

Elain Boyle had been made the Resistance’s lead healer earlier that day.

—Los maestros de las forjas son muy hábiles.

It was a new position that Matias had created for her.

Las estructuras de titanio valen para casi todo el mundo, y son mucho más ligeras que los modelos de antes.

Elain had arrived in the hospital wearing a large and ornate sunstone amulet around her neck, and now her general duties were managing and scheduling the other healers’ shifts, while she worked exclusively as Luc’s “personal” healer.

—Ya lo iremos viendo —repuso Penny.

Helena told herself she didn’t care.

Se hizo el silencio mientras Helena trabajaba.

Her chymiatria was becoming the default for the healers.

Hasta que Penny volvió a hablar:

Pace had quietly created a section in the storerooms for the tonics and medicines, letting Helena’s chymiatria bear some of the load of healing.

—¿Es cierto lo que dijo Luc?

Helena curled her fingers into a tight fist.

Cuando Soren vino a salvarnos a Alister y a mí, ¿estaba muerto?

She’d built up a large supply of ingredients since they’d recovered the ports, but she was worried about running out now that Crowther had banned her from foraging anymore.

Helena se encogió como si hubiera recibido una patada en la cabeza.

Some could be made using imported materials, but there were a few things that were hard to get her hands on if she couldn’t gather them herself.

El nombre de Soren le cayó encima como un yunque.

She sighed.

Empezó a ahogarse de nuevo.

She used to love the quietness of lab work—such a stark contrast with the hospital—but now it left her to her thoughts, and everything she pushed away in her mind crowded around, suffocating her.

La pierna de Penny se volvió borrosa ante sus ojos.

She missed Kaine.

—Cuando oí los rumores, pensé que era una ridiculez.

Whenever she thought of him, she felt as though a piece of her was missing.

Estaba convencida de que me habría dado cuenta si hubiera estado muerto.

The war had drilled itself into her bones, carving away at her until there was hardly anything left except what made her useful, an ideal component in an elaborate machine, but Kaine had reminded her that she was human; that not every trait and ability and quality she possessed only mattered insomuch as it was useful to someone else.

Pero, una vez aquí, no paro de pensar en ello, en cómo no dejó de luchar por mucho que le hirieron.

That she was allowed to breathe sometimes.

No gritó ni una vez, ni siquiera cuando empezaron a hacerlo trizas. —A Penny le temblaba la voz—.

Now, in his absence, she felt herself suffocating.

Creo que prefiero pensar que ya estaba muerto.

A Helena se le erizó la piel como si esos dedos fríos la acariciaran.

Parpadeó, intentando apartar los pensamientos y recuerdos de Soren, y se obligó a concentrarse para esquivar la herida que escocía en su memoria.

Sabía que no convenía confesarlo todo.

Se mordió el labio.

—Soren me dijo que teníamos que hacer lo que fuera, costase lo que costase, por salvar a Luc.

Penny guardó silencio un largo rato.

—No sé cómo sentirme al respecto.

Sé que estaría muerta si no hubiera venido a ayudarnos, pero… —le temblaron los labios— ¿y si era una prueba?

Después de todos estos años luchando por el bien, en el último momento, en vez de permanecer fieles a la verdad, elegimos el camino fácil.

Helena se alegró de estar a punto de terminar con la pierna de Penny, porque la conversación hizo que le temblaran las manos. «Fácil».

Detestaba esa palabra.

Tragó saliva.

—Si las acciones de una sola persona bastan para condenar a los demás, entonces los dioses son terribles y Sol es el peor de todos.

—No lo dices en serio —respondió Penny al instante.

La tomó por la muñeca apretando tanto los dedos que se le clavaron en la piel—.

Mírame, Helena.

No lo dices en serio.

También funciona al revés.

Orion pasó la prueba y fíjate en todas las bendiciones que recibieron por eso. —Penny parecía desesperada por convencerla—.

Recuerdo el día que llegaste.

Estábamos en el mismo dormitorio.

Decías que Paladia era el lugar más bonito del mundo, la llamabas «la ciudad resplandeciente».

Decías que la gente de Etras no creía mucho en los dioses, pero que aquí en el Norte entendías por qué lo hacíamos, porque ¿cómo si no iba a existir un sitio tan bello?

¿Ya no te acuerdas de eso?

Encontró la mano de Helena y le dio un apretón.

—Eso me dijiste.

Creo que, en el fondo, sigues creyéndolo.

Simplemente te… te asustaste y… cometiste un error, pero puedes arrepentirte.

Si hablas con el falcón, te explicará cómo hacerlo.

El viaje, el sufrimiento, eso es lo que necesitamos.

¿Cómo vamos a ser puros si no?

Incluso… incluso cuando las cosas se tuercen, tenemos que estar agradecidos, porque eso es lo que nos hace puros.

Penny sonreía a Helena con un fervor que pretendía convencerla.

—Por eso es mejor que todos muramos fieles a nuestras creencias antes que vivir traicionándolas y corrompiéndonos.

Sé que tenías buenas intenciones, que querías salvarnos, pero deberías haber confiado en Sol.

Helena apartó su mano.

—Penny, si creyera que simplemente vamos a morir, no me daría tanto miedo perder.

Si perdemos, nos harán cosas mucho peores que la muerte. —Sacudió la cabeza—.

No habrá nada de pureza en ello.

A pesar de recibir un tratamiento quelante durante días, Lila no recobró su resonancia.

El Consejo intentó comunicar esta información con calma, porque no querían alimentar el pánico.

En teoría, los quelantes debían haber separado el metal de la sangre de Lila para que su cuerpo pudiera expulsarlo, pero el resultado no fue el que esperaban.

Shiseo no había desvelado el contenido del mensaje que Helena le había pedido que llevara al Reducto sin hacer más preguntas, pero, por primera vez, pareció sentir alivio cuando la vio regresar al laboratorio.

Y ese gesto fue más revelador que las palabras.

Pasaron días analizando una y otra vez las esquirlas y nuevas muestras de sangre de Lila para averiguar qué estaban pasando por alto.

Cada vez que Helena regresaba de hacer un turno, siempre encontraba a Shiseo trabajando.

Al final cayó rendido en la misma mesa.

Helena permaneció sentada en silencio.

Estaba observando una llama bajo el alambique de cristal; el vapor subía por la cucurbitácea, se recopilaba en el destilador y descendía por el tubo hasta un frasco que había a un lado.

Ese mismo día, Elain Boyle fue nombrada sanadora jefe de la Resistencia.

Había sido Matias quien había creado ese puesto para ella.

Elain había llegado al hospital con un amuleto enorme de heliolita colgado alrededor del cuello y, a partir de ese momento, sus tareas consistían en gestionar el horario del resto de las sanadoras y trabajar en atender personalmente a Luc.

Helena se dijo a sí misma que no le importaba.

Su quimiatría se había convertido en algo esencial para las sanadoras.

Poco a poco, Pace había ido creando una sección en los almacenes para guardar todos los tónicos y las medicinas.

Así, la quimiatría de Helena sostenía buena parte de la carga de la sanación.

Cerró los dedos en un puño.

Desde que reconquistaron los puertos, había conseguido numerosos ingredientes, pero, al haberle prohibido Crowther seguir recolectando en el exterior, le preocupaba que se agotasen.

Había fórmulas que podía elaborar con materiales importados, pero algunas eran difíciles de conseguir si no las recolectaba ella misma.

Suspiró.

En el pasado, disfrutaba de la quietud del laboratorio, que contrastaba de manera brutal con el caos del hospital, pero ahora ese silencio la dejaba a solas con sus pensamientos, y todo lo que se esforzaba por apartar de su mente regresaba para asfixiarla.

Echaba de menos a Kaine.

Cada vez que pensaba en él sentía como si le faltase una parte de sí misma.

La guerra se le había metido hasta los huesos y se había abierto paso por su interior hasta dejar solo lo que la hacía útil: un engranaje perfecto en una maquinaria compleja.

Sin embargo, Kaine le había recordado que era humana; que sus dones y cualidades no solo eran válidos porque alguien podía aprovecharlos.

Que tenía permiso para respirar de vez en cuando.

Pero, en su ausencia, Helena sentía que se asfixiaba.

CHAPTER 54

Aprilis 1787

CAPÍTULO 54

WHEN HELENA STOOD ON THE DAM, STARING across the bridge to the Outpost, she hesitated.

Abrilis 1787

She’d missed Kaine the whole week, but now, returning, she felt dread.

Cuando Helena se plantó sobre la presa y miró hacia el Reducto que se alzaba al otro lado del puente, dudó.

He could be so unpredictable.

Había echado de menos a Kaine toda la semana.

Every moment of softness between them tended to be followed by its direct inversion.

Sin embargo, ahora que había regresado, sentía miedo.

She drew several steadying breaths, set her jaw, and made herself cross.

A veces era muy impredecible.

A necrothrall was waiting outside the tenement when she arrived.

Cada momento de ternura que compartían solía ir seguido de todo lo contrario.

Her heart dropped, and she swallowed hard, opening her satchel and pulling out the envelope along with replacements for his medical kit.

Tomó aire un par de veces para calmarse, apretó los dientes y se obligó a cruzar el puente.

Her face was burning, but she tried to control her expressions and not look directly at the necrothrall as she held it all out.

Un necrómata la esperaba en la puerta del piso.

“Here.” She shoved everything into the necrothrall’s hands and turned away.

Se le cayó el alma a los pies y tragó saliva con dificultad, pero abrió la bolsa y sacó el sobre junto con los recambios para su botiquín.

“Marino.”

Le ardía la cara, aunque hizo todo lo posible para contener su expresión y no mirar al necrómata a los ojos cuando se lo entregó todo.

She nearly jumped out of her skin at the sound of her name.

—Toma. —Lo puso en sus manos y se dio la vuelta.

She whirled around.

—Marino.

The necrothrall was the only one standing there.

Estuvo a punto de desmayarse cuando oyó su nombre.

“Did you—talk?” She’d never heard a necrothrall speak.

Se giró de golpe, pero lo único que había allí era el necrómata.

Motor function was one thing, but reanimation of the language parts of the brain was too much.

—¿Puedes… hablar? —Nunca había escuchado hablar a un necrómata.

Necrothralls didn’t talk.

Que usaran sus funciones motoras ya era inquietante, pero reactivar las partes del cerebro encargadas del lenguaje le pareció excesivo.

They never talked.

Los necrómatas no hablaban.

“Come,” it said.

Nunca lo hacían.

She followed him warily, relaxing when she realised they were headed for the panic room.

—Entra —pronunció.

He couldn’t have just told her to go there last week?

Lo siguió con cautela; solo se permitió relajarse cuando se dio cuenta de que se dirigían a la sala del pánico.

She was half indignant when she arrived, and then forgot, because before she was through the door, Kaine had her in his arms and was kissing her as if starved.

¿No podría haberle dicho la semana pasada que fuera allí?

Her fingers caught his cloak and her eyes fluttered closed as she kissed him back.

Se sentía indignada cuando llegó, pero se le olvidó en cuanto puso un pie en la puerta, porque Kaine la sostuvo en sus brazos y la besó como si estuviera hambriento.

The whole world dropped away.

Helena aferró su capa con sus dedos y cerró los ojos cuando le devolvió el beso.

She felt his teeth, hungry against her lips and tongue.

El resto del mundo desapareció.

His hands found her hips, guiding her backwards.

Sintió los dientes de Kaine, voraces contra sus labios y su lengua.

Then his lips were on her neck as she gasped, the dip of her throat, between her clothed breasts, and he was on his knees, pushing her back on the sofa, and she was under him and she had not even put down her satchel.

Las manos de él encontraron sus caderas y la empujó hacia atrás.

His hands were sliding under her clothes, lips burning a trail of desire across every inch of skin his mouth could find.

Cuando Helena jadeó, aprovechó para bajar con los labios por su cuello, hasta la hendidura de la garganta, entre sus pechos cubiertos, y él estaba de rodillas, empujándola hacia atrás en el sofá.

She had never felt so intoxicated.

Se colocó encima y Helena ni siquiera se había quitado todavía la bolsa.

His resonance hummed beneath her skin, following the pathway of her nerves and veins, mapping her.

Kaine deslizó las manos por debajo de su ropa; sus labios dejaron un reguero de deseo en cada centímetro de piel que encontró a su paso.

Not erotically, but in the same panicked way her own resonance sometimes flared when she was afraid someone was hurt and wanted to find the injury.

Helena jamás se había sentido tan extasiada.

It reached all the way to her toes and then vanished, but she scarcely noticed as his tongue ran up on her inner thigh, and then a haze of hot pleasure consumed her.

La resonancia de Kaine vibraba bajo su piel y seguía el recorrido de sus nervios y sus venas, como si la estuviera cartografiando.

Her shirt was undone, skirts up around her waist, when he sank into her.

No era de forma erótica.

She wrapped her arms tight around his neck, pulling him close, burying her face against his shoulder.

Se parecía más al pánico que sentía cuando, al atender a un herido, su propia resonancia intentaba localizar la herida.

The world had reduced itself to a single point, Kaine, his breath and body and touch.

La recorrió entera y, acto seguido, desapareció, aunque sí que se percató de que la lengua de Kaine se deslizaba por la cara interior de su muslo, hasta que notó un placer que la consumió por completo.

As they lay entwined on that too-small sofa, limbs entangled, it was like that horrible hungover morning and yet completely new.

Tenía la camisa desabrochada y la falda arrebujada alrededor de la cintura cuando Kaine se hundió entre sus piernas.

This time, they’d gotten it right.

Helena le rodeó el cuello con los brazos, lo atrajo hacia sí y enterró su rostro en su hombro.

Her eyes fluttered closed, tracing her fingers across his skin, but he sat up after only a few moments.

El mundo se redujo a una única cosa: Kaine, su respiración, su cuerpo y sus caricias.

He was looking her over, his eyes searching.

Yacer entrelazados en aquel sofá estrecho, con los cuerpos enredados, fue como aquella horrible mañana de resaca, pero totalmente distinto.

She lifted her head, still catching her breath. “What’s wrong?”

Esta vez lo estaban haciendo bien.

His thumb found the scars on her ribs. “I worried about you.

Helena estaba con los ojos cerrados, acariciando su piel con los dedos, pero Kaine se incorporó al poco tiempo.

Had a lot of time to wonder if I’d done everything right when I healed you.”

La miró de arriba abajo, como si la buscara con la mirada.

She caught his hand. “You did everything perfectly.”

Helena levantó la cabeza; aún le costaba recuperar el aliento.

He still looked worried. “And nothing’s happened since?”

—¿Qué sucede?

“No,” she said. “I haven’t left Headquarters at all since I got back.

Le tocó la cicatriz de las costillas con el pulgar.

And I—I won’t anymore—except to come straight to you.

—Estaba preocupado por ti.

I’m not—” The words caught, tangling in her throat. “I’m not allowed to.

He tenido mucho tiempo para preguntarme si lo hice todo como es debido cuando te curé.

Got very strict orders about that, so you won’t have to worry anymore.”

Helena le tomó la mano.

He gave an audible sigh of relief and sank down to her, brushing a kiss against her forehead.

—Lo hiciste todo perfectamente.

Helena closed her eyes, trying to let him have this, but her stomach clenched and her jaw trembled as she tried to swallow her emotions.

Aún parecía preocupado.

“What’s wrong?”

—¿Y no ha pasado nada desde entonces?

She looked up and found him watching her again.

—No —respondió la chica—.

“I—I liked foraging.

No he salido del Cuartel General desde que volví.

I used to go with my father, during the summers.”

Y no… no volveré a hacerlo, salvo para venir a verte.

There was a pause. “I didn’t realise it was important to you.”

No puedo… —Se interrumpió al sentir las palabras atascadas en la garganta—.

She was silent for a moment.

No me lo permiten.

Thinking of the wetlands stretched out around her, nothing but the wilds and the mountains and the brilliant blue sky above, the only place where she could breathe without smelling blood.

Tengo órdenes estrictas al respecto, así que no tienes que seguir preocupándote.

“Sometimes it was the closest thing to freedom I still had.”

Kaine soltó un suspiro de alivio y, tras besarle la frente, se dejó caer de nuevo a su lado.

She felt him freeze.

Helena cerró los ojos y le dejó saborear ese sentimiento, aunque notaba un nudo en el estómago y la mandíbula le temblaba por contener sus emociones.

“It’ll just be until the end of the war,” he said, the words half plea and half vow.

—¿Qué pasa?

A bitter laugh caught in her chest as she looked at him. “Just till then?

Helena levantó la vista y lo descubrió mirándola de nuevo.

When’ll that be?

—Me… me gusta recolectar.

And what end do you think will somehow go well for either of us?”

Solía hacerlo con mi padre en los meses de verano.

He couldn’t meet her eyes.

Hubo un silencio breve.

She looked away, too. “There are things I’ve been a part of that I know the Eternal Flame would never officially approve of.

—No sabía que era importante para ti.

I don’t know what will happen if it all comes out.”

Helena se quedó callada durante unos instantes.

Her chest tightened as she thought about those rooms underground where Crowther had taken her so many times now.

Los recuerdos del humedal se desplegaron ante sus ojos: la naturaleza, las montañas y el brillante cielo azul, el único sitio donde podía respirar sin percibir el olor a sangre.

The blood.

—Era lo más parecido a la libertad que me quedaba.

The burns, the flayed body parts, tangled nerves, split open and twisted apart in horrible, terrifying ways.

Notó que Kaine se ponía en tensión.

Helena’s name was beside Crowther’s in those prisoner logs.

—Solo será hasta que termine la guerra —replicó en un tono a medio camino entre la súplica y la promesa.

Her handwriting cataloguing in clinical terms the injuries she’d healed, the condition of the prisoners when they died or were placed into those horrible underground cells.

A Helena le sobrevino una carcajada al mirarlo.

She knew it was intentional on Crowther’s part, having her listed as the medical personnel on-site.

—¿Solo hasta entonces?

Leverage.

¿Y cuándo llegará ese momento?

At one point, he might have let it remain a latent threat, but she expected no mercy now.

¿Y quién tiene que ganar para que alguno de los dos salgamos bien parados?

If the war was won, without Luc on her side, she had few friends.

Kaine no fue capaz de mirarla a los ojos.

Kaine took her hand. “You can run.

Ella también apartó la mirada.

Say the word, and I’ll get you out.”

—La Llama Eterna jamás aprobará oficialmente algunas de las cosas que he hecho.

A craven, exhausted part of her sparked to life at those words.

No sé qué pasará cuando salga todo a la luz.

Out.

Se le formó un nudo en la garganta cuando pensó en todas las celdas subterráneas a las que Crowther la había llevado en tantas ocasiones.

Free.

La sangre, las quemaduras, las extremidades cercenadas, los nervios destrozados, abiertos y retorcidos de formas horribles y terroríficas.

Away from the war.

El nombre de Helena figuraba junto a los registros de todos aquellos prisioneros.

She hadn’t known how much she’d wanted it until she heard it offered by someone who meant it.

Era su letra la que describía en términos clínicos las heridas que sanaba, el estado de los prisioneros cuando fallecían o la ubicación exacta en la que se encontraban dentro de aquella terrible cárcel subterránea.

She’d been so quick to refuse her father when he’d wanted to return to Etras, but now she physically longed for it.

Sabía que Crowther lo había hecho a propósito, que quería que apareciera entre el personal médico.

But the war would continue, no matter where she went, and Kaine would be there.

Así podría usarlo en su contra.

He couldn’t run.

En el pasado, tal vez se hubiera conformado con una amenaza latente, pero Helena ya no esperaba compasión de él.

If she was gone, Crowther would not keep him alive.

Si ganaban la guerra, le quedaban pocos amigos, y ni siquiera Luc estaba ya de su parte.

“No,” she said, meeting his eyes.

Kaine le cogió la mano.

“The offer stands.

—Puedes huir.

Say the word, and I’ll get you out.”

Dímelo y te sacaré de aquí.

She reached up, combing a strand of pale hair back from his eyes.

Una parte cobarde y exhausta en su interior se estremeció al oír aquellas palabras.

“What about you?” she asked.

Huir.

He grimaced. “If I could run, I would have vanished while my mother was alive.”

Libertad.

“Would you go now, if you could?”

Lejos de la guerra.

His eyes seemed to ripple with heat. “With you, I would.”

No se había dado cuenta de cuánto lo deseaba hasta que lo oyó de labios de alguien que lo decía de verdad.

She forced a smile. “Then we’ll go together.

Cuando su padre le propuso volver a Etras, lo rechazó, pero ahora lo deseaba con todo su ser.

After the war.” She gripped his hand and pressed it against her chest, letting him feel her heartbeat. “When the war is over.

Sin embargo, dondequiera que fuese, la guerra continuaría, y Kaine participaría en ella. Él no podría huir.

We’ll run away somewhere no one knows us.

Si se marchaba, Crowther no lo mantendría con vida.

We’ll disappear—forever.”

—No —negó mirándolo a los ojos.

His eyes flickered, but he smiled back. “Of course.”

—Mantengo la oferta.

He was lying.

Te sacaré de aquí si me lo pides.

They both were.

Helena estiró una mano y le apartó un mechón de pelo rubio de los ojos.

It was daydream to think it possible.

—¿Y tú qué? —preguntó.

She squeezed his hand tighter until the illusion faded.

Kaine torció el gesto.

She swallowed hard, dreading what she had to say. “The Eternal Flame has recently obtained new information about the process that the Undying undergo to gain their immutability.

—Si pudiera huir, lo habría hecho cuando mi madre aún estaba viva.

I was asked to question you about the details.

—¿Te irías ahora si pudieras hacerlo?

To verify the information.”

Sus ojos se encendieron con pasión.

Kaine just stared at her for a moment.

—Si es contigo, sí.

Then his gaze turned dissociative.

Helena se obligó a sonreír.

“Kaine.” She touched him, and he started.

—Entonces nos iremos juntos.

“It’s a blur,” he said quickly. “I don’t remember.”

Cuando termine la guerra. —Le tomó la mano y se la llevó al pecho para que sintiera el latido de su corazón—.

“Anything helps.

Cuando termine la guerra.

It really does.”

Huiremos a un lugar donde nadie nos conozca.

He was silent, his chest rising and falling several times before he spoke again. “What do you want to know?”

Desapareceremos para siempre.

“There was an array involved?”

Los ojos de Kaine se humedecieron, pero le devolvió la sonrisa.

He nodded slowly.

—Por supuesto.

“Could you describe it?

Estaba mintiendo.

Or draw it?”

Ambos mentían.

He shook his head. “I never got a good look at it.

No era más que un sueño.

I remember there were nine points, and I was in the middle.

Helena le apretó la mano hasta que la ilusión se deshizo.

I was cooperating, but they still drugged me and strapped me down so I couldn’t move.”

Luego tragó saliva; le daba miedo decir lo que venía después.

He was staring at the far wall.

—La Llama Eterna ha obtenido más información sobre el proceso al que se someten los inmarcesibles para obtener la inmortalidad.

“They started to bring the staff in.

Me han pedido que te pregunte por los detalles, para verificar la información.

The ones they hadn’t already killed.

Kaine le sostuvo la mirada unos instantes.

I hadn’t known how it worked, that they were going to—when I asked what they were doing, I was told I was lucky we had so many servants, they didn’t need to use my mother.”

Después, se quedó mirando a la nada.

“They used your servants?”

—Kaine. —Helena lo tocó, y él se sobresaltó.

He nodded slowly. “We never had much company in the countryside.

—Solo veo un borrón —dijo rápidamente—.

My mother was sick so often, and with all the rumours, my father didn’t trust anyone.

No lo recuerdo.

He was busy managing the guild, so it was just the two of us there, and the servants.

—Cualquier cosa servirá.

They were almost like family, some of them.

De verdad.

My mother’s lady’s maid, Davies, had been with her since she was a girl, and came with her to Spirefell when she married.

Guardó silencio y respiró profundamente un par de veces antes de volver a hablar:

After the birth, when my mother was—Davies practically raised me the first few years.”

—¿Qué quieres saber?

“I’m so sorry, Kaine.”

—¿Había algún sello en el suelo?

He was silent for a long time, not looking at her. “There was this platform over me, and then Morrough was leaning down.

Kaine asintió levemente.

He had something in his hand.

—¿Podrías describírmelo?

The bone shard, I think.

¿O dibujarlo?

I remember screaming.

Negó con la cabeza.

When I woke up, there was still screaming, but it wasn’t me anymore.

—No llegué a verlo bien.

I couldn’t hear it, I could just feel it.

Recuerdo que había nueve puntas y que yo estaba en el centro.

Like they were sutured inside me, all mangled but still alive.”

Cooperé, pero aun así me drogaron y me ataron para que no pudiera moverme.

She stared at him in horror. “Do you still—hear them?”

Mientras hablaba, miraba la pared del fondo.

He blinked slowly. “They’re quieter now.”

—Hicieron pasar al personal de la mansión, a los que todavía no habían asesinado.

She swallowed hard. “According to the information we have, the Undying are a by-product of Morrough’s attempts to harness power without suffering from ill effects.”

Yo no sabía cómo funcionaba el proceso, qué iban a… Cuando pregunté qué iban a hacer, me dijeron que tenía suerte de tener tantos sirvientes, porque así no tendrían que usar a mi madre.

He was silent a moment. “So if we kill the Undying, that weakens him.”

—¿Mataron a tus sirvientes?

“In theory, yes.

Kaine asintió distraído.

Would destroying the talismans affect the phylacteries?

—En el campo no solíamos tener mucha compañía.

Does that kill the Undying?”

Mi madre caía enferma a menudo y, con tantos rumores, mi padre no confiaba en nadie. Él siempre estaba ocupado con el gremio, así que nos encontrábamos allí los dos solos, junto con los sirvientes.

Kaine shook his head. “No.

Algunos de ellos eran prácticamente de la familia.

He can make another, but they’re—only slightly more intelligent than necrothralls then.”

La doncella de mi madre, Davies, la había acompañado desde que era niña, y vino a Puntaférreo con ella cuando se casó.

“There must be some way, though.

Cuando nací, cuando mi madre empezó a… Davies fue la que me crio los primeros años.

We’ll figure it out.”

—Lo siento mucho, Kaine.

He looked at her, his expression beginning to clear and sharpen again. “If the Undying are the source of Morrough’s power, that means this won’t be over until they’re all dead.”

Se quedó callado un buen rato, sin atreverse a mirarla.

She knew instantly what he was trying to prepare her for. “No.

—Había una plataforma por encima de mí, desde donde se inclinaba Morrough.

I’ll find a way to reverse it.

Tenía algo en la mano.

If it’s possible to bind a soul, surely it can be unbound.”

Supongo que sería la esquirla de hueso.

“Helena …”

Recuerdo que grité.

She shook her head. “You already thought I couldn’t save you once.

Cuando recobré la consciencia, todavía se escuchaban gritos, pero no era yo quien los profería.

You should give me more credit.” She cleared her throat, refusing to have this conversation.

No los escuchaba, simplemente los sentía, como si estuvieran atrapados en mi interior.

She stood, dressing quickly. “I have to take this information back to Headquarters.”

Todos enredados, pero aún con vida.

She didn’t really care about reporting to Crowther, though.

Helena lo observó horrorizada.

She wanted to begin reviewing the array that Wagner had sketched.

—¿Sigues… oyéndolos?

She needed to do research.

Kaine cerró y abrió los ojos lentamente.

“Wait.

—Ahora están más callados.

I have something for you, although I hope you won’t need them again.” Wrapped in oilcloth were her daggers.

Helena tragó saliva.

She’d been sure they’d been washed downriver.

—Según la información que tenemos, los inmarcesibles son el resultado de los intentos de Morrough por hacerse con el poder sin sufrir las consecuencias adversas.

“How’d you find them?”

Kaine guardó silencio unos instantes.

“I had spares made.

—Entonces, si matamos a los inmarcesibles, lo debilitaremos.

It took long enough to find a metallurgist with a resonance for your alloy.

—En teoría, sí.

I figured a few extra sets might be wise.”

Si destruimos los talismanes, ¿afectará a las filacterias?

“Thank you,” she said, touching them fondly and then putting them carefully in her satchel before she began to fix her hair.

¿Así es como mueren los inmarcesibles?

“I hate your hair like that,” he said, startling her.

Kaine negó con la cabeza.

She looked up. “I could crop it instead.”

—No, puede generar otra filacteria, pero el resultado… Son poco más inteligentes que un necrómata.

He looked so offended that she laughed.

—Pero tiene que haber una forma.

“I have to keep it out of the way when working, and I’m always on call for emergencies.

La encontraremos.

It’s practical.”

El chico la miró; sus ojos volvieron a despejarse y a enfocar de nuevo.

He looked unconvinced. “I want to see you more.”

—Si los inmarcesibles son la fuente de poder de Morrough, eso significa que la guerra no acabará hasta que estén todos muertos.

Her fingers stilled.

Helena supo de inmediato que quería prepararla para lo peor.

She could see the hunger in his eyes.

—No.

Possessive.

Hallaré la forma de revertirlo.

Ravenous.

Si es posible unir almas, seguro que también se pueden desunir.

He would drag her from the war and hide her the instant she let him.

—Helena…

The conflict was visible in his eyes.

Esta negó con la cabeza.

Want.

—Ya creí una vez que no podría salvarte.

Want.

Deberías confiar un poco más en mí —carraspeó.

Want.

No deseaba tener esta conversación, así que se puso en pie y se vistió con rapidez.

She felt it like her heartbeat.

En realidad, le daba igual informar a Crowther.

If he couldn’t hide her, he would hoard her to himself as much as he was able to.

Lo que quería era revisar el sello que había dibujado Wagner para poder investigarlo.

She’d fallen for a dragon.

—Espera.

“I’ve always been on call for you,” she said. “If you call me, I’ll come here as soon as I can.”

Tengo algo para ti que ojalá no vuelvas a necesitar.

He shook his head at that. “No.

En un paño impermeable se encontraban sus dagas.

We can’t use the Outpost much longer.

Helena había creído que la corriente se las había llevado.

There’s plans for repairing it under way.”

—¿Cómo las has encontrado?

Her heart sank. “Oh.

—Hice unas de repuesto.

Then how would we—”

Tardé mucho tiempo en encontrar un metalúrgico que tuviera la resonancia de tu aleación, así que pensé que lo más sensato era encargar dagas de sobra.

“The Resistance doesn’t watch the skies,” he said. “Now that Amaris is older, it’s not difficult to fly to the East Island at night.

—Gracias —respondió, acariciándolas con cariño y metiéndolas con cuidado en la bolsa.

I’m sure there’s a rooftop somewhere.

Luego comenzó a trenzarse el cabello.

I’ll find something before next week.

—Odio que lo lleves así —le espetó Kaine, y aquello la sobresaltó.

If the ring activates only once, it’s not Resistance-related.

Alzó la mirada.

Signal back when you’re there, and I’ll come for you.”

—También podría cortármelo. —Él pareció ofenderse de tal manera que tuvo que reírse—.

She lifted her left hand.

No puedo tenerlo suelto cuando estoy trabajando, y siempre tengo que estar disponible por si hay alguna emergencia.

She’d feared the refraction effect might eventually wear off, but it still held; she could barely see the ring unless she focused.

Es práctico.

It was so light, she almost forgot about it at times.

Kaine no parecía muy convencido.

“I thought you said if I ever burned you—”

—Quiero verte más a menudo.

He captured her hand and pulled her close.

Helena dejó de mover los dedos.

His other hand slid possessively up her throat, fingers tilting her head back, and he kissed her, long and deep, before he drew away to meet her eyes.

Percibió la voracidad de sus ojos, la posesión, el hambre.

“Call me, and I will come.”

Si se lo permitía, la alejaría de la guerra y la escondería.

Y ese conflicto se hacía evidente en sus ojos.

Deseo.

Deseo.

Deseo.

Lo sentía igual que el latido de su corazón.

Si no podía esconderla, la acapararía para sí tanto como pudiera.

Se había enamorado de un dragón.

—Siempre estaré disponible para ti —replicó—.

Si me llamas, vendré en cuanto pueda.

Kaine sacudió la cabeza al oír eso.

—No, no podremos seguir usando el Reducto como punto de encuentro.

Hay planes de reconstrucción.

A Helena se le encogió el corazón.

—Ah.

¿Entonces cómo vamos a…?

—La Resistencia no vigila los cielos —afirmó—.

Ahora que Amaris ha crecido, podrá volar de noche a la isla Este.

Estoy seguro de que hay alguna azotea por allí.

Buscaré un sitio para la semana que viene.

Si el anillo se activa una sola vez, eso querrá decir que no está relacionado con la Resistencia.

Avísame tú cuando llegues e iré a por ti.

Helena levantó la mano izquierda.

Había temido que la refracción se desgastara con el paso del tiempo, pero seguía aguantando.

Ya no veía el anillo a menos que se esforzara, y era tan ligero que a veces se olvidaba de que lo llevaba puesto.

—Dijiste que si alguna vez te avisaba yo…

Kaine la tomó de la mano y la atrajo hacia sí.

La mano que le quedaba libre se deslizó por su garganta hasta que sus dedos echaron la cabeza de Helena hacia atrás.

La besó con pasión y, después, la miró fijamente a los ojos.

—Llámame y acudiré.

CHAPTER 55

Aprilis 1787

CAPÍTULO 55

KAINE CALLED HER.

Abrilis 1787

OFTEN.

Kaine la llamaba con frecuencia.

Sometimes his duties came to an end in the late evening, but most of the time it was past midnight.

A veces terminaba sus obligaciones a última hora de la tarde, pero la mayoría de las veces era ya pasada la medianoche.

When she wasn’t on shift, Helena would work in her lab until her ring burned.

Si Helena no estaba trabajando en el hospital, se quedaba en el laboratorio hasta que el anillo se activaba.

There were many buildings that were abandoned.

Había muchos edificios abandonados.

Kaine had found one with a large open roof and working lift.

Kaine había dado con uno que tenía una azotea grande y despejada, y que además contaba con un ascensor que funcionaba.

Helena didn’t have to pass through any checkpoints to reach it.

Helena no tenía que pasar por ningún puesto de control para llegar.

Sometimes Amaris wouldn’t even land.

En ocasiones, Amaris ni siquiera necesitaba aterrizar.

Helena would stand in the open-most part of the rooftop, and silent as a wraith, Amaris would drop from the sky, Kaine leaning over and snatching Helena up, and they’d be airborne, riding the wind, climbing over the buildings without being seen.

Helena esperaba en el centro de la azotea y, silenciosa como un espectro, Amaris caía del firmamento.

They’d land, and he’d pull her off Amaris, checking her over.

Kaine se echaba hacia delante y recogía a Helena.

“You’re all right?

Al instante estaban en el aire, surcando el viento, volando por encima de los edificios sin que los vieran.

Has anything happened to you?” he’d ask, even though she’d felt his resonance beneath her skin while they were flying, and he knew she wasn’t injured.

En cuanto aterrizaban, Kaine bajaba a Helena de la quimera y la examinaba de la cabeza a los pies.

She hadn’t expected him to be so obsessively worried.

—¿Te encuentras bien?

She’d observed his quick arrival at the Outpost, the careful way his eyes would track her, but she hadn’t considered how deep the fear cut into him until he didn’t have to hide it.

¿Te ha pasado algo? —preguntaba, a pesar de que Helena había notado la resonancia de Kaine bajo su piel por el camino y sabía que no estaba herida.

They’d go inside, and she’d let him see her in the light, holding her arms out to prove she was in the same condition she’d been the last time.

Helena jamás hubiera imaginado que se preocuparía hasta ese extremo.

“I’m fine.

Siempre había sido consciente de lo rápido que llegaba al Reducto, de lo cuidadosamente que la observaba, pero no se había dado cuenta de lo profundo que le atravesaba el miedo hasta que dejó de ocultarlo.

See?

Nada más entrar en la casa, Helena le permitía examinarla bajo la luz y extendía los brazos para demostrar que seguía en el mismo estado que la vez anterior.

You don’t need to worry.”

—Estoy bien.

The reassurance never seemed to have any effect.

¿Ves?

Whatever had happened to his mother had been hidden, and Enid Ferron had never told him fully—either because she couldn’t, or to spare him.

No tienes que preocuparte.

Withholding it had probably been the worse choice.

Aquella afirmación nunca parecía surtir efecto.

Kaine was like her.

Lo que le había sucedido a su madre había estado oculto, y Enid Ferron nunca se lo había contado todo, ya fuese porque no podía o porque quería ahorrarle el sufrimiento.

He obsessed over what he didn’t know more than anything else.

Sin embargo, ese secretismo había resultado ser la peor opción.

She’d meet his eyes, hold his face in her hands. “I’m fine.

Kaine era igual que ella: se obsesionaba más con lo que desconocía que con cualquier otra cosa.

Nothing has happened.”

Helena lo miró a los ojos y le sostuvo la cara entre sus manos.

Once he was finally convinced that she had no hidden injuries, a tension inside him would break.

—Estoy bien.

He’d gather her in his arms, and she’d feel his heart pounding.

No me ha pasado nada.

You did this to him, she reminded herself whenever she was tempted to grow impatient with the ritual.

Una vez que lo convencía de que no le ocultaba ninguna herida, la tensión de su cuerpo se relajaba.

You guessed where he was vulnerable and you exploited it.

La abrazaba hasta que sentía el latido de su corazón retumbando contra el suyo.

She’d run her own fingers over him, trying to detect any injuries on him before he kissed her again.

«Tú le has hecho esto —se recordaba a sí misma cuando empezaba a impacientarse con aquel ritual—.

He’d hide them or ignore them as if they didn’t exist unless she managed to discover them.

Descubriste lo que le hacía vulnerable y te aprovechaste de ello».

Nullium injuries had begun appearing among the wounded after battles.

Helena le recorría el cuerpo con los dedos para detectar alguna nueva herida antes de que él la volviera a besar.

Sometimes Kaine would end up with a shard in his body somewhere, and while its effects on him were limited, when it entered his bloodstream, it could slow his regeneration for hours unless she intervened.

Sin embargo, Kaine solía esconderlas o ignorarlas como si no existieran, a menos que Helena las descubriera.

She never had and never would heal anyone the way she healed Kaine: in his arms, pressed against his body.

Las heridas de anulitio habían empezado a aparecer en los soldados heridos en batalla.

She’d bribe him into cooperation by pressing openmouthed kisses across his shoulders, hands, and face while her resonance found every place he was hurt, checking him over meticulously until he’d grow impatient and pin her hands down, pushing her back on the bed and taking her slowly.

A veces, Kaine acababa con algo de metralla incrustada en el cuerpo y, aunque a él le afectaba de forma leve, si entraba en su torrente sanguíneo, podía ralentizar su regeneración durante horas, a menos que Helena interviniera.

It was always deliriously slowly.

Nunca había sanado ni nunca sanaría a nadie del modo en que curaba a Kaine: en sus brazos, pegada a su cuerpo.

He’d stare into her eyes until she almost felt their minds touching.

Lo sobornaba para que cooperase dándole besos con los labios separados sobre los hombros, en las manos, en la cara, y, mientras tanto, su resonancia buscaba todos los lugares que estaban heridos y revisaba su cuerpo meticulosamente.

“You’re mine.

Hasta que Kaine se hartaba, le sujetaba las manos, la empujaba sobre la cama y le hacía el amor lentamente.

You’re mine.” He’d repeat the words over and over. “Say it.

Siempre lo hacían a un ritmo que les hacía perder la cabeza.

Say you’re mine.”

Kaine la miraba a los ojos hasta que Helena sentía el roce de sus mentes.

He’d entwine their fingers, press their foreheads together, and sometimes his whole body would tremble.

—Eres mía.

She’d wrap her arms around him, trying to reassure him.

Eres mía. —Repetía esas palabras una y otra vez—.

“I promise, Kaine.

Dilo.

I’m always going to be yours.”

Di que eres mía.

There was a possessive terror in him—in the ways he touched her—as though he always expected it to be the last time he ever saw her.

Kaine entrelazaba sus dedos con los de ella, presionaba frente con frente y, en ocasiones, le temblaba todo el cuerpo.

When he didn’t summon her, time stretched, filling Helena with a bottomless dread until her ring burned again.

Helena lo abrazaba para darle seguridad.

Then she was the one who would desperately demand to know if he was all right.

—Te lo prometo, Kaine.

On the nights she slept alone, she had nightmares of him being killed.

Siempre seré tuya.

Sometimes gone forever, other times as a lich, or discovered and caught.

Había un miedo posesivo en la forma en la que la tocaba, como si creyera que esa sería la última vez que la vería.

She didn’t know which possibility to fear most.

Si Kaine no la llamaba, el tiempo se alargaba, y Helena empezaba a sentir un miedo infinito hasta que el anillo volvía a arder.

“Be careful.” It was always the last thing she said to him before he left her on some rooftop.

Entonces era ella quien, desesperada, exigía saber si él se encontraba bien.

She would hold his face in her hands, staring into his eyes. “Don’t die.”

Las noches que dormía sola, tenía pesadillas en las que alguien lo mataba.

He’d dip his head forward, kissing her inner wrist or the palm of her hand, his silver eyes locked on her face. “You’re mine.

A veces desaparecía para siempre; otras, se convertía en un liche, o lo descubrían y lo apresaban.

I’ll always come for you.”

No sabía cuál de esas opciones le daba más miedo.

He always did.

—Ten cuidado. —Era lo que siempre le decía antes de dejarla en alguna azotea.

Yet each day it felt as though the odds were being pushed higher.

Le sostenía la cara entre las manos y lo miraba a los ojos—.

Steeper.

No mueras.

The war teetered on the brink of calamity.

Kaine inclinaba la cabeza y le besaba el interior de la muñeca o la palma de la mano sin despegar esos ojos plateados de su rostro.

She wasn’t sure how far the array and his own determination could take him before everything came crashing down.

—Eres mía.

He was walking a razor’s edge.

Siempre volveré a por ti.

When he slept, she’d stare at his face and will his survival.

Siempre lo hacía.

She’d make it happen.

Sin embargo, con el paso de los días parecía que las probabilidades de éxito se volvían en su contra.

They’d go away, across the sea so no one would ever find them.

Cada vez era más difícil.

She promised herself she’d find a way.

La guerra estaba al borde de la catástrofe.

She promised him: There would be an after.

No estaba segura de hasta dónde la llevaría el sello y su propia determinación antes de que todo se viniera abajo.

“I’m going to take care of you.

Estaba caminando en el filo de una navaja.

I swear, Helena, I’m always going to take care of you.” She heard him muttering the words against her skin or into her hair in such a low voice, she could barely make them out.

Cuando dormía, Helena contemplaba su rostro y rezaba para que sobreviviera.

Some days the compulsion seemed worse than others.

Lo haría posible.

She heard him repeating it over and over one night.

Se marcharían lejos, más allá del mar, donde nadie pudiera encontrarlos jamás.

He usually stopped after a little while, but this time he didn’t.

Se prometía a sí misma que hallaría la forma de hacerlo, y se lo prometía a él: habría un después de la guerra.

She lifted her head and held his face between her hands so that she could meet his eyes. “Kaine, I’m all right.

—Yo cuidaré de ti.

Nothing’s going to happen to me.”

Te lo juro, Helena, siempre voy a cuidar de ti. —Helena lo escuchaba mascullar esas palabras contra su piel o su cabello.

He stared at her with the same bitterly resigned expression he’d worn while training her and whenever she turned to leave, like he was bracing himself, waiting for what he regarded as inevitable.

Un susurro apenas audible.

The war was a cage with no escape.

Había días en que la compulsión se agravaba.

He subsided and rested his head on her chest, listening to her heartbeat, arms framing her.

Aquella noche lo escuchó repetirlo una y otra vez.

She tangled her fingers through his hair, and it was quiet, but she could feel him mouthing the words.

Normalmente paraba al cabo de un rato, pero esa vez no lo hizo.

She hesitated before she spoke.

Helena levantó la cabeza y le sostuvo el rostro entre las manos para obligarlo a que la mirara a los ojos.

“Tell me about your mother, Kaine.

—Kaine, estoy bien.

Tell me everything you could never tell anyone.”

No va a pasarme nada.

He went silent.

La contempló con la misma expresión entre la amargura y la resignación, la que había adoptado cuando la entrenaba y cada vez que se daba la vuelta para marcharse, como si se estuviera preparando, esperando lo inevitable.

She slid her fingers over his shoulders, tracing the interconnected scars from the array. “You can tell me.

La guerra era una jaula sin escapatoria.

I’ll help you carry it.”

Aun así, se calmó y descansó la cabeza sobre su pecho, escuchando el latido de su corazón envuelto en sus brazos.

He didn’t speak for such a long time, she wondered if he’d fallen asleep.

Helena le pasó los dedos por el cabello y, aunque estaba callado, notó que seguía repitiendo las palabras.

Then he turned his head, just enough that she could see his profile.

—Háblame de tu madre, Kaine —le pidió tras un instante de duda—.

“I’d never seen anyone tortured before,” he said at last. “She was—the first person I ever saw tortured.

Cuéntame todo lo que no pudiste decirle a nadie.

He—” His jaw trembled as he struggled for words. “—they experimented on her.

Kaine permaneció callado.

Even though she wasn’t even—she hadn’t done anything.”

Ella deslizó los dedos hasta sus hombros y recorrió las cicatrices entrelazadas del sello.

As he spoke, his eyes grew wide.

—Puedes contármelo.

He stared across the room, his gaze far away.

Te ayudaré a llevar la carga.

Helena watched and she could see him, just sixteen and home for the summer holidays.

Siguió en silencio tanto tiempo que Helena se preguntó si se habría quedado dormido.

Home, walking unknowingly into a nightmare that he would never escape.

Pero entonces giró la cabeza, lo justo para que ella pudiera ver su perfil.

“I thought—” His voice was suddenly younger.

—Nunca había visto cómo torturaban a alguien —dijo al fin—.

Boyish. “For a while I thought that if I killed the Principate soon enough, she’d recover.

Ella fue… la primera persona que torturaron ante mis ojos. Él… —Le tembló la barbilla mientras buscaba las palabras—.

That I could fix it all.

Experimentaron con ella.

But she was—a shadow of herself when I returned.

Aunque ella ni siquiera estaba… No había hecho nada.

I think—I think she tried to hold on over the summer, show a brave face while I was there, but—

A medida que hablaba, fue abriendo los ojos y contempló la habitación con la mirada perdida.

“I wasn’t even gone a month.” The words were low, wavering.

Helena también lo vio: él, con dieciséis años volviendo a casa para las vacaciones de verano.

Helena laced her fingers through his hair.

Entró sin saber que estaba a punto de enfrentarse a una pesadilla de la que jamás podría escapar.

He closed his eyes and drew his chin down, his body contracting inwards.

—Pensé… —Su voz se volvió más joven, más juvenil—.

“After I killed the Principate, it took more than a day to get back, and they knew I’d done it.

Durante un tiempo, pensé que, si asesinaba al principado rápidamente, ella se recuperaría.

They’d heard, but they didn’t let her out until I gave him that fucking heart—still beating.

Que podría arreglarlo todo.

She kept having these fits; she’d crumple on the floor, or stop breathing, or sit rocking and muttering.

Pero, cuando regresé, no era más que… una sombra de sí misma.

I brought in doctors, but they said there was nothing wrong with her but a weak constitution and tendencies towards hysteria.

Creo que… creo que intentó aguantar el verano, que se mostró valiente mientras estuve presente, pero… No duró ni un mes. —Las palabras sonaron graves, temblorosas.

They recommended institutionalising her, or administering all these tonics and injections that left her in a stupor.”

Helena le pasó los dedos por el cabello.

Helena squeezed his hand, running her fingers across the array.

Kaine cerró los ojos y bajó la cabeza; se encogió sobre sí mismo.

Calculating, Cunning, Devoted, Determined, Ruthless, Unfailing, Unhesitating, and Unyielding.

—Cuando asesiné al principado, tardé más de un día en regresar, y ellos ya sabían lo que había hecho.

To avenge his mother.

Escucharon los rumores, pero no la soltaron hasta que les entregué ese maldito corazón, que todavía latía.

In penance for all the ways he believed he’d failed her.

Mi madre no paraba de sufrir ataques; se desplomaba en el suelo, dejaba de respirar o se mecía murmurando sin parar.

“I’m so sorry, Kaine.”

Hice que varios médicos la revisaran, pero todos dijeron que no le pasaba nada, que simplemente era de constitución débil y tenía tendencia a la histeria.

He was quiet.

Me recomendaron que la ingresara en una clínica o le suministrara tónicos e inyecciones que la dejaban aletargada.

He closed his eyes and drew a sharp breath.

Helena le apretó la mano y siguió recorriendo el sello de la espalda con los dedos.

“Then—” His voice cut off.

Calculador, astuto, devoto, tenaz, implacable, eficaz, resuelto y severo.

“Then—” It failed again. “She’d been doing better, I thought she might even recover, but I—I—We’d taken a new district.

Todo para vengar a su madre.

There was a list of families we were supposed to make examples of.

Como castigo por todos los momentos en los que creía haberle fallado.

Father, mother, two children.

—Lo siento mucho, Kaine.

After we killed the parents, they reanimated the mother, had her with the older girl.

Se sumió en el silencio.

I was supposed to come up with something with—with the father and the younger one.

Después, cerró los ojos y tomó aire con dificultad.

Little thing, wearing two braids with bows on them.

—Entonces… —se le quebró la voz—.

There was a birthday cake.

Entonces… —le falló de nuevo— se puso mejor.

I think it was hers.

Creí que tal vez se recuperaría, pero yo… yo… Habíamos tomado un nuevo distrito.

Durant dragged her over by her hair and handed her to me—I knew what they wanted but I ran.”

Había una lista de familias con las que debíamos dar ejemplo.

He swallowed. “I booked a ship, passage for two.

Padre, madre, dos hijas.

I thought my mother and I could just sail away together, and she wouldn’t know I couldn’t really go with her until it was too late.

Cuando asesinamos a los padres, los inmarcesibles reanimaron a la madre y la obligaron a matar a la hija mayor.

But when I went to get her, they’d gotten there first.

Se suponía que yo debía hacer algo parecido con el padre y la hija menor.

They’d brought the corpse.”

Era muy pequeña, llevaba dos trenzas con lacitos.

“Oh, Kaine …” Helena was too horrified to say more than that.

Había una tarta de cumpleaños.

He was gripping her hand so hard, she suspected there’d be bruises where his fingers were entwined.

Creo que era el suyo.

“I tried to find a way to run with her.” His voice shifted, starting to grow familiar as the story moved through his life.

Durant la arrastró por el pelo y me la puso delante… Sabía lo que querían que hiciera, pero salí corriendo. —Tragó saliva—.

Traces of his hard, controlled tone beginning to emerge. “I had everything prepared, every detail and contingency, but she wouldn’t leave without me.

Reservé dos pasajes en un barco.

I thought about forcing her, drugging her, putting her on the boat and sending her away, but I was so afraid she’d come back for me, and I didn’t want to have her locked away.

Pensé que mi madre y yo podríamos huir por el mar, y que no se daría cuenta de que no podría acompañarla hasta que fuese demasiado tarde.

I didn’t want to be someone who caged her again.”

Pero, cuando fui a buscarla, ellos se me habían adelantado.

His voice grew deadened. “If I hadn’t gone home that night … she wouldn’t have died.

Traían el cadáver de la niña.

I don’t know why I did.”

—Oh, Kaine… —Helena estaba tan horrorizada que no fue capaz de decir nada más. Él le apretaba la mano tan fuerte que temió que le saldrían moratones ahí donde se entrelazaban sus dedos.

He fell silent.

—Traté de buscar una forma de escapar con ella. —Le cambió la voz, fue adquiriendo el tono habitual conforme la historia se adentraba en su vida.

Helena shifted out from under him enough to sit up.

Empezó a emplear un tono duro y controlado—.

She couldn’t look at him without a tearing pain spreading through her chest.

Lo tenía todo preparado, había previsto cada detalle, cada contingencia, pero mi madre no quiso irse sin mí.

She touched him lightly on the forehead. “Kaine—I’m not your mother.”

Me planteé obligarla, drogarla y subirla al barco para alejarla de allí, pero me daba miedo que volviera para buscarme, y no quería que la encerraran.

He flinched, opening his mouth to deny, but she continued without letting him cut her off. “The Eternal Flame is not going to hurt me if you fail an assignment.

No deseaba ser yo quien volviera a enjaularla. —Su voz se vació de toda emoción—.

They aren’t going to torture or endanger me to punish you.

Si no hubiera vuelto a casa aquella noche…, aún seguiría con vida.

I’m not a hostage.

No sé por qué lo hice.

I’m in this war because I choose to be.

Se quedó callado.

I’m not fragile.

Helena se removió bajo su cuerpo y se incorporó.

I’m not going to break.

No podía mirarlo sin sentir una punzada de dolor en el pecho.

Please.” She brushed her thumb over the arch of his cheekbone. “Believe that about me.”

Le rozó suavemente la frente.

He shook his head. “Let me get you out.

—Kaine… Yo no soy tu madre.

I swear it won’t affect my aid to the Resistance.

El chico se encogió y abrió la boca para replicar, pero Helena siguió hablando para que no pudiera interrumpirla.

Just let me get you out.”

—La Llama Eterna no me hará daño si fracasas en una misión.

“I’m not going to run while everyone else is fighting.

No van a torturarme ni a ponerme en peligro para castigarte.

We can do this together.

No soy el rehén de nadie.

Let me help you.

Participo en la guerra por decisión propia.

You don’t have to do everything alone now.”

No estoy hecha de porcelana y no pienso romperme.

Despair flooded across his eyes.

Por favor… —Le acarició el pómulo con el pulgar—.

“You can’t ask me to run away from the war.”

Confía en mí, por favor.

His lip curled. “Why not?

Kaine negó con la cabeza.

Haven’t you done enough for them?

—Déjame sacarte de aquí.

They sold you.

Te juro que no afectará a mi colaboración con la Resistencia.

What if I’d—” His voice cut off, and he couldn’t meet her eyes. “What if you’d had the same offer from someone who’d meant it.

Pero déjame sacarte de aquí.

You would have still gone—and if I hadn’t trained you, you would have died rescuing Holdfast.”

—No pienso huir mientras los demás siguen luchando.

“And I agreed to it.

Podemos hacerlo juntos.

All of it.

Permíteme ayudarte.

No one ever made me.

No tienes que cargar con todo tú solo.

We don’t get to choose when we’ve done enough and leave others behind to bear the consequences.

La tristeza inundó sus ojos.

There are no civilians in a war like this.

—No puedes pedirme que huya de la guerra.

If they win”—she spread her hands—“everyone loses.”

Kaine hizo un gesto amargo.

He clenched his jaw, and she knew what he wanted to say, that he didn’t care.

—¿Por qué no?

He didn’t care whether anyone survived except her.

¿Es que no has hecho bastante por ellos?

Helena gave a sad sigh and dropped her head, burying her face in his shoulder.

Te vendieron.

He wrapped his arms around her.

¿Qué habría sucedido si…? —No terminó la frase, incapaz de mirarla a los ojos—.

She was almost asleep when she heard the faint whisper of his voice. “I’m going to take care of you.

¿Qué habría sucedido si hubieran recibido una oferta de alguien que quisiera aprovecharla de verdad?

I swear, I’m always going to take care of you.”

Habrías accedido igualmente… y, si yo no te hubiera entrenado, habrías muerto al rescatar a Holdfast.

KAINE WAS HELENA’S ONLY SOURCE of solace as things within the Resistance deteriorated.

—Y yo accedí a hacerlo.

When Lila finally recovered her resonance, her long convalescence seemed to have sucked the life from her.

A todas esas cosas.

She was unable to spring back the way she usually did, and the scarring from all the surgery on her chest and shoulder was so severe that it bound her movement, requiring extensive healing and therapy to regain mobility.

Nadie me obligó en ningún momento.

Helena planned out a potential treatment regimen, but then it was assigned to one of the other healers.

No podemos elegir cuándo hemos hecho suficiente y dejar a los demás atrás para que sufran las consecuencias.

Luc had requested that Helena be kept away from Lila as well as himself.

En una guerra como esta, no hay civiles.

Helena sat staring at Pace’s desk after she was informed of it.

Si ellos ganan —extendió las manos—, todos perderemos.

“You’ll still work casualty shifts,” Pace said.

Kaine apretó los dientes, y Helena supo lo que quería decir: que le daba igual.

“Right,” Helena said, in a dull voice. “I take it that means Luc’s more lucid, then?

Nunca le había importado que sobreviviera nadie más que ella.

If he’s making requests now.”

Helena dejó escapar un suspiro de pena y bajó la cabeza hasta enterrarla en su hombro. Él la rodeó con sus brazos.

Since Luc was moved to his private quarters, Helena had not seen or heard a word about him or his condition, although the Council insisted that he was still steadily recovering.

Casi se había dormido cuando oyó el susurro de su voz:

The matron’s lips twitched. “Well, ‘lucid’ is certainly a word you could use.” She cleared her throat. “I’m sure that with time, he’ll even out again.

—Yo cuidaré de ti.

You don’t need to worry about him; there’s plenty of other people doing that.”

Te lo juro, siempre voy a cuidar de ti.

Helena nodded slowly, but time was not something that the Eternal Flame had.

Kaine era el único consuelo de Helena cuando la situación en la Resistencia empezó a deteriorarse.

Luc was the keystone for the Resistance.

Cuando por fin Lila recuperó su resonancia, la larga convalecencia parecía haberle arrancado parte de su vitalidad.

Without him, everything grew quickly volatile.

Ya no era capaz de reponerse de la misma forma que antes, y las cicatrices de la cirugía que habían llevado a cabo en el pecho y en el hombro eran tan profundas que le limitaban el movimiento, por lo que necesitaba de una sanación constante y terapia para recuperar la movilidad.

Crowther began leaning more heavily on Kaine, using him to seed misinformation and sabotage, as though the Undying army were a machine to be deconstructed.

Helena diseñó un tratamiento para ella, pero se la asignaron a otra de las sanadoras.

The envelopes with orders were thicker every time Helena delivered them.

Luc había exigido que Helena se mantuviera alejada de Lila al igual que de él mismo.

Kaine made no mention of what he did, but she could tell he was on the verge of breaking under the pressure.

Ella se quedó sentada junto al escritorio de Pace cuando se lo comunicaron.

He grew steadily more desperate each time he saw her.

—Todavía tienes turnos en el hospital —dijo Pace.

It ate at Helena, watching him erode under everything he was expected to maintain and produce for both sides while Helena was trapped in Headquarters like a caged animal.

—Cierto —repuso Helena sin emoción alguna—.

Without foraging, she filled her hours with new research, Shiseo taking the lead as they tried to perfect alchemy suppression upon the Council’s request.

Si está empezando a exigir cosas, supongo que Luc está más lúcido, ¿no?

The Undying were almost impossible to take and keep captive, but with suppression, it might be possible.

Desde que trasladaron a Luc a sus aposentos privados, Helena no lo había visto ni había escuchado ni una palabra sobre él ni sobre su estado de salud, aunque el Consejo insistía en que se estaba recuperando.

She knew from Kaine that nullium interfered with the Undying’s abilities and regeneration the same as any alchemist.

Los labios de Pace esbozaron una mueca.

Shiseo designed a nullium cuff to create targeted resonance suppression, locking around the wrist to blur the resonance into a feeling like static.

—Bueno, podríamos usar la palabra «lúcido», sí —carraspeó—.

Helena tested it, locking one around her own wrist, flexing her fingers, sliding it up her arm.

Estoy segura de que, con el tiempo, volverá a ser quien era.

When it was near her elbow, she could push through the interference.

No te preocupes por él; ya tiene gente de sobra para eso.

She shook her head. “These don’t fully suppress the resonance.”

Tú cuida de ti misma, Marino.

She took it off, inspecting the interior Shiseo had lined with nullium.

Helena se limitó a asentir, aunque a la Llama Eterna no le sobraba el tiempo.

“If we really wanted to completely erase it, I think it would have to be internal,” she said. “If the nullium were encased in ceramic, that would prevent the corrosion and biointerference.

Luc era el pilar de la Resistencia.

If you put a thin tube of it right through the wrist here”—she pressed her fingers against the space between the radius and ulna—“the cuff could slot around a suppression spike and alchemically lock in place.

Sin él, todo se volvía cada vez más incierto.

I bet there wouldn’t be any resonance then.”

Crowther había empezado a depender más de Kaine, y lo usaba para sembrar información falsa y hacer sabotajes, como si el ejército de inmarcesibles fuera una máquina que había que desarmar pieza a pieza.

Shiseo looked so disturbed that Helena realised the reality of what she was proposing beyond its practical function.

Los sobres que contenían órdenes eran cada vez más gruesos.

It was one thing to think about cuffing the various Undying, all hidden behind their helmets and their dead, but when she thought about Kaine, a more likely prisoner, a pit opened inside her stomach.

Kaine nunca mencionaba lo que hacía, pero ella notaba que estaba a punto de quebrarse bajo la presión.

She shook her head. “Never mind.

Cada vez que la veía se comportaba con más desesperación.

That’s too much.

A Helena le dolía verlo desgastarse bajo el peso de todo lo que debía mantener y producir para ambos bandos, mientras ella estaba atrapada en el Cuartel General como un animal enjaulado.

We don’t need to suppress that much.”

Al no poder salir a recolectar, ocupaba su tiempo con una nueva investigación.

“It would probably work.”

Con Shiseo como jefe de laboratorio, estaba intentando perfeccionar la anulación de la alquimia.

She shook her head. “It’s not necessary.

Era algo que había solicitado el Consejo, ya que los inmarcesibles eran prácticamente imposibles de capturar y mantener encerrados, pero con esta anulación podrían conseguirlo.

This design is good enough.”

Gracias a Kaine, Helena sabía que el anulitio interfería con las habilidades y la regeneración de los inmarcesibles de la misma forma que lo hacía con cualquier alquimista.

SOMETIMES HELENA’S RING WOULD BURN twice, and often when that happened, Amaris would arrive, and Kaine would practically collapse off her back.

Shiseo había diseñado unos grilletes de anulitio que podían anular la alquimia de forma focalizada.

Other times, Amaris would appear alone.

Se cerraban alrededor de la muñeca y hacían que la resonancia se diluyera como si fuese energía estática.

Helena would climb onto the chimaera’s back, clinging to the harness as the air whipped around, and they’d fly into the underbelly of the city, to a basement, a wrecked building, or sometimes an alley, and she would find Kaine.

Helena lo puso a prueba: cerró uno alrededor de su muñeca, flexionó los dedos y lo deslizó por el brazo.

Usually a piece of nullium shrapnel would be buried into him somewhere, deep enough that he couldn’t get it out.

Cuando le llegó al codo, descubrió que podía vencer la interferencia.

She learned to always have her satchel stocked with medical tools and bandages and all kinds of different medicines.

Negó con la cabeza.

As the nullium grew increasingly effective, the injuries often required surgery.

—No anulan la resonancia completamente.

She grew adept at manual surgery with only an electric torch for light.

Se lo quitó e inspeccionó el interior, que Shiseo había recubierto de anulitio.

He wouldn’t let her knock him out, wanting to keep watch in case someone came, but he’d often be half delirious, his eyes nearly glowing silver, muttering under his breath, “I’m all right—I barely feel it.

—Para eliminarla por completo, creo que tendremos que emplear algo interno —explicó—.

Don’t worry.

Si el anulitio estuviera envuelto en cerámica, evitaríamos la corrosión y la biointerferencia.

We’ll go soon … Got it worked out.

Pero, si lo metemos en un tubito y lo introducimos en la muñeca aquí… —señaló con el dedo el espacio que había entre el radio y el cúbito—, el grillete iría unido a este punzón supresor que quedaría fijo mediante la alquimia.

Just—a little longer …”

Seguro que así no queda ni rastro de resonancia.

She’d sit with his head on her lap, singing softly to him while he stabilised, holding his hands in hers.

Shiseo parecía tan perturbado que Helena comprendió que lo que estaba proponiendo iba más allá de su función práctica.

Nullium slowed his recovery so much.

Hablaban de diseñar grilletes para los inmarcesibles, que se ocultaban bajo sus yelmos y sus muertos.

He’d have lost so much blood, he’d float on the edge of consciousness or begin trembling and go into shock.

Y, cuando pensó en Kaine, que probablemente acabaría prisionero en algún momento, sintió que el estómago se le revolvía.

She’d run her fingers and resonance across his palms, and murmur apologies.

Sacudió la cabeza.

You’re killing him.

—No he dicho nada.

You’re killing him.

Es demasiado enrevesado.

This is because of you.

No tenemos que anular la resonancia de esa forma.

She’d only let herself cry over him when he wasn’t conscious to see it.

—Funcionaría.

She gripped his hands in hers, trying to fix him.

Helena negó de nuevo.

“I’m sorry.

—No es necesario.

I’m sorry.

Este diseño nos vale.

I’m so sorry,” she said over and over.

En ocasiones, el anillo de Helena se activaba dos veces seguidas y, cuando eso sucedía, Amaris llegaba y Kaine prácticamente se derrumbaba de su lomo.

She’d wipe her eyes and then clean up the blood before he regained consciousness.

Otras veces, Amaris aparecía sola.

She’d feel the tension tear through his body the instant he came back to himself and feel him breathe when he looked up and saw her.

Helena se subía al lomo de la quimera y se agarraba al arnés, mientras el viento las azuzaba en todas direcciones.

On the long nights, Amaris would curl up behind Helena, nuzzling at Kaine’s limp hands.

Después se dirigían a las entrañas de la ciudad, a algún sótano o edificio destrozado, o también a veces a un callejón, y allí encontraba a Kaine.

Helena would sit, tracing her fingers along Kaine’s face, following his every heartbeat and promising, “I’m going to take care of you.

Solía tener algún trozo de metralla de anulitio en el cuerpo, tan incrustado que no podía extraerlo.

I promise, I’m always going to take care of you.”

Helena había aprendido a tener siempre llena la bolsa con instrumental médico, vendas y todo tipo de medicinas.

Conforme los ataques de anulitio se volvían más eficaces, había que emplear más a menudo la cirugía.

Se acostumbró a operar de forma manual con una antorcha eléctrica como única fuente de luz.

Kaine no permitía que lo dejase inconsciente.

Quería mantenerse lúcido por si aparecía alguien, aunque lo más habitual era que estuviese desvariando, con los ojos plateados vidriosos, y mascullando entre dientes:

—Estoy bien… Apenas lo noto.

No te preocupes.

Dentro de poco nos iremos de aquí… Ya lo tengo todo pensado.

Solo… solo un poco más.

Helena se sentaba con su cabeza en el regazo, le sostenía las manos y le cantaba en voz baja hasta que lograba estabilizarlo.

El anulitio hacía que su recuperación fuese mucho más lenta de lo normal.

Cuando perdía demasiada sangre, quedaba flotando al borde de la consciencia o empezaba a temblar hasta que entraba en shock.

Entonces ella le pasaba los dedos y la resonancia por las manos, sin dejar de disculparse.

«Tú lo estás matando.

Tú lo estás matando.

Esto es culpa tuya».

Solo se permitía llorar por él cuando caía inconsciente y no podía verla.

Le cogía las manos entre las suyas y trataba de arreglarlo.

—Lo siento.

Lo siento.

Lo siento —repetía una y otra vez.

Antes de que recobrara la lucidez, se enjugaba las lágrimas y limpiaba la sangre.

En cuanto Kaine volvía en sí mismo, Helena notaba cómo se tensaba de inmediato, hasta que la veía y respiraba de nuevo.

En las noches más largas, Amaris se enroscaba detrás de Helena y le daba toquecitos con el morro a las manos inertes de Kaine.

Ella se sentaba y le acariciaba la cara, sintiendo todos los latidos de su corazón.

Entonces le prometía:

—Yo cuidaré de ti.

Te lo prometo, siempre voy a cuidar de ti.

CHAPTER 56

Maius 1787

CAPÍTULO 56

THE UNDYING USED THE FIRST NULLIUM BOMB in the middle of spring.

Mayus 1787

The Resistance had known an attack like that was coming; the use of nullium had been growing ever since the Undying had used it against Lila, and although the injuries were severe, as a combat weapon nullium was limited in its utility because of how fragile it was.

Los inmarcesibles lanzaron la primera bomba de anulitio a mediados de primavera.

As a bomb, however, it was devastating.

La Resistencia sabía que un ataque así era inminente; desde que los inmarcesibles emplearon el anulitio contra Lila, lo habían estado usando cada vez más.

A few tiny pieces of shrapnel were all it took to wipe out an alchemist’s resonance.

Aunque provocaban heridas graves, las armas de anulitio eran poco útiles, ya que se trataba de una sustancia muy frágil.

If it dissolved and was distributed through the blood, the hospital had to manually suture the wounds, administer chelating agents, and then wait for the patient’s resonance to recover.

Sin embargo, las bombas fueron devastadoras.

Expert alchemical medicine combined with healing had made recovery for Resistance fighters efficient; so long as a combatant didn’t die from blood loss, injuries that in other parts of the world would take months to recover from could be healed here in days or weeks.

Para eliminar la resonancia de un alquimista, bastaba con unos pequeños fragmentos de metralla.

With nullium, however, convalescence slowed to a crawl.

Si el anulitio se disolvía y se introducía en el torrente sanguíneo, el personal sanitario tenía que coser las heridas de forma manual, suministrar agentes quelantes y esperar a que el paciente recuperara su resonancia.

The hospital had prepared as much as they could, medics and surgeons learning about manual surgery and the chymistry department producing a large supply of chelating agents, but logistics were not enough to improve morale.

La medicina alquímica avanzada, junto con la sanación, conseguía que los combatientes de la Resistencia se recuperaran con rapidez; siempre y cuando los soldados no murieran desangrados.

People were terrified.

Las heridas que en otras partes del mundo tardaban meses en curar se sanaban allí en unos días o semanas.

Alchemy and resonance were everything; the idea of being without was like returning to a pre-alchemical stone age.

Sin embargo, con el anulitio, la convalecencia se prolongaba.

Ilva, who took so much in stride, seemed knocked permanently off balance after Luc’s capture, failing to comprehend and proactively address the fallout.

El hospital se había preparado lo mejor posible: el personal médico y quirúrgico había aprendido a operar de forma manual y el departamento de quimiatría había producido una gran cantidad de agentes quelantes.

Perhaps because she was a Lapse, she was incapable of understanding the emotional severity of the mere threat, its impact on morale.

Sin embargo, toda esa logística no bastó para subir la moral.

The only bright spot was that Luc seemed to abruptly realise his responsibilities.

La gente estaba aterrorizada.

Largely cloistered in his rooms, he suddenly reappeared at an assembly that Althorne had called to soothe Resistance unrest.

La alquimia y la resonancia lo eran todo; vivir sin ambas era como regresar a la era prealquímica.

Luc appeared dressed all in white and gold, burning with righteous indignation.

Ilva, que siempre había mantenido una fachada de serenidad, desde el secuestro de Luc parecía completamente desorientada, como si no lograra comprender del todo la magnitud del problema ni cómo solucionarlo.

Physically, he was shrunken.

Tal vez se debiera a que era un lapsus, pero parecía incapaz de entender la gravedad emocional de la amenaza del anulitio y su impacto en la moral de la gente.

Though his armour concealed most of it, his features were visibly gaunt.

Lo único bueno era que, al parecer, Luc volvía a hacerse cargo de sus responsabilidades.

Still, it was as though his body were merely a shell now, and his soul shone through.

Aunque pasaba la mayor parte del tiempo encerrado en sus aposentos, apareció de repente en una asamblea que había convocado Althorne para calmar los ánimos de la Resistencia.

He seemed to radiate life.

Llegó vestido de blanco y dorado, lívido e indignado.

“Morrough, like every necromancer before him, wants the Resistance to be afraid, and for the Eternal Flame’s light to be extinguished,” he said, his blue eyes burning. “We will not give them that satisfaction.

Había adelgazado mucho.

Paladia is ours.

A pesar de que la armadura lo disimulaba, se le veía muy demacrado.

We built this city as a beacon; that light has protected the world from necromancy’s stain for generations.

Aun así, parecía que su cuerpo solo era un cascarón y que era su alma la que brillaba con fuerza.

The gods are on our side.

Por muy frágil que pareciese, aún irradiaba vida.

Sol is unconquerable.

—Morrough, como todos los nigromantes que le precedieron, quiere que la Resistencia tenga miedo y que la luz de la Llama Eterna se extinga —proclamó con los ojos azules centelleantes—.

The laws of nature will not give victory to corruption.

No le daremos esa satisfacción.

We will not fail; we know the rewards our ancestors received for their faithfulness and bravery, and we will taste the same!”

Paladia nos pertenece.

There was a grimness in his voice, and yet he was strangely breathtaking as he spoke, like the sun at its zenith.

Construimos esta ciudad como un faro, y esa luz ha protegido al mundo de la infamia de la nigromancia durante generaciones.

She could feel the mood in the air shift from uncertainty and fear to conviction.

Los dioses están de nuestra parte.

To faith.

Sol es inconquistable.

Luc kept speaking, describing the city in the loving detail of one who knew it intimately, describing the dreams he and his father had had for Paladia’s glorious future.

Las leyes de la naturaleza no le concederán la victoria a la corrupción.

The next thing Helena knew, there was a counteroffensive being assembled.

No fracasaremos; conocemos las recompensas que nuestros ancestros recibieron por su fe y su coraje, ¡y nosotros disfrutaremos de lo mismo!

Squadrons readied.

Había cierta desesperación en su voz y, aun así, resultaba extrañamente deslumbrante, como el sol en su cénit.

Luc’s new battalion, who had not yet even seen combat together, went out with four others and seized a district of the West Island.

Helena se dio cuenta de que el ambiente cambiaba: la incertidumbre y el miedo dieron paso a la convicción.

Helena watched from a skybridge as they all returned in a victory parade, followed by cheers.

A la fe.

Luc was standing on the back of a lorry, Sebastian beside him, waving as they swept through the gates.

Luc continuó hablando.

Lila had not gone.

Describió la ciudad con el detalle de quien la conoce como la palma de su mano, y habló de los sueños que su padre y él tenían para el glorioso futuro de Paladia.

Officially it was because she was still in recovery, but the reality was that the tribunal had not yet begun, the leaders concerned over how Luc might react.

Cuando Helena quiso darse cuenta, ya estaban organizando una contraofensiva y preparando escuadrones.

If he used his power as Principate to directly oppose the Council and military leaders, there was no real means to overrule him that wouldn’t result in a complete collapse of leadership, potentially fracturing the Resistance.

El nuevo batallón de Luc, que todavía no había entrado en combate, salió hacia la ciudad junto a cuatro batallones más y lograron recuperar un distrito de la isla Oeste.

So long as Luc acknowledged Lila as his paladin primary, Lila could ignore what the rest of the Council said—her vows were to Luc.

Desde un puente colgante, Helena observó cómo regresaban en un desfile de victoria, entre gritos de júbilo.

And so Lila remained in limbo.

Luc iba de pie en la parte trasera de un camión, acompañado de Sebastian, sin dejar de saludar mientras atravesaban las verjas de la entrada.

Not cleared for combat, but not really injured anymore, either.

Lila no había asistido.

She stood at the door of the Tower, applauding with everyone else, but grief shone in her face.

En teoría, seguía recuperándose, pero lo cierto era que aún no se había celebrado el juicio y a los líderes les preocupaba cómo iba a reaccionar Luc.

The counterattack had been so sudden, so brazen, the Undying had hardly mounted a defence.

Si hacía uso de su poder como principado para oponerse al Consejo y a los comandantes militares, sus órdenes no podían desestimarse sin que se produjera un colapso absoluto de liderazgo, algo que podría destrozar a la Resistencia.

Similarly, the Council was blindsided by Luc’s abrupt embrace of full leadership, and left scrambling in the wake of his decisiveness.

Mientras que él siguiera considerando a Lila su paladina primera, Lila podía ignorar cualquier instrucción del Consejo, ya que sus votos se debían a Luc.

The success of the offensive made him difficult to argue with, especially when Resistance morale rose with his ascent to claim his place on the Council.

Por eso, Lila permanecía en un limbo.

The battles began to blur together.

Aún no tenía permiso para combatir, pero ya no estaba herida.

Except now there was a medical ward for nullium injuries, and the casualty rates skyrocketed, infections and disease becoming an increasing threat.

Se plantó en la puerta de la Torre y aplaudió con todos los demás, aunque la pena era visible en su rostro.

First came overcrowding, followed by shortages in clean linens and bandages, and then the blood infections began and sickness followed.

El contrataque había sido tan repentino y descarado que los inmarcesibles no tuvieron tiempo de organizar una defensa.

Helena was on shift for days sometimes, ignoring Kaine’s signals unless they were messages for Crowther.

De forma similar, el Consejo se mostró tan desconcertado por el hecho de que Luc asumiera el liderazgo tan rápidamente que no supo cómo reaccionar ante esa determinación.

Work at least kept her from wearing grooves of worry through her mind.

Después del éxito que tuvo en la ofensiva, nadie se atrevía a discutirle nada, especialmente porque había conseguido subir la moral de la Resistencia al tiempo que se consolidaba en el Consejo.

When she was alone, she lay in bed, staring at the ceiling as she twisted Kaine’s ring around and around her finger, thinking about the array sketch Wagner had drawn.

Las batallas empezaron a mezclarse unas con otras.

Nine points.

La única diferencia era que ahora había un pabellón médico especializado para los heridos de anulitio, las bajas aumentaban sin cesar y las infecciones y las enfermedades se volvían cada vez más peligrosas.

Northern alchemy almost always used either five or eight, the elemental or celestial numbers.

Primero se notó la masificación, luego la escasez de sábanas y vendas limpias y, después, aparecieron las complicaciones médicas.

Those were the only array formulas even taught at the Institute, the exception being the Holdfasts’ pyromancy, which operated with a seven-point array, but Helena only knew of that because she’d helped Luc with his homework.

En ocasiones, Helena trabajaba durante varios días seguidos y tenía que ignorar las llamadas de Kaine, salvo que se tratara de mensajes para Crowther.

She’d never heard of a nine-point array.

Al menos, trabajar la mantenía alejada de los pozos de preocupación que acechaban su mente.

She had no idea how it was supposed to work, and her only sample was full of obvious errors and drawn by someone wholly unfamiliar with alchemical principles.

Cuando estaba sola, se tumbaba en la cama y miraba fijamente el techo mientras hacía girar una y otra vez el anillo de Kaine en su dedo.

How could she reverse what had been done to Kaine if she didn’t understand the method?

No dejaba de pensar en el sello que Wagner había dibujado.

She moved her fingers, trying to visualise the energy channels.

Tenía nueve puntas.

Her mind kept going back to Soren.

La alquimia norteña casi siempre empleaba cinco y ocho puntas, es decir, los números elementales o celestiales.

She smothered the thoughts, burying them with animancy, trying to force her mind to go around her memories of him.

Esas eran las únicas fórmulas que se enseñaban en la Academia, a excepción de la piromancia de los Holdfast, que requería un sello de siete puntas, pero Helena solo lo conocía por haber ayudado a Luc con sus deberes.

It kept niggling at her, though—not his destruction but the moment in which he’d died.

Jamás había oído hablar de un sello de nueve puntas.

She always tried to break the resonance connection before a patient died, but she’d been fully focused on Soren in that moment.

No tenía ni idea de cómo funcionaba, y el único ejemplo del que disponía estaba plagado de errores y lo había dibujado alguien que no sabía nada sobre los principios básicos de la alquimia.

The energy, the sensation of it, running through her like an electric current kept coming to mind whenever she tried to imagine channelling through a multiple of three.

¿Cómo iba a revertir lo que le habían hecho a Kaine si ni siquiera entendía el procedimiento?

It made her wonder.

Movió los dedos para intentar visualizar los canales de energía.

If Morrough could trap living souls inside bone, and the first Necromancer placed an entire town of living souls into a Stone, what would happen if someone captured the other form of energy?

Su mente no dejaba de regresar a Soren.

Had anyone ever done it?

Acalló esos pensamientos mediante la animancia y se obligó a dejar atrás todos sus recuerdos sobre él.

The next time she felt a patient on the verge of death, rather than break away, she left the connection open and tried to hold the energy as it struck.

Aun así, seguía incordiándola, no tanto por su destrucción sino por el instante en que murió.

It seared through her resonance, leaving her hand numb and twinging for hours.

Siempre intentaba romper la conexión resonántica antes de que los pacientes murieran, pero en aquella ocasión había estado totalmente concentrada en Soren.

Well, it made sense that she couldn’t just hold it.

La energía la recorrió mientras la sentía como una corriente eléctrica, y no pudo dejar de pensar en ello mientras imaginaba cómo canalizar a través de un múltiplo de tres.

It would need a container of some sort.

Eso le dio una idea: si Morrough podía atrapar almas vivas en hueso y el primer Nigromante había metido todas las almas de una ciudad en una gema, ¿qué sucedería si se capturaba otro tipo de energía?

The sunstone amulet had been … quicksilver?

¿Alguien lo había intentado?

Or glass?

La siguiente vez que notó que un paciente estaba a punto de fallecer, en vez de romper la conexión, mantuvo el contacto y se aferró a la energía que liberó al morir.

Maybe crystal.

Esta atravesó su resonancia y le dejó las manos entumecidas y cosquilleantes durante horas.

She tried a variety of substances from the storerooms, smuggling odd metals and other compounds into the hospital inside her pockets, to see if the energy would channel into any of them.

Bueno, tenía sentido que no pudiese retener esa energía.

Sunstones cracked, while metal set her pocket on fire.

Necesitaba algún tipo de recipiente.

In a box shoved to the back of a storage room, she found several large chunks of obsidian.

El amuleto de heliolita estaba hecho de… ¿mercurio?

Volcanic glass did have a higher melting point than normal glass.

¿O de vidrio?

She stuck a piece in her pocket.

Tal vez fuese cristal.

She gripped it when she felt a patient’s vitality grow thin.

Probó con distintos materiales que encontró en los almacenes e incluso introdujo de contrabando metales más extraños y otros compuestos en el hospital, para comprobar si la energía se canalizaba en alguno.

He was one of the nullium patients, hit with shrapnel that had ripped apart his organs, and the infection hadn’t responded to treatment.

Las heliolitas se resquebrajaron, y el metal blanco hizo que su bolsillo se incendiara.

She could force his heart to keep beating, but it would only make his death take longer; he’d die the moment she left.

En una caja que encontró en un rincón del almacén, había trozos enormes de obsidiana.

His skin was burning with fever, and he was gripping her hand, speaking to someone unseen, the words coming slower and slower.

El cristal volcánico tenía un punto de fundición más alto que el cristal normal.

She swallowed hard and kept her resonance open as his eyes went still.

Se metió un trozo en el bolsillo.

The death surge ran through her like an electric shock straight into the obsidian.

Cuando sintió que la vida de un paciente se extinguía, agarró la obsidiana.

Her arm went briefly numb.

Era uno de los pacientes afectados por el anulitio.

When sensation returned, he was dead, and the obsidian hummed warm against her fingers.

La metralla le había destrozado los órganos y la infección no había mejorado con el tratamiento.

She could feel it, that strange dark energy.

Helena podía obligar a su corazón a que siguiera latiendo, pero solo conseguiría ralentizar su muerte; moriría en cuanto ella se alejara.

Her fingers trembled as she closed his eyes, pulling the sheet over his face.

Tenía la piel ardiendo por la fiebre y ella sostenía su mano con fuerza sin dejar de hablar con alguien que no estaba allí.

Had she just trapped a soul in volcano glass?

Sus palabras empezaron a sonar más vagas y escurridizas.

She squeezed it.

Helena tragó saliva y mantuvo abierto el canal de resonancia cuando sus ojos perdieron la vida.

No.

La muerte la atravesó como una descarga eléctrica y fue directa a la obsidiana.

She knew what that energy felt like, the amulet and Kaine.

El brazo se le quedó dormido.

This was different.

Cuando recuperó el movimiento, el chico ya estaba muerto y la obsidiana irradiaba calidez entre los dedos de Helena.

Still, she tried to pretend it wasn’t there while she finished her shift.

Podía sentir esa extraña y oscura energía.

She hurried to her lab.

Le cerró los ojos y le cubrió el rostro con una sábana, pero entonces notó que le temblaban los dedos.

She opened the door, and stopped short at the sight of Lila, curled up on the floor, her face swollen, eyes red.

¿Acababa de atrapar un alma en un cristal volcánico?

Helena froze.

Lo apretó con fuerza.

Gods, the tribunal.

No.

It must have begun.

Sabía cómo era esa energía, por el amuleto y por Kaine.

She’d hardly seen and hadn’t spoken to Lila since before Luc’s rescue.

Esto era algo distinto.

She’d returned to her room one day to find all of Lila’s things gone and heard about a private memorial service held for Soren only afterwards.

Aun así, intentó fingir que no estaba en su bolsillo mientras acababa el turno.

As much as she had wanted to try to explain herself, she couldn’t, because officially Soren had simply died.

Después corrió al laboratorio.

But Luc would have told Lila the truth.

Sin embargo, al abrir la puerta, se detuvo en seco, pues allí estaba Lila, encogida en el suelo con la cara hinchada y los ojos rojos.

Helena stood frozen, not sure what could have possibly driven Lila here.

Helena se quedó petrificada.

“Lila.” Helena set the obsidian down, moving tentatively. “Lila, what’s wrong?

Por Dios, el tribunal.

What happened?”

Debía de haber empezado el juicio.

Lila stared at Helena without responding for a long time.

Apenas había visto a Lila ni había hablado con ella desde que rescataron a Luc.

“I made a mistake,” Lila finally said, her voice barely a whisper, “I’ve made such a mistake.”

Un día volvió a su habitación y descubrió que todas las pertenencias de Lila habían desaparecido, y se enteró de que habría un funeral privado para Soren cuando ya se había celebrado.

Helena swallowed hard. “It’s—all right.

A pesar de lo mucho que le hubiera gustado dar explicaciones, no podía hacerlo, porque la versión oficial mantenía que Soren simplemente había muerto.

I’m sure it’ll be all right.

No obstante, Luc le habría contado la verdad a Lila.

Whatever you’ve done—I’m sure it can’t be that bad.”

Helena permaneció donde estaba, no tenía ni idea de qué había llevado a Lila hasta ahí.

Soren’s ghost seemed to hang between them.

—Lila. —Helena dejó la obsidiana sobre la mesa y dio un paso hacia ella con cautela—.

“No.” Lila shook her head. “I’ve been lying to everyone.

Lila, ¿qué sucede?

My whole life, I’ve been lying.

¿Qué ha pasado?

Now—now I don’t know what to do …”

Lila miró fijamente a Helena y tardó un buen rato en responder:

Her voice was so strained, it trailed off.

—He cometido un error —dijo al fin en apenas un susurro—.

“Soren was the only person that knew,” Lila whispered.

He cometido un terrible error.

Her eyes were swimming, but the tears didn’t escape. “He always kept my secrets.

Helena tragó saliva con dificultad.

Knew what to do about things.

—No… No pasa nada.

Said it was his job—looking out for me.”

Estoy segura de que se arreglará.

“What happened?” Helena reached out tentatively.

Da igual lo que hayas hecho, seguro que no es para tanto.

Lila looked up and drew a deep breath, her chin trembling before she finally spoke. “I—I’m pregnant.”

El fantasma de Soren pareció flotar entre las dos.

Helena didn’t move.

—No. —Lila sacudió la cabeza—.

Couldn’t speak.

He estado mintiéndole a todo el mundo.

She was too stunned to even believe the words Lila had just uttered.

He estado mintiendo toda mi vida.

To know she was pregnant meant she had to be at least two or three months along, and that was assuming her cycle was regular, which Helena knew it wasn’t.

Y ahora… ahora no sé qué hacer… —Su voz sonaba estrangulada.

She’d been in the hospital at that time.

No terminaba las frases—.

“How?” was the only question Helena could even think to ask.

Soren era la única persona que lo sabía —susurró.

Never mind everything else that this meant.

Tenía los ojos vidriosos, pero no le cayó ninguna lágrima—.

Lila swallowed, her head moving jerkily, wincing when it pulled at the scars on her neck. “I know.

Siempre me guardó el secreto, siempre sabía qué hacer.

I didn’t think I could.

Decía que su trabajo era… cuidarme.

After—everything.

—¿Qué ha pasado? —Helena se acercó con cautela.

I always assumed that it wasn’t even possible.”

Lila levantó la vista y cogió aire.

“No,” Helena said impatiently. “I mean, yes, that too, but you weren’t pregnant when you were in the hospital.

La barbilla le tembló justo antes de responder:

You’ve only been out for—How would you possibly know you’re pregnant?”

—Estoy… estoy embarazada.

Lila looked down, avoiding Helena’s eyes. “That’s—that’s the secret.

Helena se quedó inmóvil.

I know I’m pregnant.”

Sin palabras.

It was then that something incredibly obvious, which Helena should have realised years earlier, finally dawned on her.

Estaba demasiado perpleja incluso para creer lo que Lila acababa de contarle.

Lila Bayard, who so often came back from battles nearly unscathed, who always recovered miraculously from her injuries, who adapted to a prosthetic leg in months when everyone said it would be a year.

Si sabía que estaba embarazada, entonces debía de estarlo desde hacía dos o tres meses, y eso suponiendo que tuviera un ciclo regular, pero Helena sabía que no era el caso.

Who had never struggled to recover from an injury until she lost her resonance.

En aquella época, Lila aún seguía hospitalizada.

“You’re a vivimancer,” Helena said.

—¿Cómo es posible? —Esa fue la única pregunta que a Helena se le ocurrió hacer.

Lila didn’t meet her eyes as she gave a small nod. “I never used it on anyone except me.

Dejó a un lado todo lo que eso implicaba.

Soren a couple of times, but only when he asked.

Lila tragó saliva y sacudió la cabeza, pero torció el gesto de dolor al sentir que le tiraban las cicatrices del cuello.

He said I couldn’t let anyone know.

—Lo sé.

Not even Mum and Dad, because if people knew I wouldn’t be allowed to be Luc’s paladin.”

Yo tampoco pensé que fuera posible después de… todo lo que ha pasado.

“All this time?” Helena said softly, startled by the sense of betrayal she felt.

Siempre di por hecho que no podría quedarme embarazada.

“I’m sorry.

—No —la cortó Helena con impaciencia—.

I wanted to tell you but—you know what it’s been like for you.

Bueno, sí, eso también, pero no estabas embarazada cuando estuviste ingresada.

I couldn’t risk that, not with Luc at stake.

Te dimos el alta hace unos… ¿Cómo sabes que estás embarazada?

I couldn’t be like you—fighting’s all I’m good at.”

Lila bajó la mirada para esquivar los ojos de Helena.

The revelation was more than Helena felt she could process right then.

—Ese… ese es el secreto.

“Who’s the father?” Helena asked, as if it wasn’t completely obvious.

Sé que estoy embarazada.

“You know it’s Luc.”

Entonces le pareció tan increíblemente obvio que Helena no entendió cómo no se había dado cuenta años atrás.

Helena nodded.

Lila Bayard, que solía volver de las batallas sin apenas un rasguño, que siempre se recuperaba milagrosamente de sus heridas, quien se había adaptado a una prótesis en la pierna en cuestión de meses cuando todo el mundo decía que tardaría un año.

She wanted to be angry, but her own secrets were worse, and the fact that Lila had turned to her in Soren’s absence spoke volumes.

La persona a la que jamás le costaba recuperarse, excepto cuando perdió su resonancia.

“You’ve probably heard, they’re planning a tribunal unless I step down as paladin voluntarily.” Lila’s voice was empty and despairing. “I used to tell myself it would all pay off in the end, but the war just kept going.

—Eres una vivemante —concluyó Helena.

I didn’t ever—I mean, a few times he tried—but I told him off every time.” Lila shook her head. “Doesn’t matter, though, seems everyone thinks we’ve been fucking each other at the front lines.

Lila no la miró a los ojos cuando asintió.

Doesn’t mean anything that we didn’t.” She looked down. “When he came back from taking that district—I know it wasn’t about me, but I felt so ruined.

—Nunca la he usado con nadie, salvo conmigo misma.

Being left behind and knowing I always will be now.

Un par de veces en Soren, pero solo cuando él me lo pedía.

He came and found me after and told me that he’d been thinking about me the whole time, and—” She shrugged. “Everyone thinks we are anyway, so—”

Me dijo que no podía permitir que nadie lo supiera.

Helena rested a tentative hand on her shoulder. “It’s all right.

Ni siquiera nuestros padres, porque, si alguien se enteraba, no me dejarían ser la paladina de Luc.

I can take care of it.

—¿Durante todo este tiempo? —preguntó Helena con suavidad, aunque lo cierto era que se sentía traicionada.

If it’s early I can get ingredients or just use vivimancy, whatever you’d prefer.

—Lo siento.

No one will know.”

Quería decírtelo, pero… sabía lo que te había pasado a ti.

“No.”

No podía arriesgarme a eso; la vida de Luc estaba en juego.

Helena stared at Lila, certain she’d misheard.

No podía ser como tú… A mí solo se me da bien luchar.

Lila drew a deep breath, avoiding her eyes. “I mean, that’s why I came.

Aquella confesión era más de lo que Helena podía asimilar en ese momento.

I knew you could do it, but—while I was waiting, I couldn’t stop thinking, what are the odds?” She shook her head. “I can’t remember the last time I had a cycle.

—¿Quién es el padre? —preguntó, como si no fuera obvio.

It’s been years.

—Sabes que es Luc.

I didn’t think I could.

Helena asintió.

I always thought Soren would be the one who’d marry and have the next generation of Bayards, but now I’m all that’s left.”

Quiso enfadarse, pero sus propios secretos eran peores, y que Lila hubiese acudido a ella en ausencia de Soren lo decía todo.

Helena had no words.

—Seguramente te hayas enterado de que quieren someterme a juicio, a menos que renuncie voluntariamente a ser paladina —le contó con una voz que sonaba hueca y desesperada—.

Lila looked down, curling smaller, as if she could feel Helena’s judgement. “It probably won’t stick.

Antes me decía a mí misma que al final todo merecería la pena, pero la guerra ha durado demasiado.

So maybe I could just wait, and—have this for a little while.”

Nunca quise… Bueno, él lo intentó en alguna que otra ocasión, pero yo siempre me negué. —Lila sacudió la cabeza—.

“And if it does—stick?” Helena asked.

Aunque ha sido en vano, todo el mundo piensa que hemos estado acostándonos en el frente.

Lila didn’t answer.

No ha servido de nada que no lo hiciéramos. —Bajó la vista—.

Helena’s chest grew tight.

Cuando regresó después de tomar ese distrito… Sé que no era por mí, pero sentí la frustración de que me hubieran dejado atrás y de saber que ya siempre lo harían.

She wanted to say Lila was being stupid.

Después vino a buscarme y me dijo que había estado pensando en mí todo el tiempo y… —Se encogió de hombros—.

A baby, during the war.

Todos creen que lo estamos haciendo, así que…

Lila wouldn’t be the first, but still, those girls were different.

Helena posó una mano en su hombro con sumo cuidado.

Lila was an alchemist.

—No pasa nada.

A warrior.

Puedo arreglarlo.

Neither of those things paired with motherhood.

Al haberlo detectado tan pronto, podemos usar medicación o la vivemancia, lo que tú prefieras.

The rules were strict.

Nadie se enterará.

“It won’t stick,” Lila said.

—No.

“That’s not an answer,” Helena said sharply. “What if it does?

Helena miró fijamente a Lila, convencida de que la había oído mal.

You are going to have a baby during a war when you’re already facing a tribunal.

La paladina tomó aire sin atreverse a mirarla.

You won’t be a paladin after that.

—Sí, vine por eso.

They won’t ever let you fight again.”

Sabía que tú podrías hacerlo, pero… mientras esperaba no dejaba de pensar.

Lila was picking at her nails, her cuticles bleeding. “Luc’s going to leave combat to take over leadership now.

¿Cuáles eran las probabilidades? —Negó con la cabeza—.

Ilva’s too old to continue as steward, and there’s no one he trusts to replace her.

No recuerdo la última vez que tuve la regla.

They say that if I step down as paladin primary, they won’t call a tribunal, Sebastian will replace me, and I’ll be cleared for combat again.” Lila drew a deep breath. “I’ll be in command of my own unit.

Han pasado años.

First woman.”

Creía que no podría quedarme embarazada.

Lila’s voice showed no pride or excitement for what would be a historic accomplishment, because there was no chance that she could reenter combat, stripped of her former rank, without the scandal following her.

Siempre pensé que sería Soren el que se casaría y engendraría la nueva generación de Bayard, pero ahora solo quedo yo.

Her reputation and legacy were irrevocably stained.

Helena no supo qué responder.

“If you said I was sick with something, no one would know I’m pregnant—and if it doesn’t take, I’ll go back into service like it never happened.”

Lila bajó la mirada y se encogió un poco más, como si percibiera los prejuicios de la sanadora.

“Or you could retire from active combat and train recruits who could use someone with your experience,” Helena said. “Those aren’t your only two options.”

—Lo más probable es que no llegue a término, así que tal vez puedo esperar y… tenerlo durante un tiempo.

“I’m not going to retire.

—¿Y si llega a término? —preguntó Helena.

That’s not how it works for us Bayards,” Lila said, her blue eyes snapping.

Lila no respondió.

She winced. “Sorry.

Helena sintió una presión en el pecho.

People keep telling me that it’s not all over, but—” She scoffed. “—I know how it works.

Quería decirle a Lila que estaba comportándose como una estúpida por pretender tener un bebé durante la guerra.

What will be remembered.

Lila no sería la primera en hacerlo, pero esas chicas eran diferentes.

It won’t be anything I ever did in combat.”

Lila era alquimista, una guerrera.

Now Helena understood.

Ninguna de esas cosas iba de la mano con la maternidad.

A pregnancy altered the narrative.

Las normas eran estrictas.

It didn’t erase the scandal, but it did reframe it; instead of a violation of vows that nearly led to calamity, it became a love story.

—No llegará a término —repitió Lila.

The Principate had already been in desperate need of an heir, but it was hard to make it a stated priority when Luc’s life was supposed to be shielded with divinity, and Luc had, for obvious reasons, always been resistant to the idea of a political marriage, which was what the Council wanted.

—Eso no es una respuesta —insistió Helena—.

A Holdfast heir could reinvigorate the Resistance.

¿Qué harás si el embarazo sigue adelante?

How could it be a doomed war when there was such a tangible symbol of the future?

Vas a tener un bebé durante una guerra cuando ya te estás enfrentando a un tribunal.

Of course Lila would prefer that version of her story, rather than the alternatives she was faced with.

No volverás a ser paladina.

Lila had always seemed unstoppable, but now Helena could see all the cracks she’d hidden.

No te dejarán combatir nunca más.

The desires she’d never let herself have.

Lila no dejaba de morderse las uñas; le sangraban las cutículas.

Helena knew something about that.

—Luc tendrá que dejar de luchar para ser líder.

“Will Luc know?”

Ilva está demasiado mayor para seguir ejerciendo como su mano derecha, y no confía en nadie más para reemplazarla.

Lila drew a breath, shaking her head. “No.

Dicen que, si renuncio a ser paladina, no me someterán a juicio.

I think it would distract him.

Sebastian aceptará mi cargo y yo podré combatir de nuevo. —Lila respiró hondo—.

He’s under so much pressure, and the transition will be a lot.

Seré comandante de mi propia unidad: la primera mujer comandante.

If he knew and then it came to nothing—it would crush him, to have hoped.”

La voz de Lila no mostraba ni orgullo ni emoción por lo que era un logro histórico, porque era imposible que volviese a entrar en combate una vez que le arrebatan su rango y se produjera el escándalo que le seguiría.

“Does Luc—want children?” Helena asked hesitantly.

Tanto su reputación como su legado quedarían manchados para siempre.

She didn’t think she’d ever heard Luc speak of children.

—Si dices que estoy enferma, nadie sabrá que estoy embarazada… Y, si el embarazo no sale adelante, volveré al servicio militar como si nunca hubiese pasado.

His hopes for the future were of the war being over, of travelling.

—O podrías retirarte del combate activo y entrenar a reclutas a los que les vendría muy bien tu experiencia —replicó Helena—.

Then again, the matter of Lila had always been carefully unspoken.

No solo tienes dos opciones.

Helena had known, but he’d never admitted it outright, not even to her.

—No pienso retirarme.

Lila nodded. “He talked about them that night.

Los Bayard no nos retiramos —expresó Lila con los ojos azules brillantes.

How he’s not like his father, he doesn’t want to just do his duty.

Después torció el gesto—.

That he wants to have a family for himself, not because of the Principate, or because he needs an heir, but just because he loves someone so much that he makes one.

Perdóname.

That’s what this would be.”

La gente no deja de decirme que no es el fin, pero… —Soltó un bufido—.

Helena swallowed hard.

Sé cómo son las cosas.

She still hated this, but she couldn’t refuse Lila. “I’ll need to talk to Crowther and see what the options are.”

Sé lo que recordarán.

Lila’s face screwed up. “Why would you go to him?

No será nada de lo que hice en combate.

He’s awful.

Ahí fue cuando Helena lo entendió.

Luc can’t stand him.”

El embarazo cambiaba la narrativa.

Helena looked away. “He’s the most pragmatic choice.

No borraba el escándalo, pero le daba otra forma; en vez de una violación de un juramento que estuvo a punto de ocasionar una catástrofe, se trataba de una historia de amor.

I don’t have the seniority to quarantine someone.

El principado necesitaba un heredero desde hacía mucho tiempo, pero era complicado convertirlo en prioridad cuando la vida de Luc debía estar rodeada de divinidad, y Luc, por razones obvias, siempre se había negado a un matrimonio concertado, que era lo que quería el Consejo.

I don’t think you want Elain or Matias involved.

Un heredero Holdfast podía darle fuerzas a la Resistencia.

The choices are Crowther or Ilva, and Ilva hasn’t been very reliable lately.”

¿Cómo iba a ser una guerra perdida si había un símbolo tan tangible del futuro?

“Fine,” Lila sighed, wincing. “Crowther, then.”

Por supuesto que Lila prefería esa versión de su historia en vez de las alternativas a las que se enfrentaba.

Lila siempre le había parecido imparable, pero Helena veía ahora todas las grietas que escondía.

Los deseos que nunca se había permitido albergar.

Helena se vio reflejada en ella.

—¿Luc lo sabrá?

La paladina tomó aire y negó con la cabeza.

—No, creo que para él sería una distracción.

Ahora mismo está bajo una presión tremenda, y la transición de poderes será complicada.

Si lo supiera y después quedara en nada… Le destrozaría haber tenido la esperanza.

—¿Luc… quiere tener hijos? —preguntó Helena con cierta vacilación.

No recordaba haber oído a Luc hablar de niños.

Lo único que le pedía al futuro era que acabase la guerra y viajar.

Aunque también era cierto que el tema de Lila nunca lo habían hablado abiertamente.

Helena siempre lo había sabido, pero Luc jamás lo reconoció, ni siquiera delante de ella.

Lila asintió.

—Aquella noche hablamos del tema.

Me dijo que él no era como su padre, que no solo quería cumplir con su deber, que deseaba tener una familia para disfrutarla, no únicamente por el bien del principado o porque tuviera que haber un heredero, sino porque amaba tanto a alguien que quería hacerlo.

Así es en este caso.

Helena tragó saliva.

Seguía sin gustarle todo eso, pero no podía negarle nada a Lila.

—Tendré que hablar con Crowther para barajar nuestras opciones.

A Lila se le descompuso la cara.

—¿Por qué vas a decírselo a él?

Es odioso.

Luc no lo soporta.

Helena esquivó su mirada.

—Es la opción más útil.

No tengo autoridad para poner a alguien en cuarentena.

No creo que quieras involucrar a Elain o a Matias.

Tus opciones son Crowther o Ilva, e Ilva no se ha mostrado muy digna de confianza últimamente.

—Está bien. —Lila suspiró con un gesto de dolor—.

Hablaremos con Crowther.

CHAPTER 57

Maius 1787

CAPÍTULO 57

ACCORDING TO RECORDS, LILA BAYARD CONTRACTED A bad case of bog cough after helping deliver supplies to the water slums at the south end of the island.

Mayus 1787

Bog cough tended to crop up every year in the early summer after the floods, as the air grew warm and damp, and the dark, recessed levels of the city, far from sunlight, found their interiors blackened with mould.

Según los informes oficiales, Lila Bayard sufría un caso grave de tos de los pantanos que había contraído después de ayudar a transportar suministros a los suburbios sumergidos, en el extremo meridional de la isla.

The symptoms were a deep cough coming from low in the lungs, and an occasional rash.

La tos de los pantanos solía aparecer todos los años a principios de verano, después de las inundaciones, cuando el ambiente se tornaba cálido y húmedo, y los niveles más oscuros y escondidos de la ciudad, que estaban apartados de la luz solar, se cubrían de moho negro.

While mostly dangerous to children and the elderly, sometimes it would linger and transform into a virulent sickness that could sweep through the city like a plague.

Los síntomas eran una tos expectorante y, en ocasiones, sarpullido.

That was the ostensible reason why the upper levels of the city preferred to be restrictive with the lower sectors of the population.

Aunque afectaba sobre todo a los niños y los ancianos, a veces se enquistaba y se volvía tan virulenta que contagiaba a toda la ciudad como si fuera una plaga.

Helena was familiar with the symptoms because her father used to treat it every summer.

Esta era la razón por la que los niveles superiores de la ciudad solían evitar cualquier contacto con los sectores más bajos de la población.

Most of the people who caught it couldn’t afford to travel up-city to a licensed apothecary.

Helena conocía bien los síntomas porque su padre los trataba todos los veranos.

Helena could replicate the symptoms almost perfectly using vivimancy, creating purplish rashes on Lila’s inner wrists and the sides of her neck, and agitating her lungs enough to make her cough violently while Pace examined her and gave the diagnosis.

La mayoría de la gente que contraía la enfermedad no se podía permitir viajar a los niveles superiores para recibir el tratamiento de un boticario autorizado.

With so many people in tight quarters, plague was a constant fear.

Mediante la vivemancia, Helena podía replicar los síntomas a la perfección, así que creó unos sarpullidos morados en las muñecas y ambos lados del cuello de Lila, y cargó sus pulmones de flemas para que tosiera con fuerza cuando vino Pace a examinarla y hacer su diagnóstico.

Lila was promptly placed in isolation in the Alchemy Tower, and everyone else involved in the supply delivery was quarantined for three days until they were declared symptom-free.

Al vivir tanta gente en tan poco espacio, el miedo al contagio era constante.

Such a common sickness did not dampen morale, particularly since it was considered primarily an affliction of the poor and unsanitary.

A Lila no tardaron en aislarla en lo alto de la Torre de Alquimia, junto a todos los que habían participado en la entrega de suministros, aunque estos fueron declarados asintomáticos al cabo de tres días.

That Lila had caught it was taken as a sign that she was still too weak from her injuries.

Una enfermedad tan común no afectó a la moral, especialmente porque se consideraba una dolencia propia de los pobres y de los entornos insalubres.

High in the sun-soaked rooms of the Alchemy Tower, she would recover.

Que Lila se hubiese contagiado solo se interpretó como un signo de que seguía demasiado débil después de tantas heridas.

Luc, however, was distraught.

En las habitaciones superiores, bañadas por el sol de la Torre de Alquimia, se recuperaría rápidamente.

He demanded to see her, but he was flatly refused.

Sin embargo, Luc empezó a agobiarse.

His own lungs still showed signs of deterioration and damage; under no circumstances was he permitted to go anywhere near Lila.

Exigió verla, pero se le negó rotundamente.

Helena hardly knew where to begin with this new secret.

Sus propios pulmones seguían deteriorados y dañados, por lo que bajo ninguna circunstancia se le permitía acercarse a Lila hasta que se recuperase por completo.

Pregnancy was not something she’d ever studied.

Helena no sabía por dónde empezar con aquel secreto.

Her experience with newborns was mostly limited to emergency situations.

Nunca había estudiado los embarazos.

She looked in the library for a few references but found the options lacking, until she remembered that Matron Pace kept most medical textbooks in the records office for easy access.

Su experiencia con los partos se limitaba a situaciones de emergencia.

“I never thought I’d find you interested in pregnancy.” Matron Pace’s comment made Helena jump as she was caught hurriedly perusing one of the books.

Buscó en la biblioteca alguna referencia, pero todo lo que encontró le pareció escaso de información, y entonces recordó que la enfermera Pace guardaba muchos libros de medicina en el despacho para tenerlos más a mano.

Helena slammed it shut, cramming it into place. “I’m not.

—Nunca pensé que te interesaría la maternidad. —El comentario de la enfermera Pace hizo que diera un respingo cuando la encontró ojeando uno de los libros.

The title just caught my eye.”

Helena lo cerró de inmediato y lo colocó en su sitio.

“You’re welcome to borrow it.”

—No me interesa, pero el título me ha llamado la atención.

“No.” Helena shook her head. “Passing curiosity was all.”

—Puedes llevártelo, si quieres.

She made for the door.

—No —negó moviendo la cabeza—, solo era curiosidad.

“Marino.” Pace’s voice was commanding.

Se dirigió a la puerta.

Helena turned.

—Marino. —La voz de Pace sonó autoritaria.

Pace was watching her like a hawk.

Helena se volvió.

“Are you in a family way?”

Pace la observaba como un halcón.

“No.”

—¿Estás embarazada?

“Accidents happen,” Pace said mildly, leaning back against her desk. “Especially during wartime.

—No.

You wouldn’t be the first.”

—A veces hay descuidos —replicó Pace apoyándose con calma en su escritorio—.

Helena released an exploding little scoff. “I’m not pregnant.”

Sobre todo, en tiempos de guerra.

“I just hope your fellow is the responsible—”

No serías la primera a la que le pasa.

“I can’t be pregnant.

A Helena se le escapó un resoplido de frustración.

I’ve been sterilised,” Helena snapped, too mortified to keep listening.

—No estoy embarazada.

Pace froze, shaking her head. “No.

—Solo espero que tu pareja sea responsable…

They wouldn’t.

—No puedo quedarme embarazada.

They couldn’t have possibly found that necessary at a time like this.”

Me esterilizaron —estalló Helena sintiendo una vergüenza tan profunda que no quería seguir escuchándola.

Helena’s cheeks were burning, but her stomach had a gnawing pit inside it. “Well, they did.

Pace se quedó muy quieta y, después, sacudió la cabeza.

Maier did it.

—No.

Ligature, same week I got back.

No harían tal cosa.

It was—it was one of the Falcon’s conditions.

Es imposible que lo consideraran necesario en los tiempos que corren.

So, like I said, not pregnant.”

A Helena le ardieron las mejillas, pero en el estómago sintió un vacío que se abría cada vez más.

She started again for the door.

—Pues lo hicieron.

“Helena, wait.” Pace’s voice was beseeching.

Maier, para ser más exactos.

Helena winced, turning reluctantly back.

Me hizo una ligadura de trompas la semana que volví.

Pace had one of her red, chapped hands pressed against her chest. “I shouldn’t have teased you.

Fue… fue una de las condiciones del falcón.

I had no idea.

Así que, como te digo, no estoy embarazada.

Maier never said anything.”

Volvió a girarse hacia la puerta.

“It’s fine,” Helena said stiffly. “I wanted to be an alchemist more, and women don’t get to do both.” She lifted her chin. “Now I won’t ever have to worry about choosing.

—Helena, espera. —La voz de Pace sonó entonces suplicante.

Besides—” She looked squarely at Pace. “—I’ll probably die young, so I’d be a terrible mother.”

Helena hizo un gesto y se volvió con desgana.

Pace studied her. “Was your mother terrible?”

Pace tenía una de sus manos rojas y agrietadas sobre el pecho.

Pace couldn’t have hurt her more if she’d kicked her.

—No debería haber insistido.

The room swam.

No tenía ni idea.

Helena’s throat closed. “How dare you.”

Maier nunca lo mencionó.

“I’m sorry, I shouldn’t have said it that way,” Pace said, but she didn’t really look sorry. “But Helena, I don’t think you know how to be honest with yourself about what you want.”

—No pasa nada —afirmó Helena con rigidez—.

“It was the only way to become a healer—we needed a healer, Ilva said I was the only person who could do it.” Helena’s jaw trembled, and she had to set it hard. “It was the choice I had, and I made it.

Prefería ser alquimista, y las mujeres no podemos tener ambas cosas. —Levantó la barbilla—.

Would you really rather I hadn’t?”

Ahora ya no tengo que preocuparme por decidir entre una u otra.

“You weren’t even seventeen.

Además —miró a Pace a los ojos—, seguramente muera joven, así que sería una madre horrible.

You’d barely lived enough to know what you wanted.”

Pace la observó atentamente.

“I feel pretty alive right now,” Helena said through gritted teeth. “And I’m fine.”

—¿Tu madre lo fue?

“Being alive is not the same as living.

Aquellas palabras le hicieron más daño que si le hubiesen propinado una patada.

I hope someday you’ll have a chance to realise the difference.”

La habitación le dio vueltas y sintió que se le formaba un nudo en la garganta.

Pace went over to the bookshelf and pulled the book that Helena had been reading off the shelf, holding it in both hands as she stared at the cover. “I was a midwife, you know.

—Cómo te atreves.

Long time ago now.” She shook her head. “I should have realised.

—Lo siento, no debería haberlo dicho así —admitió, aunque no parecía arrepentida—.

You’ve always poured your all into the present moment, as if that’s all you expect to have.”

Pero, Helena, no creo que estés siendo honesta contigo misma sobre lo que realmente quieres.

She turned back to Helena. “Perhaps a glimpse at the next generation will make the future feel a little more real for you.”

—Era la única forma de hacerme sanadora.

She held the book towards Helena.

Necesitábamos una e Ilva dijo que yo era la única que podría hacerlo. —Le temblaba la mandíbula, así que apretó los dientes para que no se notara—.

The title, The Maternal Condition: An In-Depth Study on the Science and Physiology of Gestation, glinted in the light from a window high overhead. “Lila Bayard will need the best care you can provide.”

Me pidieron que decidiera y eso hice.

Helena stared at her in astonishment. “How—?”

¿Preferirías que no hubiese elegido ser sanadora?

Matron Pace pressed the book into her hands. “I’ve been a nurse for twice as long as you’ve been alive.

—No tenías ni diecisiete años.

Your vivimancy skills are remarkable, but Lila would have had to be sick for a good three weeks before developing a rash like that.”

No habías vivido lo suficiente para saber lo que querías.

AS LUC BEGAN TAKING OVER leadership, Ilva’s health began a sudden and rapid decline as if all those years, she’d just been holding on until he was ready.

—Me siento bastante viva ahora mismo —replicó Helena entre dientes—.

Some days she was barely lucid.

Y estoy bien.

Crowther had become so concerned about Ilva’s sudden deterioration that he’d had Helena examine her.

—Estar viva no es lo mismo que vivir.

There was nothing wrong; she was just old and tired.

Espero que algún día tengas la oportunidad de descubrir la diferencia.

The war seemed to pitch back and forth in favour between the two sides.

Pace se acercó a la estantería y sacó el libro que Helena había estado ojeando.

The constant fighting seemed to grant little advantage beyond leaving the city more battered.

Lo sostuvo con las dos manos y contempló la portada.

Luc led another aggressive attack on the West Island, and they captured a warehouse.

—Fui matrona, ¿lo sabías?

It was found filled with large tublike tanks of fluid with bodies inside, tubes connected to veins, and breathing masks fastened over the noses and mouths.

Hace ya mucho tiempo. —Sacudió la cabeza—.

Resistance fighters.

Debería haberme dado cuenta antes.

All dead, but their bodies still warm.

Siempre lo das todo en el momento presente, como si creyeras que solo vas a tener eso. —Se giró hacia Helena—.

When the perimeter had been breached, a gas had been released into the masks, killing them all mere minutes before the Resistance reached them.

Si echas un vistazo a la siguiente generación, tal vez percibas el futuro como algo más real.

A procession of lorries returned to Headquarters, filled with the bodies to cremate.

Extendió el libro hacia Helena.

There were only a few captives, but one was the Warden, who proved difficult and refused to answer questions.

El título —La maternidad: un estudio exhaustivo sobre la ciencia y la fisiología de la gestación— resplandeció bajo la luz que entraba por la ventana de arriba.

Because the Warden was Luc’s captive, they couldn’t be disappeared into one of Crowther’s underground holes and tortured for information.

—Lila Bayard va a necesitar los mejores cuidados posibles.

Crowther remembered then that Kaine had taught Helena a unique method of extracting information; she had mentioned it once as an alternative when trying to dissuade him from torture.

Helena la miró anonadada.

Helena was as horrified as everyone else at all the healthy, intact, familiar faces being prepped for cremation, so close to rescue.

—¿Cómo…?

She’d immediately agreed.

La enfermera Pace dejó el libro en sus manos.

Some strings were pulled and Crowther managed to get a few hours alone with the Warden, bringing Helena with him.

—Llevo siendo enfermera el doble de años que tu vida.

The Warden was a woman, with a thin face and short cropped hair and a wide mouth.

Tienes una habilidad excepcional para la vivemancia, pero Lila tendría que haberse pasado tres semanas enferma antes de que le aparecieran esos sarpullidos.

Her pale-blue eyes instantly narrowed when she saw Helena.

Conforme Luc fue haciéndose cargo de todo, la salud de Ilva empezó a declinar rápida y repentinamente, como si todos esos años hubiese aguantado para ver el momento en el que su sobrino nieto estuviese preparado.

Each sized the other up.

Había días en los que apenas estaba en sus cabales.

Crowther settled into the shadows, leaving Helena to make her attempt.

Crowther, preocupado por el súbito deterioro de Ilva, le pidió a Helena que la examinara.

“Who are you?” Helena asked, not sure how to begin.

No tenía ninguna enfermedad; simplemente era mayor y estaba cansada.

“What’s it to you?” the Warden asked.

La guerra seguía siendo un tira y afloja para ambos bandos.

“Can’t say I’ve met any women among the Undying or their Aspirants.”

Las escaramuzas constantes apenas aportaban ventaja, salvo para causar más destrozos a una ciudad ya devastada.

“Men generally like our bodies a lot more than they like us.” The Warden looked over into the corner where Crowther was watching. “Guess I’m one of the special ones.”

Luc lideró otro ataque contundente en la isla Oeste, donde lograron tomar un almacén.

“How are you special?” Helena asked, even though she had a pretty good idea.

Lo encontraron lleno de tanques enormes con forma tubular y, en el interior, encontraron cadáveres con tubos en las venas y mascarillas sobre nariz y boca.

“Probably for the same reason you are.” The Warden had looked back and was studying Helena now. “The difference is that I’m not a traitor to my kind.”

Eran luchadores de la Resistencia.

“I’m not the one who just murdered more than a hundred people,” Helena said, struggling to keep her voice even.

Todos estaban muertos, pero sus cuerpos aún conservaban calor.

She didn’t know why it bothered her so much that this Warden was a woman, but it made her angrier.

Cuando rompieron el perímetro, las mascarillas suministraron un gas que los asesinó unos minutos antes de que la Resistencia pudiera rescatarlos.

“They would’ve killed me, given half a chance.

Al Cuartel General llegaron camiones repletos de cadáveres para incinerarlos.

I killed them first.” The Warden lifted her chin, jutting it towards Helena. “What are you?” Her eyes flicked over Helena. “Healer?

Apenas habían hecho un par de prisioneros, pero una era la custodio del almacén, quien se mostró agresiva y se negó a responder a preguntas.

I bet.

Como la custodio era una prisionera de Luc, no pudieron hacerla desaparecer en uno de los agujeros subterráneos de Crowther ni someterla a tortura para obtener información.

I was a healer once.”

Entonces, Crowther recordó que Kaine le había enseñado a Helena un método insólito para extraer información; ella misma lo había mencionado una vez para disuadirlo de seguir torturando.

Helena was doubtful about that, but the woman was talking without coercion, so she let her.

Helena se horrorizó como los demás al ver esos rostros familiares, sanos e intactos, listos para la cremación, después de haber estado tan cerca de que los rescataran.

“Didn’t want to be a healer, but there’s not a lot of choices out there for us.

Accedió sin pensárselo dos veces.

He tried to make me a nun.

Tras hablar con un par de contactos, Crowther consiguió quedarse un par de horas a solas con la custodio, y llevó consigo a Helena.

Wanted me to raise other brats born like me.

La custodio era una mujer de rostro enjuto, cabello corto y boca ancha.

Teach them how to keep their abilities in and punish them if they didn’t.

Sus ojos azul claro se estrecharon en cuanto vio a Helena, como si la estuviera evaluando.

Didn’t you?”

Crowther se quedó en las sombras y dejó que Helena hiciera lo suyo.

Helena turned to stare at Crowther, who watched, his expression unreadable.

—¿Quién eres? —preguntó Helena, que no sabía por dónde empezar.

“You know her?” Helena asked.

—¿Y a ti qué te importa? —le espetó la custodio.

“Oh yes.

—La verdad es que no he conocido a ninguna mujer entre los inmarcesibles ni los aspirantes.

Kestrel Jan often came to see us whenever someone misbehaved at the orphanage.

—A los hombres les suele gustar más nuestro cuerpo que nosotras. —La guardia miró el rincón desde donde observaba Crowther—.

Always brought a pet along, someone with a long leash whom we could aspire to become like as long as we’d do anything he asked.

Supongo que debo de ser especial.

I’m surprised, though.

—¿Por qué? —preguntó Helena, aunque ya tenía una idea.

They’re usually younger.” Her eyes flicked over Helena.

—Seguramente por el mismo motivo que tú. —La custodio se echó hacia atrás y miró a Helena de arriba abajo—.

“That’s enough, Mandl,” Crowther said sharply.

Aunque la diferencia es que yo no soy una traidora a los de mi clase.

Mandl grinned towards him. “See, I knew you’d remember me.”

—No soy yo la que acaba de asesinar a más de cien personas —afirmó Helena, esforzándose por mantener el temple.

“Pull the information and let’s be done,” Crowther said to Helena.

No sabía por qué le molestaba tanto que la custodio fuese mujer, pero esa idea la enfadaba.

Helena took a deep breath.

—Ellos me habrían asesinado a mí si les hubiera dado la oportunidad.

Mandl looked unfazed. “You’re not going to make me talk,” she said. “I used to break my bones and gouge myself open just for fun.

Yo los maté primero. —La custodio alzó la barbilla y señaló a Helena con ella—.

Just to feel something inside that hole they raised us in.

¿Qué eres? —La repasó con la mirada—.

You’re too weak to hurt me, Traitor.”

¿Sanadora?

“You’d be surprised,” Helena said, heart pounding.

Seguro que sí.

Mandl just laughed.

Yo también fui sanadora.

The bodies from the warehouse were such a fresh tragedy.

Helena lo dudaba, pero la mujer estaba hablando libremente, así que dejó que siguiera.

All those people, moments from rescue, and now they were gone because Mandl wanted to hurt the Eternal Flame and the Resistance even more than she cared about freedom.

—No quería ser sanadora, pero no hay muchas opciones para nosotras. Él quiso que me hiciera monja, que me dedicara a criar a otros mocosos que fueran como yo, que les enseñara a ocultar sus habilidades y los castigara si no lo hacían.

Helena didn’t delude herself that the Eternal Flame had the degree of moral superiority that they tried to claim, but how could anyone find the Undying better?

¿Verdad?

“Why were you keeping the prisoners in tanks like that?” she asked, maintaining a calm, steady voice.

Helena se giró para mirar a Crowther, que lo observaba todo sin inmutarse.

Mandl smiled, her wide mouth stretching across her face.

—¿La conoces?

Her fingers twirled even though her wrists were shackled with inert iron. “Come on, try touching me.

—Ah, sí.

Let’s see who breaks first.”

El cernícalo Jan solía venir a vernos cuando alguien se portaba mal en el orfanato.

Helena’s anger sat like a boulder in the pit of her stomach as she moved towards Mandl. “I’ll admit, you’re probably better than me at hurting people.

Siempre traía alguna mascota, alguien atado a quien podíamos admirar, en quien podríamos convertirnos si hacíamos todo lo que nos pedía.

I can’t beat you at your own game, but we’re playing mine.”

Pero me sorprende que seas tú; normalmente eran más jóvenes. —Posó los ojos en Helena.

Mandl’s eyes flicked over to the door and then at Crowther, the first glimmer of nervousness.

—Ya basta, Mandl —replicó Crowther con aspereza.

She forced a laugh. “What can you do?”

La mujer sonrió de lado.

Helena was behind Mandl now. “I don’t think you know this trick.”

—¿Ves?

Mandl tried to crane her neck, attempting to twist and see what Helena was doing.

Ya sabía yo que te acordabas de mí.

She jerked away as Helena slid her bare hand up from the nape of her neck, fingers lacing through the short hair.

—Sonsácale la información y acabemos con esto —le ordenó Crowther a Helena.

Mandl’s hands twisted, trying to break loose from the shackles.

La sanadora tomó aire, aunque Mandl parecía poco impresionada.

“It’s all right.” Helena’s voice was as practised and clinical as her resonance as she blocked the right nerves along the spine, making sure not to stop Mandl’s heart or suspend anything vital. “I guess there’s something to being Institute-trained after all.”

—No vas a obligarme a hablar —repuso—.

Helena slowed her heartbeat, stifling the rising terror.

Solía romperme los huesos y abrirme en canal por diversión.

Like a gas valve, tinkering with the cocktail of hormones racing through Mandl, telling her to be calm, that Helena was not a threat.

Solo para sentir algo en aquel agujero en el que nos criaron.

“You want to tell me everything I ask,” Helena said softly.

Eres demasiado débil para hacerme daño, traidora.

Mandl seized violently, trying to resist, her body lurching.

—Te sorprendería —dijo Helena con el corazón en un puño.

Her resonance flared, trying to push back against Helena, but she was too late.

Mandl se limitó a reír.

“Bitch—traitorous bitch—” she slurred as Helena winnowed through her raging emotions.

Los cadáveres del almacén eran una tragedia muy reciente.

Mandl’s eyes lost focus.

Todas esas personas, a solo unos minutos de que las rescatasen, habían muerto porque Mandl prefería hacerle daño a la Llama Eterna y a la Resistencia antes que arriesgar su propia libertad.

Her mind and body were in direct conflict, and it was impossible for her to struggle as Helena slipped into her memories.

Helena no se engañaba a sí misma; la Llama Eterna no era el faro de moralidad que pretendían ser, pero ¿cómo podía alguien pensar que los inmarcesibles eran mejores?

Kaine had made the process seem simple.

—¿Por qué almacenabais a los prisioneros en esos tanques? —preguntó con voz calmada y firme.

It was much more difficult than Helena had expected.

Mandl sonrió y su boca ancha pareció estirarse en su rostro.

The noise of another mind.

Movió los dedos, a pesar de las esposas de metal inerte que la sujetaban.

There was so much sound and energy, and Mandl’s panic and attempts at resisting made it so much harder.

—Venga, atrévete a tocarme.

Kaine had always let Helena’s thoughts wander, catching them as they passed.

A ver quién se rompe primero.

Helena couldn’t help but think there were easier ways to do it.

La rabia de Helena cayó como una losa hasta el fondo del estómago.

“What’s your name?”

Se acercó a Mandl.

Elsbeth.

—Estoy segura de que se te da mucho mejor que a mí hacer daño a los demás.

The name rang from a dozen directions all over inside Mandl’s mind, coalescing at the forefront.

No puedo vencerte en tus términos, pero aquí estamos jugando con los míos.

Mandl’s face was slack, a trickle of drool running down one side of her mouth, but her eyes followed Helena with growing fury.

Mandl miró la puerta y después a Crowther, y, por primera vez, sus ojos delataron cierto nerviosismo.

Her mind trying and failing to recoil at the way Helena was manipulating her.

Soltó una carcajada forzada.

“Why were you keeping prisoners in tanks like that?”

—¿Qué me vas a hacer?

Mandl tried to resist, but a memory flitted across her consciousness.

Helena se colocó detrás de ella.

A man in uniform was speaking: “—keep the best specimens …” Mandl’s attention in the memory wandered to a buzzing fly and everything went out of focus.

—Creo que este truco no te lo sabes.

Helena tried again. “If you had a new prisoner, what would you do with them?”

Mandl quiso doblar el cuello para ver qué estaba haciendo Helena, pero se apartó cuando ella apoyó la mano en la base de su nuca y entrelazó los dedos por su cabello corto.

Memory fragments were like tatters of moving pictures, sounds and sensation all whipping by as if carried by wind.

La prisionera retorció las manos, forcejeando para intentar liberarse de los grilletes.

She heard voices, but they were too distant to make out.

—No pasa nada —dijo Helena con una voz tan fría y profesional como la resonancia que usó para bloquearle los nervios de su columna vertebral, evitando que su corazón sufriera un infarto o que algún órgano vital quedara dañado—.

She saw the walls of a warehouse, greenish light from the tinted windows.

Supongo que haberse educado en la Academia tiene sus ventajas.

A boy whose face she half recognised, writhing.

Helena reguló el ritmo de su corazón para amortiguar el terror que empezaba a apoderarse de la custodio.

Everything blurred, but a tingle of anticipation ran along her spine.

Como si hubiera abierto una válvula de gas, manipuló el cóctel hormonal que recorría las venas de Mandl y la forzó a calmarse para que no viera a Helena como una amenaza.

The gleam of a hypodermic needle in the low light.

—Quieres responder a todas mis preguntas —dijo Helena con suavidad.

A finger flicking it to knock loose an air bubble.

Mandl se rebeló con violencia, trató de resistirse moviendo el cuerpo sin cesar.

A glimpse of the boy again.

Intentó extender su resonancia para bloquear la de Helena, pero ya era demasiado tarde.

Blur.

—Puta… puta traicionera… —farfulló mientras Helena se abría paso entre sus emociones desbocadas.

Rows of the bodies laid out on gurneys next to the tanks.

La mirada de Mandl se nubló.

A bloated corpse with yellowish eyes, grey discoloured skin.

Su mente y su cuerpo entraron en conflicto, y fue incapaz de resistirse cuando Helena se coló en sus recuerdos.

Squeezing the arm of a young man and saying, I’ll take this one next.

Kaine le había explicado el procedimiento de forma sencilla, pero a Helena le pareció mucho más complicado de lo que esperaba.

A printed form requesting ten female subjects.

El ruido de otra mente ocasionaba demasiado estrépito y energía en ella, y, unido al pánico de Mandl y sus intentos de zafarse, lo dificultaba todo aún más.

Signed Artemon Bennet.

Kaine, en cambio, siempre dejaba que los pensamientos de Helena vagaran a su antojo, y los atrapaba al vuelo.

Mandl’s hands pushing a cart with the boy lying on it, the mask and tubes still attached as she wheeled him into an empty room.

Helena no pudo evitar pensar que debía de existir una forma más fácil de hacerlo.

Shutting the door softly.

—¿Cómo te llamas?

Another shiver along her spine.

«Elsbeth».

Helena ripped her mind free, snatching her hands away, wanting to scrub them until the skin came off.

El nombre resonó desde todos los ángulos de su mente, hasta converger en un solo punto, al frente.

“What is it for?” she asked.

La cara de Mandl estaba inerte y un hilillo de baba le caía por una de las comisuras de la boca.

Her skin was crawling.

Sin embargo, sus ojos seguían a Helena con una rabia cada vez más intensa.

She didn’t want to go back into Mandl’s mind.

Su mente trataba de resistirse a la manipulación de Helena, pero sin éxito.

Mandl was breathing unsteadily, her pupils dilated so wide that the blue irises barely showed.

—¿Por qué almacenabais a los prisioneros en esos tanques?

“I’ll pull it out if you don’t answer,” Helena said, gripping Mandl by the hair. “Do you prefer that?”

Mandl intentó resistirse, pero un recuerdo emergió en su consciencia: un hombre uniformado estaba hablando: «… mantener los mejores especímenes…».

Mandl’s expression twisted, and she spat. “It keeps them fresh.”

La atención de Mandl se desvió por un instante a una mosca que pasaba por allí y el recuerdo se desvaneció.

“Fresh for what?”

Helena insistió de nuevo.

“Anything.

—Si recibieras un nuevo prisionero, ¿qué harías con él?

New bodies for the Undying.

Los fragmentos de memoria eran como imágenes en movimiento, sonidos y sensaciones que se arrastraban como si se los llevase el viento.

Test subjects.

Helena oía voces, pero eran tan distantes que no distinguía las palabras.

Thralls.

Vio las paredes de un almacén, una luz verdosa que provenía de unas ventanas tintadas.

The thralls last longer when they’re new.” Mandl was panting openmouthed, her lips growing chapped.

Un chico, que le resultó vagamente familiar, se retorcía de dolor.

“How long are they kept there?”

La imagen se desdibujó, pero sintió una punzada de anticipación.

Mandl smiled cruelly. “There’s high demand, so usually not more than a few months.

El brillo de una aguja hipodérmica bajo la luz tenue.

Electric shock keeps the muscle toned.

Un dedo golpeándola para explotar una burbuja de aire.

We slow the vitals.”

De nuevo, el chico.

It felt an eternity before Crowther was satisfied with the amount of information Helena pulled out.

Desenfoque.

By that time, Mandl’s eyes were so disoriented that they looked in different directions.

Hileras de cadáveres tendidos sobre camillas junto a los tanques.

She’d grown feverish and was slumped forward, trembling.

Un cuerpo hinchado con los ojos amarillentos y la piel gris descolorida.

“Well,” Crowther said, sneering down at Mandl, “it seems you’ll make a passable replacement for Ivy.”

Alguien presionó el brazo del joven y dijo: «Me llevo a este».

Helena said nothing.

Una solicitud que pedía diez sujetos que fueran mujeres, firmada por Artemon Bennet.

She never wanted to do it ever again.

Las manos de Mandl empujando una camilla en la que yacía un chico, aún con la mascarilla y los tubos enganchados mientras lo trasladaban a una sala vacía.

She regretted agreeing to it.

Cerró la puerta con cuidado.

She turned wordlessly to leave.

Sintió otro escalofrío en la columna.

“Traitor …” Mandl called after her.

Helena rompió el contacto con su mente y apartó las manos.

De repente, deseó frotárselas hasta arrancarse la piel.

—¿Por qué lo hacéis? —preguntó.

Tenía el vello erizado como escarpias.

No quería volver a adentrarse en la mente de Mandl.

La custodio respiraba con dificultad y tenía las pupilas tan dilatadas que apenas se distinguía el iris azul.

—Te lo sacaré a la fuerza si no me respondes —insistió Helena, y la agarró del cabello—.

¿Prefieres eso?

Mandl torció el gesto en una mueca y escupió.

—Los mantiene frescos.

—¿Para qué?

—Para lo que sea.

Cuerpos nuevos para los inmarcesibles.

Sujetos de prueba.

Necrómatas.

Los necrómatas duran más si el cadáver es reciente. —Mandl jadeaba con la boca abierta; los labios cada vez se le agrietaban más.

—¿Cuánto tiempo los mantenéis allí?

Mandl sonrió con crueldad.

—Hay mucha demanda, así que no suelen estar más que unos meses.

Las descargas eléctricas mantienen los músculos en forma.

Ralentizamos sus constantes vitales.

Pasó lo que a Helena se le antojó una eternidad hasta que Crowther consideró suficiente la cantidad de información obtenida.

Para entonces, los ojos de Mandl ya estaban tan perdidos que miraban en direcciones opuestas.

La fiebre empezó a subirle y se desplomó hacia delante, temblando.

—Bueno —dijo Crowther, bajando la vista hacia Helena—, parece que vas a ser una buena sustituta de Ivy.

Helena no respondió.

No quería volver a hacerlo.

Se arrepentía de haber accedido a ello.

Se giró sin decir una palabra.

—Traidora —masculló Mandl a su paso.

CHAPTER 58

Junius 1787

CAPÍTULO 58

SUCCESSFUL AS LUC’S RECENT OFFENSIVES WERE, THE new territory was stretching the Resistance thin.

Junius 1787

Despite the widespread admiration for Luc’s decisive and successful leadership, the higher-ups were less enthused.

Por mucho éxito que estuvieran teniendo los últimos ataques de Luc, el territorio reconquistado estaba dispersando las fuerzas de la Resistencia.

There were rumours of Luc having an explosive argument with Althorne and several other members of military command, for not consulting them.

A pesar de la admiración que despertaba el liderazgo resuelto y audaz del principado, los altos cargos no compartían ese entusiasmo.

Some of the districts were surrounded on three sides by the Undying, requiring constant patrols and defence while providing very little strategic use.

Se rumoreaba que Luc había mantenido una acalorada discusión con Althorne y otros miembros del comando militar por actuar sin consultarlos.

The districts in question also had not received their “liberation” with enthusiasm.

Había distritos que estaban rodeados por territorio inmarcesible, por lo que requerían vigilancia y defensa constantes a pesar de que su valor estratégico era escaso.

Many of the Paladians on the West Island were quite happy under Undying occupation and fearful of being labelled Resistance sympathisers if the district was eventually taken back.

Esos distritos tampoco habían recibido la «liberación» con entusiasmo.

As a result, the Resistance was forced to fend off not only attacks from the Undying’s forces but also civilian rebellions.

Muchos paladinos de la isla Oeste vivían cómodamente bajo la ocupación inmarcesible y temían que los consideraran simpatizantes de la Resistencia si el enemigo recuperaba el control del distrito.

The summer Abeyance was approaching, and the troops were concentrated down-island to defend the ports and the anticipated trade influx.

Como consecuencia, la Resistencia se vio obligada a defenderse no solo de los ataques del ejército inmarcesible, sino también de las rebeliones civiles.

The hospital remained ceaselessly full.

Se acercaba la latencia de verano, y las tropas se concentraron al sur de la isla para defender los puertos y el paso de los barcos mercantes que pronto arribarían.

No longer were the sharp deluges of battles followed by a lull to recuperate.

El hospital siempre estaba lleno.

Now it was constant, an unrelenting strain that ran everyone ragged.

Ya no se producían avalanchas de pacientes tras una batalla seguidas de un periodo de descanso.

“I don’t know what to do,” Helena said one night, sitting up because she couldn’t sleep, not even in Kaine’s arms. “I don’t know how we can win.

Ahora era constante, un goteo incesante que tenía a todo el mundo al límite.

I can’t see any way.”

—No sé qué hacer —confesó Helena una noche.

“You can’t save everyone,” he said quietly.

Se incorporó porque no podía dormir, ni siquiera en los brazos de Kaine—.

Her jaw started trembling, and she clenched her fists. “I’m not even trying to save everyone, though.

No sé cómo vamos a ganar.

I don’t know how to save anyone.

No veo salida.

I can’t figure anything out.

—No puedes salvarlos a todos —repuso él con calma.

Everything I try is a dead end.

A Helena empezó a temblarle la mandíbula y apretó los puños.

We’re running out of time.”

—Pero es que no estoy intentando salvarlos a todos.

He said nothing.

No sé cómo salvar a nadie.

“I’m just—” She scrubbed her eyes. “I’m so tired.

No consigo entenderlo.

Everything I do feels like I’m delaying the inevitable, saving someone one day so they’ll die in a worse way tomorrow.

Todo lo que se me ocurre es un callejón sin salida.

I wish I’d never become a healer.”

Nos estamos quedando sin tiempo.

She’d never admitted it to anyone before.

Kaine no respondió.

That she hated it.

—Es solo que… —Se frotó los ojos—.

She told him everything now.

Estoy muy cansada.

The truth about the Stone, and where it was, the true story of the Holdfasts, the array from Wagner, and how no matter how she tried, she couldn’t work out how the channelling was supposed to work.

Me da la sensación de que todo lo que hago no sirve más que para retrasar lo inevitable, que salvo a alguien hoy para que muera de una forma aún peor al día siguiente.

She even told him about the obsidian, and how useless it had proven to be.

Ojalá no me hubiese hecho sanadora.

She was so tired of finding possibilities that went nowhere.

Jamás lo había admitido en voz alta.

“Bring me a piece,” he told her. “Maybe you haven’t been able to test it the right way.”

Que lo odiaba.

She shook her head. “There’s already too much you need to focus on.

Entonces se lo contó todo a Kaine.

You don’t need to worry about my pointless experiments.” She cleared her throat. “Did I tell you, I’m working with my lab partner to reverse the nullium alloy, so we can use the compound from it to make inert metal?

La verdad sobre la gema y su paradero, la historia real sobre los Holdfast, el sello de Wagner y que, por mucho que lo había intentado, no lograba averiguar cómo funcionaba la canalización.

I was thinking, I could use transmutation to make a really light mesh armour with a high tensile strength, and then use the compound to remove the resonance.

También le habló de la obsidiana, que tampoco le había llevado a ninguna parte.

You would wear it under your clothes.

Estaba harta de encontrar posibilidades que no conducían a nada.

It wouldn’t interfere with your resonance, and no one could use theirs to break through it.” She traced a finger over a silvery scar on his arm. “I think I’ve almost got it all worked out.

—Tráeme un trozo —le pidió Kaine—.

Then you won’t get hurt so much.”

Tal vez no la has puesto a prueba como es debido.

He kissed the top of her head. “I’m still healing just fine.

Helena negó con la cabeza.

Bring me a piece of the obsidian.

—Tú ya tienes demasiadas cosas encima.

It’ll be more interesting to experiment with than dealing with all of Crowther’s self-defeating sabotage orders.

No quiero que te preocupes por mis experimentos inútiles. —Se aclaró la garganta—.

Everyone in the Undying is paranoid about spies now, and Morrough’s been taking more precautions than ever.”

¿Te conté que estoy trabajando con mi compañero de laboratorio para revertir la aleación de anulitio y que podamos usar el compuesto en un metal inerte?

HELENA WAS SORTING THROUGH THE various pieces of charged obsidian she’d accumulated when the windows exploded.

Se me ocurrió que podríamos transmutarlo para convertirlo en una malla de armadura ligera que fuese resistente y flexible, y que eliminara la resonancia.

A roar shuddered through the air and Tower.

Los soldados podrían llevarla debajo de la ropa y no interferiría con su propia resonancia, pero el enemigo no podría emplear la suya para atravesarla. —Con un dedo, recorrió la cicatriz plateada del brazo de Kaine—.

Lab equipment shattered across the floor.

Creo que ya casi lo tengo.

The sirens started.

Así no te harían tanto daño.

All of them.

Kaine le besó la coronilla.

Another bomb.

—Yo me curo sin problemas.

Helena headed for the stairs before her bracelet burned, running over the broken glass that covered the floors.

Tráeme un trozo de la obsidiana.

They got scattered reports of what had happened.

Será más interesante que seguir cumpliendo todas las órdenes absurdas de sabotaje de Crowther.

Several buildings had fallen, and the interconnected skybridges conjoining the cityscape had wrought massive destruction across the centre of the island.

Los inmarcesibles están ya paranoicos, y Morrough está tomando más precauciones que nunca.

The hospital prepared for the inundation they knew would come, but as they waited, only a few lorries arrived, all carrying people from the outermost edges of the collapse.

Helena estaba rebuscando entre los distintos trozos de obsidiana que había ido acumulando cuando estallaron las ventanas.

Helena was healing a heavy gash across a woman’s head when she heard the clamour that meant gurneys were being brought down the hall, but before they reached the hospital, there were voices bellowing from the hallway.

Un rugido atravesó toda la Torre y los instrumentos del laboratorio se hicieron añicos contra el suelo.

“Don’t bring them in!

Se activaron las alarmas.

Get them outside.

Todas a la vez.

Cover those windows.

Otra bomba.

Get every entrance sealed.”

Helena se lanzó escaleras abajo, justo cuando el brazalete comenzó a calentarse, y pisó los cristales rotos que cubrían el suelo.

There was muffled arguing and protests until a voice roared, “The nullium’s in the air.

Los informes de lo que había sucedido comenzaron a llegar, inconexos.

They’re covered in it.

Varios edificios se habían derrumbado y los puentes colgantes que unían los rascacielos de la ciudad habían provocado una destrucción sin precedentes en el centro de la isla.

Take them back out!”

El hospital se preparó para la avalancha que sabía que estaba por llegar, pero tras una larga espera solo aparecieron un par de camiones, y todos traían a personas que se encontraban en la zona más alejada del derrumbe.

Helena turned to stare in horror at Elain, who looked bewildered, her suncrest trembling below her throat.

Helena estaba curando un profundo corte en la frente de una mujer cuando oyó el estrépito de las camillas al moverse por los pasillos.

“Why does it matter if it’s in the air?” Elain asked.

Sin embargo, antes de que entraran al hospital, escuchó los gritos:

“Because if we inhale it, we could all lose our resonance,” Helena said, nearly frozen as all the ramifications of that began dawning on her.

—¡Que no entren!

Nullium shrapnel had been devastation enough, but they weren’t prepared for inhalation.

Dejadlos fuera.

She looked around at the hospital with all the high windows open, trying to catch the mountain breeze as the basin sweltered in the early-summer heat.

Cerrad las ventanas.

The air was hazy with dust.

Sellad todas las entradas.

They were already breathing it.

Hubo protestas y discusiones ahogadas, y una voz potente se alzó por encima de las demás:

THEY WORE CLOTH MASKS AND the casualty ward was relocated into the commons, trying to keep the new patients away from those already in the hospital, but it was impossible to tell on sight if the dust covering someone had nullium in it or not.

—Hay anulitio en el aire.

All the protocols were forgotten as more and more stretchers arrived, the injuries growing progressively worse as the rescue and recovery efforts neared the blast zone.

Están cubiertos de anulitio.

They washed off as much dust as possible, trying to reduce potential contamination while sorting out life-and-death injuries and identifying those already showing signs of nullium exposure.

¡Sacadlos de aquí!

How long would it take for nullium in the air to penetrate the lungs and reach the blood?

Helena se giró, horrorizada, hacia Elain, que parecía desconcertada.

Once it did, how long would they have before their resonance began fading?

El blasón solar temblaba junto a su garganta.

No one knew.

—¿Qué más da que esté en el aire? —preguntó.

Helena worked with a degree of ruthless abandon that she had never before dared.

—Porque, si lo inhalamos, podríamos perder nuestra resonancia —respondió Helena, y se quedó paralizada cuando empezó a comprender las consecuencias de aquello.

Every second counted.

La metralla de anulitio había sido devastadora, pero no estaban preparados para una inhalación.

She healed and healed, working with mindless desperation.

Miró a su alrededor, hacia las altas ventanas del hospital, que permanecían abiertas para que dejaran entrar la brisa de la montaña y aliviar el bochorno del verano.

The day was hot, and the dust in the air grew thick as a rare southerly wind brought it up-island towards them.

El ambiente estaba neblinoso, cargado de polvo.

The mask on her face sealed the dampness against her skin.

Ya lo estaban respirando.

Her hands grew caked with dust that she kept washing off after every patient.

Se pusieron mascarillas de tela y trasladaron la sala de urgencias a los jardines, donde trataron de mantener apartados a los nuevos pacientes de los que ya estaban ingresados.

The mask stopped working; it was so clogged with dust, it nearly suffocated her.

Sin embargo, era imposible saber a simple vista si el polvo que cubría a una persona contenía anulitio o no.

She replaced it with a wet cloth, which was what everyone without masks had already begun using.

Los protocolos quedaron relegados en cuanto empezaron a llegar más y más camillas.

“Marino!

A medida que rescataban personas de las zonas más afectadas por la explosión, las heridas se volvían cada vez más graves.

Where’s Marino?”

Limpiaron todo el polvo que les fue posible para reducir una posible contaminación y separaron a los heridos según la gravedad, identificando a aquellos que ya mostraban signos de haberse expuesto al anulitio.

Helena looked up from washing her hands. “What is it?”

¿Cuánto tardaría el anulitio suspendido en el aire en penetrar en los pulmones y llegar a la sangre?

She squinted through the haze at the man in front of her.

Una vez que lo hiciera, ¿cuánto tiempo después empezaría a fallarles la resonancia?

“What are you doing here?

Nadie lo sabía.

You’re supposed to be down-island.

Helena se lanzó a trabajar como nunca lo había hecho antes.

I’ve been looking for you.” He was in a lorry uniform, and he took her by the arm.

Cada segundo importaba.

She stared at him in confusion as he pulled her towards one of the lorries. “What?”

Sanaba sin descanso, con una desesperación inconsciente.

“There’s too much of a risk of the nullium contamination spreading if we keep bringing the wounded up-island.

Hacía mucho calor, y el polvo en el ambiente se volvió más denso cuando un extraño viento del sur lo arrastró al norte de la isla, donde se encontraba el hospital.

Takes too long anyway.

Estaba sudando tanto que la mascarilla se le adhirió a la piel.

There’s a hospital down-island but they’re overrun, not enough experience with the nullium.

Las manos se le cubrían de polvo, por lo que tenía que lavárselas después de atender a cada paciente.

You’re in charge of the nullium ward here, so you’re lead.

La mascarilla dejó de funcionar; estaba tan saturada de polvo que apenas podía respirar.

Orders are right here.” He shoved her up into the passenger side of the lorry and handed her a piece of paper.

La sustituyó con un trapo húmedo, como hacían muchas personas que no tenían mascarilla.

“I’m not in charge …” She squinted at the paper, her eyes gritty with dust. “I’m not allowed to leave Headquarters.”

—¡Marino!

She stared stupidly at the words that indicated that Helena Marino, as head of the nullium ward, was to be dispatched to the field hospital to lead the medics in treating the nullium-poisoned combatants.

¿Dónde está Marino?

It was signed by Falcon Matias.

Helena levantó la vista del lavabo.

She couldn’t even remember the last time she’d been given written orders from him.

—¿Qué sucede?

“This can’t be right.

Miró al hombre que tenía delante a través de la neblina.

Was there a meeting?”

—¿Qué estás haciendo aquí?

The engine rumbled beneath her.

Deberías estar en el sur de la isla.

“I just follow orders, Marino.

Te he estado buscando. —Llevaba el uniforme de los conductores de camión y la tomó por el brazo.

They don’t bring me in for Council meetings.

Helena lo miró, desconcertada, mientras la empujaba hacia uno de los camiones.

You were supposed to be there right off.

—¿Qué?

Kept waiting, finally went looking for you.” The driver twisted at the ignition, shifting a gear, and the lorry lurched forward.

—Corremos el riesgo de que la contaminación se extienda si seguimos trasladando a los heridos al norte de la isla.

Before she had more time to argue, they were speeding out of Headquarters and down-island.

Además, se tarda demasiado.

She could already see the ruined skyline.

Hay un hospital en el sur, pero están desbordados y no tienen experiencia con el anulitio.

“I need you to go back and tell Crowther where I’ve been dispatched.

Tú estás a cargo del pabellón de anulitio de este hospital, así que gestionarás el del sur.

I don’t think this was Council-authorised,” she said as they drove.

Aquí están las órdenes. —La metió a empujones en el asiento del copiloto del camión y le entregó un documento.

“There’s a radio at the field office.

—Yo no estoy a cargo de… —Intentó leer el papel, pero tenía los ojos llenos de polvo—.

You can check in when you arrive.”

No me está permitido salir del Cuartel General.

She always forgot how fast it was to travel by vehicle on military roads.

Contempló estupefacta las palabras que afirmaban que Helena Marino estaba al mando del pabellón del anulitio y que debía trasladarse al hospital de campaña para enseñar a los médicos de allí a tratar con los combatientes afectados por el anulitio.

In no time at all, the lorry stopped at a hastily assembled checkpoint.

El documento estaba firmado por el falcón Matias.

Everyone sent down the island into the blast zone was fitted with layers of protective clothing, masks as well as veils to try to keep out the dust.

Ni siquiera recordaba la última vez que había recibido órdenes escritas de su parte.

They stopped to dress and then continued deeper.

—No puede ser.

The dust hung in the air, and the road deteriorated, covered in rubble.

¿Ha habido alguna reunión?

It was midday, but the dust blotted out the sun so that everything glowed an eerie orange.

El motor rugió bajo sus pies.

Two bright lanterns showed through the smog, and they pulled up at the hospital.

—Yo solo cumplo órdenes, Marino.

There were already medics there, no healers, although it was hard to tell who anyone was.

No suelen llevarme a las reuniones del Consejo.

Medical workers all wore red ribbons tied around their arms.

Deberías haber llegado hace rato y, como nos cansamos de esperar, vine a buscarte. —El conductor giró la llave, metió una marcha y el camión se abalanzó hacia delante.

Here Helena saw the devastation she’d kept expecting to arrive at Headquarters.

Sin tiempo para seguir discutiendo, se alejaron a toda velocidad del Cuartel General hacia el sur de la isla.

This was the worst of it.

Helena empezó a ver los edificios que faltaban.

There were so many crushed bodies.

—Tienes que volver y decirle a Crowther adónde me han trasladado.

The armour of soldiers had splintered and sliced them apart.

No creo que esto lo haya autorizado el Consejo —le dijo por el camino al conductor.

Medics with the right resonance were transmuting the armour off, but when it came loose, blood would immediately begin pouring out.

—Hay un transmisor en el despacho de campaña.

Dust and smoke and metal and blood stained the air.

Puedes informar tú misma en cuanto llegues.

Helena could taste it despite all the layers.

Se había olvidado de lo rápido que era moverse por las carreteras militares.

There was no running water.

En cuestión de minutos, el camión se detuvo en un puesto de control improvisado.

She could barely see.

A todo el que se dirigía a la zona sur de la isla, ahí donde había estallado la bomba, se le entregaba un mono protector, mascarillas y velos para evitar la exposición.

No one had any idea where the radio was, or if they still had one.

Se detuvieron para cambiarse y luego siguieron avanzando.

They were drowning in injuries.

El polvo flotaba en el aire y el trayecto se volvió más accidentado debido a los escombros que se acumulaban en el asfalto.

Half of the medics had already lost their resonance, and there was no time to do anything but switch to manual protocols.

Era mediodía, pero el cielo estaba tan cubierto de polvo que la luz del sol tenía un sucio color naranja.

Without running water, it was impossible to keep anything clean.

A través de la neblina distinguieron dos faroles brillantes que marcaban la entrada del hospital.

Helena could feel her resonance starting to fail when General Althorne came through the door, pulling a cart with several bodies on it.

Dejaron allí el camión.

“I think they’re alive,” he said, breathing heavily.

En el interior había médicos, pero ningún sanador, aunque era complicado saber cuál era la función de cada uno.

He was coated in dust, no mask and only light armour on. “There’s at least forty trapped under a wall.

Todo el personal sanitario llevaba lazos rojos anudados en el brazo.

We can hear them, but we don’t know how to reach them without potentially collapsing it on them.”

Allí, por fin, Helena vio la devastación que en el Cuartel General habían temido que llegase.

Helena let the others check the bodies and try to find space for them.

Allí se encontraba lo peor.

The hospital was already overflowing.

Había decenas de cuerpos aplastados.

Althorne’s fingers were bloody from digging through rubble.

La armadura de los soldados se había astillado con ellos aún dentro.

He sat down heavily, coughing violently, struggling to breathe.

Los médicos que tenían la misma resonancia transmutaban el metal para quitársela, pero, cuando lo lograban, empezaba la hemorragia.

“You should be wearing a mask,” she said.

El polvo, el humo, el metal y la sangre se mezclaban en el ambiente.

“Can’t breathe in those damn things,” he said, gulping water. “No point.

Helena podía saborearlos aunque tuviese la boca cerrada.

Already lost my resonance.” Then he blinked and peered at her. “Marino?”

No había agua corriente.

“Yes?” She didn’t know Althorne had any idea who she was.

Apenas podía ver.

He leaned towards her, his voice dropping. “What are you doing here?

Nadie tenía ni idea de dónde estaba el transmisor, o si aún existía.

Get back to Headquarters before Ferron finds out about this.”

Se estaban ahogando con los heridos.

She was speechless, but of course Althorne had to have known.

La mitad de los médicos ya había perdido su resonancia, y no quedaba tiempo para nada que no fuera recurrir a los protocolos tradicionales.

She looked at him helplessly. “Matias signed the order and dispatched me here, and I can’t find the radio to get permission to return.”

Sin agua corriente, era imposible mantener la limpieza básica.

“Go back to Headquarters.

Helena empezaba a notar que le fallaba la resonancia cuando el general Althorne atravesó la puerta empujando una camilla en la que yacían varios cuerpos.

First lorry.

—Creo que siguen con vida —dijo entre jadeos.

Tell them I ordered it.

Estaba cubierto de polvo y no llevaba mascarilla, solo una armadura ligera—.

The last thing we need is Ferron going off the rails.” Althorne dragged himself up on his feet.

Hay al menos cuarenta más atrapados bajo un muro.

“Wait.” She caught him by the arm, and to her surprise, he collapsed back onto the chair.

Los oímos, pero no sabemos cómo sacarlos de allí sin que todo se les venga encima.

She reached out with her failing resonance, but all she felt was a blur.

Helena dejó que los demás comprobaran las constantes vitales de los cuerpos y trató de buscarles sitio.

“Althorne, you need a mask.

El hospital estaba desbordado.

It’ll give you lung damage to keep breathing this dust.

Althorne tenía los dedos ensangrentados de excavar entre los escombros.

You’re too valuable to risk,” she said, searching him, trying to find the injury she could tell he was hiding.

Se dejó caer con pesadez en una silla y empezó a toser con violencia, incapaz de respirar.

It was a testament to how weak he was that he sat there, letting her.

—Deberías ponerte una mascarilla —le pidió Helena.

He said nothing.

—No puedo respirar con esos trapos —afirmó, y dio un trago de agua—.

“When are reinforcements coming?” she asked. “There’s not enough people here to handle this much.

Qué más da.

We’re running out of everything.”

Ya he perdido mi resonancia. —Entonces parpadeó y la miró de nuevo—.

“They’re not,” Althorne said quietly, as if to keep anyone else from overhearing. “We’re all there is.”

¿Marino?

Helena’s heart stalled.

—¿Sí? —No sabía que Althorne supiera quién era.

He watched as several soldiers dragged in bodies on makeshift litters.

El general se acercó a ella y bajó la voz.

“We can’t risk our remaining combatants down here, losing their resonance.

—¿Qué estás haciendo aquí?

The fallout has to be contained,” Althorne said, his voice tight with resignation.

Vuelve al Cuartel General antes de que Ferron se entere de esto.

He stood and swayed.

Helena se quedó sin palabras.

“Where are you hurt?” Helena asked, blocking his path.

Claro que lo sabía, ¿cómo no iba a saberlo?

He shrugged her off, straightening, his breath laboured. “It’s shallow.

Lo miró con impotencia.

Falling rubble.

—Matias ha firmado la orden para enviarme aquí, y no encuentro el transmisor para pedir permiso para volver.

Everyone’s bleeding.

—Vuelve al Cuartel General en el primer camión que salga.

I’ll be fine.”

Diles que lo he ordenado yo.

“Althorne.” She stepped into his path. “You’re hurt.

Lo último que necesitamos es que Ferron se descontrole. —Althorne consiguió ponerse de pie de nuevo.

Badly.

—Espera. —Helena lo sujetó del brazo y, para su sorpresa, él cayó rendido en la silla.

If I had my resonance, I’d sedate you by force, because you’re not in any condition to lead recovery efforts.

Intentó examinarlo con su resonancia, pero esta era intermitente y solo sintió un borrón—.

You are too valuable.

Althorne, tienes que llevar mascarilla.

You know that.

Si sigues respirando este polvo, sufrirás daños en los pulmones.

The Resistance can’t lose you.”

Eres demasiado valioso para morir —añadió, y siguió buscando la herida que sabía que él le estaba ocultando.

He patted her on the shoulder as if she were a child. “My men are in that rubble.

Estaba claro que algo no iba bien: estaba tan débil que se quedó ahí sentado, permitiendo que ella lo examinara.

Buried and suffocating because I sent them there.”

No dijo nada.

A warning shriek rose from the rubble.

—¿Cuándo llegan los refuerzos? —preguntó Helena—.

Long and piercing, followed by another and another.

Aquí no hay gente suficiente para gestionar todo esto.

Whistles.

Se nos está acabando todo.

Helena didn’t know what it meant.

—No hay —respondió Althorne en un susurro, como si no quisiera que los demás lo escucharan—.

Althorne’s face hardened.

Somos los únicos que quedamos.

He pushed her aside with a sweep of his arm. “Block the doors.

A Helena se le paró el corazón.

They’ve sent in necrothralls; they’ll be coming for the bodies.”

El general observó cómo unos soldados arrastraban más cuerpos hasta unas literas improvisadas.

He strode past her, and Helena stood, torn between trying to stop him and the urgency of securing the hospital.

—No podemos arriesgarnos a que vengan más combatientes y pierdan también su resonancia.

Before she could decide, he vanished into the dust.

Tenemos que contener este brote —continuó Althorne con voz tensa pero resignada.

She turned to face the hospital.

Al intentar incorporarse, perdió el equilibrio.

“We need to move all the bodies as far back into the building as possible,” she said, her voice shaking. “If there’s not enough room—stack the dead.

—¿Dónde estás herido? —preguntó Helena interponiéndose en su camino.

We have to secure the doors.”

Althorne la apartó y se enderezó, pero seguía respirando entrecortadamente.

The thought of being locked in a field hospital again made her vision blur.

—Es superficial.

She forced herself to stay focused, curling her fingers until she felt the scars on her palm.

Me cayeron encima unos escombros.

“Can’t we let Headquarters know we’re under attack?” a medic asked, voice muffled through protective gear. “They have to send people.”

Todo el mundo está sangrando.

Helena shook her head. “They’re not coming.

Lo superaré.

The nullium has to be contained.”

—Althorne —insistió ella, volviendo a plantarse delante del general—.

Everyone around her froze, staring.

Estás herido de gravedad.

She probably wasn’t supposed to tell them that.

Si tuviera resonancia, te sedaría a la fuerza, porque no estás en condiciones de seguir rescatando soldados.

Helena had never been a leader, and she had no idea how to suddenly begin being one.

Eres demasiado valioso.

She was not the kind of person that anyone believed in, and standing, covered in dust, soaked in blood and gore—it was not the time for it.

Lo sabes.

She focused on practicalities.

La Resistencia no puede permitirse perderte.

“Our job is to keep everyone here safe.

Él le dio una palmadita en el hombro, como si hablara con una niña.

We’ll move them back and put up obstacles.

—Mis hombres están bajo los escombros, enterrados, se asfixian.

The Undying won’t come here themselves; nullium affects them, too.”

Y fui yo quien los envió ahí.

“But there’s no room to move anyone unless we can break through the walls, and no one here has the resonance for that.

Un aullido de advertencia se alzó desde la escombrera, al que le siguió otro, más largo y agudo.

We’re already out of space,” a medic said. “And how are we going to block the doors?”

Eran silbatos.

Helena looked around.

Helena no entendió su significado, pero el semblante de Althorne se endureció.

He was right.

La apartó de un manotazo.

If they protected the survivors, they’d have to leave the dead to be taken.

—Cerrad las puertas.

Which would cost them dearly later on.

Han mandado a los necrómatas; vienen a por los cuerpos.

There was no room, and no means.

La dejó atrás y Helena se quedó ahí, inmóvil, sin saber si debía detenerlo o asegurar el hospital.

She was in command.

Antes de que pudiera decidirse, Althorne ya había desaparecido entre el polvo.

She had a stupid slip of paper declaring it.

Ella se giró hacia el hospital.

“We’ll evacuate,” she said, not caring whether the nullium was supposed to be contained down-island.

—Hay que mover todos los cuerpos a la parte trasera del edificio —ordenó con voz trémula—.

It would be worse if the Undying got hold of all their casualties. “We won’t go into Headquarters, but if we get close enough, they might not pursue.

Si no hay espacio suficiente…, apilad a los muertos.

If the Council minds, they can blame me.”

Tenemos que cerrar las puertas.

A flurry of activity followed as bodies were prepared for transfer.

Solo con pensar que iba a encerrarse en un hospital de campaña, se le enturbiaba la vista.

Helena went and commandeered all the lorries, using the crumpled slip of paper that named her as head of the nullium ward as proof of legitimacy.

Se obligó a mantener la concentración y cerró los dedos hasta que notó las cicatrices en las palmas de las manos.

They crammed as many bodies as possible into the lorries.

—¿No podemos avisar al Cuartel General de que nos están atacando? —preguntó un médico.

Dead at the bottom, injured on top.

La voz llegó amortiguada a través del traje protector—.

A medic or nurse departed with each lorry.

Tienen que enviarnos refuerzos.

The wait for their return felt interminable as they readied group after group.

Helena negó con la cabeza.

They could hear the fighting.

—No vendrá nadie.

Fire glowed through the smog.

Hay que contener el anulitio.

Whistles kept sounding on all sides, like a signal of wolves closing in, except it wasn’t night; the world was red.

Todos se quedaron petrificados y la miraron fijamente.

Helena’s muscles were burning from lifting, over and over.

Seguramente no debería haberles dicho la verdad.

The bodies never seemed to stop.

Helena nunca había sido una líder y no tenía ni idea de cómo convertirse en una de repente.

She and one other medic were left, even though there were still wounded and more bodies that they had to get out.

No era la persona más indicada para que la creyeran, y ahí plantada, cubierta de polvo y empapada de sangre y vísceras, no parecía el mejor momento para intentarlo.

“I’ll stay,” he said. “Take this one.”

Se centró en los asuntos prácticos.

Helena shook her head. “I’m lead.

—Nuestro trabajo es mantener a salvo a todos.

I go last.”

Los trasladaremos al fondo y levantaremos una barricada.

He stepped back, thumping the lorry.

Los inmarcesibles no entrarán aquí; a ellos también les afecta el anulitio.

“I’ll wait with you, then,” he said.

—Pero no hay espacio para mover a nadie, a menos que tiremos abajo los muros, y nadie tiene resonancia para hacerlo.

She could only see his eyes, and they were crusted all around until they were black with dust.

Ya estamos sobrepasados —intervino un médico—.

He reminded her of Luc.

¿Y cómo vamos a atrancar las puertas?

“No,” she said quickly, looking away. “Go, that’s an order.”

Helena echó un vistazo a su alrededor.

She watched him swing up into the cab next to the driver as the lorry pulled away, driving carefully through the debris.

Tenía razón.

She could just barely make out the Alchemy Tower in the distance.

Si protegían a los supervivientes, tendrían que permitir que se llevaran a los muertos, y eso traería consecuencias aún peores en el futuro.

The flame at the top like a small sun.

No había ni espacio ni medios.

The lorry stopped.

Pero ella estaba al mando.

Helena squinted through the dust, trying to make out why.

Tenía un estúpido trozo de papel que lo decía.

There was another lorry approaching, swerving back and forth so that the departing lorry couldn’t pass it.

—Hay que evacuar —afirmó.

Suddenly the approaching lorry sped up, and Helena could see through the dust enough to make out the bloated grey face of the driver.

Le importaba un bledo que hubiera que contener el anulitio en la parte sur de la isla.

The Resistance lorry’s wheels screamed as it went into a rapid reverse, but rubble scattered across the road prevented evasion.

Sería mucho peor si los inmarcesibles se hacían con las víctimas—.

The approaching lorry crashed into it head-on.

No iremos al Cuartel General, pero, si nos acercamos lo suficiente, puede que no nos persigan.

There was a bright flash.

Si el Consejo os pone alguna pega, echadme a mí la culpa.

Lo que siguió fue un torbellino de actividad mientras se preparaban para su traslado.

Helena se dedicó a coordinar los camiones y utilizó la hoja arrugada de papel que la nombraba jefa del pabellón de anulitio como prueba de legitimidad.

Metieron en los camiones tantos cuerpos como les fue posible: los muertos abajo y los heridos arriba.

En cada camión viajaba un miembro del personal sanitario.

La espera hasta que regresaban se le hizo interminable, aunque mientras tanto se dedicaban a preparar un grupo tras otro.

Oían el combate que se estaba produciendo.

Veían el fuego brillar a través de la niebla.

Los silbatos no dejaban de sonar por todos los rincones, como una señal que indicaba que los lobos se estaban acercando, excepto que no era de noche.

El mundo entero se había teñido de rojo.

Helena notó que le ardían los músculos de tanto levantar peso.

El número de cuerpos era incesante.

Solo quedaban ella y otro médico, aunque todavía faltaban muchos heridos y aún más cadáveres que trasladar.

—Yo me quedo —se ofreció el hombre—.

Vete en este camión.

Helena negó con la cabeza.

—Soy la jefa.

Me iré la última.

El médico dio un paso atrás y le indicó al camión que avanzara.

—Me quedaré contigo entonces.

Solo le veía los ojos y estaban tan cubiertos de polvo que parecían negros.

Le recordó a Luc.

—No —replicó al instante, y apartó la mirada—.

Vete, es una orden.

Lo observó subirse a la cabina junto al conductor y el camión se puso en marcha, sorteando los escombros de la carretera.

Apenas alcanzaba a distinguir la Torre de Alquimia en la lejanía.

La llama de lo alto parecía un sol en miniatura.

El camión se detuvo.

Helena entornó los ojos para ver más allá del polvo y entender qué ocurría.

Un camión venía de frente y se movía hacia delante y hacia atrás, bloqueando el paso del vehículo que acababa de salir.

De repente, el camión que avanzaba de frente aceleró.

Helena pudo distinguir entre el polvo la cara grisácea e hinchada del conductor.

Las ruedas del camión de la Resistencia chirriaron mientras intentaba dar marcha atrás.

Sin embargo, los escombros esparcidos por la carretera no permitieron que se alejara demasiado.

El camión del necrómata se estrelló contra el otro.

Hubo un fogonazo de luz.

CHAPTER 59

Junius 1787

CAPÍTULO 59

HELENA LAY SQUINTING, STRUGGLING TO SEE, BUT everything was dim, blurring.

Junius 1787

When she tried to breathe, pain radiated through her, so sudden it jolted her back into consciousness.

Helena yacía en el suelo.

She clutched her chest, trying to draw breath, but she couldn’t.

Entornó los ojos, esforzándose por ver algo más, pero todo era un borrón difuso.

What had happened?

Cuando intentó respirar, sintió un dolor tan repentino por todo el cuerpo que recobró la consciencia de golpe.

She couldn’t remember.

Se llevó una mano al pecho e intentó inhalar, pero apenas lo consiguió.

She fought to breathe, and a low whistling sound came from somewhere.

¿Qué había sucedido?

Then it all rushed back.

No lo recordaba.

The lorries, they crashed and—

Intentó respirar mientras escuchaba un silbido agudo que provenía de alguna parte.

There must have been another bomb.

Entonces lo vio todo en su mente de nuevo: los camiones, el choque y…

She struggled, trying to pull herself up.

Debía de haber estallado otra bomba.

She tried to spot the explosion, but the landscape was wrong.

Trató de ponerse en pie.

Where was the road?

Quiso ubicar la explosión, pero el paisaje había cambiado por completo.

There was just fire and a crater.

¿Dónde estaba la carretera?

Agony bloomed through her.

Solo había fuego y un cráter.

Her vision turned red.

Un dolor agónico la atravesó y su visión se tiñó de rojo.

A whistling sound like a boiling kettle kept coming from somewhere.

De alguna parte seguía brotando ese silbido, como si fuera una tetera hirviendo.

She tried to find it and realised it was coming from her throat.

Cuando intentó localizarlo, se dio cuenta de que provenía de su propia garganta.

She moved cautiously.

Se movió con extremo cuidado.

If she’d damaged her spine—

Si se había dañado la columna…

Calm down.

«Cálmate.

Focus.

Concéntrate.

Assess your condition and act from there.

Evalúa tu estado y actúa en consecuencia».

She forced herself to look down and gave a strangled whimper.

Se obligó a mirar hacia abajo y un gemido ahogado se le escapó de sus labios.

There was a piece of metal buried in the centre of her chest, splitting her sternum.

Tenía un trozo de metal clavado en medio del pecho, justo en el esternón.

She kept staring at it, too shocked to move at first.

No consiguió apartar la mirada; estaba demasiado estupefacta para moverse.

She was going to die.

Iba a morir.

She was going to die in a field hospital, just like her father.

Moriría en un hospital de campaña, igual que su padre.

All that vivimancy just to run into the same fate.

Tanta vivemancia…, para acabar sufriendo el mismo destino.

She closed her eyes, struggling to stay calm as feeling crept back over her.

Cerró los ojos e intentó mantener la calma mientras recuperaba la sensación de su propio cuerpo.

She could sense her fingers.

Sentía los dedos de las manos.

Toes.

También los de los pies.

Her spine was intact at least.

Al menos, no se había dañado la columna.

She kept trying to breathe, but she wanted to scream with every hitch of her lungs.

Intentó respirar, pero lo único que quería era gritar a todo pulmón.

It was worse than a knife wound; the agony seemed to radiate outwards, seething like cracks through every rib.

El dolor era peor que una puñalada; irradiaba en todas direcciones, extendiéndose como una fractura por las costillas.

It consumed the whole of her consciousness.

Le ocupaba el total de su consciencia.

Get up.

«Levántate.

You have to get up.

Tienes que levantarte».

She could barely make herself move.

A duras penas logró ponerse en marcha.

She looked towards the road again.

Volvió a mirar hacia la carretera, aunque ya solo era un agujero.

There was just a hole.

Había desaparecido, pero aún quedaba gente en el hospital.

The road was gone, but there were still people in the hospital.

Consiguió levantar la mano y se arrancó la mascarilla.

She managed to get her hand up and peel the mask off.

Pensó que ya daría igual si sufría daños por inhalar el polvo.

She didn’t think that lung damage from dust mattered anymore.

El aire era mucho más frío.

The air was so much cooler.

Inspiró un poco.

She managed a half breath.

No podía morir.

She couldn’t die.

Trató de levantarse y respirar de forma superficial, como si jadeara.

She fought to her feet, managing shallow, panting breaths, and nearly fainted when she got upright.

Estuvo a punto de desmayarse cuando se incorporó.

Every movement was agony.

Cada movimiento era una agonía.

The need to breathe warred with the excruciating misery of forcing her ribs and lungs to shift.

La necesidad de respirar peleaba con el dolor insoportable que le causaba mover sus costillas y pulmones.

She bit down on her lip as she tried to shuffle towards the doors.

Se mordió el labio y comenzó a andar hacia las puertas, paso a paso.

One step at a time.

Notaba en los pulmones las ganas de toser, pero se contuvo.

Her lungs kept agitating her with the urge to cough, but she fought it back.

Cada vez que lo intentaba, sentía un dolor tan candente y agudo que se tambaleaba y perdía la visión.

Pain exploded through her each time, bright white, so searing she’d waver, unable to see.

Si tosía, se desmayaría, y estaría muerta antes de que recobrara la consciencia.

If she coughed, she would faint, and she’d be dead before she regained consciousness.

No iba a morir.

She would not die.

Tenía que esperar.

She would wait.

Alguien vendría a buscarla.

Someone would come back and find her.

Maier la operaría.

Maier could operate.

Shiseo trabajaría sin descanso para encontrar el quelante apropiado, y se recuperaría en un abrir y cerrar de ojos.

Shiseo would work night and day to find the right chelator, and she would make herself recover quickly.

Le había prometido a Kaine que estaría a salvo, que no le pasaría nada.

She’d promised Kaine that she was safe, that nothing would happen to her.

No podía morir.

She could not die.

Atravesó las puertas y encontró una bandeja con instrumental abandonado y unos cuantos frascos.

She made it through the doors.

Rebuscó entre ellos hasta dar con uno de láudano.

There was a tray with a few discarded instruments and bottles on it.

Nada más descorchar el tapón, dio un trago y el líquido le provocó escozor en la lengua.

She fumbled through them until she found a vial of laudanum.

No obstante, no tomó demasiado, ya que quería mantenerse lúcida.

She managed to unscrew the lid and forced down a sip of the tongue-biting contents.

Buscó entre los demás medicamentos algún estimulante que le permitiera seguir avanzando.

Not too much.

En ese momento hubiera matado por un antitusivo.

She had to stay lucid.

Se convenció de volver a mirarse el pecho.

She searched the rest of the supplies, looking for something, a stimulant to keep herself going.

Llevaba tantas capas de ropa que no consiguió ver exactamente dónde le penetraba la metralla ni si era anulitio que se disolvería en su sangre o un trozo desperdigado del camión.

She’d kill for a cough suppressant.

Ojalá pudiera arrancárselo, pero sabía que no era buena idea.

She forced herself to look down at her chest.

Si le había perforado el corazón o la aorta, se desangraría y moriría en cuestión de segundos.

She was wearing so many layers, she couldn’t see exactly where the shrapnel went in to tell if it was nullium dissolving into her blood or just a stray piece of the lorry.

Tal vez ese trozo de metal la estaba manteniendo con vida.

She wanted to pull it out but knew better.

Alguien vendría.

If it had punctured her heart or aorta, she’d bleed to death in seconds.

Solo debía esperar a que volviese un camión.

It might be keeping her alive.

Se obligó a seguir caminando, porque le resultaba más fácil que quedarse sentada sintiendo la herida.

Someone would come.

Examinó a los pacientes que quedaban.

She could wait until a lorry came back.

El más cercano era un chico al que le habían quitado ya la armadura.

She made herself keep moving, because it was easier than sitting, feeling the injury.

Le faltaba un brazo.

She checked the remaining patients.

Tenía una vía intravenosa en el otro, pero bajo su cuerpo había un charco con demasiada sangre.

The nearest was a boy who’d been cut out of his armour.

Con una mano temblorosa, Helena le comprobó el pulso y, al no encontrarlo, le cerró los ojos y buscó más pacientes.

He was missing an arm.

Había más fallecidos, y otros tantos inconscientes; solo unos pocos seguían despiertos.

There was an intravenous drip in his remaining arm, but there was so much blood pooled beneath him.

Los examinó a todos y tomó nota de dónde se encontraban.

Reaching feebly for a pulse and finding none, she drew his eyes closed and moved on.

El láudano le había calmado el dolor hasta el punto de poder moverse con mayor facilidad.

Most were dead, several unresponsive; only a few were still conscious.

—¿Mamá…? —gimió uno de los soldados, que cogió la muñeca de Helena cuando esta pasó a su lado.

She checked all of them, noting where they were.

La sanadora sintió una punzada de dolor en el pecho que se extendió hasta la columna y puso fin al alivio.

The laudanum had managed to numb her enough that she could move a little easier.

Estuvieron a punto de flaquearle las piernas y se mordió tan fuerte la lengua que saboreó la sangre en la boca.

“Mum …?” one of the soldiers moaned, catching her wrist as she passed.

El soldado tenía el yelmo aplastado contra el cráneo.

Pain ripped through her chest and up her spine, shattering the relief.

En la abertura se asomaba su rostro, con una parte magullada.

Her legs nearly gave out, and she bit down on her tongue so hard her mouth flooded with blood.

Una sangre espesa brotaba de su cabeza y empapaba el pallet sobre el que estaba tendido.

His helmet was crushed around his skull.

—Mamá… —repitió.

Through the openings, one side of his face was mangled.

—Llegará dentro de poco.

There was thick blood oozing from his head onto the pallet underneath him.

No le soltó la muñeca.

“Mum …” he said.

Volvió a tirar de ella.

“She’ll be here soon.”

La visión de Helena se tornó blanca.

He wouldn’t let go of her wrist.

—Mamá… Lo siento.

He tugged again.

Se me olvidó despedirme.

Her vision flashed white.

Lo siento.

“Mum … sorry.

—No pasa nada, n-no te preocupes —lo tranquilizó Helena.

Forgot to say goodbye.

Sintió que sus dedos se relajaban hasta soltarle la mano.

Sorry.”

Cuando bajó la vista, comprendió que había muerto.

“It’s all right, d-don’t worry,” she said.

Dio otro sorbo al láudano.

His fingers relaxed enough for her to slip her hand free.

Cada vez le costaba más evitar la tos.

She looked down.

No sabía si la sangre que tenía en la boca provenía de sus pulmones o de la lengua.

He was dead.

Aguzó el oído para escuchar si se acercaban más camiones.

She took another sip of laudanum.

El sonido de la batalla comenzaba a apagarse.

It was growing harder and harder to keep from coughing.

Se acercó con esfuerzo a las puertas.

She couldn’t tell if the blood in her mouth was from her lungs or her tongue.

Conforme pasaban los minutos, estaba más convencida de que su herida era demasiado grave para los medios de los que disponía la Resistencia.

She tried to listen for any sound of the lorries.

Los huesos partidos y la posible perforación en el corazón requeriría una cirugía manual muy precisa que Maier no sería capaz de realizar sin alquimia.

The sounds of fighting were fading.

Probablemente, también tuviera un pulmón perforado.

She headed for the doors.

Necesitaría al menos dos cirujanos, quizá tres.

She was growing increasingly certain that her injury was beyond the Resistance’s means.

Si habían activado el protocolo de emergencia que solía aplicarse cuando había heridos en masa, nadie excepto Luc o Sebastian era lo bastante importante como para prescindir de tres cirujanos.

The bone and potential heart damage would require extensive manual surgery beyond what Maier could manage without alchemy.

Apoyó la cabeza en la pared.

One of her lungs was likely punctured.

Incluso si la operaban y todo salía bien, sus probabilidades de vivir eran escasas.

She’d need at least two surgeons, possibly three.

Correría un grave riesgo de complicaciones e infección que agotaría los ya limitados suministros.

If triage protocols were in place, which they would be given the mass injuries, no one except Luc or Sebastian would qualify for three surgeons.

El hospital salvaría a más personas si la dejaban morir.

She leaned her head against the wall.

Cualquier análisis médico lo confirmaría.

Even with a successful surgery, her likelihood of survival would be low.

Independientemente de si llegaban los camiones o no, Helena iba a morir.

She’d be at high risk of complications and infection, a drain on their limited supplies.

Miró su mano y deseó tener resonancia para enviar un mensaje pulsado a Kaine, para decirle de algún modo que lo sentía, que lo había intentado.

The hospital would save far more people if they passed her over.

La visión se le nubló; los bordes comenzaron a difuminarse, como una tela que se encoge lentamente.

Any half-rate medical assessment would realise that.

Cuando parpadeó, vio a alguien delante de ella.

Whether the lorries arrived or not, she was going to die.

Su mente se tambaleó entre la neblina de dolor hasta que cayó en la cuenta de que se trataba de un necrómata.

She looked down at her hand, wishing she had the resonance to send a pulse code to Kaine.

La miraba con confusión, como si no tuviera claro si estaba viva o muerta.

Some way to tell him she was sorry.

Notó un espasmo en los pulmones, unas ganas violentas de toser, de expulsar el fluido que inundaba su pecho.

That she had tried.

Se le escapó un gemido rasgado al intentar contenerlas.

The edge of her vision was beginning to fade, unravelling like fabric, slowly shrinking smaller and smaller.

Por el rabillo del ojo percibió movimiento.

When she blinked, there was someone standing in front of her.

Había más necrómatas.

Her mind stumbled through the fog of pain before realising it was a necrothrall.

El sonido de la batalla había cesado.

It stood studying her as if confused about whether she was dead or alive.

Althorne y sus hombres habían muerto o se habían retirado.

Her lungs seized, trying to force a cough, to clear the fluid inside her chest.

Los necrómatas venían al hospital a por los muertos y los supervivientes.

A rasping whimper escaped her as she tried to hold it back.

No podía permitir que se llevaran a los supervivientes.

Movement caught her eye.

Dio un paso atrás y buscó un bisturí, algo afilado, un instrumento que causara una muerte rápida e indolora.

There were more necrothralls.

No permitiría que los llevaran al puerto Oeste.

The sounds of fighting had ceased.

Pero solo encontró vendas sucias y frascos vacíos de medicamentos.

Althorne and his men had died or fallen back.

Necesitaba un bisturí.

The necrothralls were coming for the hospital.

Sintió un bulto bajo su ropa.

For the dead and the survivors.

Tardó un instante en recordar qué guardaba en el bolsillo: la obsidiana.

She couldn’t let them take the survivors.

La tenía en la mano cuando estalló la bomba y se la habría escondido sin pensar.

She stepped back, trying to find a scalpel, something sharp, something that would be quick and painless.

Al intentar sacarla, se hizo un corte en el dedo.

She wouldn’t let them be taken to West Port.

El fragmento debía de haberse roto en la explosión, pero aún estaba afilado.

All she could find were filthy bandages and empty bottles of medicine.

Helena iba demasiado lenta.

She needed one scalpel.

Los necrómatas ya estaban dentro.

Something under her clothes bumped against her leg.

Había cadáveres junto a la puerta, y algunos necrómatas los apartaban a rastras, pero el resto se adentró en el hospital.

It took her a moment to remember what was there.

No se movían muy deprisa, pero eran más rápidos que Helena.

The obsidian.

Alcanzaron a los supervivientes antes que ella.

She had been holding it when the bomb went off; she’d shoved it in her pocket without thinking.

—¡No! —chilló con una voz rasgada que resonó en su pecho.

She fumbled for it and slit her finger open.

Uno de los necrómatas se dirigió hacia Helena, y ella trató de defenderse.

The piece must have shattered in the explosion, but it was sharp at least.

Lo único que tenía a mano era la obsidiana.

She was too slow.

Atacó al necrómata con ella.

The necrothralls were already inside.

Su piel suave y en descomposición se rasgó con facilidad y la punta del arma tocó hueso.

There were bodies by the door, and several necrothralls had stopped there, dragging them away, while the rest moved deeper.

Aunque apenas había empleado la fuerza, el movimiento le provocó tanto dolor que le fallaron las piernas.

They weren’t moving fast, but they were faster than Helena.

Cuando se le despejó la mente, estaba en el suelo…, al igual que el necrómata.

They reached the survivors before she did.

Sus dedos, cubiertos de sangre, sostenían la obsidiana, cuyos bordes se clavaban en su piel.

“No!” Helena rasped out, her raised voice splitting her chest.

Aún quedaban muchos otros necrómatas.

One of the necrothralls moved towards her.

Se le echaron encima y sus cuerpos taparon la luz rojiza que se colaba por la puerta.

She tried to fend it off.

Helena sintió el viento en la cara.

All she had was the obsidian.

Cerró los ojos.

She slashed at the necrothrall with it.

Cuando quiso abrir los ojos de nuevo, los párpados le pesaban, como si las pestañas se le hubieran enredado.

The soft, deteriorating skin split easily on contact, and then the tip hit bone.

Intentó moverse, pero su cuerpo no respondió.

She’d used barely any force, but that pressure alone caused enough pain that her legs failed her.

Abrió los ojos de par de par.

When her head cleared, she was on the ground—and so was the necrothrall.

Había una luz tan deslumbrante que la cegaba y todo lo demás se veía borroso y distorsionado a su alrededor.

Blood dripped from her fingers where she was gripping the obsidian, the edges of the black glass buried in her skin.

Se removió en el sitio y entrecerró los ojos.

There were still so many necrothralls.

Kaine estaba a su lado, pálido y con los ojos desencajados; su rostro parecía más demacrado que nunca.

They moved towards her, bodies blotting out the reddish light filtering through the door.

—Tú…

Wind fluttered across her face.

La palabra sonó como un crujido extraño.

Her eyes slid shut.

Notaba la lengua seca y pastosa, como si no hubiese bebido agua en días.

WHEN SHE TRIED TO OPEN her eyes again, they were heavy, as if her lashes had tangled.

No sentía nada del cuello para abajo.

When she tried to move—her body wouldn’t.

Intentó bajar la vista, pero no podía moverse.

She tore her eyes open.

Estaba paralizada.

There was glaring light, and everything was blurred until she found a vague dark shape near her.

Intentó ver su propio cuerpo, pero lo único que distinguió fue una vía intravenosa en su brazo.

She recoiled, then squinted.

Al forzar la vista, vio los frascos suspendidos de suero y otros medicamentos, que volcaban su contenido en la sonda.

Kaine was standing beside her, pale and wide-eyed, his face impossibly haggard.

—¿Cómo? —preguntó, con la voz quebrada y atascada en su garganta—.

“You …”

¿Qué has hecho…?

The word emerged cracked and croaking.

—¿Qué he hecho? —repitió Kaine con calma—.

Her tongue was thick and dry, as if she hadn’t touched water in days.

Te he salvado la vida. —Estaba respirando entrecortadamente—.

She couldn’t feel anything below her neck.

Gracias a las innumerables exigencias de Crowther, el Sumo Nigromante ha tomado una miríada de medidas de precaución.

She tried to look down but couldn’t move.

Solo tres personas sabían lo de la bomba antes de que estallara.

She was paralysed.

Y yo no era una de ellas.

Her eyes crossed as she tried to look down her body.

Cuando me enteré y envié a mis necrómatas, pensé que estaba comportándome como un paranoico.

All she could make out was an intravenous drip in her arm.

Seguro que entienden que no puedo frenar todas las putas estrategias.

When she squinted, she could see saline and other things in upended glass vials all running down into the tube.

Lo hacía por mi bienestar mental, me dije a mí mismo.

“What?” she asked.

Para ver lo que había sucedido y saber lo mal que estaban las cosas.

The words crackled in her throat and slurred across her tongue. “What’d you do …?”

Tú no estarías allí, por supuesto.

“What did I do?” Kaine repeated slowly. “I saved your life.”

Me dije a mí mismo que no estarías allí, que estarías a salvo en el Cuartel General, porque ese era el trato que habíamos hecho, joder.

He was breathing unsteadily. “Crowther, with his endless demands, has the High Necromancer taking a myriad of precautionary measures.

¿No fue eso lo que prometiste?

Only three people knew about that bombing before it happened.

¿Que no te castigarían?

And I wasn’t one of them.

Lo sabía… Te dije que esto pasaría…

When I got word, I thought I was being paranoid sending my thralls in.

Se le rompió la voz.

Surely, they’d understand that I can’t stop every fucking thing.

—No fue… Crowther… —Al menos, hablar le humedecía la lengua, pero se moría por un trago de agua.

This was for my peace of mind, I told myself.

Aún notaba la mente torpe.

To see the fallout, so I’d know how bad things were.

No entendía cómo había llegado allí.

You wouldn’t be there, of course.

—¡No los defiendas! —Kaine estaba lívido de rabia—.

I told myself you wouldn’t be there, you’d be safe in Headquarters, because that is the damned deal.

¿Te haces una idea de lo cerca que has estado de morir?

Isn’t that what you promised?

He tenido que contratar a todo un equipo médico para mantenerte con vida.

That they wouldn’t punish you?

Si no pretendían matarte, ¿por qué te dejaron sola en ese puto hospital?

I knew—I told you this would happen—”

—Estábamos… evacuando —respondió Helena poco a poco; su lengua empezaba a obedecer.

His voice broke.

—¿Tú sola?

“Wasn’t … Crowth—” Speaking moistened her tongue at least, but she was dying for water.

—Yo estaba… al mando. —Sorprendentemente, sintió que recobraba la lucidez—.

Her mind was still foggy.

Los soldados… no se merecían morir solos.

She couldn’t understand how she was there.

Intentó incorporarse.

“Don’t defend them!” Kaine looked feral with rage. “Do you have any idea how close you came to dying?

Creía que sería capaz de pensar con más claridad si podía sentarse un momento para procesar lo que le había sucedido.

It took an entire medical team to keep you alive.

—Pues yo no vi a nadie allí mientras tú morías.

Why would they leave you alone in that fucking hospital if they weren’t trying to kill you?”

No sabía por qué trataba de razonar con él, pero quería tranquilizarlo para poder reorientarse ella misma.

“Were … evacuating,” she said slowly, pacing her words, her tongue gradually complying.

—Estamos en guerra, Kaine.

“Alone?”

La gente muere.

“I was—in charge.” She felt eerily lucid. “Soldiers—didn’t deserve to die alone.”

Teniendo en cuenta las muertes que tú has provocado, deberías saberlo mejor que nadie.

She tried to get up.

Sabes que no voy a priorizar mi vida por encima de la de los demás.

She felt as if she’d be able to think more clearly if she could just sit up for a minute and figure out what had happened to her.

La miró fijamente durante unos interminables segundos; su rostro delataba la furia que sentía.

“Well, I didn’t see anyone there while you were dying.”

—Pues deberías. —De repente, su voz adquirió un tono gélido y sus ojos brillaron con un plateado que era casi blanco—.

She wasn’t sure why she was trying to reason with him, but she wanted him to calm down so that she could reorient herself.

Te lo he advertido.

“It’s a war, Kaine.

Si te pasa algo malo, me encargaré personalmente de reducir la Llama Eterna a cenizas.

People die.

Y es una promesa, no una amenaza.

Given your personal death toll, you should know that better than anyone else.

Ten en cuenta que tu supervivencia es tan indispensable como la de Holdfast.

You know that I’m not going to prioritise my survival over everyone else’s.”

Si tú mueres, mataré a todos los miembros de la Resistencia.

He stared at her for a long terrible moment, the rage stark on his face. “Well, you should.” He was suddenly ice-cold, and his eyes gleamed so silver that they were almost white. “Because I have warned you, if something happens to you, I will personally raze the entire Order of the Eternal Flame.

Es evidente que ver peligrar sus vidas es lo único que hace que valores la tuya propia.

That isn’t a threat, it’s a promise.

Helena lo contempló completamente anonadada, aunque ese sentimiento no tardó en convertirse en pura rabia.

Consider your survival as much a necessity to the Resistance as Holdfast’s.

—¿Cómo te atreves?

If you die, I will kill every single one of them.

¡Cómo te… atreves! —Había subido tanto el tono que la voz se le quebró.

Given that the risk to their lives is the only way to make you value your own.”

Si hubiera podido moverse, se habría abalanzado sobre él para darle una paliza con sus propias manos.

Helena stared at him, dumb with shock that slowly twisted into rage.

Quería gritarle.

“How dare you?

Sin embargo, más allá de esa rabia, un horror profundo se instaló en ella por todo lo que aquello implicaba.

How—dare you!” Her voice rose so high, it cracked.

Kaine se había convertido en la amenaza que Crowther siempre temió.

If she could have moved, she would have thrown herself at him and tried to beat him to death with her bare hands.

En el pasado se había mostrado leal para vengar a su madre, pero Helena ocupaba ahora su lugar, y eso había desatado en él una obsesión y una rabia incontrolables.

She wanted to scream at him.

Helena cerró los ojos, incapaz de mirarlo a la cara, y en su mente apareció el uróboro como una imagen de autodestrucción infinita: un dragón que se devoraba a sí mismo eternamente.

But beyond her fury was an even greater sense of horror at what this meant.

Se le escapó un sollozo casi roto que le sacudió los pulmones violentamente.

He’d become the very threat that Crowther had feared.

Intentó respirar para calmarse y que la habitación dejara de darle vueltas.

Once he would have been loyal to them for the sake of avenging his mother, but Helena had usurped that, given him a new and uncontrollable source of obsessiveness and rage.

La superficie bajo su cuerpo se hundió.

She closed her eyes, unable to look at him, and the ouroboros flashed through her mind, that image of endless self-annihilation.

Unos dedos metieron un mechón de pelo suelto por detrás de su oreja y le acariciaron la mejilla.

A dragon forever consuming itself.

—Conozco tu expresión como la palma de mi mano —suspiró—.

She gave a rasping sob that rattled her lungs violently, and as she fought to breathe, the room went still.

Estás pensando que ahora tendrás que matarme, ¿verdad?

The surface beneath her shifted.

Que soy una carga demasiado pesada.

Fingers tucked a stray curl behind her ear before brushing across her cheek.

Helena no dijo nada y se negó a abrir los ojos.

“I know your face too well.” He sighed. “You’re thinking you’ll have to kill me now, aren’t you?

—¿De verdad lo harías? —Lo miró fijamente—.

That I’m too much of a liability.”

Ya sabes que… sabes que yo no te elegiría por encima de todos los demás.

She said nothing, refusing to open her eyes.

Sabes lo que pasará si la Resistencia pierde.

“Would you really do it?”

No puedo elegirte.

She looked at him. “You know—you know I will not choose you at the price of everyone.

Ni tampoco te salvaría si lo hiciera.

It wouldn’t even save you if I did.”

Entonces Kaine apartó la mirada.

He looked away then. “You’d never forgive yourself.”

—Y jamás te lo perdonarías.

Her jaw trembled. “No.

A ella le tembló la barbilla.

I wouldn’t—” Her throat grew thick.

—No, lo cierto es que no… —Se le formó un nudo en la garganta.

She struggled to swallow, unable to lift her head. “But it wouldn’t be the first unforgivable thing I’ve done.

Le costaba tragar y no podía levantar la cabeza—.

What’s one more line for the history books?”

Pero no sería lo primero que soy incapaz de perdonarme.

He was silent for a long time.

¿Qué más da otra línea en los libros de historia?

“What will you do when I’m gone?” he asked, as if that was all that mattered.

Kaine guardó silencio durante un buen rato.

“I’m sure you can imagine.”

—¿Qué harás cuando yo ya no esté? —le preguntó, como si eso fuera lo único que importase.

The ceiling blurred at the thought of a world where Kaine was gone and she was alone, with no one to blame but herself.

—Seguro que te haces una idea.

She hated this war.

El techo se distorsionó al imaginar un mundo en el que Kaine ya no estuviera y ella estuviera sola, sin nadie más que ella misma a quien culpar.

She had thought she could do anything.

Detestaba la guerra.

That she was strong enough for it.

Al principio, pensaba que podría con todo, que era lo suficientemente fuerte, que no habría límite que no estuviera dispuesta a cruzar o soportar.

That there would be no limit to what she was willing to do or endure.

Por lo visto, Kaine se había convertido en ese límite.

Apparently, Kaine had become her limit.

No podía imaginar su vida sin él.

She couldn’t imagine herself without him.

No creía que pudiese seguir existiendo.

She didn’t think she’d even exist anymore.

Se le escapó un sollozo estrangulado y sus pulmones se encogieron en busca de oxígeno.

She gave a choking gasp, struggling for air, lungs rattling.

De repente, Kaine estaba sobre ella, sujetándole la cara entre las manos, ladeando su cabeza para que pudiera respirar mejor.

Suddenly Kaine was over her, holding her face in his hands, tilting her head so she could breathe.

Ese era el único abrazo que podía ofrecerle.

That was all the embrace possible.

—Solo quiero que vivas, Helena. —Le temblaba la voz—.

“Just live, Helena.” His voice was shaking. “That’s all I’m asking you to do for me.”

Es lo único que te pido.

Helena gave a low sob, lungs whistling as she fought to breathe. “I can’t promise that.

Helena soltó un sollozo más grave y oyó cómo le silbaban los pulmones al intentar tomar aire.

You know I can’t promise that.

—No puedo prometerte eso.

But I can’t risk what you’ll do if I die.”

Sabes que no puedo.

He kissed her.

Pero tampoco puedo arriesgarme a que cumplas lo que quieres hacer si muero.

She could taste the plea on his lips.

Kaine la besó y ella sintió la súplica en sus labios.

“I’m sorry,” she kept saying again and again, “I’m sorry I did this to you.”

—Lo siento —repitió Helena una, y otra, y otra vez—.

A harsh buzz broke the air.

Siento haberte hecho esto.

Kaine went rigid and jerked back with a curse.

Sonó una fuerte vibración.

Another buzz.

Kaine se puso en tensión y se alejó mascullando una maldición.

Two long and two short.

Se produjo otra vibración.

Each time the noise came, the lights in the room dimmed, flickering ominously.

Dos largas y dos cortas.

He looked around, his teeth gritted. “Fuck.

Cada vez que se oía, la iluminación parpadeaba como un mal presagio.

I’m being called back to the city.” He stepped away but kept staring down at her.

Kaine miró a su alrededor con los dientes apretados.

She could see the calculation in his eyes as he seemed to hesitate over something.

—Mierda.

Finally an expression of despair flashed across his face.

Quieren que vuelva a la ciudad. —Dio un paso hacia atrás sin apartar la vista de Helena.

“Davies,” he said.

Había cálculo en sus ojos, como si estuviera sopesando distintas opciones, aunque finalmente lo que se abrió paso por su rostro fue una expresión desesperada—.

His voice barely carried, and his eyes went out of focus for a moment. “Come here.”

Davies, ven aquí —ordenó en voz baja, y sus ojos se desenfocaron durante un instante.

The door behind him opened, and a woman entered.

Se abrió la puerta que había detrás de él y entró una mujer.

Helena didn’t know enough about servants’ uniforms to place what she was, but she recognised the name.

Helena no sabía lo suficiente sobre uniformes del servicio para saber su rango, pero sí reconoció su nombre.

Enid Ferron’s lady’s maid stood beside Kaine, looking down at Helena with rheumy blue eyes.

La doncella de Enid Ferron se colocó junto a Kaine y observó a Helena con unos ojos azules y vidriosos.

A faint whiff of something dry but organic drifted into the room with her.

La habitación se inundó de un olor leve, seco pero orgánico.

She was dead but so expertly reanimated, she looked almost lifelike.

Estaba muerta, pero la habían reanimado con tanta destreza que parecía viva.

Helena looked around the room and towards the window, realising that she couldn’t see any buildings, just sky and trees.

Helena miró a su alrededor y luego hacia la ventana.

“Where are we?” she asked abruptly.

Entonces reparó en que no veía ningún edificio, solo cielo y árboles.

She didn’t even know how long she’d been unconscious.

—¿Dónde estamos? —preguntó de repente.

“Spirefell.

Ni siquiera sabía cuánto tiempo llevaba inconsciente.

My family’s country estate,” Kaine said, pulling on his uniform, the black coat and cloak. “I’ll explain more later.

—En Puntaférreo.

I have to go.

La finca familiar de los Ferron —contestó Kaine mientras se ponía el uniforme de abrigo y la capa negra—.

Don’t be afraid of Davies.

Ya te lo explicaré más tarde.

She won’t hurt you.”

Tengo que irme.

Helena kept staring at the necrothrall.

No temas a Davies.

One of the servants who’d died when Kaine became Undying, whose life was responsible for his immortality and immutability.

No te hará daño.

He’d reanimated her?

Helena observó a la necrómata.

“I’m sorry,” he was saying, “I thought I had more time to explain.

Era una de las criadas que habían muerto para que Kaine se convirtiera en inmarcesible, por lo que había dado su vida para que él alcanzara la inmortalidad.

You’ll be safe here.

¿La habría reanimado él?

No one will find you.

—Lo siento —siguió diciendo—.

I’ll be back as soon as I can.

Pensé que tendría más tiempo para explicaciones.

“Davies, take care of her.” He leaned over Helena one last time, stroking her hair. “You’re safe.

Aquí estarás a salvo.

I promise.”

Nadie podrá encontrarte.

Then he was gone.

Volveré tan pronto como me sea posible.

She could hear something in the walls and floor moving but couldn’t see what it was as she was left paralysed, in the care of a necrothrall.

Davies, cuídala. —Se inclinó sobre Helena una última vez y le acarició el cabello—.

She looked at it—her—again.

Estás a salvo.

Davies stood watching Helena, her gaze vague but constant.

Te lo prometo.

“Can I have water?” Helena finally asked.

Y, sin más, se marchó.

Davies poured a cup of water from a pitcher on a table nearby and then brought it over to Helena and helped her sip enough to wet her mouth.

Helena oyó un chasquido en las paredes y el suelo, como si algo se moviera, aunque no pudo ver nada.

It was bitter; Helena recognised the taste of laudanum.

Estaba inmovilizada en manos de una necrómata.

She had no idea it was possible to reanimate necrothralls to this degree.

La volvió a mirar.

The woman seemed alive.

Davies estaba ahí de pie, observándola con una mirada perdida pero imperturbable.

“You were Enid Ferron’s lady’s maid, weren’t you?” Helena asked, fighting the wave of exhaustion the drug brought upon her.

—¿Me das un poco de agua? —preguntó Helena al cabo de un rato.

Davies nodded slowly as if she understood the question.

Davies sirvió un vaso de agua de una jarra que había sobre la mesa y se lo acercó a Helena.

Helena struggled to focus.

Luego la ayudó a beber, aunque solo fuera para mojarse los labios.

“You’ve been here, all this time?”

Estaba amarga, y ella reconoció al instante el sabor del láudano.

Another nod.

No tenía ni idea de que se podía reanimar a necrómatas hasta este punto.

Davies mouthed a word silently.

Esa mujer parecía viva de verdad.

Kaine.

—Eras la doncella de Enid Ferron, ¿verdad? —preguntó Helena, que luchaba contra el cansancio que el medicamento le estaba provocando.

If that were true, it meant she’d been reanimated for nearly seven years without showing any signs of decay.

Davies asintió lentamente, como si comprendiera la pregunta.

Helena hadn’t known that was even possible.

Helena notó que le costaba enfocar la vista.

“Why?

—¿Has estado aquí todo este tiempo?

Why would he do that to you?”

Otro asentimiento.

If the necrothrall answered, Helena wasn’t conscious enough to see it.

Davies vocalizó una palabra en silencio. «Kaine».

She slipped in and out of lucidity, in more pain each time she came awake.

Si era cierto, significaba que la había reanimado hacía casi siete años, pero no mostraba ningún signo de putrefacción.

Davies was sitting in a chair beside her, knitting what appeared to be socks.

Helena no comprendía cómo podía ser aquello posible.

The numbness was wearing off.

—¿Por qué?

Pain was shifting from a distant impression to a weight steadily bearing down harder and harder.

¿Por qué te haría algo así?

Her throat was bruised and raw inside; she must have been on a breathing apparatus at some point.

Si la necrómata respondió, Helena ya no estaba consciente para escucharlo.

When the pain grew oppressive enough to wake her again, she found that Kaine had returned.

Perdía y recuperaba la lucidez de forma intermitente y, cada vez que despertaba, el dolor era más profundo.

He was standing beside her, replacing several of the vials connected to the intravenous drip.

Davies estaba sentada en una silla a su lado, tejiendo lo que parecían unos calcetines.

“What happened to the medical team?” Helena asked, her tongue thick and dry again. “The people you had save me.

El entumecimiento empezó a desvanecerse.

What did you do to them?”

El dolor pasó de ser una impresión distante a una carga que le pesaba cada vez más.

He stared down at her.

Sentía la garganta hinchada y en carne viva por dentro, como si hubiera tenido un tubo respiratorio en algún momento.

The room was dark; his black uniform made him blend into the shadows, but his pale hair and eyes almost glowed.

Cuando el dolor se convirtió en tan insoportable que la despertó por completo, descubrió que Kaine había regresado.

“Don’t ask questions you don’t want answers to.”

Estaba de pie a su lado y cambiaba algunos de los frascos que se vertían en la vía intravenosa.

“Did you kill them?” Her voice sharpened.

—¿Qué le ha pasado al equipo médico? —preguntó Helena, que volvía a tener la lengua pastosa y seca—.

He flicked a switch, filling the room with dim orange light.

Las personas que me salvaron la vida.

“No, I didn’t kill them.

¿Qué les has hecho?

An entire medical team turning up dead would have raised questions.

Kaine la miró.

They think they saved a woman who died under interrogation yesterday.

La habitación estaba a oscuras y el uniforme negro hacía que se camuflara entre las sombras.

And they do not care at all that they spent hours saving you for the ostensible purpose of my torturing you to death afterwards.

Aun así, su cabello rubio y sus ojos brillaban en la oscuridad.

They were proud to be of service.

—No hagas preguntas para las que no quieres respuesta.

You are, after all, a terrorist, they said.”

—¿Los has matado? —Se le agudizó la voz.

She knew he was trying to distract her. “So you would have killed them but didn’t because it would have raised inconvenient questions.”

El chico encendió un interruptor y toda la habitación se iluminó con un naranja tenue.

His eyes flashed. “Yes, I did all of this for convenience, which you know I have so abundantly in my life with my two mutually exclusive masters.”

—No, no los he matado.

Guilt caught in Helena’s throat like a stone. “I don’t want you to kill people because of me.”

Que todo un equipo médico aparezca muerto habría despertado sospechas.

He gave a barking laugh. “What exactly is it that you think I do with all my time?

Creen que salvaron a una mujer que murió ayer en un interrogatorio.

I kill people.

Y les da igual haberse pasado horas salvándote para que al final alguien acabara torturándote hasta la muerte.

I order other people to kill people.

Están orgullosos de haber servido a la causa.

I train people to kill people.

Después de todo, eres una terrorista.

I sabotage and undermine people so that they will be killed, and I do it all because of you.

Ellos mismos me lo dijeron.

Every word.

Helena sabía que estaba intentando distraerla.

Every life.

—Entonces quieres decir que los habrías matado pero no lo hiciste porque sus muertes hubieran despertado preguntas incómodas.

Because of you.”

La rabia iluminó los ojos de Kaine.

She gave a ragged gasp as the room tilted, swimming as the blood drained from her head.

—Sí, todo esto lo hago por comodidad.

The viciousness in his expression vanished. “Wait.

Ya sabes que tengo dos amos que me exigen exclusividad.

Helena, I didn’t—”

La culpa hizo que a Helena se le formara un nudo en la garganta.

“No,” she said harshly. “Don’t even try to take it back.”

—No quiero que mates a nadie por mí.

“I—” His voice was soft.

A Kaine se le escapó una carcajada.

Pleading.

—¿Qué es lo que crees que hago todos los días?

“No,” she said again. “It’s true.

Mato a gente.

What you said is entirely true.

Ordeno a otros que maten a gente.

Everything you do is on my head, too.

Entreno a personas para que maten a gente.

Every life …”

Saboteo y socavo a personas que acaban muertas, y todo lo hago por ti.

“Don’t.” He sat on the edge of the bed, picked up her right hand. “Don’t carry it.

Cada palabra, cada vida.

It’s not yours.

Todo ha sido por ti.

Stop trying to carry a whole damned war on your shoulders.”

La habitación empezó a darle vueltas, y se le escapó un grito ahogado.

“This is all my fault, though,” she said. “I did this to you.

Sintió que flotaba, como si la sangre abandonara su cabeza.

I made you like this.

La crueldad del semblante de Kaine se desvaneció de golpe.

Someone should regret that, and you can’t.

—Espera, Helena, no pretendía…

But if I do—maybe that will be enough to make you stop someday.”

—No —lo interrumpió con dureza—.

He looked away and said nothing.

No te atrevas a retirarlo.

She watched his fingers move across hers, wishing she could feel it.

—Yo… —Su voz se tornó suave, suplicante.

“What’s happening in the city?” she asked.

—No —repitió la chica—.

He was silent for a few seconds. “Althorne’s dead.

Es cierto.

There were several units trapped in one of the buildings; they got them out, but he died during the retreat.

Lo que dices es la pura verdad.

From our estimates, the Resistance has lost at least half their active forces.

Todo lo que haces también es culpa mía.

We retook the ports two days ago.”

Cada vida…

There was nowhere for the despair of that information to go but to lance into her mind.

—Para. —Se sentó al borde de la cama y le sostuvo la mano derecha—.

No twisting horror in her gut; no sense of emptiness.

No sigas por ahí.

She could not feel her body.

No es culpa tuya.

She could only think.

Deja de llevar sobre tus hombros la carga de toda esta condenada guerra.

“There has been considerable backlash to the bombing, though.

—Pero esto sí que es culpa mía —repuso—.

They didn’t expect the dust to contaminate both islands.

Yo te hice esto.

There’s been panic and outrage over the widespread loss of resonance, the hospitals are overwhelmed with patients needing chelators, and the death toll for the Resistance, while significant, has provided us almost no new necrothralls because Durant forgot that the nullification compound would interfere with reanimation.

Yo te convertí en lo que eres.

They have to pump fresh blood into the corpses to reanimate them.

Alguien debería arrepentirse de ello, y tú no puedes.

So I doubt it will happen again.

Pero, si lo hago yo…, tal vez eso baste para que algún día dejes de hacerlo.

At least not on that scale.”

Kaine apartó la mirada y no respondió.

A paltry source of comfort, but it was something.

Helena observó cómo le acariciaba los dedos y deseó poder sentirlo.

“I don’t know what to do,” she finally said. “I can’t ignore a threat to the Eternal Flame.”

—¿Qué está pasando en la ciudad? —preguntó.

He sighed, head dipping. “I was just angry.”

El chico estuvo callado durante unos segundos.

“You’re always angry, but you can’t make threats like that or reduce a war like this into a simplistic blame game.

—Althorne ha muerto.

And you can’t hold the Resistance hostage to control me.”

Había varias unidades atrapadas bajo uno de los edificios; consiguieron sacarlos a todos, pero el general murió en la retirada.

His shoulders slumped. “If you die, Helena, I’m done.

Según nuestras estimaciones, la Resistencia ha perdido al menos a la mitad de su ejército activo.

I won’t continue this.

Retomamos los puertos hace dos días.

I’m tired.”

No había lugar en su cuerpo que pudiera ya soportar la desesperación que le causó esa información, excepto sentirla como una lanza en la cabeza.

He looked at her, and she could see the whole war in his eyes, the toll that came from struggling with no end in sight, driven by a terror of what might happen if he ever stopped.

No notó un horror que le retorciera las entrañas, no hubo sensación de vacío.

“I mean it.

No sentía su propio cuerpo, así que solo le quedaba pensar.

I won’t kill them—but I will be done.

—Aun así, ha habido muchas consecuencias después del bombardeo.

You are my terms of service.

No imaginaron que el polvo acabaría contaminando las dos islas.

The contract is void if you die.”

La gente ha sucumbido al pánico y a la rabia por haber perdido la resonancia, y los hospitales están llenos de pacientes que necesitan agentes quelantes.

She managed to turn her head a little. “There is a life for you on the other side of this war.

Aunque la Resistencia ha sufrido unas bajas considerables, apenas hemos recuperado cuerpos para convertirlos en necrómatas, porque Durant olvidó mencionar que el compuesto anulador interferiría con la reanimación.

You have the Stone.

Tienen que bombear sangre fresca en los cadáveres para poder reanimarlos, así que dudo que vuelva a pasar.

If Morrough dies, you might be fine, and you’d be free.

Al menos, no a esa escala.

You could do—all sorts of things.

Un consuelo nimio, pero era algo al fin y al cabo.

Don’t reduce your world to me.”

—No sé qué hacer —expresó Helena al cabo de un rato—.

His lip curled, a flash of teeth. “Oh, and do you have a list of post-war plans that you’ve forgotten to mention?”

No puedo ignorar una amenaza a la Llama Eterna.

She averted her eyes. “Do as I say, not as I do.”

Kaine suspiró y bajó la cabeza.

He laced their fingers together as they lapsed into a silence as empty as the future.

—Solo estaba enfadado.

“You could—become a healer,” she finally said, straining to feel the sensation of his hand against hers.

—Siempre estás enfadado, pero no puedes soltar ese tipo de amenazas o reducir una guerra a un simple juego de reparto de culpas.

A smile ghosted at the corner of his mouth. “I hadn’t considered that.”

Y no puedes tener a la Resistencia de rehén para controlarme.

“You should.

Kaine bajó los hombros.

You have a talent for it—although your bedside manner is terrible.”

—Helena, si mueres, se acabó.

“It would be something to balance out that death toll of mine,” he said, not looking at her.

No seguiré con esto.

“I shouldn’t have said that.

Estoy cansado.

It’s not your fault.”

Cuando la miró, vio todo el peso de la guerra en sus ojos, la carga que suponía luchar sin ver el final, impulsado únicamente por el miedo de lo que podría pasar si dejaba de cumplir órdenes.

He shook his head, staring at the wall. “Maybe that was true once, but I believe I own it all now.”

—Lo digo en serio.

She swallowed, willing her fingers to move so she could squeeze his hand. “You are so much more than what the war has done to you.”

No los mataré…, pero no volveré a trabajar para ellos.

Her voice shook with conviction, but he still wouldn’t look at her.

Tú eres mi única condición.

“You are,” she said desperately. “Just—just like I am.

Si mueres, el contrato será papel mojado.

There’s more to both of us—it’s just waiting to get out.

Helena consiguió ladear un poco la cabeza.

Someday, we’ll leave all this behind.

—Hay vida para ti más allá de esta guerra.

Go far away, and you’ll see.

Tienes la gema.

The two of us—I think we could.”

Si Morrough muere, tal vez sigas con vida y serás libre.

He made no answer, but she dimly felt his fingers grip hers tighter.

Podrías hacer… cualquier cosa.

“I promise—you’ll see …” Her eyelids began to droop.

No reduzcas tu mundo a mí.

“Go to sleep.

Kaine hizo un gesto que dejó los dientes a la vista.

You have a long recovery ahead of you.”

—Ah, ¿tú tienes una lista de cosas que hacer después de la guerra y no la has mencionado?

She resisted, trying to stay awake. “How long have I been here?”

La chica esquivó su mirada.

“Don’t worry about that.”

—Haz lo que te digo, no lo que hago.

“How long?”

Kaine entrelazó los dedos con los suyos y se sumieron en un silencio tan vacío como su futuro.

“… It’s been four days since the bombing.”

—Podrías… ser sanador —dijo Helena al cabo de unos instantes.

Four days?

Se estiró para sentir el tacto de su mano contra la suya.

Blood was suddenly pounding in her ears, and her lungs rattled when she tried to breathe.

El atisbo de una sonrisa asomó a las comisuras de la boca de Kaine.

“Kaine—you have to get word to Crowther that I’m alive.”

—No me lo había planteado.

“Don’t worry about them.” His voice was hard.

—Pues tienes… Tienes un talento natural… Aunque el trato con el paciente deja mucho que desear.

“No, listen.

—Así podría compensar las muertes que llevo a cuestas —replicó sin mirarla a los ojos.

You have to tell him.”

—No debería haber dicho nada.

He stroked her cheek. “Just rest.”

No es culpa tuya.

She fought to move, needing him to understand. “No.

Kaine sacudió la cabeza y se quedó mirando la pared.

Promise me.

—Puede que eso fuera cierto en el pasado, pero creo que ahora debo asumir la responsabilidad.

Promise you’ll send word.

Helena tragó saliva.

Make sure he knows that I’ll come back.”

Deseó poder mover los dedos para apretarle la mano.

If Crowther thought she was dead, he might decide that Kaine was too much of a risk to keep alive.

—Eres mucho más de lo que esta guerra ha hecho contigo. —Lo dijo tan convencida que le tembló la voz, pero Kaine siguió sin mirarla—.

“Promise me—promise you’ll get word—”

Lo digo en serio —repitió con desesperación—.

“All right.

Igual… igual que yo.

I’ll send word, I promise.

Somos mucho más… y esa parte aún está ahí, deseando salir.

Rest.”

Algún día, dejaremos todo esto atrás.

The throbbing pulse of blood in her head slowed, and she relaxed.

Nos iremos lejos, ya lo verás.

He tucked a curl behind her ear.

Los dos solos… Creo que podremos hacerlo.

“You’ll be here at least three weeks unless the nullium clears from your blood before then.”

Kaine no respondió, pero Helena sintió que le apretaba levemente los dedos.

“There’s a chelator the Eternal Flame developed—”

—Te lo prometo… Ya lo verás… —Empezaron a cerrársele los ojos.

He tapped the tip of her nose. “The Undying have chymists and are also familiar with metal-sequestering agents.”

—Duerme.

She rolled her eyes.

Te queda una larga recuperación por delante.

“You’ll get your resonance back … but it will be a long time for you.

Helena se resistió y trató de permanecer despierta.

You had several shrapnel injuries, and you inhaled a significant amount as well.

—¿Cuánto tiempo llevo aquí?

It’s hard to say how long it’ll take.

—No te preocupes por eso.

You’ll have to recover the old-fashioned way.

—¿Cuánto?

Go to sleep.

—Han pasado cuatro días desde el bombardeo.

Loath as I am to admit it, the war will still be here when you wake.”

¿Cuatro días?

De repente, sintió que el corazón le retumbaba en los oídos y que le dolían los pulmones al intentar respirar.

—Kaine… Tienes que avisar a Crowther de que sigo viva.

—No te preocupes por ellos —dijo con voz grave.

—No, escúchame.

Debes decírselo.

Kaine le acarició la mejilla.

—Descansa.

Helena intentó moverse; tenía que hacerle entrar en razón.

—No, prométemelo.

Prométeme que lo avisarás.

Que te asegurarás de que sepa que voy a volver.

Si Crowther pensaba que estaba muerta, tal vez decidiera que Kaine era un riesgo demasiado alto como para mantenerlo con vida.

—Prométemelo… Prométeme que lo avisarás…

—Está bien.

Lo avisaré, lo prometo.

Ahora descansa.

Notó cómo se calmaba el bombeo de sangre en su cabeza y se relajó.

Kaine le colocó un mechón de pelo detrás de la oreja.

—Vas a estar aquí al menos tres semanas, hasta que no haya restos de anulitio en tu sangre.

—La Llama Eterna ha desarrollado un quelante…

Le dio un toquecito en la nariz.

—Los inmarcesibles tienen quimiatras y conocen perfectamente los agentes quelantes del metal.

Helena puso los ojos en blanco.

—Recuperarás tu resonancia, pero tardarás bastante en recuperarte.

Has sufrido varias heridas de metralla y has inhalado una cantidad importante de anulitio.

No sé decirte cuánto tardarás en recomponerte.

Tendrás que recuperarte con calma, mediante el descanso.

Duerme.

Por mucho que deteste admitirlo, la guerra seguirá aquí cuando despiertes.

CHAPTER 60

Junius 1787

CAPÍTULO 60

BEING INJURED WAS HORRIBLE.

Junius 1787

HELENA WAS ACCUSTOMED to the efficiency of healing to circumvent the slowest and more unbearable aspects of recovery; having to suddenly endure the natural speed of healing was utter misery.

Estar convaleciente era horrible.

She spent much of the first week in a drugged stupor, feverish with an infection.

Helena estaba acostumbrada a que la eficiencia de la sanación resolviera los aspectos más lentos e insoportables de la recuperación, así que verse obligada a aguantar el ritmo natural de su cuerpo le resultó muy molesto.

When she finally grew lucid again, she found Kaine still beside her.

La mayor parte de la primera semana la pasó aturdida por la medicación, con fiebre por la infección.

He had a large stack of books and folios that he was flipping through.

Cuando recobró la lucidez, encontró a Kaine a su lado.

“What are you doing?” she asked after watching for a little while.

Tenía encima una pila de libros y documentos y los estaba hojeando.

His eyes flicked up. “Studying human anatomy for my future career as a healer,” he said in a dry voice.

—¿Qué estás haciendo? —le preguntó tras observarlo un rato.

She knew that the real answer was that he would have to be her healer once the nullium was cleared from her system, but she played along. “We can open a practice together, like my parents did.

Él levantó la mirada.

Up on a cliff.

—Estudiar anatomía humana para mi futura carrera como sanador —respondió con sequedad.

We’ll be able to look out the windows and see the tides.”

Helena sabía que la respuesta sincera era que él tendría que convertirse en su sanador cuando el anulitio desapareciese de su sistema.

He raised an eyebrow. “Do I get any say about this future life of ours, or are you making all the decisions?”

Aun así, le siguió el juego.

“Do you have ideas?”

—Podemos abrir una consulta los dos juntos, como hicieron mis padres.

There was a pause. “Can’t say I do.”

En lo alto de un acantilado.

She drew a slow breath.

Así podremos disfrutar de las vistas y ver la marea.

She could move her fingers now.

Kaine arqueó una ceja.

As her fingers flexed, she realised her right hand was bandaged, the fingers splinted, and she remembered the last moments in the field hospital.

—¿Yo tengo algo que decir sobre esa futura vida que tendremos o vas a tomar tú todas las decisiones?

“I almost forgot,” she said. “I think I discovered something in the hospital.”

—¿Tienes alguna idea que aportar?

He looked up.

Se hizo el silencio.

“The obsidian I told you about.

—La verdad es que no.

I had some in my pocket when the necrothralls came.

Helena dejó escapar el aire poco a poco.

I think—I think I severed a reanimation with it.”

Ya podía mover los dedos.

“Are you sure?”

Al flexionarlos, se dio cuenta de que tenía la mano derecha vendada y los dedos escayolados, y recordó los últimos momentos en el hospital de campaña.

She squinted, trying to remember more details, but all she recalled was the red-orange light, and the pain. “Not entirely, but I think we should test it again.”

—Casi se me olvida —dijo—.

“Well, don’t worry about that right now.” He snapped his book shut and came over to change the bandages.

Creo que descubrí algo en el hospital.

She’d regained enough mobility that as he peeled off the gauze, she lifted her head, determined to see.

Kaine levantó la mirada.

Running like a ragged seam down the centre of her chest was a huge incision, sewn closed with black thread and bone wire.

—¿Te acuerdas de la obsidiana de la que te hablé?

The skin was swollen, yellow, and white and pink.

Tenía un trozo en el bolsillo cuando llegaron los necrómatas.

Helena had seen more wounds than she could count, watched innumerable people grieve over the loss of who they’d been before and what their bodies had become.

Creo que… creo que corté una reanimación con ella.

She knew all the things to say, the encouragement and reassurances, that it would be all right, that it would get better.

—¿Estás segura?

Staring at the wound, she forgot all of it.

Entrecerró los ojos mientras trataba de recordar algo más, pero lo único que se le vino a la cabeza fue la luz roja anaranjada y el dolor.

“My gods,” she said, head dropping, her throat convulsing, too horrified to keep looking.

—No del todo, pero pienso que deberíamos probarla otra vez.

“It’ll heal.

—Bueno, tú no te preocupes por eso ahora. —Cerró el libro de golpe y se acercó a cambiar las vendas.

Give it time,” he said quietly as he checked for signs of infection.

Cuando retiró la tela, Helena notó que recuperaba un poco de movilidad.

She knew from treating Lila that she would scar.

Levantó la cabeza con ganas de ver algo más.

Even if she tried to heal herself afterwards, organised all the matrices, there was a limited time frame for preventing scars, and something about nullium seemed to have a mild keloid effect on the tissue.

En el centro del pecho, como una costura serrada, se extendía una profunda incisión cosida con hilo negro y alambre de cerclaje.

She drew several sharp breaths.

La piel estaba hinchada, teñida en tonos amarillentos, blancos y rosados.

She was lucky to be alive.

Helena había visto más heridas de las que podía recordar, había sido testigo de cómo los pacientes lloraban por lo que habían sido y en lo que se habían convertido sus cuerpos.

A few scars were nothing compared with the injuries others in the Resistance would carry for life.

Sabía lo que debía decir, las frases de aliento y confianza, que todo se arreglaría, que todo mejoraría con el tiempo.

She still had all her limbs, both eyes and ears.

Pero, al mirar su propia herida, todo eso se le olvidó.

Even all her teeth.

—Por Dios… —exclamó.

She was very lucky by any metric.

Dejó caer la cabeza, sintiendo un nudo en la garganta; le había dado tanto miedo que no quería seguir mirándola.

What did a scar matter?

—Se curará.

It would be fine.

Dale tiempo —dijo Kaine en voz baja mientras buscaba señales de infección.

She could feel Kaine watching her and forced herself to speak. “I think your scars are prettier than mine,” she finally said.

Después de haber tratado a Lila, sabía que le quedaría cicatriz.

“I have a better healer.”

Aunque intentara sanarse a sí misma cuando recuperara la resonancia y reorganizara las matrices, el tiempo para evitar marcas era limitado, y el anulitio parecía tener un efecto queloide sobre los tejidos.

IT TOOK THREE WEEKS JUST for the nullium in Helena’s blood to reduce enough that Kaine could use resonance to monitor her healing, although actual transmutation was still far off.

Respiró hondo un par de veces.

Her own resonance was barely a hum in her veins.

Tenía suerte de seguir con vida.

Whenever Kaine was absent, Davies stayed with her.

Unas cuantas cicatrices no eran nada comparadas con las heridas que algunos miembros de la Resistencia tendrían que soportar de por vida.

Helena’s head was finally clear enough to notice more of her surroundings.

Aunque conservaba todas las extremidades, los dos ojos, las orejas e incluso todos los dientes.

The room was sterile.

Lo mirase por donde lo mirase, había tenido suerte.

Almost bare.

¿Qué importaba una cicatriz?

There was a bed, a towering wardrobe, a desk, and a chair.

Todo se arreglaría.

Falcon Matias had more indulgent quarters, and he was supposed to be an ascetic.

Se dio cuenta de que Kaine la estaba observando y se obligó a decir:

When she teased Kaine about it, he grimaced. “This is my room.”

—Creo que tus cicatrices son más bonitas que las mías.

Helena fell silent, looking around again, abashed. “Oh.

—Yo tuve una sanadora mejor.

I thought that a country house would have bigger rooms.”

El anulitio en la sangre de Helena tardó tres semanas en reducirse lo suficiente para que Kaine pudiera usar la resonancia y evaluar su recuperación, aunque aún no estaba preparada para sanar de esa manera.

He nodded. “There are larger ones.

La resonancia de Helena apenas era un murmullo en sus venas.

I moved in here because it was closer to my mother’s room, then never left.”

Cuando Kaine no estaba, era Davies quien le hacía compañía.

“I’m sorry I brought you back,” she said.

Helena notó que tenía la mente cada vez más despejada y que ya podía hacer inventario de lo que la rodeaba.

He shook his head. “You didn’t.

La decoración de la habitación era mínima, casi inexistente.

I come back to check on the servants.”

Había una cama, un armario hasta el techo, un escritorio y una silla.

She hesitated but then asked, “Are they all dead?”

El falcón Matias había tenido unos aposentos más confortables, y eso que era un monje asceta.

He nodded.

Cuando se lo comentó en tono de broma a Kaine, este torció el gesto.

“Why did you—?”

—Es mi habitación.

He looked away, his throat dipping as he rubbed his hands together. “It was just after.

Helena se quedó callada y miró a su alrededor con cierta vergüenza.

I don’t remember everything.

—Vaya.

I could feel them screaming inside me.

Pensaba que en una casa de campo habría habitaciones más grandes.

I found their bodies piled up in a corner like discarded rags.

El chico asintió.

They were still warm.

—Las hay más grandes.

I’d never—I didn’t even realise what I was doing.

Me mudé aquí porque estaba más cerca de la habitación de mi madre, y después nunca me fui.

I was trying to put them back.”

—Siento haberte traído de vuelta —dijo Helena.

“So they’re—them?”

Kaine negó con la cabeza.

He shook his head. “I don’t know what they are.

—No ha sido por ti.

I like to think I was able to put a part of them back, that it’s why it got easier after that, but it’s more likely that they act like themselves because I want them to.

Volví para echarles un ojo a los criados.

I just—can’t seem to let go.”

Helena dudó, pero tenía que saberlo.

When Helena was finally able to have a pillow, Davies would prop up books for her to read during the hours when Kaine was absent.

—¿Están todos muertos? —Kaine asintió—.

She was curious about the kind of library that existed at Spirefell, but Davies unfortunately did not seem to be literate, at least not anymore.

¿Por qué los…?

The books Helena received were largely at random.

El chico apartó la vista y tragó saliva mientras se frotaba las manos.

One day, she received an encyclopaedia of butterfly species, the next a florilegium of Cetus’s earliest writings.

—Fue justo después.

Because “Cetus” had written thousands of alchemical texts and letters, dated across centuries, excerpts were often assembled into various collections by scholars based on which parts of his work and history they happened to consider legitimate.

No recuerdo nada.

Depending on the florilegium’s edition, Cetus was born in ten different countries.

Los oía gritar en mi interior.

Sometimes he was a king, other times a priest; some letters even claimed he’d worked with Orion himself.

Encontré sus cuerpos amontonados en un rincón, como si fueran alfombras viejas.

In the florilegum Helena received, Cetus was very taken by an ancient Khemish cult, which claimed that human resonance was the alchemisation of mankind.

Todavía estaban calientes.

That alchemists were an ascendant form.

No pretendía… No me di cuenta de lo que estaba haciendo.

“Sounds like something alchemists would believe about themselves,” Kaine said in the late evening while she was telling him about it.

Solo quería devolverles la vida.

He was much more interested in Helena’s lungs than in ancient cults.

—Entonces son… ¿ellos?

Helena tried not to wince as the bandages came off. “Do the Undying have a religion?”

Kaine sacudió la cabeza.

“The High Necromancer is our deity,” Kaine said, tracing his resonance carefully along her ribs where several had cracked. “Our lives are in servitude to his infinite power.”

—No sé qué son.

“If he’s that powerful, why doesn’t he come out and win the war?”

Me gusta pensar que fui capaz de devolverles una parte de su esencia, que por eso me resultó más fácil seguir haciéndolo después, pero lo más probable es que se muestren tal como eran porque yo quiero que lo hagan.

He glanced up for a moment. “He’s a god.

Simplemente… no soy capaz de dejarlos marchar.

You’ll notice that making humans die for them is the gods’ primary mode of operation.

Cuando por fin Helena pudo usar una almohada, Davies le empezó a traer libros para leer durante las horas en que Kaine no estaba presente.

You’d think Sol could personally smite a few necromancers if he hates them so passionately, but somehow, it’s always the Holdfasts coordinating those efforts.

Sentía curiosidad por saber qué tipo de biblioteca había en Puntaférreo, pero, por desgracia, Davies resultó ser analfabeta, o al menos lo era como necrómata.

Makes one wonder if he really cares.”

Helena recibía libros de temas muy diversos.

Ever since she’d told him about Orion and why the Holdfasts had become Principates, he seemed to think that if he just criticised the Eternal Flame enough, she’d give up on the Resistance.

Un día, le entregó una enciclopedia de especies de mariposas, seguido de una antología de los primeros escritos de Cetus.

Her sigh made her lungs rattle, and Kaine seemed to completely forget the conversation for several minutes.

Como «Cetus» había escrito miles de textos y cartas alquímicas a lo largo de varios siglos, los académicos solían agrupar sus obras en distintas colecciones según la temática o la historia que consideraran legítima.

“Since Holdfast started showing up in combat, Morrough has stayed far away from the front lines,” he said at last.

Según la edición de la antología, Cetus había nacido en diez países distintos.

“But if he’s so afraid of Luc, why didn’t he kill him when he was captured?”

A veces era rey; en ocasiones, sacerdote; y en algunas cartas se afirmaba que había trabajado con el mismísimo Orion.

Kaine shook his head. “I don’t think he wants him dead.

En la antología que recibió Helena, Cetus se interesaba por una antigua secta khemiata que sostenía que la resonancia humana era la alquimización de la humanidad y que los alquimistas eran seres ascendentes.

The orders have always been to take him alive.

—Parece algo que les gustaría creer a los alquimistas —comentó Kaine por la noche, cuando ella le habló del tema.

I used to think it was because Morrough feared usurpation from whoever made the killing blow, but now, after that capture, I think it’s something else.

A él le interesaba más el estado de los pulmones de Helena que las antiguas sectas.

Holdfast has been at the front lines for six years.

Ella se esforzó por no torcer el gesto cuando le retiró las vendas.

Do you really think that if Morrough wanted him dead, he couldn’t have found a way to kill him by now?”

—¿Los inmarcesibles tienen religión?

IT WAS FOUR WEEKS AFTER the bombing before Helena could get up without feeling like she’d shatter.

—El Sumo Nigromante es nuestro dios —repuso Kaine, que extendió su resonancia por las costillas de Helena, hasta el punto donde algunas de ellas se habían fracturado—.

Her resonance had feebly returned, and the bandages were off, but the wiring remained because her sternum was still worryingly delicate.

Nuestras vidas están dedicadas al servicio de su poder infinito.

Before lacing on a chest brace, she sat with a mirror, looking at the scar that ran down between her breasts.

—Si tan poderoso es, ¿por qué no da la cara y gana la guerra?

It was far from pretty.

Kaine levantó la vista un instante.

She’d always admired the way Lila wore her scars, her jokes about naming them; it was only now that she began to realise how difficult it was to be proud of them.

—Es un dios.

The visual evidence of the injury would never go away.

Y, como habrás notado, el modus operandi de los dioses suele ser que los humanos mueran en su nombre.

In a moment of intimacy it would be all there was to see.

Aunque Sol podría destruir a los nigromantes si tanto los odia, por algún motivo, siempre son los Holdfast los que se encargan de ello.

Staring at it in the cold light of day, she couldn’t help but think that someday Kaine might not want someone who had the war so overtly carved into them.

Al final, uno se pregunta si le importa de verdad.

Surely he’d want to be able to forget sometimes.

Desde que le contó la verdad sobre Orion y por qué los Holdfast se habían convertido en principados, Kaine parecía pensar que, si criticaba lo suficiente a la Llama Eterna, Helena acabaría rindiéndose con la Resistencia.

Now, with her, it would be impossible.

Ella soltó un suspiro que le provocó dolor en los pulmones, y Kaine pareció olvidarse de la conversación durante unos minutos.

He was sorting the vials of medicine on the table, but she could feel him observing her from the corner of his eye.

—Desde que Holdfast ha vuelto a la batalla, Morrough se ha mantenido alejado del frente —dijo entonces.

“It’ll fade,” she said quickly.

—Pero, si le tiene tanto miedo a Luc, ¿por qué no lo mató cuando lo capturó?

Her face was burning.

Kaine negó con la cabeza.

She dropped the mirror, putting her hand over the scar to hide it.

—Creo que no quiere matarlo.

It took the span of her entire hand.

Las órdenes siempre han sido capturarlo con vida.

“Once I’m better, I’ll treat it every day so—it’ll fade more,” she said.

Antes creía que era porque Morrough temía que alguien más le arrebatara el mérito del golpe final, pero, después de aquella captura, creo que la razón es otra.

She could feel a divot in the bone where it had refused to regenerate.

Holdfast ha combatido en el frente durante los últimos seis años.

She could attach titanium plating there to reinforce the bone, but given her repertoire, it might interfere with her work.

¿De verdad crees que, si Morrough lo quisiera muerto, no habría encontrado ya alguna manera de matarlo?

Part of the reason titanium was so medically useful for alchemists was because the resonance for it was rare.

Cuatro semanas después del bombardeo, Helena logró levantarse sin sentir que se desmoronaba.

Her jaw trembled. “It won’t look like this forever.”

Había recuperado apenas un ápice de su resonancia y ya no iba vendada, pero todavía le quedaba el alambre, ya que su esternón seguía muy delicado.

He set a vial down.

Antes de colocarse el corsé en el pecho, se sentó frente al espejo para ver la cicatriz que se extendía entre sus pechos.

His silver eyes were intent, his attention like a beam of light through a magnifying glass, suddenly focused solely on her.

No había belleza alguna en esa marca.

He stepped over and gently but firmly pulled her hand away.

Siempre había admirado cómo Lila lucía sus cicatrices con orgullo, cómo bromeaba y les ponía nombre.

She knew he’d seen the scar more than she had, and in far worse stages than this, but she hated having him look at it.

Ahora comprendía lo difícil que era estar orgullosa de ellas.

“Do you see my scars that way?” he finally said. “When you look at me, are they all you see?”

Esa herida jamás desaparecería.

She flinched. “No.”

En un momento íntimo, sería lo único que estuviera a la vista.

“Well.” He met her eyes. “I don’t see you that way, either.

Tras contemplarla bajo la fría luz del día, Helena no pudo evitar pensar que tal vez llegara el día en que Kaine no querría a alguien con una marca tan pronunciada.

You’re mine.” He let go of her wrist and lifted his hand, the fingertips tracing the scarring until it was covered by his palm, warm against her bare skin, then sliding up to curve around her neck. “You are.

Hasta él querría olvidarse de todo en algún momento.

It doesn’t matter what happens to you, you will still be mine.”

Sin embargo, le resultaría imposible si esa cicatriz permanecía con ella.

HELENA SAW ONLY BITS OF the house.

Él se encontraba ordenando los frascos de medicina en la mesa, pero Helena sabía que la estaba mirando por el rabillo del ojo.

Spirefell.

—Se atenuará —comentó Helena rápidamente.

They took walks through the dim hallways as she tried to adapt to the way her chest ached when she moved.

Le ardía el rostro.

Breathing deeply made it feel like her sternum would snap.

Soltó el espejo y se llevó la mano a la cicatriz para taparla.

The house was an old, heavy style long abandoned in the city.

Le ocupaba toda la mano.

Everywhere was detailed in dark wrought iron, even the floors run through with it.

—Cuando me ponga mejor, la trataré todos los días para que… se difumine un poco más —añadió.

There was a melancholy beauty to it.

Tocó con la mano una melladura en el hueso, justo donde se había negado a regenerarse.

In the foyer, an intricate mosaic of the ouroboros dragon was inlaid in the marble floor.

Podría introducir una placa de titanio para reforzar el hueso, pero, con su repertorio, tal vez aquello interfiriera en su trabajo.

Meticulously rendered in both grandeur and savagery.

Uno de los motivos por los que los alquimistas empleaban el titanio en la medicina era porque había pocos que tuvieran resonancia titánica.

She studied it from the landing above.

Le tembló la barbilla.

The Ferrons must have been so proud when the house was built.

—No será siempre así.

They must have thought they’d defeated god.

Kaine dejó un frasco sobre la mesa.

That night, she pulled Kaine into the bed.

Sus ojos plateados la miraron con determinación, como si fuera un rayo de luz atravesando una lupa.

He’d slept in the chair beside it every night, her hand in his, ignoring her arguments that surely there were other beds in his house.

De repente, solo tenía ojos para ella.

Now he finally gave in to her.

Dio un paso al frente y, con suavidad, pero también firmeza, le apartó la mano del pecho.

She curled against him, having missed the warmth and comfort of his body.

Helena sabía que él había visto esa cicatriz más veces que ella misma, y en un estado mucho peor que el actual, pero detestaba que la mirase.

A few more days and she would go back.

—¿Así es como ves tú mis cicatrices? —preguntó al cabo de unos segundos—.

She’d convalesced there longer than she’d meant to, but the return trip would be hard, and she’d be no use at Headquarters if she wasn’t recovered.

Cuando me miras, ¿es lo único en lo que te fijas?

Everything would be different.

Ella torció el gesto.

The bombing had decimated the Resistance, wiped out their supplies.

—No.

Everything they’d gained in the last year, gone, and now Morrough knew there was a spy.

—Bien. —La miró a los ojos—.

The Undying were looking for Kaine, trying to lure him out, but that would not stop Ilva or Crowther from coercing him into doing whatever they deemed necessary.

Porque yo tampoco te veo así.

She had to go back.

Eres mía. —Le soltó la muñeca y levantó la mano hasta que las yemas de sus dedos dibujaron toda la cicatriz, que quedó oculta bajo la palma de su mano.

She held him, her heart beating so hard it made her whole chest throb.

Helena sintió el calor de su piel, que subió hasta la curva de su cuello—.

She pulled him closer, tilting her head back, and kissed him.

Lo eres.

His hand rose up to caress her cheek, but he began to draw away.

Da igual lo que te pase, seguirás siendo mía.

She knew he was going to say she was still recovering.

Helena apenas había visto algunas partes de la casa, en Puntaférreo.

She was so sick of her convalescence.

Dieron paseos por los pasillos tenuemente iluminados mientras se acostumbraba al dolor que sentía en el pecho cada vez que se movía.

Of having so little time and never getting to spend it in the ways she wanted.

Cuando respiraba hondo, tenía la sensación de que su esternón iba a romperse.

“It’ll be fine if we’re careful,” she said, not letting go. “Please.

La casa estaba decorada en un estilo anticuado y recargado que hacía mucho que ya no se usaba en la ciudad.

I want you before I go.”

Había detalles de hierro forjado en todos los rincones, hasta los suelos eran un entramado metálico.

He was careful.

Tenía una belleza melancólica.

Slow and gentle.

En el suelo de mármol del vestíbulo había un mosaico de un dragón uróboro, dispuesto de forma meticulosa para mostrar su grandeza y su violencia a partes iguales.

He touched her as though she were glass.

Helena lo analizó desde el rellano del piso superior.

He pushed into her and she caught his face in her hands, pulling him close so that their noses and foreheads brushed, her fingers trembling.

Los Ferron debieron de sentirse muy orgullosos al construir esa casa.

I love you.

Debieron de pensar que, de algún modo, habían derrotado a los dioses.

It was right at the tip of her tongue, but she hesitated, biting the words back.

Aquella noche, Kaine durmió con ella en su cama. Él había pasado las noches sentado en una silla a su lado, sosteniéndole la mano y haciendo caso omiso a las veces que le sugirió que habría otras camas en la casa.

There was a part of her that felt she might doom them if she said it.

Esta vez, él cedió.

If there were important things left unspoken, tomorrow would come.

Helena se acurrucó en sus brazos; había echado de menos el calor y el consuelo que le brindaba su cuerpo.

She kissed him instead.

En unos días, volvería a la rutina.

I love you.

Ya había reposado más tiempo del que hubiera querido, pero sabía que el viaje de regreso sería duro y que no serviría de nada presentarse en el Cuartel General si no se recuperaba completamente.

She told him in the way she held him close; in the way her mouth met his; in how her hands trailed across his skin, mapping him, memorising every detail of what it was to be with him, his scars under her fingers.

Todo sería distinto.

I love you.

El bombardeo había diezmado la Resistencia y había agotado sus suministros.

I love you.

Todo lo que habían ganado en el último año se había perdido, y Morrough sabía que había un espía entre sus filas.

She told him in the way she let go of herself and held on to him instead.

Los inmarcesibles estaban buscando a Kaine, querían sacarlo de su escondite, pero eso no frenaría a Ilva o a Crowther cuando decidieran obligarlo a hacer lo que ellos quisieran.

With every beat of her heart.

Tenía que volver.

I love you.

Sostuvo a Kaine contra su pecho y sintió cómo el latido de su corazón vibraba en todo su torso.

I will always love you.

Lo atrajo hacia sí, ladeó la cabeza y le dio un beso.

I will always take care of you.

Kaine levantó la mano para acariciarle la mejilla, pero se detuvo.

IT WAS DUSK WHEN SHE left.

Helena sabía lo que iba a decirle: que todavía se estaba recuperando.

She stepped outside for the first time.

Sin embargo, estaba harta de estar convaleciente, de tener tan poco tiempo y no dedicarlo a lo que realmente deseaba.

Spirefell was a sprawling house which curved in, connecting with the other buildings to form a large courtyard with an overgrown garden in the centre.

—Si tenemos cuidado, no me pasará nada —le aseguró sin apartarse—.

Amaris was there, waiting restlessly.

Por favor.

Her wings fanned out and fluttering.

Quiero estar contigo antes de marcharme.

Kaine lifted Helena carefully, the chest brace absorbing the pressure of her weight.

Kaine fue muy cuidadoso.

As he swung up behind her, she looked towards the house.

Lo hicieron despacio, suave.

In the summer gloaming, it looked almost like an immense slumbering dragon itself, curling inwards, the spires like spines.

La acarició como si fuera de cristal.

It was covered in vining roses which crept all the way up the front, nearly covering it.

Cuando la penetró, Helena sostuvo su rostro entre las manos hasta que sus frentes se rozaron; los dedos le temblaban.

Davies and an old male servant, possibly a butler, stood at the top of the wide flight of stone steps, watching.

«Te quiero».

When Amaris launched herself into the air, it was like being punched in the ribs.

Tenía esas palabras en la punta de la lengua, pero vaciló durante un instante y las contuvo.

Helena doubled over, gasping from pain, and she felt Kaine tense and nearly turn Amaris back.

Había una parte de ella que creía que, si pronunciaba esas palabras, acabarían condenados.

She gripped his leg. “I’m all right.”

Si quedaba algo importante por decir, siempre habría un mañana.

They were airborne for longer than Helena had ever been before.

En lugar de eso, le besó.

Amaris flew towards the mountains, trying to beat the moonrise.

«Te quiero».

It was close enough to the Abeyance that Lumithia was a crescent, not too bright as she rose.

Se lo dijo en la forma en que lo atraía hacia sí, cuando se encontraban sus bocas, en cómo sus manos le acariciaban la piel, cartografiándolo, memorizando cada detalle que componía su ser, recorriendo sus cicatrices con los dedos.

They landed on the top of a building dangerously close to Headquarters.

«Te quiero».

When Helena looked south, she saw why.

«Te quiero».

A wall had been erected, marking off Resistance territory.

Se lo dijo en la forma en la que se dejaba llevar para que él la sostuviera.

It was more than halfway up the island.

Con cada latido de su corazón. «Te quiero.

Beyond, she could see the gash bisecting the city where the bomb had gone off, the buildings fallen.

Siempre te querré.

The centre of the island was cratered.

Siempre cuidaré de ti».

“We lost that much?”

Estaba anocheciendo cuando se marchó.

“No, but you don’t have the forces to hold more,” Kaine said grimly, swinging down and helping her carefully off Amaris’s back.

Helena salió al exterior por primera vez.

She was nauseated with pain, fighting hard to breathe as she squeezed Kaine’s hand, but she couldn’t bring herself to say goodbye.

Puntaférreo era una mansión enorme que se curvaba hacia dentro y tenía un patio cerrado con un jardín desbordante en el centro.

She had a growing fear of anything final.

Allí se encontraba Amaris, impaciente, con las alas desplegadas y en movimiento.

She could feel it all coming to an end.

Kaine la llevó en volandas, y el corsé absorbió la presión de su peso.

“Be careful,” was all she said.

Cuando él se colocó a su espalda, Helena miró la casa.

“Helena, please—” His voice broke, stopping her in her tracks.

Bajo el resplandor del verano, le parecía un dragón descomunal en hibernación, enroscado hacia dentro, con los chapiteles como si fueran púas.

She turned back, and he gripped her shoulders.

La fachada frontal estaba cubierta casi por completo de rosas trepaderas, y Davies y un criado anciano, que probablemente fuese el mayordomo, observaban todo desde lo alto de un tramo de escalones de piedra.

She knew what he wanted to ask her, could see it in his eyes.

Cuando Amaris despegó, Helena sintió como si le dieran un puñetazo en las costillas.

Run away and don’t come back.

Se dobló sobre sí misma y se le escapó un grito ahogado de dolor.

But he knew she wouldn’t.

Kaine se puso en tensión y estuvo a punto de hacer regresar a Amaris, pero ella le agarró la pierna.

He swallowed, not meeting her eyes. “Don’t get hurt again,” he said instead. “Don’t—”

—Estoy bien.

She rose up on her toes and cut him off with a kiss.

Estuvieron volando durante mucho más tiempo del que Helena había volado jamás.

“Be careful,” she whispered. “Don’t die.”

Amaris se dirigía hacia las montañas, intentando vencer la salida de la luna.

WHEN HELENA APPEARED AT THE gates in boys’ clothes, struggling to breathe, her reception was one of far more suspicion than joy.

Estaba tan cerca de la latencia que Lumitia era una medialuna que no alumbraba demasiado.

She was placed in a holding cell for an hour before Crowther appeared to have her let out.

Aterrizaron en la azotea de un edificio que estaba peligrosamente cerca del Cuartel General.

“You sure?” the guard said to him. “She’s been listed among the dead for almost a month.”

Cuando Helena miró hacia al sur, comprendió por qué.

“Yes, she was found by one of the splinter factions,” Crowther said. “I knew they’d send her back eventually.

Habían levantado un muro para demarcar el territorio de la Resistencia.

Let her out.”

Ocupaba más de la mitad de la isla.

Helena didn’t know if the splinter factions of Resistance fighters existed at all, or if they were an invention to cover up all of Crowther’s illicit activities.

Al otro lado, vio el tajo que había diseccionado la ciudad, ahí donde había estallado la bomba y los edificios se habían desplomado.

A great deal of Kaine’s intelligence and activities were attributed to these alleged groups.

El centro de la isla era un cráter.

Crowther looked as if he had not slept in weeks.

—¿Tanto hemos perdido?

His face was haggard, his eyes bloodshot, and he appeared mostly angry about having to go out of his way to get Helena released.

—No, pero no tenéis ejército para defender más territorio —respondió Kaine con gesto sombrío.

Helena wanted to know what had happened while she’d been gone, but before the door of the holding cell was unlocked, he was already walking away.

Acto seguido, se bajó y la ayudó a desmontar del lomo de Amaris.

“Go to the hospital.

El dolor le provocaba náuseas y tenía que esforzarse para respirar; le apretó la mano a Kaine.

The matron’s on shift.

Aun así, no fue capaz de despedirse.

I’ll deal with you tomorrow,” he said over his shoulder.

Cada vez le daba más miedo que aquello estuviera llegando a su fin.

Matron Pace wept at the sight of her. “You’re alive!

Sentía que el final estaba cerca.

I should have gone.

—Ten cuidado —fue lo único que pudo decir.

When I heard they sent you—I—”

—Helena, por favor… —Se le rompió la voz de tal manera que ella se detuvo en seco y se giró.

“I’m glad you didn’t,” Helena said.

Kaine la tomó por los hombros.

She was exhausted from the flight and journey back.

Sabía lo que le iba a pedir, lo leía en sus ojos: «Huye y no vuelvas».

There was a grinding pain in her chest.

Pero él también sabía que no lo haría, así que tragó saliva, incapaz de mirarla a los ojos.

She pressed her hand gingerly against her sternum, trying to relieve the pressure.

—No dejes que te hagan daño otra vez —dijo en su lugar—.

Pace ushered her into a space enclosed by curtains. “How did you survive?”

No…

Helena stuck with the vagaries of Crowther’s excuse. “I don’t really remember.

Helena se puso de puntillas y lo hizo callar con un beso.

We were in the hospital and there was another explosion.

—Ten cuidado —susurró—.

When I woke, I’m not sure where I was.

No mueras.

I’d had an operation, and I was mostly left to recover.”

Cuando Helena apareció en la puerta con ropa de chico e incapaz de respirar bien, la recibieron con más cautela que alegría.

“Let me see.”

La tuvieron encerrada en una celda durante una hora, hasta que Crowther apareció para sacarla.

If she were Pace, she’d be the same, so she allowed her clothes to be removed and the chest brace carefully unfastened to reveal the scarring down her chest.

—¿Está seguro? —le preguntó un guardia—.

“Oh.” Pace’s hand trembled, but then she inspected it more carefully. “This is … good work.”

Aparece en la lista de fallecidos de hace un mes.

She’d clearly expected some kind of back-alley surgery utilising twine and kitchen knives. “Whoever their surgeon is, we should try to bring them in.”

—Sí, la encontró uno de los grupos disidentes —respondió Crowther—.

“I never saw who it was,” Helena said. “I’m getting better, but my resonance is still unstable.”

Sabía que la mandarían de vuelta en algún momento.

Pace attempted a smile, but it was more grimace. “Fortunately, chelator is one of the few things we still have in sufficient supply.”

Dejadla salir.

“How bad are things?” Helena asked.

Helena no sabía si los grupos disidentes dentro de los combatientes de la Resistencia existían realmente, o si era algo que se había inventado Crowther para encubrir todas sus actividades ilícitas.

Pace did not stop moving as she continued to examine Helena and began prepping her arm for an intravenous drip. “I only hear things secondhand.”

Buena parte de lo que hacía Kaine y también gran parte de la información que obtenía acababa atribuyéndose a esos grupos fantasma.

“How bad are people saying it is?”

Crowther parecía no haber dormido en las últimas semanas.

Pace shook her head. “Of our remaining combatants, more than a third are still showing signs of the nullium poisoning.

Estaba demacrado, tenía los ojos inyectados en sangre y haber tenido que ir para sacar a Helena de la cárcel le resultaba, a todas luces, un incordio.

The wind’s shifted, so we’re spared most of the dust now, but even the parts of the island that are still intact are dangerous.

Helena quería saber todo lo que había pasado desde que desapareció, pero, apenas se abrió la puerta de su celda, Crowther ya se había dado la vuelta.

At least until there’s rain.”

—Ve al hospital.

“I heard that Althorne died.”

Pace está de servicio.

“And Ilva.”

Mañana hablamos —le espetó por encima del hombro.

“What?” Helena stared at Pace in shock.

La enfermera Pace se echó a llorar en cuanto la vio.

“A little more than a week ago.

—¡Estás viva!

Her heart failed from the stress.

Debería haber ido yo.

Luc is inconsolable.

Cuando me enteré de que te enviaron allí, yo no…

You should go see Lila tomorrow.

—Me alegro de que no lo hicieras —repuso Helena.

She was devastated when she learned you were listed among the dead.”

Estaba agotada por el vuelo y el regreso.

No mention of Luc’s reaction to Helena’s presumed death.

Sentía una punzada de dolor en el pecho.

Her throat tightened.

Se llevó la mano contra el esternón para intentar aliviar la presión.

“How is she?”

Pace la condujo a un sitio cerrado por cortinas.

“Progressing.

—¿Cómo es posible que hayas sobrevivido?

Everything is quite healthy.”

Helena repitió la excusa vaga de Crowther.

THE BOMBING HAD DAMAGED THE island’s structural foundation and flood infrastructure, and it was impossible to repair due to the risk of nullium exposure.

—La verdad es que no lo recuerdo.

The Resistance had also lost almost all their prisoners because the building had collapsed, including Crowther’s, whom he’d moved to keep from Ivy’s grasp.

Nos encontrábamos en el hospital cuando se produjo otra explosión.

They were all presumed dead, but it was impossible to verify much of anything within the blast zone.

Cuando desperté, no sé muy bien dónde estaba.

Even the smuggled aid received from Novis was now difficult to obtain, and the scale of injuries too great to let patients evacuate to Novis.

Me operaron y me dejaron sola para que me recuperara.

Their monarchical neighbour was beginning to signal a dwindling enthusiasm for both providing resources and absorbing Paladia’s injured.

—Déjame ver.

The war had gone from teetering in the balance to a Resistance free fall.

De haber sido al revés, Helena habría hecho lo mismo, así que permitió que Pace le retirara la ropa y el corsé poco a poco, dejando al descubierto la cicatriz que le cruzaba el pecho.

Without Althorne or Ilva, the Council was reduced to three: Matias and Crowther, who had almost entirely opposing views, and Luc, who distrusted both of them.

—Hala. —A Pace le temblaba la mano, pero inspeccionó la cicatriz con sumo cuidado—.

Crowther had always operated from the shadows, allowing Ilva to take the lead with his tacit support.

Está… muy bien hecho.

Now he was alone, seeming to shrink and writhe under the glaring scrutiny of Luc, like a spider without its web, fumbling about on overlong legs.

Era evidente que esperaba algún tipo de cirugía más chapucera, con cordel y cuchillos de cocina.

There was a part of Helena that wanted to leave him to his fate, but she knew that the more powerless Crowther felt, the greater his danger to Kaine.

—Sea quien sea tu cirujano, deberíamos pedirle que venga a trabajar aquí.

She sat, watching him move around his office, pausing at various maps and diagrams now riddled with black slashes of ink.

—No llegué a ver quién era —replicó Helena—.

“How much communication have you been in—with Ferron?” she asked, exhausted from the journey from hospital to Tower.

Estoy mejor, pero mi resonancia sigue siendo inestable.

“None, except that you were alive and would be returned once you were out of danger.

Pace intentó sonreír, pero solo consiguió forzar una mueca.

Why?”

—Por suerte, los quelantes son de las pocas cosas que todavía nos quedan.

Helena drew a labouring breath. “I think I’ve discovered something.

—¿Cómo de mal estamos? —preguntó Helena.

Ever since Wagner—I was studying the array, thinking about the different kinds of resonance energy to understand the process Morrough uses.”

Pace no dejó de moverse mientras seguía examinándola y le preparaba el brazo para colocarle una vía intravenosa.

A wary look entered Crowther’s eyes.

—Solo sé lo que escucho de pasada.

“You know, normally arrays are elemental or celestial, five or eight axis points.

—¿Cómo dice la gente que estamos?

But Luc’s pyromancy uses seven, and Wagner drew nine for the ritual.

Pace negó con la cabeza.

Kaine confirmed it was nine, so I was trying to think differently about the energy.

—De los soldados que nos quedan, más de un tercio sigue mostrando síntomas de envenenamiento por anulitio.

When I’d try to envision how it would work, I kept thinking about a feeling I have in the hospital sometimes—”

El viento ha cambiado de dirección, así que ya no cae polvo, pero hasta las partes de la isla que están intactas corren peligro.

“Marino, get to the point.”

Al menos hasta que llueva.

“When a patient dies, there’s an inverted form of the energy that Morrough utilises to make the Undying.

—Me han dicho que Althorne ha muerto.

The vitality changes, and there’s this moment as it dissipates when I feel it.”

—E Ilva.

“And …”

—¿Qué? —Helena miró a Pace conmocionada.

“Before the bombing, I figured out a way to channel it and trap it inside obsidian.

—Hace poco más de una semana.

It didn’t seem to do anything, but when I was at the field hospital, I cut one of the necrothralls with it, and it collapsed—as if the reanimation had been severed.”

Su corazón no aguantó el estrés.

Crowther looked over sharply. “Are you sure?”

Luc está desconsolado.

She shifted and grimaced as pain fractalled like lightning through her chest. “Well, I was injured, but I’m pretty sure.

Deberías ir a ver a Lila mañana.

I’ve replayed it again and again.

Se quedó destrozada cuando se enteró de que aparecías entre los fallecidos.

We should test it.” She swallowed hard. “I have a few more pieces, and once my resonance is stable again, I can make more.”

No mencionó la reacción de Luc al enterarse de la presunta muerte de Helena.

“Bring them, I’ll see who I can pass the idea off to.” He waved her away in dismissal.

A ella se le formó un nudo en la garganta.

Helena didn’t move.

—¿Cómo se encuentra?

It wasn’t that she’d expected to be credited; she just had no intention of letting Crowther casually exploit her anymore.

—Todo sigue su curso.

“You must be very busy now,” she said.

Está bastante sana.

“Indeed. I am.”

El bombardeo había dañado los cimientos de la isla y los tanques de inundación, y era imposible repararlos debido al riesgo de exposición al anulitio.

“I’ll help you, but I want something in return.”

La Resistencia también había perdido a casi todos sus prisioneros, ya que el edificio en el que estaban confinados se había derrumbado.

Crowther’s eyebrows rose. “And what is that, pray tell?”

Entre ellos se encontraban los detenidos de Crowther, a los que había movido para evitar que Ivy los capturara.

“I want to know and approve every order you’re giving Kaine.”

Los daban por muertos, pero nadie podía verificar lo que sucedía en la zona de impacto.

Crowther’s bloodshot eyes flashed dangerously.

Incluso la ayuda que recibían de Novis era muy difícil de conseguir, y había tantos heridos de gravedad que resultaba imposible evacuar a los pacientes al país vecino.

Helena didn’t blink. “I’m offering you a deal.

El entusiasmo de la monarquía por enviar recursos y aceptar heridos de Paladia estaba empezando a decaer.

What you do is illicit, and you have no allies on the Council to cover it up anymore.

La guerra había dejado de ser una contienda entre dos bandos: ahora era una caída libre de la Resistencia.

You need someone.

Sin Althorne e Ilva, el Consejo se reducía a tres personas: Matias y Crowther, con visiones totalmente opuestas, y Luc, que no se fiaba de ninguno de los dos.

I’m offering to be your shadow.

Crowther siempre había operado en la sombra, lo que permitía a Ilva ejercer el liderazgo con su respaldo tácito.

I’ll provide you with what you need, same way you did for Ilva.

Ahora que estaba solo, parecía encogerse y retorcerse bajo la mirada escudriñadora de Luc, como una araña fuera de su red que patalea con unas patas demasiado largas.

But Kaine is my condition.”

Una parte de Helena quería dejarlo a su suerte, pero sabía que, cuanto más impotente se sintiera Crowther, más peligro corría Kaine.

His expression grew scathing. “You’re overestimating your value, Marino.”

Se sentó y lo observó moverse de un lado a otro del despacho, deteniéndose frente a mapas y diagramas plagados de surcos de tinta negra.

Helena’s mouth twisted in a bitter smile. “I’m not, though, am I?

—¿Cuánta comunicación has mantenido con… Ferron? —le preguntó, exhausta tras el paseo desde el hospital hasta la Torre.

You said it yourself: I am an exceptional asset.

—Ninguna, salvo para informarme de que seguías viva y volverías cuando tu vida dejara de correr peligro.

Why else would you and Ilva spend so much time manipulating me?

¿Por qué?

Always been so quick to take advantage of what I can do while treating it like it’s of no use to anyone.

Helena respiró hondo con dificultad.

By all means, replace me if you can.”

—Creo que he descubierto algo.

Crowther’s fingers curled into a fist, eyes narrowing, but he said nothing.

Desde que Wagner… Estuve estudiando el sello y pensando en las distintas energías resonánticas para entender el proceso que emplea Morrough. —Los ojos de Crowther se iluminaron con cautela—.

Her heart rammed against the damaged bone. “You have overutilised Kaine.

Verás, normalmente, los sellos son elementales o celestiales, es decir, de cinco u ocho puntas.

If I were a lower-calibre healer, you would have killed him a dozen times over in the last several months.

Sin embargo, la piromancia de Luc emplea siete y Wagner dibujó uno de nueve para el ritual.

I have told you this, but you ignored it because you know I’ll do whatever it takes to save him.”

Kaine confirmó que eran nueve, así que empecé a observar las energías desde otra perspectiva.

Her face contorted with anger. “But the fact that he will do anything you ask doesn’t mean you can keep demanding it.

Cuando traté de visualizar cómo funcionaría, no dejaba de pensar en una sensación que tengo a veces en el hospital…

I have done the unconscionable for the Eternal Flame, and I have let him suffer for it because what other choice do we have?

—Marino, ve al grano.

But now everything we achieved, that he paid for, is gone.

—Cuando un paciente muere, hay un pico de energía que es la inversa a la que usa Morrough para crear a los inmarcesibles.

We have nothing to show for it.

La vitalidad cambia y, durante un instante, la percibo antes de que se disipe.

I won’t let you keep forcing him to pay the price while you stall for time.”

—Y…

Crowther was silent for a moment. “A trade, then?

—Antes del bombardeo, descubrí una forma de canalizar esa vitalidad y atraparla dentro de obsidiana.

Is that what you’re proposing?

No creí que sirviera de nada, pero, cuando estuve en el hospital de campaña, corté a un necrómata con ella y se derrumbó, como si le hubiera arrancado la reanimación.

Yourself—your cooperation—in exchange for Ferron’s safety?”

Crowther la miró de arriba abajo con interés.

Helena gave a tight nod.

—¿Estás segura?

If Kaine had any idea what she’d come back to do, he probably would have ripped out his own talisman before letting her return.

Helena se removió en el sitio, torciendo el gesto cuando sintió un dolor que le atravesó el torso.

Clearly she was learning; she was not so easy to read anymore.

—Bueno, estaba herida, pero estoy bastante segura.

There was a pause, then Crowther laughed.

Lo he repasado en mi mente una y otra vez.

“What an odd turn of events.” He stood, still chuckling. “Very well.

Deberíamos ponerlo a prueba. —Tragó saliva—.

Follow my orders, and he will stay alive.

Tengo más fragmentos de obsidiana y, cuando recupere mi resonancia, puedo hacer más.

I’m not Ilva; I have no interest in seeing Ferron prematurely dead for the sake of vengeance.

—Tráelos.

Why begrudge a weapon its uses?

Veré a quién puedo pasarle la idea. —Le hizo un gesto para que se fuera de allí.

Even if that weapon is an abomination.”

Pero Helena no se movió.

He walked around his desk, a ghastly smile on his face. “You know, I had a nearly identical version of this conversation with Ferron earlier this year.”

No es que esperara algún reconocimiento; simplemente no pensaba permitir que Crowther siguiera explotándola.

Helena refused to react, meeting his eyes.

—Debes de estar muy ocupado ahora —comentó.

“So long as you make yourself useful to me, I’ll let you approve Ferron’s assignations.

—Así es.

But if you ever disobey me, or cross me, I will—”

—Te ayudaré, pero quiero algo a cambio.

“Yes, I know what you’ll do,” Helena said.

Crowther arqueó las cejas.

IT TOOK A WEEK BEFORE Helena’s resonance was stable again.

—No me digas… ¿Y de qué se trata?

During that time, she functioned as a test subject for Shiseo as they developed a tablet form for the chelators, to reduce the overcrowding and demand on saline.

Sus ojos inyectados en sangre se iluminaron peligrosamente.

In that same week, a weapons specialist gave an obsidian spear to an ambitious young man hoping to join Luc’s unit.

Helena no se inmutó.

Even before he returned, the rumours reached Headquarters about a miraculously effective weapon.

—Quiero hacer un trato.

The weapons specialist was evasive about his methods, although he was obliged to admit that Crowther was the one who’d given him the obsidian.

Estás haciendo cosas ilegales y ya no tienes aliados en el Consejo que te cubran las espaldas.

Everyone leapt to the conclusion that the properties of the obsidian came from pyromancy; that the obsidian must be infused with holy, cleansing fire.

Necesitas a alguien.

The new weapon secured Crowther’s place and influence not only on the Council but over the Eternal Flame.

Me ofrezco para ser tu mano en la sombra.

Once Helena was finally recovered enough to resume work, she was told that because of her injuries she would no longer work in the casualty ward but be assigned the less rigorous task of palliative care and last rites.

Te daré lo que necesites, igual que hacía Ilva.

She wore a heavy black habit with myriad hidden pockets filled with obsidian glass and tended to the patients that couldn’t be saved.

Pero Kaine es mi condición.

She’d thought she’d seen the worst of the hospital, but she realised now that she was used to seeing those with some chance of survival.

La expresión de Crowther se torció en una mueca de desdén.

Now she sat with men whose bodies seemed turned inside out, hearts exposed, faces lopped off, sometimes so little of them left that it seemed impossible that they were alive.

—Te tienes en muy alta estima, Marino.

They’d hold on to her, often mistaking her for someone else as she tended them like a carrion bird.

Helena esbozó una sonrisa amarga.

As unprecedented a breakthrough as the obsidian was, it was impossible to keep up with the demand, especially in the hands of soldiers trained with steel.

—En realidad, no.

Though its edges were sharper than razors, the glass shattered easily, making the weapons unreliable.

¿No es cierto?

The obsidian was effective not only on necrothralls but liches as well.

Tú mismo lo dijiste.

When one soldier managed a blow through the chest, the lich died, all his necrothralls collapsing with him.

Soy excepcional.

The talisman was brought back, and Helena examined it.

¿Por qué, si no, pasasteis tanto tiempo Ilva y tú manipulándome?

There was no sense of energy.

Siempre dispuestos a aprovechar lo que podía hacer, pero dejando claro que no servía para nada más.

She compared it with others.

Adelante, sustitúyeme si puedes.

When it was cut in half, powder as fine as dust poured out.

Los dedos de Crowther se cerraron en un puño.

Kaine summoned her that night.

Entornó los ojos, pero no respondió.

Her ring burned twice, and she practically ran out of Headquarters.

Helena sintió que el corazón le latía con fuerza contra el hueso fracturado.

She stood on the rooftop, hand pressed against her chest, numbing the grinding pain as she waited.

—Has empleado a Kaine más allá de lo razonable.

“What happened today?” he asked as Amaris landed heavily on the roof.

Si yo fuera una sanadora sin importancia, lo habrías matado diez veces en los últimos meses.

He didn’t dismount, which meant the conversation would be short.

Te avisé, pero me ignoraste porque sabes que haré lo que sea para salvarle la vida. —La rabia se hizo patente en su rostro—.

She could feel every second they’d been separated, the weight of it.

Pero que él esté dispuesto a hacer lo que sea no significa que tú puedas seguir exigiendo sin más.

“What do you mean?”

He hecho lo impensable por la Llama Eterna y he permitido que él sufriera las consecuencias porque ¿qué otra opción teníamos?

“We’ve all been recalled from combat.

Sin embargo, después de lo que hemos conseguido, después de lo que él ha hecho, no tenemos nada que lo demuestre.

Effective immediately.

Todo se ha ido al traste.

The thralls and Aspirants will continue to fight, but the Undying have all been withdrawn from the front lines.”

Y no pienso dejar que sigas obligándole a pagar ese precio mientras tú ganas tiempo.

“Someone killed a lich with the obsidian,” Helena said. “Do you think maybe he—the lich—died?

Crowther se quedó callado unos instantes.

That Morrough can’t bring him back anymore?”

—¿Y quieres hacer un trato?

Kaine was silent for a few moments.

¿Eso es lo que me estás proponiendo?

“Seems you’ve found a weapon to kill us,” he finally said.

¿Tu cooperación a cambio de la seguridad de Ferron?

She couldn’t read the emotion in his voice.

Helena se limitó a asentir.

All the exhilaration drained from her.

Si Kaine hubiera sabido que había regresado para esto, se habría arrancado el talismán antes de permitirlo.

She’d spent so much time afraid of Kaine’s immortality, knowing that his discovery or apprehension would be without means of escape; he could be tortured forever, without even the hope of death.

Era evidente que ella estaba aprendiendo; ya no era tan fácil adivinar sus intenciones.

Now it was very likely that he could die.

Se hizo un silencio que se vio interrumpido por una carcajada de Crowther.

She had made this possible.

—Qué inesperado giro de los acontecimientos. —Se levantó sin dejar de reír por lo bajo—.

She had not saved him; she had created a new way to lose him instead.

De acuerdo.

“Be careful,” she said.

Sigue mis órdenes y Ferron continuará con vida.

He was studying her. “Did they let you recover before they set you back to work?”

Yo no soy Ilva; no me interesa que Ferron muera antes de tiempo por una venganza personal.

She managed a smile. “Yes.

¿Por qué negarle a un arma su utilidad, aunque esa arma sea una abominación?

Moved me out of the casualty ward.

El hombre rodeó su escritorio con una sonrisa escalofriante.

My duties are less rigorous now.”

—¿Sabes?

He nodded. “Well, that’s something.”

A principios de este año, tuve una conversación prácticamente idéntica con Ferron.

There was a pause.

Helena se mantuvo impasible y lo miró a los ojos.

She had so much she wanted to say, to tell him, but she knew he was already lingering too long.

—Mientras me seas útil, permitiré que seas tú quien apruebe las misiones de Ferron.

“If the obsidian does what we think, the Eternal Flame will be a real threat to Morrough now.

Pero, si me desobedeces o me enfadas, me encargaré de…

He’s sure to respond accordingly,” he finally said. “You should prepare for that.”

—Sí, sé muy bien lo que harás —replicó Helena.

She nodded wordlessly, and he relaxed on the reins, Amaris immediately moving to spring, the wind rushing around her wings.

Helena tardó una semana más en recuperar por completo su resonancia.

“Don’t die.”

En ese tiempo, hizo de conejillo de Indias para Shiseo.

She must have said it too quietly, because he didn’t answer.

Estaban desarrollando un quelante en forma de pastilla, con el objetivo de reducir la demanda exorbitada de suero.

En esa misma semana, un experto en armas le entregó una lanza de obsidiana a un joven ambicioso que quería entrar en la unidad de Luc.

Antes de que regresara, los rumores de un arma de efectividad milagrosa habían llegado al Cuartel General.

El experto en armas no reveló sus métodos, aunque tuvo que admitir que había sido Crowther quien le había entregado la obsidiana.

Todo el mundo llegó a la conclusión de que las propiedades de la obsidiana provenían de la piromancia; que la obsidiana debía de estar imbuida de un fuego sagrado y purificador.

La nueva arma aseguró el puesto y la influencia de Crowther, no solo dentro del Consejo, sino también en la Llama Eterna.

Cuando por fin Helena estuvo en condiciones de volver al trabajo, le dijeron que, debido a sus heridas, ya no podría incorporarse al pabellón de emergencias, y que quedaba relegada a una tarea menos exigente: cuidados paliativos y ritos de despedida.

Vestía un hábito de tela pesada y negra, lleno de bolsillos ocultos en los que guardaba cristales de obsidiana, y atendía a los pacientes que no tenían salvación.

Por mucho que creyera que había visto lo peor del hospital, allí comprendió que siempre había trabajado con los que tenían alguna posibilidad de sobrevivir.

Ahora se sentaba junto a hombres que parecían tener el cuerpo del revés, el corazón fuera, las caras reventadas; a veces quedaba tan poco de ellos que parecía imposible que siguieran con vida.

Se aferraban a ella y, a menudo, la confundían con otra persona mientras los atendía como si fuera un ave carroñera.

A pesar de que la obsidiana había sido un descubrimiento sin precedentes, resultaba imposible mantener el ritmo de la demanda, sobre todo entre soldados acostumbrados a entrenar con acero.

Aunque el borde era más afilado que una cuchilla, el cristal se partía con facilidad, lo que hacía que las armas fueran poco fiables.

Aun así, descubrieron que la obsidiana no solo funcionaba contra los necrómatas, sino también contra los liches.

Cuando un soldado consiguió atravesarle el pecho a un liche, este murió, y todos sus necrómatas cayeron con él.

Recuperaron el talismán y Helena lo examinó.

No quedaba en él ni rastro de energía.

Lo comparó con los demás y, al cortarlo por la mitad, se deshizo en una arenilla más fina que el polvo.

Kaine la llamó esa noche.

Cuando el anillo le ardió un par de veces, Helena salió corriendo del Cuartel General.

Subió a la azotea y esperó, con la mano contra el pecho para intentar aplacar el dolor insoportable que sentía.

—¿Qué ha pasado hoy? —le preguntó Kaine en cuanto Amaris aterrizó con pesadez sobre el tejado.

No desmontó, lo que significaba que la conversación sería breve.

Helena notaba físicamente cada segundo que pasaban separados, lo mucho que le pesaba.

—¿A qué te refieres?

—Nos han ordenado retirarnos del combate con efecto inmediato.

Los necrómatas y los aspirantes seguirán luchando, pero los inmarcesibles han sido apartados del frente.

—Un soldado mató a un liche con la obsidiana —respondió Helena—.

¿Crees que es posible que… el liche… haya muerto?

¿Que Morrough no pueda traerlo de vuelta una vez más?

Kaine guardó silencio unos segundos.

—Parece que has encontrado la forma de matarnos —dijo al fin.

No logró descifrar la emoción de su voz, pero ella sintió cómo todo su entusiasmo se desvanecía.

Había pasado mucho tiempo temiendo la inmortalidad de Kaine, consciente de que, si lo descubrían o lo apresaban, no podría escapar; lo torturarían eternamente, sin la esperanza de la muerte.

Ahora era muy probable que pudiese morir.

Ella lo había hecho posible.

No solo no lo había salvado, sino que había creado una nueva forma de perderlo.

—Ten cuidado.

Él la estaba mirando con atención.

—¿Te han dejado recuperarte antes de ponerte a trabajar otra vez?

Helena esbozó una sonrisa.

—Sí, ya no trabajo en el pabellón de emergencias.

Me han asignado una tarea menos exigente.

Kaine asintió.

—Al menos es algo.

Se hizo el silencio.

Había tantas cosas que quería decirle, tantas que contarle, pero sabía que ya se había entretenido demasiado.

—Si la obsidiana hace lo que creemos, la Llama Eterna se convertirá en una amenaza real para Morrough.

Y él reaccionará ante ello —explicó Kaine al cabo de unos instantes—.

Deberíais prepararos para eso.

Helena se limitó a asentir mientras él relajaba las riendas.

Amaris se dispuso a saltar de inmediato y el viento se levantó alrededor de sus alas.

—No mueras.

Debió de haberlo dicho en voz muy baja, porque Kaine no respondió.

CHAPTER 61

Julius 1787

CAPÍTULO 61

WHEN HELENA HAD NO RITES TO PERFORM, Crowther still kept her busy.

Julius 1787

Since she’d proven her usefulness with Mandl, he saw no reason not to continue utilising her to increase his influence and control in the Council.

Cuando Helena se quedaba sin ritos de despedida que celebrar, Crowther se aseguraba de mantenerla ocupada.

She refused to use her vivimancy for torture, experimenting with her animancy instead, trying to perfect the methods for extracting information.

Teniendo en cuenta lo útil que había sido con Mandl, él no veía motivos para no seguir aprovechándose de ella y así reforzar su posición en el Consejo.

She could not afford to fail.

Aunque Helena se negaba a emplear la vivemancia como método de tortura, se había mostrado dispuesta a experimentar con la animancia para encontrar una forma eficaz de sonsacarles información a los prisioneros.

The Helena of two years ago would not recognise the person she was becoming.

Y no podía permitirse cometer errores.

Every line she’d once believed herself incapable of crossing, she passed over without hesitation now.

La Helena de dos años atrás no habría reconocido a la persona en la que se estaba convirtiendo.

Sometimes, she pushed too far, until it felt as though she were crawling beneath a prisoner’s skin, their consciousness and her own briefly occupying the same mind-space.

Ahora cruzaba límites que jamás se habría creído capaz.

They’d grow sick with fevers afterwards, as if suffering from some kind of poisoning, but it was effective, so she overlooked the side effects, believing them manageable until Crowther told her that two of her “subjects” had died.

A veces, iba tan lejos que tenía la sensación de estar correteando bajo la piel de los prisioneros, como si su consciencia ocupara por un momento el mismo espacio mental que la de ellos.

She had never caused a death before.

Cuando eso ocurría, los prisioneros acababan enfermos, con el cerebro ardiendo, como si los hubiera envenenado.

Not like that.

Pero el procedimiento era efectivo, así que no prestó atención a las secuelas hasta que Crowther le dijo que dos de sus «sujetos de prueba» habían muerto.

She became very careful, even though Crowther considered it a waste of time and mercy.

Nunca había matado a nadie antes.

She found that brief, repeated sessions were safer than long ones, the fevers milder, as if tolerance could be developed.

No de esa forma.

And once that happened, it was even easier for her to extract what she wanted.

A partir de entonces, se volvió mucho más cuidadosa, pese a que Crowther consideraba su actitud una pérdida de tiempo y compasión.

“I think I might be able to heal Titus Bayard,” she said late one night to Shiseo.

Helena descubrió que las fiebres que sufrían eran menos virulentas cuando las sesiones eran breves pero recurrentes, como si los prisioneros desarrollaran cierta tolerancia a su poder.

The Eternal Flame had selected a new general for the Council.

Una vez alcanzado ese punto, Helena podía extraer la información que deseara con mucha más facilidad.

They’d lost so many in the bombing, the line of succession had been convoluted.

—Creo que ya sé cómo curar a Titus Bayard —le dijo una noche a Shiseo.

Hutchens had a good record, but he was too awed by Luc.

La Llama Eterna había escogido a un nuevo general para el Consejo.

Shiseo paused, looking up from an obsidian knife he was making.

Habían perdido a tantos hombres durante el bombardeo que la línea de sucesión se había truncado.

Helena drew a deep breath. “When General Bayard was injured, I didn’t understand what needed to be done—I didn’t realise that an injury like his wasn’t the same as other wounds.

Hutchens tenía un buen historial, pero se dejaba llevar demasiado por la admiración que sentía por Luc.

I had an idea earlier this year, but when I tried to test it, Titus reacted badly.

Shiseo dejó a un lado el cuchillo de obsidiana que estaba preparando y Helena respiró hondo antes de continuar:

Still.” She looked down. “With my work lately, I realised the trick is working in increments and building a tolerance.

—Cuando hirieron al general Bayard, yo no entendía qué tenía que hacer.

Once I do that, I think it could work.”

Me equivoqué al tratar la herida como si fuera cualquier otra lesión.

Shiseo tilted his head. “How?”

A principios de año ya se me había ocurrido una manera de abordar el problema, pero Titus no reaccionó bien cuando intenté ponerla a prueba.

She wet her lips. “There are paths the mind follows, thoughts and memories.

Gracias al trabajo de las últimas semanas —bajó la vista—, he caído en la cuenta de que la clave está en avanzar poco a poco para reforzar su tolerancia.

When I healed Titus, I didn’t know, and I trapped him.

Una vez que lo consiga, creo que mi idea funcionará.

It might be too late, but if I could get in, maybe I could make a way back out for him.” She swallowed awkwardly. “I do something like that to myself sometimes.

Shiseo ladeó la cabeza.

Use my resonance to alter how I think, where my mind goes.”

—¿Cómo?

Shiseo considered for a minute. “It sounds complicated.”

Helena se humedeció los labios.

She looked down. “I think I’m going to try at least.”

—Los pensamientos y los recuerdos son como caminos en la mente.

Crowther showed callous interest. “If you wish.

Como yo no lo sabía cuando curé a Titus, acabé dejándolo atrapado en su propio cerebro.

If you kill Bayard, it will spare us a mouth to feed.”

A lo mejor ya es demasiado tarde, pero tal vez pueda ofrecerle una vía de escape si consigo entrar en su cabeza. —Tragó saliva con incomodidad—.

She swallowed hard. “I’m trying to be helpful.”

Es algo que pongo en práctica en mi propia mente de vez en cuando.

His lip curled. “When I want something, Marino, I’ll tell you.”

Recurro a la resonancia para alterar mis pensamientos y darle a mi cerebro una nueva ruta.

They’d just received word that Kaine had been dispatched to Hevgoss on a diplomatic mission without warning.

—Suena complicado —dijo Shiseo tras considerarlo.

He hadn’t even had time to tell her, he’d just sent an encoded message on one of the radio channels, and then he was gone.

Helena agachó la mirada.

No goodbye.

—Creo que tengo que intentarlo.

THE ONLY THING GOING WELL was Lila’s pregnancy.

—Haz lo que consideres oportuno —intervino Crowther con cruel interés—.

Lila was bored but healthy, healthier than Helena had seen her in years.

Si matas a Bayard, pues tendremos una boca menos que alimentar.

The pregnancy showed no risk of miscarriage.

—Solo intento ayudar —replicó ella tragando saliva con fuerza.

“Are you all right?” Lila asked.

Crowther torció el gesto en un gesto desdeñoso.

Helena had her hand on Lila’s stomach, her eyes closed, trying to separate Lila’s louder heartbeat from the baby’s in an attempt to tell if it felt healthy.

—Cuando quiera que hagas algo, Marino, te lo pediré.

Foetal heartbeats were much faster, but it was confusing to sense two people simultaneously.

Acababan de enterarse de que habían enviado a Kaine a Hevgoss en una misión diplomática sin previo aviso. Él ni siquiera había podido ponerse en contacto con Helena directamente.

Helena opened her eyes, dry and burning from exhaustion.

Solo le había dado tiempo a enviar un mensaje en clave por uno de los canales de radio antes de partir sin despedirse.

“I’m fine,” she said, though she felt as if she were bleeding to death inside.

Lo único que iba bien era el embarazo de Lila, que estaba aburrida pero sana, mucho más de lo que Helena la había visto en años.

She’d seen so little of Kaine, and now he was gone and she didn’t know when he’d return.

No había motivos para temer un riesgo de aborto.

Her days were spent waiting for people to die, no longer even trying to save them.

—¿Estás bien? —le preguntó Lila a Helena, que tenía una mano puesta sobre su vientre y había cerrado los ojos para intentar distinguir el latido del bebé del de su madre y comprobar que todo estuviera bien.

Lila looked sceptical. “You don’t look fine.

La frecuencia cardiaca fetal siempre era mucho más rápida de lo normal, pero percibirla junto a la de otra persona resultaba confuso.

You don’t look like you sleep at all.

Helena abrió los ojos, secos e irritados por el cansancio.

Pace said you were badly injured.

—Sí, estoy bien —respondió, aunque tenía la sensación de estar muriéndose por dentro.

Are you recovered?

Había visto muy poco a Kaine en los últimos días y ahora se había marchado y no sabía cuándo volvería.

You know better than anyone how important full recovery is.”

Ya ni siquiera se esforzaba por salvar a la gente, solo pasaba los días esperando a que murieran.

Helena shook her head. “It’s not that.

Lila la miró escéptica.

My shifts are longer now but they’re not hard.

—Pues cualquiera lo diría, porque pareces llevar días sin dormir.

I need to go, I have—more work.”

Pace me comentó que has estado bastante malherida.

Lila spoke as she started to stand. “You don’t say it, but you think I’m selfish, don’t you?”

¿Estás ya recuperada del todo?

Helena sighed, staring down at her hands. “You’ve been through a lot; I don’t blame you for wanting something.

Tú más que nadie sabes lo importante que es sanar bien.

I just don’t understand why you want this right now.

Helena negó con la cabeza.

You should at least go to Novis where you’ll be safe.” She shrugged. “Maybe having the Principate’s heir would be enough to convince them to send some medical supplies.”

—No es por eso.

Lila had thus far refused to “come out of quarantine,” and was still pretending to be contagious with bog cough.

Los turnos que me han asignado son más largos, pero no tan duros.

“I want to wait a little longer,” Lila said. “Just to be sure.”

Tengo que irme, hay… mucho trabajo que hacer.

RHEA AND TITUS WERE WAITING in one of the private rooms.

—Sé que jamás me lo dirías, pero me consideras una egoísta, ¿verdad? —dijo Lila cuando se puso de pie.

Helena had written to Rhea, telling her that there was a possible treatment opportunity that she wanted to discuss.

Helena suspiró y se miró las manos.

“What would it entail exactly?” Rhea asked, gripping Titus by the arm to keep him from wandering.

—Has sufrido mucho, así que no te culpo por querer algo bueno en tu vida.

“It would be a series of procedures,” Helena said, rubbing her hands against her black habit, trying to get her palms dry. “It’s similar to what I tried earlier this year, but I know how to control the reaction now.

Lo que no entiendo es por qué has tomado esta decisión precisamente ahora.

If we worked slowly, with short procedures, followed by recovery periods, I think Titus will adapt to the process.

Yo que tú me marcharía a Novis, donde al menos no correrás peligro. —Se encogió de hombros—.

And then I can attempt to heal him without causing the reaction he had last time.”

Puede que tener al heredero del principado allí sirva para convencerlos de que nos envíen suministros médicos.

Rhea squeezed Titus’s hand, leaning towards Helena, her eyes bright. “So you’ve done this before?” Her voice trembled with eagerness.

Lila se había negado a dejar la «cuarentena» y todavía fingía estar presa de un brote de tos de los pantanos.

Helena cleared her throat, wanting to temper expectations. “Not this exactly.

—Quiero aguardar un poco más, solo para estar segura.

But a related procedure.

Rhea la esperaba junto con Titus en una de las salas privadas.

It’s not without risk, though.

Helena le había enviado un mensaje para decirle que quería hablar con ella sobre un posible tratamiento.

Are you familiar with mithridatism?”

—¿En qué consistiría exactamente? —le preguntó la mujer, sujetando el brazo de su marido para que no se alejara de ella.

Rhea shook her head.

—Sería un procedimiento a largo plazo —explicó Helena mientras se secaba las manos contra el hábito negro—, pero similar a lo que intentamos a principios de año.

Helena drew a deep breath. “It’s a method of developing immunity to poison through low dosage.

Ahora ya sé cómo controlarlo y, si trabajamos despacio, con intervenciones breves seguidas de periodos de recuperación, creo que Titus podría adaptarse al proceso.

The process of going deep enough to heal Titus will have—similarities; he’ll have a sort of immune response to my resonance, in the form of brain fevers.

La idea es curarlo sin provocar la reacción que tuvo la última vez.

We’ll have to monitor them, keep them under control.

Rhea estrechó la mano de Titus y se inclinó hacia Helena.

If they’re too high, we’ll have to take longer breaks.

Le brillaban los ojos.

The goal will be building up his tolerance for my resonance in the delicate parts of the brain.”

—Entonces ¿ya lo has puesto en práctica antes? —preguntó con la voz temblorosa de emoción.

That was all mostly true, with only a few details omitted.

Helena carraspeó, porque no quería darle demasiadas esperanzas.

Rhea nodded. “Yes—yes—whatever you—”

—No exactamente.

The door opened before she could finish speaking and Luc entered, followed by Sebastian.

Era un procedimiento similar.

“Rhea, what are you doing?” Luc asked, his voice breathless.

Pero te advierto que conlleva ciertos riesgos.

Rhea looked startled by the intrusion. “Helena’s found a way to heal Titus.”

¿Sabes lo que es el mitridatismo? —Rhea negó con la cabeza—.

Luc looked at Helena, his eyes hard, bright, and feverish. “You can’t be serious.”

Es una técnica que consiste en administrar dosis pequeñas de veneno con la idea de desarrollar inmunidad a él.

Helena started to answer, but it wasn’t a question and it wasn’t directed at her.

Para curar a Titus, tendré que entrar en su cerebro y el proceso será… similar, porque su sistema inmunitario responderá a mi resonancia con fiebres.

He’d turned back to Rhea.

Habrá que hacerle un seguimiento para mantener la reacción bajo control y hacer pausas más largas si le sube demasiado la temperatura.

“You’re going to trust her after what she did to Soren?”

La idea es conseguir que tolere mi resonancia en las zonas más delicadas del cerebro.

Helena flinched, her mind nearly pitching itself into that clawing wound inside her.

Aunque había omitido algunos detalles, todo lo que le había dicho era cierto.

She swallowed hard. “Luc, Soren died.

Rhea asintió.

I’m sorry I couldn’t save him, but this procedure for Titus could work.

—¡Sí!

Think of how valuable it would be to get him back.”

Sí, haz lo que consideres…

Luc looked back at her again, a look of disgust in his eyes. “That’s what this is about to you?

La mujer se interrumpió cuando Luc abrió la puerta de la sala y entró seguido de Sebastian.

Value?” He looked at Titus, who’d grown restless from the tension in the room. “You look at what you did to him, and see a wasted military asset?”

—¿Qué haces, Rhea? —le preguntó sin aliento.

“What?

—Helena ha encontrado la manera de curar a Titus —explicó ella, sorprendida por la intrusión.

No.

Luc miró a Helena con una expresión severa, intensa y febril.

That’s not what I meant.”

—No me creo que lo estés diciendo en serio. —Helena se dispuso a contestar, pero no le estaba hablando a ella.

He stared at her again, his eyes blistering as sunburn. “You lay as much as a finger on him, and I’ll—”

Se había vuelto a mirar a Rhea—.

“She won’t,” Rhea said, breaking in. “Thank you, Helena—Healer Marino, I appreciate the offer, but I think we’ll pass.”

¿De verdad confías en ella después de lo que le hizo a Soren?

Luc gave a sharp nod and then turned on his heel, walking out without a backwards glance.

Helena se estremeció y su mente estuvo a punto de lanzarse de cabeza al interior de esa dolorosa herida que aún estaba abierta en su interior.

Sebastian wavered, looking at Rhea and Titus, his expression conflicted before he turned, following Luc.

Tragó saliva con fuerza.

When they were gone, Rhea’s face crumpled, and she gave an audible gasp before pressing her face in her hands.

—Soren murió, Luc.

Helena could find no words.

Siento en el alma no haber podido salvarlo, pero este procedimiento podría funcionar.

She sat numb with shock as Rhea stood, not looking at Helena as she led Titus out.

Piensa en lo que significaría tener a Titus de vuelta.

Once she was alone, Helena pulled her gloves on and headed for the Alchemy Tower.

Luc la miró de nuevo con desagrado.

When the lift opened, she was surprised when Sebastian stepped out alone, a weary expression on his face.

—¿Eso es lo que te importa?

He paused, resting a hand on her shoulder. “It was good of you to try.”

¿Cuánto puede valer alguien para la causa? —Miró a Titus, que se había puesto nervioso al percibir la tensión en el ambiente—.

Helena couldn’t quite bring herself to look at him.

¿Es que acaso solo lo ves como un efectivo militar echado a perder después de lo que le hiciste?

She stared at his chest, at the suncrest on his armour.

—¿Qué?

“Why is he doing this?” she asked. “Everyone understands.

No, eso no es lo que quería decir.

Even if they think it was wrong, they understand.

La mirada de Luc era tan abrasadora como un sol ardiente.

He won’t even try.”

—Como le pongas un solo dedo encima, te juro que…

Sebastian sighed. “You know why.”

—No lo hará —intervino Rhea—.

She wasn’t sure that she did, but she nodded and stepped into the lift.

Gracias, Helena…, es decir, sanadora Marino, aprecio la oferta, pero creo que será mejor dejarlo.

There were three guards stationed outside Luc’s door, and they shook their heads when she approached.

Luc asintió bruscamente, se giró sobre los talones y se marchó sin mirar atrás.

She went to her own room and climbed out the window, walking carefully up and around the low slope.

Sebastian les dirigió una última mirada indecisa a Rhea y a Titus antes de salir tras él.

Luc’s hair gleamed golden in the setting sun.

En cuanto se retiraron, Rhea se desmoronó con un jadeo y se cubrió el rostro con las manos.

He was sitting hunched on his heels, twirling something in his fingers.

Helena se había quedado sin palabras.

He brought it up to his mouth, flames sparking in his fingertips as he inhaled.

Aturdida por la conmoción, vio que Rhea se incorporaba sin mirarla y sacaba a Titus de la sala.

His whole body seemed to come loose, and he sagged in on himself.

Una vez sola, Helena se puso los guantes y se dirigió hacia la Torre de Alquimia, pero se encontró a Sebastian esperándola dentro del ascensor.

Watching, she was reminded of how soft his face used to be, the brightness of it.

Para su sorpresa, había regresado solo y parecía alicaído.

Now the war had chewed him down to the bone.

Tras una breve pausa, le tocó el hombro a Helena.

He sat there, out of armour, so shrivelled he reminded her of an insect exoskeleton, like the shed dragonfly nymphs that clung to the water reeds.

—Te honra haberlo intentado.

He was hollowed out.

Helena no fue capaz de mirarlo a la cara, así que clavó la vista en su pecho, en el blasón solar que decoraba su armadura.

Smoke curled from his lips as he slowly exhaled.

—¿Por qué me está haciendo esto? —preguntó—.

He was smoking opium.

Todo el mundo lo ha entendido.

She stared in horror at how casually he did so.

Incluso quienes consideran que me equivoqué.

As though it were an old habit.

Luc ni siquiera ha intentado ponerse en mi lugar.

He pulled the pipe from his mouth, catching sight of her.

Sebastian suspiró.

His expression hardened, growing more alert. “Go away.”

—Ya sabes por qué.

“No,” she said, and came closer.

No estaba segura de saberlo, pero asintió y entró en el ascensor.

He spun the pipe in his fingers again, his jaw rippling with anger.

Cuando se acercó a la habitación de Luc, los tres guardias que vigilaban la puerta negaron con la cabeza al unísono en cuanto la vieron, así que Helena regresó a su propio dormitorio, salió por la ventana y recorrió la suave pendiente del tejado para rodear el edificio.

If he hit her again, she’d probably fall from the Tower and die.

El cabello rubio de Luc resplandecía bajo la luz del atardecer.

She stood only a few steps away. “I couldn’t save him.

Estaba sentado sobre los talones, encorvado, y le daba vueltas a algo entre los dedos.

Even if I’d killed myself trying, it wouldn’t have been enough.

Se llevó el objeto a los labios y una llamita le iluminó las yemas de los dedos cuando inhaló.

What is it you wish I’d done instead?”

Dejó caer los hombros y todo su cuerpo pareció relajarse.

Rather than answer, he shook like an autumn leaf on the verge of falling loose.

Mientras lo observaba, Helena pensó en lo dulce y alegre que había sido su rostro.

He seemed to be trying to speak, but at the same time his hand was bringing the pipe back to his lips, fingers sparking a feeble flame.

La guerra lo había carcomido hasta los huesos.

He inhaled so long that when he stopped, the pipe nearly tumbled from his fingers.

Allí sentado, sin su armadura, estaba tan consumido que le recordaba al exoesqueleto de un insecto, como las mudas que las libélulas dejaban en los juncos tras la metamorfosis.

She feared he’d fall, and knelt to catch him, but he looked up, meeting her eyes, and he—he didn’t look angry anymore, he just looked exhausted.

Ya no quedaba nada de él en su interior.

“What happened to us, Hel?”

Luc exhaló lentamente y unas volutas de humo escaparon de entre sus labios.

She stared at him, and her pathetic, starved heart leapt for a moment before she realised the obvious.

Era opio.

This wasn’t Luc; this was the opium talking.

Fumaba como si llevara haciéndolo toda la vida, con una indiferencia que a Helena le resultó espantosa.

“A war.” She looked away from him to the ruined city before them.

Luc se apartó la pipa de los labios al verla.

A view which had once been so beautiful.

Su expresión se endureció, se hizo más afilada.

“You used to believe in me,” he said, his voice faraway. “What did I do that made you stop?”

—Vete.

“I still believe in you, Luc,” she said. “But we have to win this war.

—No —replicó ella acercándose.

We can’t make choices because we want a certain story to tell later.

Él volvió a darle vueltas a la pipa entre los dedos mientras apretaba los dientes con rabia.

There’s too much at stake.”

Si la golpeaba, era muy probable que Helena cayera de la Torre y muriera.

“No,” he said. “This is how we win.

Se detuvo a unos cuantos pasos de él.

This is how we’ve always won.

—No pude salvarlo.

My father, and grandfather, all the Principates going all the way back to Orion.

Ni muriendo yo misma en el intento habría podido hacerlo.

They won by trusting that good would triumph over evil, and I will do the same.”

¿Habrías preferido que hubiera sido así?

She looked at him in despair.

En vez de responder, Luc tembló como una hoja seca a punto de caer de su rama.

His index finger flicked against his thumb, ignition rings sparking, and again fire filled his palm, running along his fingers.

Parecía estar tratando de decir algo, pero se llevó la pipa a los labios y la prendió con una débil llamita.

He cradled the flames like a kitten before his fingers closed around it, leaving only a tongue as he tucked the opium pipe between his lips and brought the flame close to the bowl again.

Inhaló durante tanto rato que la pipa estuvo a punto de escurrírsele de entre los dedos.

Her hand clenched into a fist, fighting a wince as she listened to him inhaling.

Helena se arrodilló junto a Luc, por miedo a que se cayera del tejado, pero entonces él levantó la vista, encontró su mirada y ya… ya no parecía enfadado, sino agotado.

“What if it’s not that simple, though?” she said. “Everyone who wins says they were good, but they’re the ones who tell the story.

—¿Qué nos ha pasado, Hel?

They get to choose how we all remember it.

Ella lo miró y su corazón, hambriento y falto de cariño, dio un vuelco cuando comprendió lo evidente: no era Luc el que hablaba, sino el opio.

What if it’s never that simple?”

—Una guerra.

He shook his head. “Orion became sun-blessed because he refused to break his faith.”

Desvió la vista hacia el paisaje en ruinas que se extendía ante ellos.

Helena exhaled, burying her face in her hands.

Hubo un tiempo en que la ciudad había sido hermosa.

She heard his rings spark, and the pipe hissed as the opium vaporised.

—Antes creías en mí —dijo con voz distante—.

“Luc—please, let me help you.” She tried to reach towards him.

¿Qué he hecho para que dejes de hacerlo?

He flinched away, rage suddenly flashing across his face. “Don’t—touch me.”

—Sigo creyendo en ti, Luc.

He was teetering dangerously close to that immense fall, as if the Abyss still called to him.

Pero tenemos que ganar esta guerra; no podemos tomar decisiones basándonos en la historia que queremos contar luego.

She didn’t know how to draw him back anymore, what to say that he’d still hear.

Hay demasiado en juego.

“Do you remember what I promised you, Luc, that night you came out here?” she asked, her voice pleading.

—No —replicó Luc—.

He gave no response.

Así ganaremos.

His gaze had settled back into a dim stupor, the sunset limning his gaunt features as though gilding him.

Así hemos ganado siempre.

“I promised I’d do anything for you.” She curled her fingers into a fist. “Maybe you didn’t realise how far I was willing to go.”

Así ganaron mi padre, mi abuelo y todos los principados hasta el mismísimo Orion.

“Don’t say that,” he said, suddenly alert again. “Don’t make it all my fault.

Todos ganaron confiando en que el bien siempre vence al mal, y yo he de hacer lo mismo.

I thought you could heal him.”

Helena lo miró angustiada y él chasqueó los dedos para activar sus anillos de ignición.

She closed her eyes. “Sometimes people die.

Dejó que el fuego le lamiera la palma de la mano, que le corriera por los dedos, y lo acunó como si fuera un gatito.

You can’t save everyone.

Cerró el puño en torno a él y lo convirtió en una única llama antes de llevarse la pipa a los labios para prenderla una vez más.

Neither of us can.

Helena apretó el puño y reprimió un estremecimiento cuando lo oyó inspirar hondo.

Please let me try to heal Titus.”

—Pero ¿qué pasará si no es así de simple? —insistió—.

“I can’t.” He stood, stumbled down onto the balcony of his room, and disappeared.

Todos los que ganan dicen que ellos fueron los buenos, pero en realidad son los que cuentan la historia.

IT HAD BEEN OVER TWO weeks with no word when Helena’s ring finally burned again.

Ellos deciden cómo recordarla.

She ran out of Headquarters without a backwards glance.

¿Y si nunca fue tan simple?

When she reached the rooftop and saw Kaine already there, standing beside Amaris, her knees nearly gave out.

Luc negó con la cabeza.

He was in uniform, clean and polished, wearing a row of medals as if he’d just come from a ceremony.

—Orion fue bendecido por el sol porque se negó a renunciar a su fe.

“You’re back.” It was all she could manage to say, already reaching out for him when he was still steps away.

Helena suspiró exasperada y enterró la cara entre las manos.

He pulled her into his arms. “Have you been all right?”

Oyó un chisporroteo seguido del siseo de la pipa al evaporarse el opio.

She managed a nod but then her head dropped against his chest, and she was so tired, her eyes closed, listening to his heart, legs threatening to give out.

—Luc…, por favor, déjame ayudarte. —Ella hizo amago de acercarse.

He’d come back.

Él se apartó y un inesperado destello de rabia le surcó el rostro.

She couldn’t ask for more than that, but it had felt so long.

—No… me toques.

As if every minute of his absence had cut into her.

Estaba acercándose peligrosamente al borde de una caída descomunal, como si lo estuviera llamando el abismo.

“What’s wrong?” he finally asked.

Helena ya no sabía cómo hacerle entrar en razón ni qué decir para que la escuchara.

Everything.

—¿Te acuerdas de lo que te prometí la noche que viniste aquí, Luc? —le preguntó en tono suplicante.

“Nothing,” she said. “I think I forgot to breathe after you left.”

Luc no respondió.

He wrapped his arms around her shoulders again, but he was tense, his attention elsewhere.

Tenía la mirada perdida; el atardecer delineaba sus rasgos demacrados como si los cubriera de oro.

Dread seeped through her like blood in water.

—Te prometí que haría lo que fuera por ti. —Cerró el puño—.

She lifted her head. “What is it?”

Tal vez no entendiste hasta dónde estaba dispuesta a llegar.

He wasn’t looking at her; he was staring towards the blazing light of the Alchemy Tower. “I’m sure you realised: My trip was a diplomatic mission.

—No digas eso —le pidió como si hubiera recuperado una repentina lucidez—.

We went to establish a formal alliance with Hevgoss, proprietary alchemical research in exchange for their mercenary forces.”

No hagas como si toda la culpa fuera mía.

“We guessed it was that.”

Pensaba que podrías curarlo.

“The new Hevgotian ambassador is—partial to my company.

Ella cerró los ojos.

Keeping him entertained is my primary responsibility for the moment.

—A veces, la gente muere.

Does Crowther have any outstanding orders?”

Ni tú ni yo ni nadie podemos salvar a todo el mundo, pero te pido por favor que me dejes intentar curar a Titus.

She shook her head. “No.

—No puedo.

We’ve been waiting to see what happened.

Luc se puso en pie, bajó con torpeza hasta el balcón de su dormitorio y desapareció.

He’ll want a report, but that’s all for now.”

Llevaba dos semanas sin tener noticias de Kaine cuando, al fin, el anillo se calentó.

His eyes narrowed. “There’s nothing?” There was a tension in his voice.

Helena salió corriendo del Cuartel General sin mirar atrás y, al llegar al tejado y ver a Kaine esperándola allí junto a Amaris, estuvieron a punto de fallarle las piernas.

“Not yet.

En su uniforme impoluto llevaba una hilera de medallas, como si acabara de participar en algún acto oficial.

You just got back.”

—Has vuelto —fue lo único que consiguió decir mientras extendía los brazos antes de haber llegado a su lado siquiera.

Rather than look relieved, his eyes got that strained look that appeared when he was sure she was injured and he just didn’t know; he drew back, looking her over. “What happened?”

Kaine la atrajo hacia sí para abrazarla.

She furrowed her eyebrows, shaking her head. “Nothing.”

—¿Todo bien estas últimas semanas?

He didn’t believe her, she could tell.

Helena se las arregló para asentir, pero acabó apoyando la cabeza contra su pecho.

Panic was creeping across his features.

Estaba tan agotada que cerró los ojos, creyendo por un instante que desfallecería mientras escuchaba los latidos de su corazón.

She wished she’d come up with some errand for him; he was clearly certain that something must have happened to her for him to be given any reprieve.

Había vuelto.

She sighed and caught his hand.

No podía pedir más.

“After Althorne and Ilva died, I told Crowther that you were being overutilised, and I made him agree not to put so much on you.”

Pero tenía la sensación de que había pasado una eternidad, como si cada minuto de su ausencia le hubiera abierto una herida.

He scoffed. “And he just agreed to that?”

—¿Algo va mal? —preguntó él al cabo de un momento.

“No.

Todo.

I made a deal with him.

—Nada —dijo ella—.

Because of the obsidian and the Council being less stable, he’s vulnerable, he needs someone, and I told him that could be me, but only if I got to approve your orders from now on.”

Es que creo que dejé de respirar cuando te marchaste.

Instead of looking relieved, he snatched his hand away from her.

Kaine le pasó los brazos por los hombros de nuevo, aunque con rigidez, como si su mente estuviera en otra parte.

“You did what?” He spat the question. “You thought that would help me?

El miedo se extendió por las venas de Helena como la sangre por el agua.

That is the last thing I want.”

Levantó la cabeza.

A stab of exhausted, furious hurt cut through her. “Why?

—¿Qué pasa?

Is protection exclusively your right?

Kaine no la estaba mirando, sino que tenía la vista clavada en la luz cegadora de la Torre de Alquimia.

Am I supposed to sit around while you win the war for me?

—Imagino que ya lo sabrás, pero el viaje ha sido una misión diplomática.

Is that how you see this?” She gestured furiously between them.

Nos enviaron a Hevgoss para formalizar una alianza.

“That was the deal,” he snapped.

Llevaremos a cabo una investigación alquímica en su nombre a cambio de que nos apoyen con los mercenarios que luchan entre sus filas.

“Well, I didn’t agree to that.

—Sí, ya lo suponía.

Besides, I’m not doing anything dangerous.

—El nuevo embajador hevgotiano me ha… cogido cariño.

I’m not even allowed to go outside anymore.”

Mi principal responsabilidad ahora es mantenerlo entretenido.

He stared at her, enraged.

¿Queda alguna orden de Crowther pendiente por cumplir?

“Kaine—don’t be like this.”

Helena negó con la cabeza.

He didn’t budge.

—No, estábamos esperando a ver qué ocurría.

The space between them was ice-cold, as though all their ghosts surrounded them.

Querrá un informe, pero eso es todo por el momento.

They were both drenched in the dead.

Kaine la miró con suspicacia.

The war was an abyss that took everything and was never satisfied.

—¿Nada más? —En su voz se notaba cierta tensión.

There was always more required.

—No, nada más.

Another life.

Piensa que acabas de volver.

An additional measure of blood.

En vez de mostrarse aliviado, adoptó esa expresión tensa que se adueñaba de su rostro cuando tenía la certeza de que Helena no estaba bien y él no sabía por qué.

Be better.

Dio un paso atrás y la estudió de arriba abajo.

Smarter.

—¿Qué ha pasado?

More ruthless.

Ella lo miró desconcertada y negó con la cabeza.

Quicker.

—Nada.

More cunning.

Helena sabía que no la creía, pues el miedo se abrió paso por sus facciones.

Accept a second portion of pain.

Le habría gustado tener alguna tarea que encargarle; estaba claro que Kaine pensaba que le daban esa tregua porque a ella le había pasado algo.

It was never enough.

Finalmente, suspiró y le cogió la mano.

Helena had nothing left to sacrifice.

—Después de que Althorne e Ilva murieran, le dije a Crowther que estaban abusando de tu colaboración y le pedí que bajara un poco el ritmo.

Everything remaining would cost too much to lose.

—¿Y él accedió sin más? —resopló incrédulo.

Yet she was expected to be docile and cooperative, a comforting possession, and she was not.

—No, hice un trato con él.

She swallowed bitterly. “What did you expect me to do?”

Lo de la obsidiana y la inestabilidad en el Consejo lo han dejado en una posición vulnerable.

“I don’t want you in this fucking war.” The rage in his voice was raw. “All I do is worry about what will happen to you if I fail to meet all requirements.

Como necesitaba a alguien de su lado, le dije que yo lo apoyaría con la condición de que me deje supervisar tus misiones de ahora en adelante.

If you get captured, you have no idea what they’ll—”

En vez de mostrarse aliviado, Kaine se liberó de su agarre.

“I do know,” she snapped, cutting him off. “What do you think I do with all my time?

—¿Por qué has hecho eso? —escupió—.

I heal the people the Undying don’t manage to kill.

¿En qué momento pensaste que eso me ayudaría?

Everyone—everyone from the lab near the East Port, I treated them—watched them die.

Es lo último que quiero.

They all died.

Un pinchazo de dolor, cansancio y rabia la atravesó.

I am so aware of the risks, I think sometimes that I will go mad from knowing them.

—¿Por qué?

Why do you think I fight so hard?”

¿Me vas a decir que solo tú tienes el derecho de proteger a las personas que te importan?

Her voice splintered.

¿Se supone que debo quedarme de brazos cruzados mientras ganas la guerra por mí?

She turned away, despair clawing through her.

¿Es así como ves lo nuestro? —Hizo un gesto furioso señalando el espacio entre los dos.

She’d told herself that it would all be better once he was back.

—Ese era el trato.

That she’d breathe again.

—Yo nunca accedí a eso.

But all she felt was renewed terror, the feeling that everything was crumbling, and she couldn’t stop it until she was left living every second bracing herself, unable to enjoy even the moments they had.

Además, no estoy haciendo nada peligroso.

“I’ll tell Crowther you’re back.” Her voice was empty. “And let you know what he wants.”

Ya ni siquiera me dejan salir del Cuartel General.

She wanted to vanish.

Kaine la miró furioso.

She was so tired of everything, of begging him not to get caught, not to die, to come back to her.

—Venga…, no seas así —le suplicó Helena.

Of trying to convince herself that a promise meant anything in a war like this.

Pero Kaine no dio su brazo a torcer.

“Be careful,” she said.

Un muro gélido los separaba, como si todos sus fantasmas se hubieran congregado de repente a su alrededor.

He caught her by the arm. “Wait.

La muerte los había calado hasta los huesos.

Don’t go.”

La guerra era un abismo insaciable que se lo tragaba todo.

She shook her head. “Kaine—I’m so tired—I don’t want to fight.”

Siempre quería más: otra vida, un poco más de sangre.

“We won’t.” He was looking at her more closely now. “Come with me.

Los obligaba a ser mejores, más listos, implacables, rápidos y calculadores.

You’re worked to death.

A aceptar otra dosis de dolor.

They can spare you for a night.

Nada era suficiente.

We won’t fight.”

Pero Helena ya no quería sacrificar más; lo que le quedaba era demasiado valioso como para perderlo.

She managed to nod.

Aun así, de ella se esperaba que fuera dócil, que cooperara, que fuera un trofeo capaz de ofrecer consuelo cuando la realidad era muy distinta.

The flight was a dull haze; she barely felt the wind.

Tragó saliva con amargura.

She was half asleep when Amaris landed.

—¿Qué esperabas que hiciera?

Kaine carried her inside and laid her on the bed.

—¡No quiero que te involucres en esta puta guerra! —exclamó Kaine con la voz rota por la rabia—.

She felt him pulling off her shoes, and then he sat on the edge of the mattress, his hand resting between her shoulders.

Me paso las horas temiendo lo que podría ocurrirte si no cumplo con mi cometido.

He was safe.

Si me capturan, no te haces una idea de lo que…

He had come back.

—Lo sé perfectamente —lo interrumpió sin miramientos—.

She roused the instant his hand withdrew.

¿Qué te crees que hago yo todo el tiempo?

He paused. “I need to eat and wash.”

Yo soy quien se encarga de curar a todas las personas que los inmarcesibles no consiguen matar.

She caught his hand, gripping it so tight her nails bit into his skin. “I was afraid you’d die.

Yo traté… traté a los prisioneros que encontraron en el laboratorio del puerto Este y… tuve que verlos a todos morir.

You said you couldn’t leave without special arrangements, and you were gone so suddenly, I thought—you might not come back.” Her voice was thick. “You’re always in danger, and I can never ask you to stop.”

A todos.

He ran his thumb across her knuckles. “You know I would if I could.

Soy tan consciente de los riesgos que corremos que a veces pienso que van a acabar volviéndome loca.

I’d run with you and never look back.”

¿Por qué crees si no que me esfuerzo tanto?

“I know—” Her voice broke. “Don’t die, Kaine.

Se le quebró la voz y se dio la vuelta mientras la desesperación la devoraba por dentro.

You can’t leave me behind.”

Se había repetido que todo mejoraría cuando Kaine regresara, que podría respirar tranquila de nuevo.

He sank back down beside her, and didn’t leave until she stopped crying and fell asleep.

Pero lo único que sentía era un renovado pavor; tenía la sensación de que todo se desmoronaba a su alrededor sin que ella pudiera hacer nada para detenerlo.

When the bed dipped, she woke to find him on the far side of the mattress.

Acabaría pasando cada segundo de su vida preparándose para lo peor, incapaz de disfrutar siquiera de los momentos que compartiera con Kaine.

His hair was damp and hung over his eyes.

—Avisaré a Crowther de tu regreso. —Habló con tono desprovisto de emoción—.

She shifted across the bed and into his arms, burying herself there, letting her eyes close as she traced her fingers across his skin.

Y te diré lo que quiere.

She would know him blind.

Deseó desaparecer.

He caught her hand and rolled her under him.

Estaba harta de todo, de suplicarle que tuviera cuidado de no dejarse atrapar, que no muriera, que regresara con ella.

He studied her, that ever-present grief visible in his eyes, until she lifted her head and kissed him.

Estaba harta de tratar de convencerse a sí misma de que una promesa significaba algo en una guerra como aquella.

His hand slid up to wrap around her throat, and his thumb nestled under her jaw.

—Ten cuidado.

A gradual, deepening kiss.

—Espera. —Kaine la agarró del brazo—.

She laced her fingers through his silver-white hair.

No te vayas.

She never thought she could know a person with such slow intimacy.

Helena negó con la cabeza.

She knew exactly how he would press his lips against the pulse-point of her throat, the way his body shifted when she was beneath him.

—Estoy muy cansada… No quiero que nos peleemos.

The grip of his hands on her hips, his teeth grazing her inner thighs, and the heat of his tongue.

—No lo haremos. —Ahora la miraba con más atención—.

“Mine.

Ven conmigo.

You’re mine,” he said as he kissed her.

Te has dejado la piel trabajando y no les pasará nada por prescindir una noche de ti.

“Always.”

Te prometo que no nos pelearemos.

Helena asintió con esfuerzo.

El tiempo se le pasó como un borrón a lomos de Amaris; de hecho, casi ni notó el viento.

Estaba medio dormida cuando la quimera aterrizó, así que Kaine la llevó en brazos hasta la cama.

Le quitó los zapatos, se sentó en el borde del colchón y le puso una mano entre los omoplatos.

Kaine estaba a salvo.

Había vuelto.

Helena se despertó en cuanto apartó la mano.

—Tengo que comer algo y darme una ducha —explicó el chico tras una breve pausa.

Ella le cogió la mano y se la estrechó con tanta fuerza que le clavó las uñas en la piel.

—Tuve miedo de que murieras.

Dijiste que no podías marcharte sin una serie de preparativos, pero desapareciste de un momento a otro y pensé… pensé que no volverías. —Tenía la voz pastosa—.

Te expones a un peligro tras otro y no puedo pedirte que pares de hacerlo.

—Ya sabes que lo dejaría todo si estuviera en mi mano —dijo acariciándole los nudillos con el pulgar—.

Huiría contigo sin mirar atrás.

—Lo sé… —Se le rompió la voz—.

No mueras, Kaine.

No me dejes.

Kaine se tumbó a su lado y no se movió hasta que Helena dejó de llorar y se quedó dormida.

Cuando el colchón volvió a hundirse, Helena se despertó y lo encontró al otro lado de la cama, con el cabello húmedo pegado a la frente.

Se acurrucó entre sus brazos y cerró los ojos mientras deslizaba los dedos por su piel.

Lo reconocería incluso a ciegas.

Kaine, por su parte, le cogió la mano, hizo que se tumbara de espaldas y se inclinó sobre ella para observarla con esa tristeza indeleble tan suya, hasta que Helena levantó la cabeza y lo besó. Él subió la mano hasta rodearle el cuello, apoyando su pulgar bajo la mandíbula, y profundizó el beso lentamente.

Helena le enterró los dedos entre los mechones plateados.

Nunca había imaginado que llegaría a conocer a una persona de una forma tan íntima.

Sabía que Kaine le besaría ese punto del cuello donde su pulso era más visible.

Reconocía la forma en que su cuerpo se movía al inclinarse sobre ella, el contacto de sus manos en las caderas, la caricia de sus dientes en la cara interna de los muslos y el calor de su lengua.

—Eres mía.

Solo mía —le dijo mientras la besaba.

—Ahora y siempre.

CHAPTER 62

Augustus 1787

CAPÍTULO 62

NEWS OF THE UNDYING’S ALLIANCE WITH HEVGOSS was of no surprise.

Augustus 1787

Letters were dispatched to the surrounding countries, urging them to object, to pressure Hevgoss into withdrawing, but there was little response.

Descubrir que los inmarcesibles se habían aliado con Hevgoss no fue ninguna sorpresa.

Even Novis was slow to reply and tepid in their condemnation.

Se enviaron misivas a los países vecinos para animarlos a oponerse y presionar a Hevgoss para que se retractara, pero apenas obtuvieron respuesta por su parte.

“Let’s focus on the bright side: This alliance with Hevgoss is a clear sign that our obsidian offensive is having an effect,” General Hutchens said with casual assurance to the assembled members of the Eternal Flame.

Incluso Novis tardó en responder mostrando su repulsa sin mucha convicción.

On paper, Hutchens had an excellent record—he’d been in command of the ports and only given them up after the bombing because the Resistance couldn’t maintain control of them without leaving Headquarters vulnerable.

—Centrémonos en la parte positiva.

Not only had Hutchens managed to extensively sabotage the ports prior to retreating, but he’d done it with almost no casualties.

La alianza con Hevgoss demuestra que recurrir a la obsidiana ha funcionado —dijo el general Hutchens dirigiéndose al resto de los miembros de la Llama Eterna con tono despreocupado.

He was a good choice, but he was also a true believer in Luc and Sol and the Eternal Flame, and his confidence in their eventual victory was implicit.

En teoría, Hutchens tenía un historial intachable: había estado al mando de la zona portuaria y habría conseguido defenderla del bombardeo si la falta de recursos no hubiera obligado a la Resistencia a renunciar a ella para evitar poner en riesgo el Cuartel General.

Details like supplies and the humdrum labour of war tended to fall beneath his consideration.

Pese a todo, antes de iniciar la retirada, se había asegurado de sabotear los muelles sin apenas causar bajas.

Sol would provide.

Hicieron bien en contar con él, aunque, como buen devoto de Luc, Sol y la Llama Eterna, tenía una fe ciega en que la victoria estaba asegurada.

Crowther could not and did not trust him, and it was creating an ever-widening gap between the true circumstances of the war and how Hutchens and the rest of the Council understood them.

Tal era su confianza en que Sol proveería que solía pasar por alto el aprovisionamiento o las tareas más rutinarias.

“What we need to do is increase our obsidian supply and hit them hard before the Hevgotian mercenaries arrive.”

Crowther no podía ni quería confiar en él, por lo que cada vez había una mayor disonancia entre las circunstancias reales de la guerra y la visión que Hutchens y el resto de los miembros del Consejo tenían del conflicto.

Helena wanted to throw up at the mere thought of producing more obsidian.

—Lo que debemos hacer es acumular más obsidiana y atacarlos sin piedad antes de que lleguen los mercenarios hevgotianos.

Even if she could, only so many people died in circumstances in which she could be present.

A Helena se le revolvió el estómago solo de pensar en producir más obsidiana.

“We lost more than half of our forces and territory the last time we were about to perform a similar offensive.” With all the upheaval in the Council, Crowther was forced to speak for himself, and even when his comments were pertinent, he lacked the charisma to make anyone agree with him. “While I am optimistic about the effect of our obsidian, there is a risk that Hevgotian mercenaries means more nullium usage.

Aunque pudiera, ya había alcanzado el límite de muertes que era capaz de presenciar.

Hevgoss has few alchemists; the battalions arriving will be from the prisons.”

—Perdimos más de la mitad de nuestras fuerzas y de nuestro territorio la última vez que intentamos llevar a cabo una ofensiva similar. —Con la inestabilidad que reinaba en el Consejo, Crowther se estaba viendo obligado a intervenir más de lo acostumbrado y, si bien sus observaciones eran acertadas, carecía del carisma necesario para conseguir convencer a los demás de que se pusieran de su lado—.

Hutchens shook his head. “I doubt we’ll see more nullium.

Aunque confío en el efecto de la obsidiana, hay que tener en cuenta que corremos el riesgo de que la llegada de los mercenarios vaya acompañada de un aumento en el uso de anulitio.

I don’t think they can afford to blow up any more territory.

Hevgoss no dispone de muchos alquimistas y enviarán a sus tropas desde las prisiones.

The dust affected the West Island, too.”

Hutchens negó con la cabeza.

“We’ll plan better this time,” Luc said.

—No creo que los inmarcesibles vuelvan a recurrir al anulitio, porque no pueden permitirse perder más territorio.

He had a certain tone that he used in meetings now.

Y recordemos que el polvo residual ha afectado también a la isla Oeste.

It was deeper, more authoritative.

—Esta vez nos aseguraremos de pulir nuestra estrategia a fondo —intervino Luc.

In the past he’d speak tentatively unless riled. “Regardless of what happened in the past, we can’t afford to lose more.

En las últimas reuniones había adoptado un tono distinto al hablar, más grave y autoritario.

The Undying have never wanted living soldiers before.

A no ser que lo sacaran de sus casillas, antes solía mostrarse mucho más inseguro—.

This change in tactics is an undeniable sign that we’re doing something right.

Independientemente de cómo hayamos llegado hasta aquí, creo que estaremos todos de acuerdo en que no podemos permitirnos perder más batallas.

Ask anyone who’s been in combat lately—they’ve pulled all the Undying out, living and lich alike, it’s all necrothralls and Aspirants.

Los inmarcesibles nunca habían querido contar con soldados vivos hasta ahora, así que yo interpreto este cambio de estrategia como una prueba indiscutible de que estamos haciendo algo bien.

The obsidian’s changed everything.

Preguntad a cualquiera que haya estado en el frente últimamente.

Negotiating for an alliance is an admission they can’t win on their own.

Hemos conseguido derrotar a inmarcesibles vivos, liches, necrómatas y aspirantes por igual.

I’m with Hutchens, I say we hit them hard.

La obsidiana ha cambiado el rumbo de la guerra.

The Undying are trying to go to ground; we’ll dig them out.”

Con esta alianza, están admitiendo que no se ven capaces de ganar solos.

“Even if it were possible to win so decisively, there’s still the risk of Hevgoss trying to sweep in and collect the spoils of war regardless of which side emerges victor,” Crowther said. “This may be the time to negotiate with Novis.

Coincido con Hutchens: vayamos con todo a por ellos.

Reticent as they’ve been in recent months, I doubt the queen is pleased by the threat of Hevgoss obtaining Paladia’s resources.

Los sacaremos de su escondrijo a la fuerza.

With the right incentives, she may renew her support.

—Aunque fuera posible asegurar nuestra victoria de una manera tan decisiva, hay que tener en cuenta que Hevgoss podría intentar salir ganando sin importar qué bando gane —apuntó Crowther—.

Perhaps a high-profile diplomatic visit as a show of respect—”

Quizá haya llegado el momento de negociar con Novis.

“I’m not leaving Paladia,” Luc said, cutting Crowther off with a look of overt disdain. “You think it would inspire confidence in our troops if they see me leave on a diplomatic mission amid rumours about reinforcements coming from Hevgoss?”

Por muy reticentes que se hayan mostrado en estos últimos meses, no creo que a la reina le haga ninguna gracia que Hevgoss se quede con los recursos de Paladia.

Crowther’s eyebrows pinched together. “You would be the most effective negotiator.

Con el incentivo adecuado, es posible que vuelva a apoyarnos.

Your appearance in the Novis court would be a greater compliment than any other resources or representatives we could afford to send.

Tal vez convenga que el principado les haga una visita diplomática para mostrar nuestro respeto y…

Any proxy would—”

—No pienso salir de Paladia —lo interrumpió Luc sin molestarse en disimular el desprecio que Crowther despertaba en él—.

“It’s out of the question.

¿Cómo se supone que voy a inspirar confianza a nuestras tropas si me embarco en una misión diplomática mientras se rumorea que Hevgoss va a apoyar a los inmarcesibles?

If you want to send someone to Novis, by all means.

Crowther frunció el ceño.

But I’m not leaving Paladia.” There was furious vehemence in Luc’s voice.

—La negociación sería mucho más efectiva si acudís vos en persona.

Helena had known that Crowther intended to make such a proposal.

Ningún recurso o representante que pudiéramos permitirnos enviar a la corte de Novis se entendería como una muestra de respeto tan grande como vuestra presencia, principado.

He’d even weighed the possibility of revealing Lila’s pregnancy, trying to coerce Luc into taking the trip under the pretence of escorting her and his “heir” to safety.

Cualquier otro delegado no…

However, Lila was still adamant about concealing the pregnancy.

—No es negociable.

To reveal it in the context of her fleeing to Novis would be a dangerous gamble.

Si quieres enviar a alguien a Novis, me parece bien, pero yo no pienso irme de aquí —sentenció Luc con una rabiosa vehemencia.

In the end, it was Matias who went, along with a box of gold that Luc transmuted.

Helena ya sabía que Crowther tenía intención de presentar aquella propuesta.

It wasn’t what anyone wanted, but as Helena watched Matias ceremonially depart, an old knot in her chest unravelled at seeing him gone.

Había considerado utilizar el embarazo de Lila para coaccionar a Luc y obligarlo a desplazarse hasta Novis con la intención de escoltar a la joven y a su «heredero» a un lugar seguro.

He was barely across the border before the Resistance was readying for battle.

Sin embargo, Lila se había negado en redondo a hacer público su embarazo, así que sacarlo a la luz en aquella reunión habría sido una jugada demasiado arriesgada.

It was suicide.

Al final, fue Matias quien viajó al reino vecino con un cofre de oro transmutado por Luc.

They didn’t have the combatants or nearly enough resources for it.

Nadie quedó satisfecho con la decisión, pero, cuando Helena lo vio partir ceremoniosamente hacia Novis, notó que el nudo que llevaba años oprimiéndole el pecho desaparecía.

Scavenging groups went into the ruins, trying to recover what weapons and armour they could.

Apenas había cruzado la frontera cuando la Resistencia se dispuso a prepararse para la batalla.

They were strictly banned from bringing back any of the dead.

Era una misión suicida.

Those who’d died in the fallout zone had to be left until a means of safe ceremonial disposal was possible.

Aunque no quedaban soldados ni recursos suficientes para afrontar la situación, los exploradores salieron a recorrer las ruinas de la ciudad para intentar recuperar todas las armas y armaduras que pudieran encontrar.

Anyone who wanted to fight could fight, alchemist or not, adult or not, man or not.

También les prohibieron estrictamente traer cadáveres de vuelta al Cuartel General.

There was no time to train anyone.

Quienes murieran en la zona afectada tendrían que permanecer allí hasta que encontraran una forma segura de llevar a cabo una ceremonia fúnebre.

They didn’t even have weapons for them.

Cualquiera dispuesto a luchar era bienvenido a unirse a las filas de la Resistencia, independientemente de su edad, de su género o de que tuviera poderes alquímicos.

There were boys and girls practising with sticks, trying to make themselves slingshots.

Pero no había tiempo para entrenar a nadie.

No armour because there was none in their sizes.

Ni siquiera tenían armas que ofrecer.

The sight made Helena sick.

Allí donde Helena mirara, había niños y niñas practicando con palos o intentando fabricar tirachinas caseros.

They were battle fodder.

Y ninguno llevaba armadura, pues no había de su tamaño.

They’d be slaughtered in minutes.

A Helena se le revolvía el estómago.

But they would do that rather than allow necromancy.

Eran carne de cañón.

This doomed assault was relying on a miracle, on the conviction that by risking everything, they would be rewarded.

Morirían a los pocos minutos de pisar el campo de batalla.

Glory and blessings and eternity to those who believed.

Pero la Resistencia prefería recurrir a ellos que a la nigromancia.

Just as Sol had blessed Orion.

Aquel ataque abocado al fracaso dependía de un milagro, de la seguridad de que se verían recompensados por arriesgar todo cuanto tenían.

But there was no Ilva now to create a miracle.

Porque la gloria, la bendición y la eternidad aguardaba a quienes no perdían la fe.

“I want to build a bomb,” she said, entering Crowther’s office in the middle of the night and finding him sitting there, wide awake.

Igual que Orion había recibido la bendición de Sol.

He was always awake.

Pero ya no contaban con Ilva para obrar milagros.

His already narrow face had grown skeletal.

—Quiero fabricar una bomba —dijo Helena nada más entrar en el despacho de Crowther.

He looked eighty, but she knew he was not even fifty.

Había ido a hablar con él en mitad de la noche, pero lo encontró despierto, siempre lo estaba.

“I didn’t know that explosives were anywhere within your field of expertise,” he said with dry contempt.

Su rostro, ya de por sí delgado, cada vez estaba más demacrado.

She sat without invitation.

Aunque ni siquiera había cumplido los cincuenta, parecía tener ochenta años.

Crowther sighed.

—No me habías dicho que también eras experta en explosivos —comentó con desdén.

Helena had once thought that Kaine had tested the outermost limits of her capacity for internal conflict, but Crowther was a new realm entirely.

Helena se sentó sin esperar a que le ofreciera asiento, y Crowther suspiró.

She had never hated and needed someone so intensely.

Durante un tiempo, ella había pensado que nadie ponía tan a prueba el límite de sus conflictos internos como Kaine, pero lo de Crowther estaba a otro nivel.

He was the only means by which she could do anything meaningful, the only member of the Eternal Flame who listened to her at all.

Jamás había odiado y necesitado a alguien tanto como a él.

Yet he held her obedience at Kaine’s throat like a knife.

Crowther podía permitirle a Helena hacer algo de utilidad, puesto que era el único miembro de la Llama Eterna que se tomaba la molestia de escucharla.

The hunt for spies within the Undying had intensified.

El problema era que usaba su obediencia como un arma contra Kaine.

All their other informants had disappeared without a trace.

La caza de espías entre los inmarcesibles se había intensificado.

The risk of using Kaine or even the information he sent was too great.

El resto de sus informadores habían desaparecido sin dejar rastro, así que recurrir a Kaine o incluso a la información que les proporcionaba suponía correr un riesgo demasiado alto.

“I used to help Luc with his pyromancy fundamentals.

—Solía ayudar a Luc a practicar los fundamentos de la piromancia.

I’m familiar with the technical processes of incendiary function.

Además, estoy familiarizada con los procesos técnicos de la combustión, y sus reglas son las mismas con o sin resonancia.

The rules apply with or without resonance,” she said.

Crowther arqueó una ceja y movió los dedos de la mano derecha para que los anillos de ignición se rozaran unos con otros.

One of Crowther’s eyebrows rose, and the fingers on his left hand fluttered, ignition rings brushing against each other.

—He estado pensando en ello desde hace tiempo… —Estaba tan nerviosa que incluso le dolía la garganta—.

“I’ve been thinking about it for a while …” Her throat was aching from nervousness. “We’ll use the obsidian in the same way the Undying used the nullium bomb.

Podríamos utilizar la obsidiana igual que los inmarcesibles usaron el anulitio en su bomba.

We could use nullium, too.”

De hecho, también podríamos combinar ambos materiales.

“Wouldn’t an explosion melt the obsidian?”

—¿Y no se fundiría la obsidiana en la explosión?

“No.

—No.

Shiseo has some experience with pyrotechnics; they’re used in Eastern celebrations.

Shiseo tiene experiencia con la pirotecnia que se utiliza para las celebraciones orientales.

Between the two of us, there’s a decent amount of technical knowledge.

Entre los dos sumamos un conocimiento bastante extenso.

If we build it right, we can harness the explosive force but limit the heat.

Si lo hacemos bien, podríamos limitar el calor desprendido por la bomba sin comprometer su fuerza explosiva.

It won’t be anything near the scale of their bombing, but we don’t need it to be.”

No tendría el alcance de su ataque, pero daría igual.

“You are remarkably confident for someone with nothing but a basic alchemy certification.”

—Confías mucho en tu trabajo para no disponer más que de un certificado básico en alquimia.

Helena’s jaw tensed, but she pressed on. “We have a lot of scrap obsidian.

Helena apretó los dientes, pero siguió hablando:

Knapping an edge with obsidian leaves a lot of discarded shards and pieces that are either too thin or too small for use.

—Tenemos una buena cantidad de fragmentos de obsidiana.

Those are all I’ll need, so it won’t interfere with production.”

Durante el proceso de fabricación de las armas, se generan esquirlas y pedacitos demasiado delgados o pequeños como para servir de utilidad.

She pulled out a folded stack of papers. “We’ll need these components forged in the Athanor Furnace.”

Esos residuos bastarían para la bomba, así que ni siquiera interferiríamos en la producción. —Sacó un montón de papeles doblados—.

He glanced at the designs. “I can’t make any promises.

Lo único que necesitaríamos sería que nos prepararan estos componentes en el Horno de Athanor.

But …” He sighed. “I suppose it might be of use.”

Crowther les echó un vistazo a sus diseños.

HELENA WAS BOTH DESPERATE AND terrified of what was to come.

—No te prometo nada, pero… —suspiró— supongo que nos vendrá bien.

If the attack was a success, if the bomb could do enough to weaken Morrough, could Luc kill him?

Pensar en lo que estaba por venir la aterrorizaba y desesperaba a partes iguales.

If he did, what would happen to Kaine?

Si la ofensiva salía bien y la bomba debilitaba lo suficiente a Morrough, ¿podría Luc acabar con él?

When she slept, she had endless nightmares of digging through Morrough’s corpse in the darkness with her bare hands, arms coated in his blood, ripping out his bones, trying desperately to find the piece that held Kaine’s life.

¿Y qué pasaría con Kaine si lograban derrotarlo?

In her dreams, Luc always approached, like a rising sun.

Cada vez que cerraba los ojos, caía presa de las pesadillas.

She would plead for time, try to explain herself, but Luc never heard.

Soñaba que hurgaba en el cadáver de Morrough a oscuras, con las manos desnudas, y que se manchaba los brazos enteros de sangre buscando desesperada el hueso que albergaba la vida de Kaine.

Every time she burned, too.

Mientras le arrancaba uno a uno todos los huesos del cuerpo, Luc se acercaba a ella como un sol naciente.

In the cold light of day, she knew it wouldn’t be like that.

Al verlo, ella trataba de explicarse y le suplicaba que la entendiera, pero él nunca la escuchaba.

She would be in Headquarters, in the hospital.

El sueño siempre terminaba con ella envuelta en llamas.

She wouldn’t know anything until it was too late.

Al despertar, sabía que la realidad sería muy distinta.

Every day she wondered if she was working towards her own doom and Kaine’s destruction.

Cuando Morrough fuera derrotado, ella estaría en el Cuartel General, trabajando en el hospital.

After how poorly he’d reacted to Helena’s mere involvement in the war effort, she didn’t tell him about the bomb.

No se enteraría de nada hasta que ya fuera demasiado tarde.

It wasn’t difficult to hide it; he was so busy with the ambassador, they scarcely had any time to do more than exchange urgent information.

Y cada día se preguntaba si su esfuerzo acabaría con su propia perdición o con la destrucción de Kaine.

It was only when she and Shiseo completed all the components that she went to the roof and called for him.

Después de lo mal que él había reaccionado cuando Helena le contó que había empezado a involucrarse más activamente en la guerra, había decidido no contarle lo de la bomba.

She had to wait a long time.

Tampoco le costó ocultárselo: su papel como embajador lo mantenía tan ocupado que apenas encontraban tiempo para verse aparte de para intercambiar la información más urgente.

When Kaine arrived, he was dressed in formal attire, sharp and polished.

No subió al tejado para llamarlo hasta que Shiseo y ella no tuvieron listos todos los componentes de su proyecto.

“I can’t stay,” he said. “What is it?”

Tardó un buen rato en aparecer y, cuando lo hizo, iba vestido con un traje formal, sobrio e impecable.

“We have a new weapon,” she said quickly. “Is there a time or place where a lot of the Undying will be in proximity?

—No voy a poder quedarme mucho rato.

Somewhere you won’t be.

¿Qué sucede?

It could be planted up to two days in advance.”

—Tenemos una nueva arma —se apresuró a decir ella—.

His expression hardened. “A bomb?”

¿Sabes si habrá algún momento en que una gran cantidad de inmarcesibles se reunirán cerca?

She gave a tense nod.

Lo ideal sería un evento en el que tú no tengas que estar presente.

“Obsidian?”

Podríamos colocarla hasta con dos días de antelación.

“And nullium, so you need to be well clear.”

La expresión de Kaine se endureció.

He nodded and looked at her pointedly. “I hope they’re not building it at Headquarters.”

—¿Habéis fabricado una bomba? —Ante el asentimiento de Helena, preguntó—: ¿De obsidiana?

She shook her head. “No.

—Y anulitio, así que tendrás que estar bien lejos de allí.

It’s off-site.”

Kaine asintió y le dedicó una mirada cargada de significado.

He exhaled. “Well, the Resistance is taking this final assault seriously at least.

—Espero que no la guardéis cerca del Cuartel General.

The Hevgotian force will cross the western border within the week, but several militocrats and officials will arrive in a day.

Ella negó con la cabeza.

There’s to be a welcome banquet for them the following evening.

—No, está en otro sitio.

Most of the Undying will be in attendance; even Morrough may be there briefly.”

—Bueno —exhaló—, al menos la Resistencia se está tomando su última ofensiva en serio.

She nodded.

Las fuerzas hevgotianas cruzarán la frontera oeste esta semana, pero unos cuantos estratócratas y oficiales vendrán a Paladia en un día.

That would work. “Can you place it without suspicion?

Se va a celebrar un banquete en su honor la noche siguiente de su llegada.

And then get away?”

La mayor parte de los inmarcesibles asistirán e incluso puede que Morrough se deje caer por allí.

His eyes softened. “No one pays attention to necrothralls the way they should.

Helena asintió.

They assume anyone using them must be on their side.

Tal vez funcionara.

If I rip out the reanimation, I can take over someone else’s and use them to make a delivery.

—¿Podrías colocar la bomba sin levantar sospechas y luego marcharte de allí?

It won’t be easily traced back to me.”

La mirada de Kaine se suavizó.

“And you won’t be there?

—Nadie les presta tanta atención como debería a los necrómatas.

When it goes off.” She was afraid that he was evading the question.

Dan por hecho que quienes los dirigen están de su lado.

Standing there, the two of them looked worlds apart.

Si le arranco la vitalidad al necrómata de otro inmarcesible, puedo dirigirlo para que la coloque y nadie vinculará el ataque conmigo.

He was clean and pristine, in a tailored uniform, wearing a row of intricate medals, while she stood ragged, in male-sized standard-issue clothes washed to threads.

—¿Estás seguro de que te dará tiempo a marcharte de allí antes de que explote?

“How far away do I need to be?”

Le daba miedo que estuviera evadiendo la pregunta.

“Far enough not to breathe it in.

Kaine y ella parecían pertenecer a dos mundos completamente distintos. Él iba vestido con un uniforme hecho a medida limpio y decorado con una hilera de intrincadas medallas, mientras que ella llevaba ropas reglamentarias andrajosas y demasiado grandes.

There will be micro-shards in the air.

—¿Cuánto tendré que alejarme?

We don’t know what effect they’ll have.

—Lo suficiente como para que no respires el humo.

You should be far away.”

Habrá micropartículas en el aire y no sabemos qué efecto tendrán.

“I’ll run an errand around that time.

Lo mejor será que estés a la mayor distancia que puedas.

The ambassador enjoys making himself inconvenient.

—Me aseguraré de hacer un recado llegado el momento.

I’m sure I can convince him to want something unreasonable and distant.”

Al embajador le gusta ser un incordio, así que estoy seguro de que podré convencerlo de pedirme algo absurdo y difícil de conseguir.

She nodded. “Make it a long errand.

Helena asintió.

I’ll bring it tomorrow evening.”

—Pues que sea un recado largo.

“No.” His voice cracked like a whip, and all the softness vanished. “Crowther’s not using you to transport a bomb.”

Te traeré la bomba mañana.

She shook her head. “It won’t be activated until the components are joined, and there’s a countdown.

—No. —La voz de Kaine restalló como un látigo, carente de la dulzura que había destilado hacía un momento—.

I’m not going to get blown up carrying it,” she said. “You can’t put it together on your own if you don’t know how to join the pieces.”

No toleraré que Crowther te utilice para transportar una bomba.

“I don’t care.

Helena negó con la cabeza.

Tell Crowther to figure out another way.” He’d turned bloodlessly pale, that inhuman gleaming rising beneath his skin.

—Mientras los componentes no se junten, no se activará.

“But if I don’t come,” she said, ready to resort to anything if he’d just cooperate, “that means I won’t see you again until—until after.”

Además, le hemos puesto un temporizador.

He didn’t waver. “Then I’ll see you after.

No me va a explotar en las manos —lo tranquilizó—.

Send someone else.”

No serás capaz de ensamblarla si no te enseño a hacerlo.

Her breath caught in her lungs. “Kaine …”

—Me da igual.

He glared at her. “I found you after a bombing.

Dile a Crowther que busque otra manera de traerla.

I had to watch them cut you open, trying to get the shrapnel out.

Se había quedado blanco como el papel y su piel empezaba a emitir ese característico brillo inhumano.

You nearly died so many times on the operating table, I lost count.

—Pero, si no la traigo yo, no volveré a verte hasta… hasta después de la explosión —dijo, dispuesta a recurrir al juego sucio con tal de hacerlo cooperar.

If you’d been an inch closer to the blast, that shrapnel would have gone through your heart.

Kaine no cedió.

You want me to set a bomb, I will do it, but you will not touch it.

—Pues nos veremos después.

Do you understand?”

Que se encargue otra persona.

She swallowed bitterly, grateful that she hadn’t told him any details that might have revealed her involvement. “Fine.

A Helena se le entrecortó la respiración.

If that’s what you want.”

—Kaine…

She turned to go.

—Recuerda cómo te encontré tras el otro bombardeo —dijo fulminándola con la mirada—.

There was so much she needed to do.

Tuve que ver cómo te abrían en canal para sacarte la metralla.

Take inventory, finish the bomb, help prep the hospital.

Perdí la cuenta de las veces que estuviste a punto de morir en aquella mesa de operaciones.

She’d been assigned to the casualty ward again.

De haber estado un centímetro más cerca, la metralla te habría atravesado el corazón.

Kaine pulled her to him. “Come back here in a few hours.”

Si quieres que coloque una bomba, lo haré encantado, pero no permitiré que te acerques a ella lo más mínimo.

She shook her head. “Now’s hardly the time.”

¿Ha quedado claro?

He didn’t seem to remember that he was the one who couldn’t linger.

Helena tragó saliva con amargura, agradecida por haberle contado lo justo y no haber mencionado que había sido ella quien la había fabricado.

He wouldn’t let go.

—Está bien.

She wished that all of this had begun sooner; there was so much time they’d missed.

Como tú quieras.

“All right,” she said finally, giving in. “But you have to leave now.”

Se dio la vuelta para marcharse.

He let go slowly. “I’ll call for you.”

Todavía tenía muchas tareas pendientes: hacer el inventario, terminar la bomba, ayudar a preparar el hospital.

After reporting to Crowther, she headed to the off-site lab where she and Shiseo used their resonance in tandem to assemble the final components.

Por si fuera poco, habían vuelto a asignarle un turno en el servicio de urgencias.

They’d built the bomb to be as compact as possible, but it was still nearly the size of a child.

Kaine tiró de ella para detenerla.

It would need to be placed in the centre of a room.

—Nos vemos aquí en unas horas.

Bombs themselves were not a new alchemical development, but they’d been banned for almost a hundred years after it was decided they were uncivilised.

—No creo que sea buen momento —le recordó negando con la cabeza.

Although banning them had done nothing to stop their development; Hevgoss was famously partial to such technology, viewing it as an equaliser against alchemists.

Parecía haber olvidado que era él quien tenía prisa, porque se negó a soltarla.

With the right manipulation of the air and flames, Luc held firebombs in his fingertips.

Helena deseó que su relación hubiera florecido mucho antes, pues habían perdido un tiempo precioso.

A great deal of his homework had involved arrays and technical studies, drilling all the various ways in which fire could be manipulated and weaponised.

—Está bien —cedió al final—, pero ahora tienes que irte.

Helena had utilised much of it.

Kaine la soltó despacio.

The trick had been designing something that would cause a powerful explosion without melting their obsidian.

—Te llamaré.

Shiseo had taught her a technique for a combination alloy fusion utilising dual array transmutation.

Después de informar a Crowther, Helena regresó al laboratorio externo, donde Shiseo y ella combinaron su resonancia para ensamblar las últimas piezas de la bomba.

It was complicated and dangerous.

Se habían asegurado de que fuera lo más compacta posible, pero seguía ocupando casi tanto como el tamaño de un niño pequeño, así que tendrían que colocarla en el centro de una habitación.

Even with all the arrays stabilising their resonance, Helena burned several fingertips nearly to the bone.

Aunque las bombas no eran un invento alquímico como tal, llevaban casi un siglo prohibidas por considerarse armas poco elegantes.

“Are you all right?” Shiseo asked as she sat trying to quickly regenerate the tissue.

Pese a todo, eso no había frenado su desarrollo.

Her fingertips hurt so much, it was hard to even feel her resonance, but years of practice made it natural to soothe the damaged nerve endings and regenerate them.

De hecho, era bien sabido que Hevgoss sentía predilección por aquel tipo de tecnología, pues consideraba que los ponía en igualdad de condiciones con los alquimistas.

Later she’d fix the dermal layer so that it wouldn’t be obvious to the eye.

Con la correcta manipulación del aire y las llamas, Luc era capaz de crear bombas incendiarias.

“It’s nothing,” she finally managed to say, blinking hard and staring at her hands, at the lines that ran across her fingers and palm.

Gran parte de sus deberes se centraban en los sellos y los estudios técnicos que diseccionaban las distintas formas de manipular el fuego y convertirlo en un arma.

Out of habit, she pressed her fingers against her sternum, feeling the faint dip in the bone.

Helena había utilizado muchos de esos conocimientos en la bomba.

The scar had faded some, but the ache where the bone had split lingered. “Is it done?”

La clave había sido diseñar un mecanismo que causara una explosión lo más violenta posible sin llegar a fundir la obsidiana.

He set the two pieces on the worktable, and she eyed them wearily.

Shiseo le había enseñado a fusionar aleaciones para combinarlas mediante un sello transmutacional doble.

He looked at her. “We’ll finish this tomorrow.

Era una técnica complicada y peligrosa, e, incluso con todos los sellos que habían dibujado para estabilizar su resonancia, Helena se había abrasado varios dedos casi hasta el hueso.

Your hands need to recover, and you need rest.”

—¿Estás bien? —le preguntó Shiseo cuando se sentó para regenerarse lo más rápido posible.

She gave him a faint smile. “I will tonight.”

Le dolían tanto las manos que casi no sentía la resonancia, pero los años de práctica habían conseguido que curar las terminaciones nerviosas le resultara tan fácil como respirar.

SHE STAYED PREOCCUPIED UNTIL LATE into the night, rechecking the medical inventory.

Más adelante se regeneraría la dermis para que las cicatrices no fueran tan visibles.

Her epinephrine injections were nearly out, but there was no record of who’d taken them.

—No ha sido nada —consiguió decir, parpadeando furiosa, mientras contemplaba las líneas que le surcaban los dedos y la palma de la mano.

Helena left a brusque note.

Se tocó el esternón por la costumbre, buscando la suave hendidura en el hueso.

If Elain was going to run everything, she could at least enforce the rules.

La cicatriz ya no se le notaba tanto, pero el punto donde el hueso se había fracturado todavía le dolía.

She was rolling a mountain of sterilised bandages into spools when her ring burned.

—¿Está hecho?

Amaris barely landed; Kaine swept her off the roof and they were airborne.

Shiseo dejó dos piezas sobre la mesa y Helena las contempló agotada.

The instant they were inside, he had her pinned against the wall, his lips ravenous on hers.

—Terminaremos mañana —le dijo el hombre sin apartar la vista de ella—.

She gripped him tightly.

Tienes que curarte las manos y descansar un poco.

Her fingertips were still numb, but she hardly noticed.

Ella le ofreció una leve sonrisa.

His hands slid up until her face was cradled in them.

—Ya descansaré esta noche.

His forehead pressed to hers, breath mingling a moment before he kissed her again, drawing her farther inside.

Se mantuvo ocupada revisando el inventario médico hasta última hora de la noche.

Their every step hurried.

Alguien casi había dejado sin existencias las inyecciones de epinefrina, pero quienquiera que se las hubiera llevado no lo había hecho de manera oficial.

They were always running out of time.

Helena garabateó una nota cortante.

Someday, she promised herself, someday I am going to love him in a moment that isn’t stolen.

Si Elain iba a tomar las riendas, al menos podía asegurarse de que se cumplieran las normas.

“Are you all right?” he asked once they were inside, where it was lit enough that he could look at her.

Estaba colocando una pila de vendas esterilizadas cuando el anillo se calentó.

He reached out, and she knew that if he touched her, he’d use his resonance and realise her hands had been recently injured, so she caught his hand in hers, curling his fingers closed and clasping it against her chest.

Amaris apenas tuvo tiempo de aterrizar cuando Kaine levantó a Helena en volandas y alzaron el vuelo una vez más.

“Yes.” She nodded. “Now I’m all right.”

En cuanto estuvieron a resguardo, él la pegó contra la pared y la besó con un hambre feroz.

He stared at her, and she knew she looked tired, thin, and so sallow from being always indoors with little natural light.

Helena se aferró a él con fuerza y, aunque se le durmieron los dedos, casi ni lo notó.

The bombing had broken most of the windows, and even the few that survived were boarded up and sealed in case the wind brought the nullium towards Headquarters again.

Kaine le acunó el rostro entre ambas manos.

“I should have called you sooner.” His thumb traced along her cheekbone.

Apoyó la frente en la suya dejando que sus alientos se entremezclaran antes de besarla de nuevo y guiarla por la casa con paso apresurado.

She shook her head. “It wouldn’t have been worth the risk.

Siempre iban contra reloj.

It’s dangerous for you to fly so near like that.

«Algún día —se prometió—, algún día le daré todo mi amor en un instante que no sea robado».

Someone could shoot you with obsidian.” A tremor ran through her just saying it aloud. “We shouldn’t be doing this.

—¿Te encuentras bien? —le preguntó Kaine una vez que llegaron a una estancia lo bastante iluminada como para distinguir sus facciones.

It’s stupid to take this risk.”

Extendió una mano y Helena cayó en la cuenta de que, si la tocaba, usaría su resonancia y se daría cuenta de que se había hecho daño hacía poco tiempo, así que se le adelantó.

She was suddenly struggling to breathe.

Le estrechó una mano, le cerró los dedos y se la llevó contra el pecho.

He pulled his hand free and then held her head in both his hands, as if trying to quiet her mind for her.

—Sí —asintió—.

“We’re safe here,” he said.

Ahora ya estoy bien.

For now.

Kaine la miró.

For this moment.

Helena sabía que estaba agotada, que había perdido peso y que estaba pálida por la falta de exposición a la luz natural.

But not really.

El bombardeo había destrozado la mayor parte de las ventanas del Cuartel General, pero habían tapiado incluso las que habían quedado intactas por miedo a que el aire arrastrara el anulitio y se colara en el edificio.

Not ever.

—Debería haberte llamado antes —dijo Kaine mientras le acariciaba la mejilla con el pulgar.

Still she nodded, trying to believe it, not wanting to poison what little time they had left.

—No habría merecido la pena —replicó ella negando con la cabeza—.

She rose up on her toes, kissing him, pulling his arms around her.

No deberías volar tan bajo.

Don’t let this be the last time.

Es peligroso y alguien podría dispararte con obsidiana. —Un escalofrío le recorrió el cuerpo con tan solo imaginarlo—.

She didn’t close her eyes.

No deberíamos estar haciendo esto.

She kept them open and watching him, trying to notice every detail.

Somos unos necios por correr riesgos.

She wanted to commit everything to memory, the way he felt under her hands and against her skin, as if sufficient detail could make this secret thing real enough to endure; as if she could write it into the universe so deeply that even a war could not erase it.

De pronto le costaba respirar.

Afterwards, he gathered her against his chest, chin resting on the top of her head as his fingers drew patterns across her skin.

Kaine desenredó los dedos que tenían entrelazados y acunó el rostro de Helena entre sus manos, como si quisiera acallar sus pensamientos.

I’m going to take care of you.

—Aquí estamos a salvo.

I’m always going to take care of you.

De momento.

He didn’t say it audibly, but she could hear it in the shifting of the air, the way his jaw moved when he mouthed the words.

Durante un rato.

She’d hoped to sleep, to experience one last hour of peace, but she was too afraid.

Pero no duraría.

When she sat up, Kaine’s quicksilver eyes were instantly guarded.

No para siempre.

She didn’t say anything for a moment, holding his hand in hers, studying his face, this aspect of him that was hers alone.

De todas formas, asintió y se obligó a creerlo.

She entwined their fingers, trying to find the right words.

No quería echar a perder el poco tiempo que les quedaba.

“Kaine,” she finally said, “there’s a chance—we’re hoping that this attack will be the end of the war.

Se puso de puntillas, lo besó y tiró de sus brazos para que la rodeara con ellos.

We don’t—we aren’t sure how much longer we’re going to last if it isn’t.”

«Por favor, que esta no sea nuestra última vez».

His hand twitched.

No cerró los ojos.

“If it isn’t—” Her chest jerked, and she gave a tight, half-sobbed laugh. “—well, we’ll just keep fighting, then.

Observó todos los movimientos de Kaine en un intento por recordar cada segundo juntos.

But if it is … I—I don’t know what will happen to you.

Quería grabarse a fuego en la memoria la sensación de su cuerpo en las manos, contra la piel, como si pudiera hacer de su secreto algo lo bastante real como para perdurar en el tiempo.

I’m sorry.

Como si pudiese dejarlo escrito en el tejido del universo, de manera que la guerra no lograra borrarlo.

I tried to find a way”—she looked down—“I couldn’t figure out—”

Más tarde, Kaine la estrechó contra su pecho y apoyó la barbilla sobre su cabeza mientras trazaba dibujos en su piel con los dedos.

“It’s fine,” he said.

«Voy a cuidar de ti.

She shook her head. “Maybe if Morrough’s killed, your soul just goes back to you.

Nunca dejaré de hacerlo».

We don’t know that it won’t.

No lo dijo en voz alta, pero Helena percibió sus palabras como un cambio en el aire, y notó que su mandíbula se movía al articular los sonidos.

There’s a chance.

Había tenido la esperanza de poder dormir, de pasar una última hora en paz, pero estaba demasiado asustada.

Or maybe the Stone would be enough to—”

Cuando se incorporó, los ojos grises como el mercurio de Kaine mostraban una expresión cauta.

She was grasping, and they both knew it.

Helena permaneció en silencio durante un momento, sosteniendo una de sus manos entre las suyas y admirando su rostro, pues esa versión de él era suya y solo suya.

“It could,” she said insistently, squeezing his hand. “So, if that happens, if you’re all right when it’s over, you have to run.

Entrelazó los dedos con los de él mientras intentaba encontrar las palabras adecuadas.

All right?

—Existe la posibilidad… —empezó por fin—.

Get away as fast as you can.

Tenemos la esperanza de que esta ofensiva ponga fin a la guerra.

Don’t let yourself be captured.”

No estamos seguros… No sabemos cuánto tiempo más aguantaremos si no sale como esperamos.

His eyes narrowed. “Where will you be?”

Notó que la mano de Kaine se crispaba entre las suyas.

Helena looked down, playing with the ring on his hand.

—Si la guerra no termina… —A Helena se le estremeció el pecho y dejó escapar una carcajada estrangulada, al borde del sollozo—, pues imagino que seguiremos luchando.

It had been so long since she’d seen hers.

Pero, si ganamos…, n-no sé qué ocurrirá contigo.

“You know me, I’ll be in the hospital.

Lo siento.

There will be a lot of injuries, so I wouldn’t be ready right away—so you just go, and I’ll catch up.”

He intentado encontrar una manera… —Bajó la vista—.

He scoffed. “If I survive, I’m not going anywhere without you.”

No he conseguido…

She pressed her fingers to his lips, hushing him. “No.

—No pasa nada.

You can’t risk getting caught.”

Ella negó con la cabeza.

He pushed her fingers away from his mouth, but she wouldn’t let him interrupt.

—A lo mejor recuperas tu alma si matamos a Morrough.

She had thought about this in circles, and there was little chance that Crowther would let her slip away without paying for her necromancy.

No hay por qué dar por hecho lo contrario.

If she was lucky, she’d just be expelled from the Eternal Flame.

Siempre hay una posibilidad.

It would be the quickest and quietest resolution, but even that might take weeks or months.

Quizá la Gema de los Cielos baste para…

“Go south, towards the sea.

Estaba dando palos de ciego y ambos lo sabían.

When I can, I’ll come, I’ll look for you, and it’ll be just like we said—we’ll disappear.”

—Podría bastar —insistió estrechándole la mano—.

His eyes narrowed into slits. “And how long do you expect I’d be waiting?”

Lo que intento decir es que, si todo sale bien cuando esto acabe, tienes que escapar, ¿vale?

Helena’s eyes dropped. “I don’t know.

Huye tan rápido como puedas y no dejes que te capturen.

It might be—a little while.”

—¿Y qué pasará contigo? —preguntó él mirándola con suspicacia.

“Why?”

Helena bajó la vista y jugueteó con el anillo de Kaine.

“Because—there will be a lot of things that will happen once it’s over.

Hacía mucho tiempo que no veía el que ella llevaba.

But I’m sure once it is, they’ll rather I just disappear, so then I’ll come look for you, all right?

—Ya me conoces.

I think it would be good that way.

Estaré en el hospital.

For you.

Habrá muchos heridos, así que no podré marcharme enseguida… Tú asegúrate de escapar y yo ya te alcanzaré.

You might realise you want other things once you have real choices—”

Kaine resopló.

His fingers curled around the back of her neck, pulling her close until their faces were nearly touching.

—Si sobrevivo, no pienso ir a ningún lado sin ti.

“You’re mine,” he said almost against her lips. “Mine.

Helena le puso los dedos en los labios para hacerlo callar.

You swore it.

—No, no puedes arriesgarte a que te atrapen.

Your Resistance sold you to me.

Él la apartó, pero Helena no iba a permitir que la interrumpiera.

I’m not going anywhere without you.

Llevaba días dándole vueltas al asunto y creía que era muy poco probable que Crowther fuera a dejarla ir sin que pagara por haber usado la nigromancia.

And if anyone touches you, immortal or not, I will kill them.”

Con un poco de suerte, se limitarían a expulsarla de la Llama Eterna.

He didn’t wait for a reply; he kissed her as though his lips were a brand on hers.

Pero, incluso a pesar de ser la decisión más rápida y discreta, podría llevarles semanas o meses.

SHISEO WAS THE ONLY OTHER choice for delivering the bomb.

—Ve al Sur, en dirección al mar.

He and Helena coated the very exterior of it with a fine layer of mo’lian’shi which Shiseo had extracted from nullium dust.

Yo me reuniré contigo en cuanto pueda.

After that, it was coated in Helena’s mirroring elixir.

Te buscaré y haremos lo que siempre hemos dicho: desapareceremos.

Shiseo had tinkered with the composition and made it workable on larger surfaces.

Kaine entornó los ojos todavía más.

Once it was all assembled, it would be difficult to notice, and the exterior inertia would make it invisible to anyone searching by resonance.

—¿Y cuánto tiempo crees que tendré que esperarte?

As they finished, Helena slipped her ring off, studying it.

—No lo sé —admitió Helena bajando la mirada—.

The mirroring was rubbing off.

Puede que… tarde un poco.

If she was arrested, she’d be searched, and any metal removed.

—¿Por qué?

That would include Kaine’s ring.

—Porque… habrá mucho que hacer cuando la guerra acabe.

“Would mo’lian’shi interfere with an entanglement?” she asked.

Aun así, estoy segura de que preferirán que desaparezca cuando ya no me necesiten, así que iré a buscarte, ¿vale?

Shiseo studied the half-visible ring. “If you left a small part exposed, you could probably still use it.” He eyed her knowingly. “That would keep it hidden if someone searched you using resonance unless they were very thorough.”

Creo que hacerlo así será lo mejor para ti.

That was all she needed to know.

A lo mejor descubres que quieres otra cosa cuando tengas la verdadera posibilidad de elegir…

Muttering an apology to Kaine for the burn he was about to get, she coated all but one section.

Kaine la agarró por la nuca y tiró de ella hasta que sus rostros estuvieron a punto de tocarse.

Once it cooled, she dipped her ring into the mirroring elixir, refreshing the concealment, watching it vanish.

—Eres mía —dijo casi contra sus labios—.

WHILE SHISEO WAS DELIVERING THE bomb, Helena went to check on Lila.

Mía.

If the hospital ended up inundated, it would be a while before she’d come again.

Me lo has prometido.

The bump between Lila’s hips had grown undeniable, but Lila was almost manic with regret, questioning her decision for the first time.

La Resistencia te vendió a mí.

Her nails were all bitten to the quick. “I can’t believe that the final battle is happening now,” she said, watching the combatants as they milled below. “I should be out there.”

No pienso ir a ningún lado sin ti.

“It’s not as if you knew,” Helena said, tiredly.

Mataré a quien se atreva a tocarte, ya sea inmortal o no.

It was too late for Lila to change her mind now.

No esperó a que respondiera y la besó como si la estuviera marcando con un hierro al rojo vivo.

“Do you think this’ll be it?” Lila asked. “Are our chances good?”

Shiseo era la única persona aparte de ella que podía encargarse de entregar la bomba.

“As good as they can be,” Helena said.

Helena y él habían cubierto el exterior del artefacto con una delgada capa del mo’lian’shi que Shiseo había extraído del polvo de anulitio y con otra del elixir de distorsión que Helena había preparado.

Win or lose, all she felt was dread, but it had to end now.

Shiseo había conseguido alterar su composición para hacer que funcionara en superficies más amplias.

It could not go on.

Una vez que la bomba estuviera lista, sería difícil de detectar.

“He’s awake,” Lila said, holding out her hand for Helena’s. “Come feel.

Además, su inercia exterior la volvería invisible a la resonancia.

Right here.”

Cuando terminaron, Helena se quitó su anillo y lo estudió con detenimiento.

Lila caught Helena’s hand and pressed it on her stomach, just above her hip bone.

La distorsión ya no era tan efectiva como al principio.

There was a pause, then, without using resonance, Helena felt a strange flutter against her palm.

Si la arrestaban, la registrarían y le quitarían cualquier metal que llevara encima.

“Feel that?” Lila asked.

Y eso incluía el anillo de Kaine.

Helena nodded, letting her resonance sweep through Lila to the baby, finding the heartbeat quick as the flutter of a bird’s wings.

—¿Crees que el mo’lian’shi interferiría con un enlace espejo? —preguntó.

There were no more kicks.

Shiseo contempló la joya apenas visible.

“He probably went to sleep,” Lila said.

—Si dejas una pequeña zona sin cubrir, lo más seguro es que puedas seguir usándolo. —La miró con expresión comprensiva—.

Helena still didn’t know where Lila got the conviction that the baby was a boy, but she’d named him Apollo and referred to him as Pol. “You should feel him at night—I think he does somersaults.

Salvo que te vieras sometida a un registro exhaustivo, eso lo mantendría oculto en caso de que alguien utilice la resonancia contigo.

Gets his feet all the way up to my ribs.”

No necesitaba saber más.

“I can’t imagine where he gets his athletic troublemaking genes from,” Helena said in a dry voice, pulling her hand away.

Murmuró una disculpa en silencio, pensando en la quemazón que Kaine estaba a punto de sentir y cubrió casi toda la superficie del anillo con mo’lian’shi.

“He’ll have all the fun we missed,” Lila said, letting her shirt fall over her stomach. “You know, I think I’ll be happy for him to be a peacetime baby.

Al cabo de un rato, cuando se hubo enfriado, bañó la joya de nuevo con el elixir de distorsión para asegurarse de que quedaba bien escondida y la vio desaparecer.

I bet there will be a lot of babies in the next few years.

Mientras Shiseo entregaba la bomba, Helena fue a comprobar cómo estaba Lila.

They’ll all go to the Institute together like we did.

Si el hospital acababa saturado de heridos, no sabía cuándo tendría la oportunidad de verla otra vez.

D’you think you’ll ever have children?”

El bulto que crecía en su vientre ya era imposible de disimular, y Lila, consumida por las dudas, empezaba a preguntarse si había tomado la decisión correcta.

Helena shook her head without a word.

Se había mordido las uñas hasta la raíz.

“You might change your mind someday,” Lila said coaxingly. “Just have to find the right sort for you.

—No me puedo creer que esta sea ya la batalla final —dijo mientras veía a los soldados moverse de un lado a otro por la ventana—.

You’d be a good mum.”

Debería estar ahí con ellos.

“I’m a healer; we don’t do things like that,” Helena said.

—No era algo que hubieras podido prever —le respondió Helena, agotada.

“But you only became a healer because of the war.

Ya era demasiado tarde para que Lila cambiara de opinión.

No one’s going to expect you to keep doing it once it’s over.”

—¿Crees que ha llegado el momento?

For all of Lila’s exceptionalism and understanding of the perilous role she occupied, somehow she didn’t seem to realise that most people never had the chances she did, whether by birth or by ability.

¿Tenemos opciones de ganar?

Lila was a once-in-a-lifetime talent, with the beauty to match, and a name with centuries of legacy behind it.

—Tantas como la situación lo permite.

The rules did not bend like that for anyone else.

Helena estaba aterrorizada, pero, independientemente de que ganaran o perdieran, la guerra tenía que acabar ya.

Especially not Helena.

No podían seguir así para siempre.

She changed the subject.

—Está despierto —dijo Lila, que extendió una mano hacia Helena—.

“I really think you should tell Luc.

Ven a notar cómo se mueve.

He should know before this battle starts.

Justo aquí.

That way if things go wrong, the Eternal Flame will know the importance of getting you to safety.”

Lila cogió la mano de Helena y la puso sobre su vientre, por encima del hueso de la cadera.

Lila was silent for a surprisingly long moment.

Al cabo de un instante, Helena notó una extraña agitación sin necesidad de recurrir a la resonancia.

“He already knows,” she finally said quietly, averting her eyes from Helena’s.

—¿Lo has notado? —preguntó Lila.

“What?”

Helena asintió y recurrió a su don para colarse en su cuerpo y encontrar el latido del bebé, tan rápido como el aleteo de un pajarillo.

“He broke in, through the window, when I was first placed in quarantine.

Pero ya no dio ninguna patada más.

He was so worried that I told him the truth.

—Seguro que ya ha vuelto a cerrar los ojos, el muy dormilón —dijo Lila.

He said if people knew, they’d make me leave.

Helena no sabía por qué estaba tan segura de que el bebé era un niño, pero ya lo llamaba Apollo o, simplemente, Pol, de manera cariñosa—.

Send me to Novis.

Deberías ver lo mucho que se mueve por las noches.

He needed me, so I kept saying I wanted it to be a secret.

Yo creo que se pasa las horas dando volteretas, porque te juro que lo noto clavarme los pies en las costillas.

He made me promise not to tell anyone.”

—Vaya, me pregunto de quién habrá heredado los genes de atleta problemático —comentó Helena con aspereza al apartar la mano del vientre de su amiga.

Helena was struck dumb for several moments. “He’s known this whole time?

—Podrá disfrutar de todos los buenos momentos que nosotros tuvimos que perdernos. —Lila se bajó la camisa—.

That you’re pregnant, and I’m the one caring for you?”

Me alegro de que vaya a vivir una infancia en paz, ¿sabes?

If Luc knew and allowed this, why was he so opposed to her healing Titus?

Estoy segura de que nacerán muchos niños en los próximos años y todos estudiarán juntos en la Academia, igual que nosotros.

It made no sense.

¿Te ves teniendo hijos en el futuro?

Lila flushed. “Sorry.

Helena negó con la cabeza sin decir nada.

I wanted to tell you, but I didn’t want him upset.

—A lo mejor cambias de idea algún día —insistió como si tratara de convencerla—.

He’s still not doing very well.”

Solo tienes que encontrar al hombre adecuado.

“I need to go,” Helena said, standing up unsteadily.

Estoy segura de que serías una madre fantástica.

Lila tried to stop her, blocking the door. “No.

—Soy sanadora.

You’re angry, I can tell.

Ese camino no es para nosotras.

Please, let me explain.”

—Pero fue la guerra lo que te obligó a convertirte en sanadora.

Helena stared at her.

Nadie espera que sigas ejerciendo cuando todo haya terminado.

Lila looked so much like her father, cast in a feminine mould—the height, the pale hair and blue eyes, even a scar on one side of the head.

Para ser alguien tan consciente de lo excepcional y peligroso que era el cargo que ocupaba, Lila no parecía darse cuenta de que las oportunidades de las que ella había disfrutado, ya fuera por la familia en la que había nacido o por sus propias habilidades, no estaban al alcance de la mayoría.

“I don’t need an explanation from you,” Helena said. “I need to talk to him.”

Lila poseía un talento único, una belleza que no se quedaba atrás y un apellido que arrastraba siglos de historia.

She searched everywhere for Luc.

Ella tenía el privilegio de poder saltarse las normas sin que hubiera consecuencias, pero el resto del mundo no tenía esa suerte.

Everyone she asked gave a different location: He was in a meeting, he was asleep, he was in the commons, the mess.

Y mucho menos Helena.

Everywhere she went, he was always a few minutes ahead of her.

Decidió cambiar de tema:

Finally, she tracked him down in the hospital, but he was in a private room, under guard, no admittance.

—Creo que deberías decírselo a Luc.

Helena stood waiting, and finally Elain emerged carrying a tray with several syringes and empty vials on it, and a tense furrow between her eyes.

Merece saberlo antes de la batalla.

“I need to see Luc,” Helena said.

Además, si la cosa se tuerce, la Llama Eterna sabrá que tiene que priorizar tu seguridad.

Elain started at the sight of her. “He’s resting.”

Para sorpresa de Helena, Lila guardó silencio durante un buen rato.

Helena looked down at the tray, and Elain tried to turn it from her view.

—Ya lo sabe —admitió en un susurro, sin atreverse a encontrar la mirada de Helena.

“Why are you giving him all that?” Helena asked, eyes flicking from vial to vial. “These shouldn’t be combined, and he’s too young to need half of them.

—¿Perdón?

And these—” She snatched up a syringe with her writing on it. “—these are for dire emergencies only.

—Se coló por la ventana cuando me pusieron en cuarentena y lo vi tan preocupado que tuve que contarle la verdad. Él me dijo que me obligarían a marcharme si alguien se enteraba, que me enviarían a Novis.

If you overuse them, you’re going to give him heart failure.

He insistido en mantenerlo en secreto porque Luc me necesita.

Who approved this?”

Me hizo prometer que no se lo contaría a nadie.

Elain’s eyes flashed indignantly. “I’m his healer.”

Helena se quedó muda de asombro.

—¿Lo ha sabido desde el principio?

¿Y cómo es que no se ha quejado de que me haya estado encargando yo de tus cuidados si sabía lo del embarazo?

Si Luc había permitido aquello, ¿por qué se había mostrado tan inflexible con lo de Titus?

No tenía sentido.

Lila se puso colorada.

—Lo siento.

Quería decírtelo, pero sabía que Luc se enfadaría.

Todavía no se encuentra muy bien.

—Tengo que irme —dijo Helena poniéndose de pie con torpeza.

Lila se adelantó para intentar detenerla, colocándose delante de la puerta.

—No, está claro que te ha molestado.

Por favor, déjame que te lo explique.

Helena la miró.

Lila se parecía tanto a su padre que era como una versión femenina de él: igual estatura, el cabello rubio, los ojos azules…, e incluso compartían una cicatriz en el lateral del rostro.

—No eres tú quien debe darme explicaciones.

Voy a hablar con Luc.

Lo buscó por todas partes, pero cada vez que preguntaba por él le daban una respuesta distinta: estaba en una reunión, descansando, en el patio, en la sala común… Siempre parecía sacarle un par de minutos de ventaja.

Al final, logró rastrearlo hasta el hospital, pero estaba en una habitación privada y vigilada, sin acceso para visitas.

Helena lo esperó hasta que vio a Elain salir con una bandeja llena de jeringuillas y frasquitos vacíos.

Tenía el ceño fruncido en una expresión tensa.

—Necesito ver a Luc —le dijo.

—Está descansando —respondió Elain con un sobresalto al verla.

Helena inspeccionó el contenido de la bandeja, aunque Elain trató de ocultárselo.

—¿Por qué le estás dando todo eso? —le preguntó mientras examinaba cada frasquito—.

No deberías mezclar esos medicamentos.

Además, Luc es demasiado joven para necesitar muchos de ellos.

Y… —cogió una jeringuilla cuya etiqueta estaba escrita con su propia caligrafía—, esto es solo para casos de extrema urgencia.

Si se abusa de ello, puede causar una insuficiencia cardiaca.

¿Quién ha aprobado este tratamiento?

Un destello de indignación surcó la mirada de Elain.

—Yo soy su sanadora.